<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 38.9: original edition by S. Swaminathan</title>
                <title type="alt">No. 9. (A.R. No. 9 of 1912.) TEṈKĀŚI, TENKASI TALUK, TIRUNELVELI DISTRICT. On the west and south walls, central shrine, Vīśvanāthaśvāmin temple.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>	
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv38p0i0009</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p><hi rend="bold">King: Jaṭilavarman <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Tribhuvanachakravarttin Parākrama-Pāṇḍya <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Kulaśēkharadēva Pāṇḍya Year Śaka 1419 śu. di. 3, <hi rend="italic">uttiram</hi> = 1497 A.D.</hi></p>						
                            
                            <p>This inscription records that a certain Nallaperumāḷ Śaivasikhāmaṇi Bhaṭṭaṉ, who was a priest at the Viśvanātha temple at Dakshiṇakāśi in Teṉṉāri-nāḍu forfeited his right of worship in the temple for inexplicable reasons, in the fifteenth regnal year of the king. The privileges appended with the right of worship such as the ownership of house, gardens and its surroundings and also one and half <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> of tax-free land at Ilāñjapaṟṟu, owned by the temple, and other privileges were now conferred on Pichcha Bhaṭṭaṉ Paḍikkāśuvaittāṉ belonged to <hi rend="italic">Bhāradvāja-gōtra</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bōdhayana-sutra.</hi> The latter was also conferred the right of cultivation of the lands given. It appears that when the kinsmen <hi rend="italic">(ñādi)</hi> of Śaivaśikāmaṇi Bhaṭṭaṉ refused to accept the responsibility (of worship in the above temple after the latter lost his right) this arrangement had been made. It is also stated that the new priest should discharge his duties while enjoying the privileges.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Koḍumalūr-uḍaiyāṉ figures as the signatory of the record.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-03-23" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-03-18" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">śakābdaM</hi> <num value="1419"><g type="numeral">1000</g> 4 <g type="numeral">100</g> <g type="numeral">10</g> 9</num>l mel cellā niṉṟa <hi rend="grantha">svastiśrī</hi> ko<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi><hi rend="grantha">ṭila</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmmarā</hi>ṉa <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vana<hi rend="grantha">ccakra</hi>vat=tikaḷ kāttikai nāḷ piṟantu <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>pa</unclear></hi>rākkiṟama pāṇṭiya <gap reason="lost" quantity="10" unit="character"/> Iraṇṭān tiyatiyum <hi rend="grantha">pūrvvapakṣa</hi>ttu <hi rend="grantha">tri</hi>tikaiyum maṅkalavāramum peṟṟa Uttirattu nāḷ <hi rend="grantha">bhāradvājagotra</hi>ttu <hi rend="grantha">bodhā</hi>yana<hi rend="grantha">sutra</hi>ttu piccapaṭṭaṉ paṭikkācuvaittāṉ putuvaikku vāyttapaṭṭaṉukku teṉṉāri nāṭṭuc cittirāna<hi rend="grantha">di</hi> Uttiratirattu <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇakāciyil Uṭaiyār vi<hi rend="grantha">śva</hi>nātaṉ koyilukku muṉṉāḷ paṭṭar <surplus>ma</surplus> paṅku <num value="100"><g type="numeral">100</g></num>m pāka niṉṟa taṉakku nallaperumāḷ caivacikāmaṇi paṭṭaṉ caraperāy Ivaṉ ceytu ponta turamum patiṉ A
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>ñcāvatu mutalukku muṭṭi Ivaṉukku ñātiyā<surplus>ṉa</surplus>y Uḷḷavarkaḷum taṅkaḷukku veṇṭām Eṉṟu pokaik koṇṭe nāḷatu mutalukku Ēṭṭa <gap reason="lost" quantity="11" unit="character"/> ṉāyinār kovilil Acal nampukku Aṟṟa mariyāti Iṉṉāyiṉār tiruvītiyil pañcappiṟakārattil melaic ciṟakil patimūṉṟu muḻattu maṉai Oṉṟum toṭṭamum toṭṭak kūṟum Iṉṉāyinār tevatāṉamāṉa Ilañcipaṟṟil Iṟai Ili nilam Oru mā Araiyum Uṭaimaiyum maṟṟum Uḷḷa cuvantiraṅkaḷu paṟṟit turamumañ ceytu potumpaṭi kaṟpittuviṭṭa Aḷa
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>vukku Immariāti Ile Iṉṉāḷ mutalukku Ivvolai piṭipāṭākak koṇṭu cantatippiṟavecame <hi rend="grantha">candrā</hi>tittavaṟ ce <gap reason="lost" quantity="10" unit="character"/> Ākak kaiyyāṇṭu koṇṭu maṇaiyum toṭṭamum toṭṭakkūṟum Iṟaiyiliyum maṟṟumuḷḷa cuvantira<supplied reason="omitted">ṅ</supplied>kaḷum paṟṟik kār pacāṉam Iṟaiyiliyum payiṟkoṇṭu turamum muṭṭāmal ceytu potavum pāṟka Ivai koṭumaḷūr Uṭaiyāṉ <choice><sic>Ē</sic><corr>E</corr></choice>ḻuttu <g type="pc"/>tu<hi rend="grantha">lyaM</hi><g type="pc"/> 
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="commentary"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 38.9 (ARIE/1911-1912/C/1912/9) by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2019_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2019_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">10-11</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">9</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl n="ARIE">
                        <ptr target="bib:ARIE1911-1912"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">41</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="appendix">C/1912</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">9</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
