<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 32, part 2, no. 91: original edition by S. Swaminathan</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 91. KARUNTAṬṬĀṄKUḌI, TANJAVUR TALUK, TANJAVUR DISTRICT.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName>
						<name>DHARMA team</name>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv32p2i0091</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>On the south wall of the central shrine (beneath the niche containing the image of Dakshiṇāmūrtti now covered by a cement floor) in the Vasishṭēśvara temple.</p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">Year 11: 982 A.D.</hi></p>						

						<p>Built in at the end.</p>						

						<p>Records that during the 17th regnal year of Rājakēsarivarman (Sundarachōḷa), Poyyili, a serving woman residing at Śīvigaiyār-śēri made an endowment for burning a perpetual lamp for the merit of her son, Araiyaṉ Vīrachōḻaṉ. The temple officials Nandi Vemban, Nandi Aiyyāṟaṉ, Ūrkiḻāṉ Satti and Pagaimadan Satru Kālaṉ received half of the endowed amount or forty-eight sheep from the shepherd Muḷḷūraṉ Śivaṉ and had agreed to burn half-a-lamp out of the amount. They also gave a written agreement <hi rend="italic">(ōlai)</hi> to this effect. But they did not carry out the charity. During the eleventh regnal year of Uttamachōḷa (982 A.D.) the <hi rend="italic">śrīkariyam</hi> official Maṉukulamārttāṇḍa Mūvēndavēḷāṉ, a resident of Milaṭṭūr having heard this enquired into the matter summoned both the parties. The shepherd produced the <hi rend="italic">ōlai</hi> but the temple officials (who received the <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> from the shepherd) had expired by this time. The <hi rend="italic">śrīkāriyam</hi> official ruled that three individuals (possibly the progenies of the temple official) should burn one perpetual lamp after procuring ninety-six sheep themselves as a fine for the defalcation of the <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> made by their predecessors.</p>						

						<p>Published in <hi rend="italic">Varalāṟu,</hi> Issue No. 1 (1993) pp. 32-33.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2026-05-05" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/>kopparakecaripanmaṟku yāṇṭu <num value="11"><g type="numeral">10</g> 1</num> nṟāvatu tañcāvūrk karuntiṭṭaikkuṭi <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>varkku kovirācakecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>rkku yāṇṭu <num value="17"><g type="numeral">10</g> 7</num> vatu civikaiyār ceri Irukkum peṇṭāṭṭi poyyili
<lb n="2"/>tan makan Araiyaṉ viracoḻaṉaic cātti Oru tirunontāviḷakku vaikka Ataṉil pāti viḷakkukku ṉey Aṭṭa kaṭava Iṭaiyan muḷḷuran civaṉiṭai viḷakkālum vanta kācu koṇṭu Ittaḷit tirukkoyiluṭaiyānkaḷ na
<lb n="3" break="no"/>nti vempaṉum nanti Ayyāṟaṉum Ūr kiḻāṉ cattiyum pakaimatan catru kālaṉum Ivvaṉaivarum kokāṭṭi Arai viḷakkālum <hi rend="grantha">4<unclear>8</unclear></hi> Āṭṭālum taṅkaḷil licainta kācu koṇṭu <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkku Iṭaiyaṉiṭṭu kuṭutta mutalaṭai yolaiyuṅ ku<supplied reason="omitted">ṭu</supplied>ttu Araiviḷa
<lb n="4" break="no"/>kkuc cuṭṭi pecātitāka <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> Ātittaṭaṟaṅ kuṭuttu Arai viḷakkum Ivvaḷavum muṭṭik kiṭakka Ivvāṇṭu <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāriyam ceykiṉṟa milaṭṭuruṭaiyāṉāṉa maṉukulamārttā<hi rend="grantha">ṇḍa</hi> muventaveḷān Itu keṭṭu Iraṇṭu tiṟavaraiyum Aḻaittu Ārāntu veḷippa
<lb n="5" break="no"/>ṭa Imanṟāṭi muntevarkku Iṭṭu kuṭutta mutalaṭai yolaiyum Aṟuti kaittiṭṭuṅ kuṭuttu kokāṭṭi kācu koṇṭa tirukoyiluṭaiyārkaḷ cettu poṉamaiyil Avarkaḷil Ūrkiḻān cattiyum pakai matan cūṟṟi
<lb n="6" break="no"/>yaṉaiyum ka<unclear>ṇa</unclear>vati cūṟṟiyaṉaiyum Ipparicu vaittār vaitta <unclear>tan</unclear> mattaik keṭuttu Uṅkaḷ <unclear>pi</unclear>tukkaḷ kācu koṇṭamaiyil Itinu<unclear>k</unclear>ku taṇṭamāka Inṟu munpu ninṟa Immuvirum I viḷakku Oṉṟiṉā<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied> Āṭu toṇṇūṟṟārum niṅkaḷe koṇṭu<note n="207-1">Rest of the inscription is built inside the floor.</note> 
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 32, part 2, no. 91 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2012_01"/></bibl> automatically converted to DHARMA conventions.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2012_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">206-207</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">91</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
