<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 32, part 2, no. 230: original edition by S. Swaminathan</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 230. (A.R. No. 577 of 1920.) UḌAIYĀRGUḌI, CHIDAMBARAM TALUK, SOUTH ARCOT DISTRICT.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName>
						<name>DHARMA team</name>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv32p2i0230</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>On the west wall, central shrine in the Anantēśvara temple. King: Rājakēsarivarman (Rājarāja I)</p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">Year 2: 987 A.D.</hi></p>						

						<p>This inscription opens by stating that a letter <hi rend="italic">(śrīmukham)</hi> was sent by the emperor to the <hi rend="italic">peruṅguṟi-pperumakkaḷ</hi> (members) of Śrī Vīranārayaṇachchaturvēdimaṅgalam (situated) on the northern bank (of the river Kāvēri). According to that Sōman, his younger brothers, Ravidāsan <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Pañchavan brahmādhirājaṉ and his younger brother Paramēśvaraṉ <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Irumuḍich-chōḷa brahmādhirājan, had been found guilty of treason as they murdered Karikāla chōḷa, who took the head of Pāṇḍya. As per the order, the properties (of the above two persons) their brother Malaiyaṉūrāṉ, of their younger brothers and sons, of their wives and other kith and kin were to be taken over by Brahmaśrīrājan of Kōṭṭaiyūr and Chandrasēkharabhaṭṭan of Puḷḷamaṅgalam.</p>						

						<p>The inscription records further that the <hi rend="italic">sabhā</hi> were to arrange in co-operation with these two persons for the sale at current prices of all these lands and to remit the proceeds to the treasury in accordance with the royal order. The order concludes with the statement that it was written by Kurukkāḍi-Kīḻāṉ.</p>						

						<p>Accordingly two and odd <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> of land (as per the old measurement) and six residential houses owned by Ravidāśa (the second traitor), his mother and his sons were seized by the <hi rend="italic">sabhā.</hi> These were purchased for 112 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold from the <hi rend="italic">sabhā</hi> by Bharatan <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Vyāḷagajamallaṉ, the son of Nakkaṉ Aravaṇaiyāṉ of Veṇṇaiyūr. He inturn endowed the same to the Tiruvanantēśvara-bhaṭṭārakar temple at the above village in order to defray ten <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy daily and also a <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> per annum to a brāhmaṇa for supplying drinking water in the <hi rend="italic">maṇḍapa,</hi> before the temple, called <hi rend="italic">Mūvāyirattu-aru-nūṟṟuvaṉ</hi> and also for the daily feeding of sixteen brāhmaṇas, including five <hi rend="italic">Śivayōgins,</hi> at the temple.</p>						

						<p>Published in <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind.,</hi> Vol. XXI pp. 168-170.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2026-03-17" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svastiśrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi> ko<hi rend="grantha">rāja</hi>ke<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>riva<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>r<hi rend="grantha">kk</hi>u yāṇṭu 2 Āvatu vaṭakarai <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m śrī vira</hi>nā<hi rend="grantha">rā</hi>yaṇa<hi rend="grantha"> cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttup peruṅkuṟip perumakkaḷukku <hi rend="grantha">cakra</hi>vatti<hi rend="grantha"> śrī mukha</hi>m pāṇṭiyaṉait talaikoṇṭa karikāla coḻaṉaik koṉṟa <hi rend="grantha">drohi</hi>ka<unclear>ḷā</unclear>ṉa <hi rend="grantha">soma</hi>ṉai <gap reason="lost" quantity="10" unit="character"/> ṟampi
<lb n="2"/>ravi<hi rend="grantha">dāsa</hi>ṉāṉa pañcavan<hi rend="grantha">brahmādhirāja</hi>ṉum Ivaṉ ṟampi <hi rend="grantha">parameśvara</hi>ṉāṉa Irumuṭiccoḻa <hi rend="grantha">brahmādhirāja</hi>ṉum Ivakaḷuṭap piṟanta malaiyaṉūrāṉum Ivakaḷ tampimāru mivakaḷ makkaḷitum Ivar <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇi<unclear>mār</unclear> perālu mi <gap reason="lost" quantity="7" unit="character"/> ṟam ttam
<lb n="3"/>perappaṉmāritu mivakaḷ makkaḷitu mivakaḷu<hi rend="grantha">kk</hi>up piḷḷai kuṭutta māmaṉ māritum tāyoṭuṭap piṟanta (māmaṉ) māmaṉmāritu mivakaḷuṭap piṟanta peṇkaḷai veṭṭāriṉavu mivakaḷ makkaḷai veṭṭāriṉavumāka Ivvaṉaivar mu<unclear>ṟi</unclear>yum nammāṇaikkuriyavāṟu ko
<lb n="4" break="no"/>ṭṭaiyūr <hi rend="grantha">brahmaśrīrāja</hi>ṉum puḷḷamaṅkalattu <hi rend="grantha">candraśekha</hi>ra<hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṭṭaṉaiyum perttantom tāṅkaḷu mivakaḷ kaṇkāṇiyoṭu mivakaḷ coṉṉavāṟu nammāṇaikkuriyavāṟu kuṭiyoṭu kuṭipeṟum vilaikku viṟṟut tālattiṭṭuka Ivai kurukāṭi kiḻāṉeḻutteṉṟu Ipparicu vara I
<lb n="5" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">śrī mukha</hi>ttiṉ meṟppaṭṭa malaiyaṉūrāṉāṉa pāppaṉacceri <hi rend="grantha">re</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">dāsakrama</hi>vittaṉum Ivaṉ makaṉu mivaṉṟāy periyanaṅkaic cāṉiyumim muvaritumāṉa nilam <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> viranārāyaṇa<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu miypaṭākai tevaṉmaṅkalamāṉa paṭṭila nilam <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> viranārāyaṇa<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedi</hi>
<lb n="6" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">maṅgala</hi>ttu <hi rend="grantha">sabh</hi>aiyār pakkal veṇṇaiyūr nāṭṭu veṇṇaiyūruṭaiyāṉ nakkaṉaravaṇaiyāṉāṉa pallava muttaraiyaṉ makaṉ parataṉāṉa <hi rend="grantha">vyāḷagajamal</hi>lappallavaraiyaṉeṉin nilam paḻampaṭi Iraṇṭe mukkāleyorumāvu makamaṉaiyāṟumāka Innilamu mim maṉaiyum nūṟṟorupatti
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ru kaḻañcu poṉ kuṭuttu vilai koṇṭivvūr tiruvanan=te<hi rend="grantha">śva</hi>rattu <hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṭṭārakar koyilile yivvāṭṭai <hi rend="grantha">meṣa</hi>nāyaṟṟu nāyaṟṟukkiḻamai peṟṟa pūraṭṭāti ñāṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>vat Āḷvār koyil muṉpu muvāyirattaṟu nūṟṟuvaṉāṉa nilaiyampalattu taṇṇiraṭṭum <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇaṉoruvaṉukku nica
<lb n="8" break="no"/>tam patiṉāḻi nellu māṭṭai vaṭṭamoru kācum nicatam patiṉaiyvar <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇaruṇpataṟkumāka patiṉāṟu Ivaṟṟu ḷeyyevar <hi rend="grantha">śi</hi>vayo<hi rend="grantha">gi</hi>kaḷuṇṇavum vaiytteṉ Ar<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yaṉ <hi rend="grantha">bhara</hi>taṉāṉa <hi rend="grantha">vyāḷagajamal</hi>lap pallavar<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yaṉeṉ I<hi rend="grantha">dha<unclear>r</unclear>mma</hi>m <hi rend="grantha">rakṣi</hi>kkiṉṟa <hi rend="grantha">mahāsabhai</hi>yār <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> pātaṅkaḷeṉ talaimeliṉa <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> 
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 32, part 2, no. 230 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2012_01"/></bibl> automatically converted to DHARMA conventions.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2012_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">369-370</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">230</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
