<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.6: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 6. ON THE SOUTH WALL, SECOND TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0006</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This and the next inscription, though of different date, are engraved continuously in two sections. No. 6 fills the whole of the first section and part of the first line of the second section.</p>						

						<p>The inscription describes a number of gifts, which were made until the 29th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Rājakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi>, by <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi>, who was the elder sister of <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi> and the queen of <hi rend="bold">Vallavaraiyar Vandyadēvar</hi>. As, according to the large Leyden grant,<note n="68-1">Dr. Burgess' <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey of Southern India</hi>, Vol. IV, p. 207.</note> Rājarāja was the son of Parāntaka II., it is evident that the name of his sister, <hi rend="italic">Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi>, is an abbreviation for <hi rend="italic">Parāntakaṉ magaḷ Kundavaiyār, i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kundavaiyār</hi>, the daughter of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> (II.).</p>						

						<p>Paragraph 2 records a gift of gold to the same two goddesses, who are mentioned in the inscription No. 2.<note n="68-2">See above, page 14.</note> According to paragraph 1, these two images had been set up in the temple of <hi rend="bold">Rājarājēśvara</hi> by <hi rend="bold">Kundavaiyār</hi> herself. The same princess had set up an image of her mother, to which she presented certain ornaments (paragraphs 3 to 5). Other ornaments were given to the image of the god <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi> (paragraphs 6 and 7), which had been set up by king <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi> (paragraph 1), and to his consort (paragraphs 8 and 9), who was one of the two goddesses referred to in paragraph 2. The remainder of the inscription treats of endowments to these two goddesses (paragraph 10), to the image of <hi rend="bold">Poṉmāḷigaittuñjiṉa-dēvar</hi> (paragraph 14), and to the image of the mother of <hi rend="bold">Kundavaiyār</hi> (paragraph 19). These endowments were made in the following manner. Kundavaiyār deposited certain sums of money (<hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>), which were subsequently borrowed on interest by the inhabitants of certain villages from the shrine of <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvara</hi> (paragraph 1), the saint in whose name the money affairs of temples are generally transacted.<note n="68-3">See Vol. I, p. 92, note 6.</note> The interest had to be paid yearly into the treasury of the <hi rend="bold">Rājarājēśvara</hi> temple at <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> either in paddy or in money. In the former case, the interest was three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy<note n="68-4">Compare Vol. I, Nos. 85 and 146.</note> for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, and in the latter 12(1/2) per cent. If it is assumed that the rate of interest was the same in both cases, one <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> would correspond to the value of 24 <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> or 2 <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy. In two instances (paragraphs 18 and 21), money was deposited for purchasing a number of sheep, from the milk of which two private individuals had to supply daily a certain amount of ghee for lamps.<note n="68-5">Compare Vol. I, Nos. 82, 83, 148 and 150.</note> The value of one sheep was reckoned as (1/8) <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>. In paragraphs 14 and 19, the value of various daily requirements is given in measures of paddy; the whole list probably represents the daily wants of a single <hi rend="italic">pujārī</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">First section</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrīḥ</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tirumakaḷ polapperunilaccelviyuntaṉakkey Urimai pūṇṭamai maṉakkoḷakkāntaḷūrccālai kalamaṟuttaruḷi veṅkaināṭuṅkaṅkapāṭiyuntaṭikaipāṭiyum nuḷampapāṭiyuṅkuṭamalaināṭuṅkollamuṅkaliṅkamum muraṭṭeḻil ciṅkaḷar Īḻa<unclear>ma</unclear>ṇṭalamum Iraṭṭapāṭi Eḻarai Ilak<unclear>ka</unclear>mum muṉ<unclear>ṉī</unclear>rppaḻantīvu paṉṉīrāyiramuntiṇṭiṟal veṉṟittaṇṭāṟkoṇṭa taṉṉeḻil vaḷa<unclear>rūḻi</unclear>yuḷellāyāṇṭuntoḻutaka viḷaṅkum yāṇṭey ceḻi<unclear>ya</unclear>raittecu koḷ ko<hi rend="grantha">rājakesari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>mma</hi>rāṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāvatu varai Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār ko<unclear>yi</unclear>lil Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarā<unclear>jad</unclear>e</hi>var tiruttamakkaiyār vallavaraiyar va<hi rend="grantha">ndyade</hi>var <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>viyār Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār Eḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉikaḷ <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśva<unclear>ri</unclear></hi>yārkkum tañcaiviṭaṅkar nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yārkkum poṉmā<unclear>ḷi</unclear>kaittuñciṉa<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varāka Eḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉikkum Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār tammaiyāka Eḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉikkum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var Eḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉi <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi>kkum Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār kuṭutta poṉ Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉuṅkuṭiñaikkallāl niṟai Eṭuttum <hi rend="grantha">ratna</hi>ṅkaḷ caraṭu
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ñcaṭṭamuñceppāṇikaḷum Arakkum piñcum nīkki <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkan</hi> Eṉṉuṅkācukallāl niṟai Eṭuttum Ivarkaḷukku veṇṭum nivantaṅkaḷukku Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār policaiyūṭṭukku vaitta kācu <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>ttiṉiteḻuntaruḷi Iru<unclear>n</unclear>ta <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>para</unclear>masvāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha">mūlabhratya</hi>nā<hi rend="grantha">ki</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha"> caṇḍeśvarar</hi> pa<unclear>k</unclear>kal policaikku Ūrkaḷilār koṇṭa kācum kallil veṭṭiṉa <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied> dakṣi</hi>ṇameruvi<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>ṭa</unclear>ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yārum tañcaiviṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yāruntiruviḻā Eḻu<unclear>n</unclear>taruḷum potu Eṟiyaruḷuntiruvaraṅkaṇiyakkuṭutta poṉ taṇṭavāṇikku kāl māṟṟu nalla poṉ mūvāyirattu Aiññūṟṟukkaḻañcum taṇṭavāṇikku Orumāṟṟuttaṇṇiya poṉ Āyirattu Aiññūṟṟukkaḻañcum Ākappoṉ Aiyyāyirakkaḻañcu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi> Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār tammaiyāka Eḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉikkukkuṭuttaṉa <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">3</supplied></hi> kampi Irupatiṉāl poṉ Aṟukaḻañcey kuṉṟi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">4</supplied></hi> tālimaṇivaṭam Oṉṟu tāli Uṭpaṭappoṉ nāṟkkaḻañcey Āṟu mañcāṭiyuṅkuṉṟi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">5</supplied> dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi>kkukkuṭuttaṉa <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">6</supplied></hi> Ekāvalli Oṉṟikkotta<note n="69-1">Read oṉṟiṟkotta.</note> paḻa<unclear>mu</unclear>ttu Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttum kuṟumuttum Āka muppattaiñcum pavaḻam Iraṇṭum <hi rend="grantha">rājā</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rttam</hi> Iraṇṭum tāḷimpamum paṭukaṇṇuṅkokkuvāyum Uṭaiyatu niṟai nāṟkkaḻañcey Eṭṭu mañcāṭiyum nāṉku māvukku vilai kācu patiṉoṉṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">7</supplied> dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari-</hi> yārkkukkuṭuttaṉa [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">8</supplied></hi> Ekā
<lb n="3" break="no"/>valli Oṉṟiṟkotta paḻamuttu Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttuṅkuṟumuttum Āka muttu muppattaiñcum pavaḻam Iraṇṭum <hi rend="grantha">rājā</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rttam</hi> Iraṇṭum tāḷimpamum paṭukaṇṇuṅkokkuvāyum Uṭai<unclear>ya</unclear>tu niṟai nāṟkaḻañcey Oṉpatu mañcāṭiyuṅkuṉṟikku <unclear>vi</unclear>lai kācu paṉṉiraṇṭu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">9</supplied> dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yāruntañcaiviṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yāruntiruviḻā Eḻuntaruḷum potu tiruamirtukkuntiruppaḷḷittāmattukkuntiruviḷakkeṇṇaikkum Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭum Aḻivukkuppolicaiyūṭṭukku vaitta kācil nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭu muṭiccoḻanāṭṭu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m ja</hi>nanā<hi rend="grantha">thacca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupatteṭṭāvatu pacāṉ mutal kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ mukkuṟuṇi neṟpolicaiyākattañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkāl<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>l <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Aḷakkakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu Irunūṟiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Aḷakkakkaṭava nellu Aiympatiṉ kalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="10"><g type="numeral">10</g></num>*]</hi> nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭu Āvūrkkūṟṟattu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m</hi> Irumputalākiya <hi rend="grantha">ma</hi>nu<hi rend="grantha">kulacūḷāma</hi>ṇi<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupatteṭṭāvatu pacāṉ mutal kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicaiyākattañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār
<lb n="4"/>perum paṇṭārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Aḷakkakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu nūṟiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Aḷakkak<unclear>ka</unclear>ṭava nellu Irupattaiṅkalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="11"><g type="numeral">10</g> 1</num>*]</hi> keraḷāntakavaḷanāṭṭu Uṟaiyūrkkūṟṟattu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m rājāśra</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">cca<unclear>tu</unclear>rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāvatu mutal kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicaiyākattañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Aḷakkakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu Aiññūṟiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Aḷakkakkaṭava nellu nūṟṟirupattaiṅkalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="12"><g type="numeral">10</g> 2</num>*]</hi> nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭukkiḻārkkūṟṟattupperumilaṭṭur Ūrār yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāvatu mutal kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicaiyākattañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājī<unclear>śva</unclear>ram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl Aḷakkakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu Irunūṟiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Aḷakkakkaṭava nellu Aiympatiṉ kalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="13"><g type="numeral">10</g> 3</num>*]</hi> poṉmāḷikaittuñciṉa<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">-</hi> rāka Eḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉikkuttiruvamutukkuppotu paḻaarici I<unclear>ru</unclear>nāḻi Āka Iraṇṭu potaikkuppaḻaarici nāṉāḻikku nellukkuṟuṇi Irunāḻiyum neyyamutu potu Iruceviṭaraiy<unclear>ā</unclear>ka Āḻakkukku nellu nāṉāḻiyum kaṟia
<lb n="5" break="no"/>mutu potu mūṉṟākakkaṟiamutu Āṟukku nellu Aṟunāḻiyum paruppuamutu potu Uḻakku Āka Urikku nellu nāḻi Uriyum caṟkkaraiamutu potu kaiycāka Araippalattukku nellu nāḻi Uriyum porikkaṟiamutukku ney potu Oṉṟe kāṟceviṭāka ney Iru<unclear>ce</unclear>viṭaraikku nellu Irunāḻiyum vāḻaippaḻaamutu potu Oṉṟāka Iraṇṭukku nellu nāḻiyum tayiramutu potu Uri Āka nāḻikku ne<unclear>l</unclear>lu muṉṉāḻiyum kaṭukukkum miḷakukkum Uppukkum nellu Uri Āḻakkum viṟakakku<note n="70-1">Read viṟakukku.</note> nellu nāṉāḻiyum Aṭaikkāyamutu pākkuppotu nālākappākku Eṭṭum veḷḷilaiamutu muppattiraṇṭukkum nellu nāḻiyum Ākappoṉakappaḻanellu Uṭpaṭa nicatam nelluttūṇi Irunāḻi Uri Āḻakku Āka Orāṭṭaikku nellu nūṟṟu Irupattu Oṉpatiṉ kalaṉey Irutūṇippatakku Orunāḻiyum Eṟṟam nellukkuṟuṇi Eḻunāḻiyum Āka nellu nūṟṟu muppatiṉ kalattukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ tañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Āṭava<unclear>l</unclear>lāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl kācu Oṉṟukku mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicaiyāka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val celuttuvataṟkku vaitta kācil vaṭakarai<hi rend="grantha">rājendra-</hi> ciṅkavaḷanāṭṭu poykaināṭṭukkaṇṭarā<hi rend="grantha">dityacca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāva<unclear>tu</unclear> mutal kācu O
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicai Ākattañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Aḷakkakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu Aiññūṟṟu Irupatiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Aḷakkakka<unclear>ṭava</unclear> nellu nūṟṟu muppatiṉ kalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="14"><g type="numeral">10</g> 4</num>*]</hi> Ivarkke cārttum tirupparicaṭṭattukkukkācu Irupattāṟuntirunamaṉikai nālukkukkācu Iraṇṭun<unclear>tiru</unclear>voṟṟāṭai nālukkukkācu Iraṇṭuntirumeṟkkaṭṭi nālukkukkācu Iraṇṭuntiruppāvāṭai patiṉāṟukkukkācu nāluntiruppaḷḷittāmattukku nicatam Akkam Araiyāka Orāṭṭaikku Akkam nūṟṟu Eṇpatu Ivai kācu Oṉṟukku Akkam paṉṉiraṇṭākakkācu patiṉaiñcum Ākakkācu Aiympattoṉṟukkukkācu Oṉṟukkuttiṅkaḷ Araikkāl Akkappalicai Āka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val celuttuvataṟkku vaitta kācil <hi rend="grantha">rājendra-</hi> ciṅkavaḷanāṭṭuttaṉiyūr <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vīranārāyaṇa<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāvatu mutal kāciṉ vāyttiṅkaḷ Araikkāl Akkappolicaiyāka Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟuntañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār paṇṭāratitu<note n="71-1">Read paṇṭārattu .</note> <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val policai Iṭakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu nūṟṟuttoṇṇūṟṟu Āṟiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Iṭakkaṭava kācu Irupattu nālarai <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="15"><g type="numeral">10</g> 5</num>*] rājendra</hi>ciṅkavaḷanāṭṭuttaṉiyūr <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>parāntaka<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedi</hi>
<lb n="7" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">maṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāvatu mutal kāciṉ vāyttiṅkaḷ <unclear>Araikk</unclear>āl Akkappolicai Āka Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟuntañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār paṇṭārattu <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val policai Iṭak<unclear>ka</unclear>ṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu nūṟṟu Orupattiraṇṭiṉāl <unclear>Ā</unclear>ṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Iṭakkaṭava kācu patiṉālu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="16"><g type="numeral">10</g> 6</num>*]</hi> nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭukkiḻārkkūṟṟattu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m</hi> cū<unclear>la</unclear>maṅkalattu <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yār yāṇ<unclear>ṭu</unclear> Irupattoṉpatāvatu mutal kāciṉ vāyttiṅkaḷ Araikkāl Akka<unclear>p</unclear>policaiyā<unclear>ka</unclear> Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟuntañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār paṇṭārattu <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val policai Iṭakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu nūṟiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum <unclear>Iṭa</unclear>kkaṭava kācu paṉṉiraṇṭarai <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="17"><g type="numeral">10</g> 7</num>*]</hi> Ivarkkey <hi rend="grantha">sandhi</hi>viḷakkuppattukku nicatam ney Uḻakk<unclear>ā</unclear>ka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Erippatarkku veṇṭum Āṭu toṇṇūṟṟu Āṟukkukkācu Oṉṟukku Āṭu muṉṟāka vaitta kācil pāṭṭattāḷaṉ Āccaṉ Aṭikaḷ koṇṭa kācu muppattiraṇṭiṉāl nicatam Aṭṭakkaṭava ney Uḻakku <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="18"><g type="numeral">10</g> 8</num>*]</hi> Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var tiruttamakkaiyār vallavaraiyar va<hi rend="grantha">ndyade</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">r mahāde</hi>viyār Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār tammai Āka ḻuntaruḷuvitta tirumeṉikkuttiruamurtukkuppotu paḻaarici Irunāḻi Āka Iraṇṭu potaikku paḻaarici nānāḻikku nellukkuṟuṇi Irunāḻiyum neyamutu potu Iruceviṭarai Āka Āḻak<unclear>ku</unclear>
<lb n="8" break="no"/>kku nellu nāṉāḻiyuṅkaṟiamutu potu mūṉṟākakkaṟiamutu Āṟukku nellu <unclear>Aṟunāḻiyu</unclear>m paruppuamutu potu Uḻakku Āka Urikku nellu nāḻi Uriyum caṟkkaraiamutu potu kaiycāka Araippalattukku nellu nāḻi Uriyum porikkaṟiamutukku ney po<unclear>tu O</unclear>ṉṟey kāl ceviṭāka Iruceviṭaraikku nellu Irunāḻiyum vāḻaippaḻaamutu potu Oṉṟāka Iraṇṭukku nellu nāḻiyum ta<unclear>yira</unclear>mutu potu Uri Āka nāḻikku nellu muṉṉāḻiyum kaṭukukkum miḷakukkum Uppukkum nellu Uri Āḻakkum viṟakukku nellu nāṉāḻiyum Aṭaik<unclear>k</unclear>āyamutu pākkuppotu nālāka Eṭṭum veḷḷilaiamutu muppattiraṇṭukkum nellu nāḻiyum Ākappoṉakappaḻanellu Uṭpaṭa nicatam ne<unclear>l</unclear>luttūṇi Irunāḻi Uri Āḻakku Āka Orāṭṭaikku nellu nūṟṟu Irupattu Oṉpatiṉ kalaṉey Irutūṇippatakku Orunāḻiyum Eṟṟam nellukkuṟuṇi Eḻunāḻiyum Āka nellu nūṟṟu muppatiṉ kalattukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ tañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl kācu Oṉṟukku mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicai Āka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val celuttuvataṟkku vaitta kācil nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭukkarampaināṭṭukkuntavainallūr Ūrā<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied> yāṇṭu Irupattoṉ(pata)patāvatu mutal kācu Oṉṟukku Ā
<lb n="9" break="no"/>ṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicaiyākattañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrāja<unclear>rā</unclear>jīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇ<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ārattey Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉum marakkālāl <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Aḷakkakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu Aiññūṟṟu Irupatiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Aḷakkakka<unclear>ṭa</unclear>va nellu nūṟṟu muppatiṉ kalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="19"><g type="numeral">10</g> 9</num>*]</hi> I<unclear>var</unclear>kkey cārttuntirup<unclear>pa</unclear>ricaṭṭattukku Āṭṭ<unclear>ai va</unclear>ṭṭaṉ kācu muppattāṟuntirunamaṉikai nālukkukkācu Iraṇ<unclear>ṭun</unclear>tiruvoṟṟāṭai <unclear>nā</unclear>lukkukkācu Iraṇṭuntiruppāvāṭai patiṉāṟukkukkācu nāluntirumeṟkkaṭṭi <unclear>nā</unclear>lukkukkācu Iraṇṭuntiruppaḷḷittāmattu<unclear>k</unclear>ku nicatam Akkam Arai Āka Orāṭṭaikku Akkam nūṟ<unclear>ṟu</unclear> Eṇpatu Ivai kācu Oṉṟukku A<unclear>k</unclear>kam paṉṉira<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭāka va<unclear>nta</unclear> kācu patiṉaiñcum Āka Orāṭṭaikkukkācu Aṟupattoṉṟukkukkācu Oṉṟukkuttiṅkaḷ Araikkāl Akkappalicaiyāka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val celuttuvataṟkku vait<unclear>ta</unclear> kācil <hi rend="grantha">rājendra</hi>ciṅkavaḷanāṭṭuttaṉiyūr <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>parāntaka<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār yāṇṭu Irupattoṉpatāvatu mutal kāciṉ vāyttiṅkaḷ Araikkāl Akka<unclear>p</unclear>policaiyāka Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟuntañ<unclear>cā</unclear>vūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya-</hi> val policai Iṭakkaṭavarkaḷākakkoṇṭa kācu nāṉūṟṟu Eṇpatteṭṭiṉāl Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Iṭuṅkācu Aṟupattoṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="20">2 <g type="numeral">10</g></num>*]</hi> Ivarkke<unclear>y</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">sandhi-</hi> viḷakkuppattukku nicatam ney
</p>

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Second section</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/>Uḻakku Āka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Erippatarkku veṇṭum Āṭu toṇṇūṟṟāṟukkukkācu Oṉṟukku Āṭu <unclear>mū</unclear>ṉṟāka vaitta kācil pāṭṭattāḷaṉ kaliyaṉ <unclear>pa</unclear>rataṉ koṇṭa kācu muppattiraṇṭiṉāl nicatam Aṭṭakkaṭava ney Uḻakku <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="21">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 1</num>*]</hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. Hail ! Prosperity ! Until the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Rājakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>, who,—while (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) heart rejoiced, that, like the goddess of fortune, the goddess of the great earth had become his wife,—in his life of growing strength, during which, having been pleased to cut the vessel (<hi rend="italic">in</hi>) the hall (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kāndaḷūr</hi>, he conquered by his army, which was victorious in great battles, <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgai-nāḍu, Gaṅga-pāḍi, Taḍigai-pāḍi, Nuḷamba-pāḍi, Kuḍamalai-nāḍu, Kollam, Kaliṅgam, Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">which was the country</hi>) of the <hi rend="bold">Śiṅgaḷas</hi> who possessed rough strength, the seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-pāḍi</hi>, and twelve thousand ancient islands of the sea,—deprived the <hi rend="bold">Śeṛiyas</hi> of their splendour, while (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) was resplendent (<hi rend="italic">to such a degree</hi>) that (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) was worthy to be worshipped everywhere;—<hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi> gave to the images (<hi rend="italic">tiru-mēṉi) (of the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, and (<hi rend="italic">of the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viṭaṅkar</hi>,—which (<hi rend="italic">two images</hi>) had been set up in the temple, (<hi rend="italic">called</hi>) the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>, by <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the venerable elder sister of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the great queen of <hi rend="bold">Vallavaraiyar Vandyadēvar</hi>,—to the image which had been set up to <hi rend="bold">Poṉmāḷigaittuñjiṉa-dēvar</hi>,<note n="72-1"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the god who was sleeping in the golden palace.’</note> to the image which <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi> had set up to her mother, and to the image (<hi rend="italic">of the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, which had been set up by the lord. <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>,—gold which was weighed by the stone (<hi rend="italic">used in</hi>) the city (<hi rend="italic">kuḍiñai-kal</hi>) and called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>, and jewels (<hi rend="italic">ratna</hi>) which were weighed by the jewel weight (<hi rend="italic">kāśu-kal</hi>) called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkaṉ</hi>,—excluding the threads (<hi rend="italic">śaraḍu</hi>); the frames (<hi rend="italic">śaṭṭam</hi>), the copper nails (<hi rend="italic">śeppāṇi</hi>), the lac (<hi rend="italic">arakku</hi>) and the <hi rend="italic">piñju</hi>. For the expenses (<hi rend="italic">nibandha</hi>),<note n="73-1">From paragraphs 10 to 21 it appears, that the term <hi rend="italic">nibandha</hi> included food, clothing, garlands, and oil for lamps.</note> which are required by these (<hi rend="italic">gods</hi>), <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi> deposited money (<hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>), to be put out to interest (<hi rend="italic">poliśai). (The amount of this gold, these jewels, these deposits</hi>) and the money, which the inhabitants of (<hi rend="italic">certain</hi>) villages had received on interest from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvara</hi>, who is the first servant<note n="73-2"><hi rend="italic">Mūlabhṛitya</hi> is a synonym of <hi rend="italic">Ādidāsa</hi>, the usual title of Chaṇḍēśvara; see Vol. I, p. 116, note 3.</note> of the supreme lord (<hi rend="italic">paramasvāmin</hi>), who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,—was engraved on stone (<hi rend="italic">as follows):</hi>—</p>

<p>2. For decorating the sacred hall (<hi rend="italic">tiruvaraṅgu</hi>),<note n="73-3"><ta>araṅku</ta> or <ta>araṅkam</ta> is a <hi rend="italic">tadbhava</hi> of the Sanskrit <de>raṅga</de>. Compare an inscription of Kṛishṇarāya of Vijayanagara, which records the building of a <hi rend="italic">raṅga-maṇḍapa</hi> in connection with a temple of Śiva; <hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi>, pp. 363 and 370.</note> which (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, and (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, are pleased to enter, when they are carried in procession (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) the sacred festival (<hi rend="italic">tiru-viṛā),—(she</hi>) gave three thousand five hundred <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> of gold, which was a quarter superior in fineness to the (<hi rend="italic">gold standard called) daṇḍavāṇi</hi>, and one thousand five hundred <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> of gold, which was one (<hi rend="italic">degree</hi>) inferior in fineness to the <hi rend="italic">daṇḍavāṇi</hi>,—altogether, five thousand <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>3. To the image, which <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi> had set up to her mother, (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) gave:—</p>

<p>4. Twenty ear-rings (<hi rend="italic">kambi</hi>), consisting of six <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>5. One string of beads for the marriage-badge (<hi rend="italic">tāli-maṇi-vaḍum), (consisting of</hi>) four <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, six <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi> of gold,—including the marriage-badge (<hi rend="italic">itself</hi>).</p>

<p>6. To (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi> (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) gave:—</p>

<p>7. One ornament consisting of a single string,<note n="73-4"><hi rend="italic">Ēkāvalli</hi> is a corruption of the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">ēkāvali</hi>.</note> on which were strung thirty-five old pearls,—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, roundish pearls (<hi rend="italic">aṉuvaṭṭam</hi>), polished pearls (<hi rend="italic">oppu-muttu</hi>) and small pearls (<hi rend="italic">kuṟu-mūttu</hi>),—two corals (<hi rend="italic">pavaṛam</hi>), two lapis lazuli (<hi rend="italic">rājāvarta), (one) tāḷimbam,<note n="73-5">Compare the Kanarese and Telugu <hi rend="italic">dāḷimba</hi>, which is a <hi rend="italic">tadbhava</hi> from the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">dāḍima</hi>, ‘the pomegranate.’</note> (one) paḍugaṇ</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kokkuvāy</hi>, and which weighed four <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, eight <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and four tenths, corresponding to a value of eleven <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>8. To (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) gave:—</p>

<p>9. One ornament consisting of a single string, on which were strung thirty-five old pearls,—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, roundish pearls, polished pearls and small pearls,—two corals, two lapis lazuli, (<hi rend="italic">one) tāḷimbam, (one) paḍugaṇ</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kokkuvāy</hi>, and which weighed four <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, nine <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi>, corresponding to a value of twelve <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>10. For the sacred food (<hi rend="italic">tiru-amirdu</hi>), temple-garlands (<hi rend="italic">tiruppaḷḷittāmam</hi>), oil for the sacred lamps, and other expenses (<hi rend="italic">aṛivu</hi>), which are required, when (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, and (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, are carried in procession (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) the sacred festival, (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) deposited money, to be put out to interest. Having agreed to measure from (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi><note n="74-1">According to the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Tamoul-Français</hi>, <ta>pacāṉ, pacāṉam</ta> or <ta>picāṉam</ta> is a kind of coarse paddy which ripens late.</note> in the twenty-eighth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury (<hi rend="italic">bhaṇḍāra</hi>) of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi>) called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>,—the members of the assembly (<hi rend="italic">sabhā</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Jananāthachaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Muḍichchōṛa-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to measure every year fifty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy for the two hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>), which they have received out of (<hi rend="italic">that money</hi>).</p>

<p>11. Having agreed to measure from (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the twenty-eighth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi>) of paddy per year as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Irumbudal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Manukulachūḷāmaṇi-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Āvūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to measure every year twenty-five <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy for the one hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received.</p>

<p>12. Having agreed to measure from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Rājāśraya-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Uṟaiyūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷāntakavaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to measure every year one hundred and twenty-five <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy for the five hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received.</p>

<p>13. Having agreed to measure from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>) three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>,—the villagers of <hi rend="bold">Perumilaṭṭūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Kiṛār-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to measure every year fifty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy for the two hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received.</p>

<p>14. Having agreed to measure from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi>) called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Gaṇḍarādityachaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Poygai-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Vaḍakarai-Rājēndrasiṁha-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to measure every year one hundred and thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy for the five hundred and twenty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received out of the money, which (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) had deposited (<hi rend="italic">under the condition</hi>), that every year, as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy should be measured as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi> for (<hi rend="italic">the requirements of</hi>) the image, which had been set up to <hi rend="bold">Poṉmāḷigaittuñjiṉa-dēvar</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">One) kuṟuṇi</hi>) and two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>) of paddy (<hi rend="italic">are required</hi>) for (<hi rend="italic">conversion into</hi>) four <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of old rice (<hi rend="italic">to be used</hi>) for the sacred food (<hi rend="italic">tiruvamudu</hi>) at both times (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>),—two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>) of old rice (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; four <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) āṛakku</hi><note n="74-2">The usual form of this word is <hi rend="italic">āṛākku</hi>.</note> of ghee (<hi rend="italic">ney-amudu</hi>),—two <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> and a half (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time;<note n="75-1">Accordingly, a <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> was equal to (1/6) <hi rend="italic">āṛakku</hi>, one of which is again equal to (1/8) <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>; see page 48, note 5.</note> six <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for six dishes of curry (<hi rend="italic">kaṟi-amudu</hi>),— three dishes of curry (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of pulse (<hi rend="italic">paruppu-amudu),—(one) uṛakku (being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of paddy for half a <hi rend="italic">palam</hi>) of sugar (<hi rend="italic">śaṟkarai-amudu),—(one) kaiśu (being used</hi>) each time;<note n="75-2">Accordingly, a <hi rend="italic">kaiśu</hi> was equal to (1/4) <hi rend="italic">palam</hi>.</note> two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for two <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> and a half of ghee, to prepare fried curry (<hi rend="italic">porikkaṟi-amudu</hi>),— one and a quarter <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi>) of ghee (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi>) of paddy for two plantains (<hi rend="italic">vāṛaippaṛa-amudu</hi>),—one (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; three <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> of curds (<hi rend="italic">tayir-amudu),—(one) uri (being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) āṛakku</hi> of paddy for mustard (<hi rend="italic">kaḍugu</hi>), pepper (<hi rend="italic">miḷagu</hi>) and salt (<hi rend="italic">uppu</hi>); four <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for fire-wood (<hi rend="italic">viṟagu</hi>); and (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> of paddy for eight areca-nuts (<hi rend="italic">aḍaikkāy-amudu</hi>),—four nuts (<hi rend="italic">pākku) (being used</hi>) each time,—and for thirty-two betel-leaves (<hi rend="italic">veḷḷilai-amudu</hi>);—altogether,—including the old paddy for the boiled rice (<hi rend="italic">pōṉagam),—<note n="75-3">This refers to the 1 <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> and 2 <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy, which are mentioned first in the list.</note> (one) tūṇi</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi, (one) uri</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) āṛakku</hi> of paddy every day,<note n="75-4"><ta>nicatam</ta> is probably a corruption of <de>nityam;</de> see Vol. I, page 116, note 6.</note> one hundred and twenty-nine <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">tūṇi, (one) padakku</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy every year, or,—(<hi rend="italic">including</hi>) the excess (<hi rend="italic">ēṟṟam</hi>) of (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṟuṇi</hi> and seven <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy,—one hundred and thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy.<note n="75-5">The calculation of the amount of paddy, which was to be supplied daily, is as follows:— <table>[C1]Paddy. [C1]— [C1]<hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi>. [C2]<hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi>. [C3]<hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>. [C4]<hi rend="italic">uri</hi>. [C5]<hi rend="italic">āṛakku</hi>. [C1]For conversion into 4 <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of husked rice [C2].. [C3]1 [C4]2 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For 1 <hi rend="italic">āṛakku</hi> of ghee [C2].. [C3].. [C4]4 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For 6 dishes of curry [C2].. [C3].. [C4]6 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For 1 <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of pulse [C2].. [C3].. [C4]1 [C5]1 [C6].. [C1]For (1/2) <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of sugar [C2].. [C3].. [C4]1 [C5]1 [C6].. [C1]For 2(1/2) <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> of ghee [C2].. [C3].. [C4]2 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For 2 plantains [C2].. [C3].. [C4]1 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For 1 <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of curds [C2].. [C3].. [C4]3 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For mustard, pepper and salt [C2].. [C3].. [C4].. [C5]1 [C6]1 [C1]For fire-wood [C2].. [C3].. [C4]4 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]For 8 areca-nuts and 32 betel-leaves [C2].. [C3].. [C4]1 [C5].. [C6].. [C1]Total [C2]1 [C3].. [C4]2 [C5]1 [C6]1</table> If the amount of paddy required per year is divided by this total, we find that the year was reckoned as consisting of 360 days. The excess (<hi rend="italic">ēṟṟam</hi>) was evidently added in order to simplify accounts by fixing a round number, thus:— <table>[C1]—[C2]<hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>. [C3]<hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi>. [C4]<hi rend="italic">padakku</hi>. [C5]<hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi>. [C6]<hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>. [C1]Paddy required per year. [C2]129 [C3]2 [C4]1 [C5].. [C6]1 [C1]Excess [C2].. [C3].. [C4].. [C5]1 [C6]7 [C1]Total [C2]130 [C3].. [C4].. [C5].. [C6]..</table></note> </p>

<p>15. For realizing fifty-one <hi rend="italic">kāśu,—<note n="75-6">These 51 <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> are made up of 24(1/2) <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> in paragraph 15, 14 in paragraph 16, and 12(1/2) in paragraph 17.</note> viz</hi>., twenty-six <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for the sacred cloth<note n="75-7"><ta>paricaṭṭam</ta> is perhaps the same as <ta>parivaṭṭam</ta>.</note> to be worn by this (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>),<note n="75-8">This refers to the image of Poṉmāḷigaittuñjiṉa-dēvar, which was mentioned in the preceding paragraph.</note> two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for four sacred curtains,<note n="75-9"><hi rend="italic">Namaṉigai</hi> is probably a further corruption of <hi rend="italic">yamaṉigai</hi> (Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">yavanikā</hi>). Compare <ta>namaṉ</ta> (or <ta>ñamaṉ</ta>) for <ta>yamaṉ</ta> (Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">Yama</hi>).</note> two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for four sacred towels (<hi rend="italic">tiruvoṟṟāḍai</hi>), two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>) for four sacred canopies (<hi rend="italic">tiru-mēṟkaṭṭi</hi>), four <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for sixteen sacred cloths on which rice is offered (<hi rend="italic">tiruppāvāḍai</hi>), and fifteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>) for temple-garlands (<hi rend="italic">tiruppaḷḷittāmam</hi>), at the rate of half an <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per day or one hundred and eighty <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per year,—<note n="76-1">As in the preceding paragraph, the year is reckoned as consisting of 360 days.</note> twelve <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> being reckoned as one <hi rend="italic">kāśu,—(she</hi>) deposited money (<hi rend="italic">under the condition</hi>) that, as long as the moon and the sun endure, one eighth <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per month should be paid as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.<note n="76-2">As an <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> (Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">aksha</hi> ?) is (1/12) <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, the rate of interest comes to 12(1/2) per cent per annum. In the present case, the result is 24(1/2) out of 196 <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, as stated at the end of the paragraph.</note> Having agreed to pay every year from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, one eighth <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per month as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Vīranārāyaṇa-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a free village (<hi rend="italic">? taṉiyūr</hi>) in <hi rend="bold">Rājēndrasiṁha-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to pay every year twentyfour and a half <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for the one hundred and ninety-six <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received out of (<hi rend="italic">that money</hi>).</p>

<p>16. Having agreed to pay every year from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, one eighth <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per month as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Parāntaka-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a free village in <hi rend="bold">Rājēndrasiṁhavaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to pay every year fourteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for the one hundred and twelve <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received.</p>

<p>17. Having agreed to pay every year from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, one eighth <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per month as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Śū[la]maṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Kiṟār-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to pay every year twelve and a half <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for the one hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received.</p>

<p>18. <hi rend="bold">Pāṭṭattāḷaṉ Āchchaṉ Aḍigaḷ</hi> has to pour out daily (<hi rend="italic">one) uṛakku</hi> of ghee for the thirty-two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which he has received out of the money, which (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) had deposited for (<hi rend="italic">purchasing</hi>),—at the rate of three sheep for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>,—ninety-six sheep, (<hi rend="italic">the milk of</hi>) which is required (<hi rend="italic">for preparing ghee</hi>), in order to keep ten twilight lamps (<hi rend="italic">saṁdhi-viḷakku</hi>) burning for this (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>),<note n="76-3">See page 75, note 8.</note> as long as the moon and the sun endure, at the rate of (<hi rend="italic">one) uṛakku</hi> of ghee per day.</p>

<p>19. Having agreed to measure from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>,—the villagers of <hi rend="bold">Kundavai-nallūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Karambai-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to measure every year one hundred and thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy for the five hundred and twenty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received out of the money, which (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) had deposited (<hi rend="italic">under the condition</hi>), that every year, as long as the moon and the sun endure, three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy should be measured as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi> for (<hi rend="italic">the requirements of</hi>) the image, which <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi>,—(<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the venerable elder sister of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the great queen of <hi rend="bold">Vallavaraiyar Vandyadēvar</hi>,—had set up to her mother. (<hi rend="italic">One) kuṟuṇi</hi> and two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy (<hi rend="italic">are required</hi>) for (<hi rend="italic">conversion into</hi>) four <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of old rice (<hi rend="italic">to be used</hi>) for the sacred food (<hi rend="italic">tiru-amurdu</hi>) at both times (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>),—two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of old rice (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; four <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) āṛakku</hi> of ghee,—two <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> and a half (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; six <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>) of paddy for six dishes of curry,—three dishes of curry (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of pulse,—(<hi rend="italic">one) uṛakku (being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of paddy for half a <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of sugar,—(<hi rend="italic">one) kaiśu (being used</hi>) each time; two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy for two <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> and a half of ghee, to prepare fried curry,—one and a quarter <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu (being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> of paddy for two plantains,—one (<hi rend="italic">being used</hi>) each time; three <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>) of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi> of curds,—(<hi rend="italic">one) uri (being used</hi>) each time; (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">one) āṛakku</hi>) of paddy for mustard, pepper and salt; four <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi>) of paddy for fire-wood; and (<hi rend="italic">one) nāṛi</hi>) of paddy for eight areca-nuts,—four (<hi rend="italic">nuts being used</hi>) each time,—and for thirty-two betel-leaves;—altogether,—including the old paddy for the boiled rice,—(<hi rend="italic">one) tūṇi</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">nāṛi, (one) uri</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) āṛakku</hi> of paddy every day, one hundred and twenty-nine <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">tūṇi, (one) padakku</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy every year, or,—(<hi rend="italic">including</hi>) the excess of (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṟuṇi</hi> and seven <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> of paddy,—one hundred and thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy.</p>

<p>20. For realizing sixty-one <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> every year,—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, thirty-six <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> every year for the sacred cloth to be worn by this (<hi rend="italic">goddess</hi>),<note n="77-1">This refers to the image of the mother of Kundavaiyār, which was mentioned in the preceding paragraph.</note> two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for four sacred curtains, two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for four sacred towels, four <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for sixteen sacred cloths on which rice is offered, two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for four sacred canopies, and fifteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for temple-garlands, at the rate of half an <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per day or one hundred and eighty <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per year,—twelve <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> being reckoned as one <hi rend="italic">kāśu,—(she</hi>) deposited money (<hi rend="italic">under the condition</hi>) that, as long as the moon and the sun endure, one eighth <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per month should be paid as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>. Having agreed to pay every year from the twenty-ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure; one eighth <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> per month as interest for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the large treasury of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>,—the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Parāntaka-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a free village in <hi rend="bold">Rājēndrasiṁha-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have to pay every year sixty-one <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for the four hundred and eighty-eight <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received out of (<hi rend="italic">that money</hi>).</p>

<p>21. <hi rend="bold">Pāṭṭattāḷaṉ Kaliyaṉ [Pa]radaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Bharata) has to pour out daily (<hi rend="italic">one) uṛakku</hi> of ghee for the thirty-two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>), which he has received out of the money, which (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) had deposited for (<hi rend="italic">purchasing</hi>),—at the rate of three sheep for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>,—ninety-six sheep, (<hi rend="italic">the milk of</hi>) which is required (<hi rend="italic">for preparing ghee</hi>), in order to keep ten twilight lamps burning for this (<hi rend="italic">goddess</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, at the rate of (<hi rend="italic">one) urakku</hi>) of ghee per day.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.6 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">68-77</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">6</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
