<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 2.73: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">II.—INSCRIPTIONS OF THE PALLAVA DYNASTY. No. 73. KASAKUDI PLATES OF NANDIVARMAN PALLAVAMALLA.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0073</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>On the 30th April 1891, Professor Julien Vinson, of Paris, was good enough to send me a reprint<note>The pages are numbered 433 to 469.</note> of his paper <hi rend="italic">Spe4cimen de Pale4ographie Tamoule</hi>, which contains an analysis of, and extracts from, the subjoined copper-plate inscription. The original plates had been discovered in 1879 at <hi rend="bold">Kaśākūḍi</hi>, 4 kilometres from Kāraikkāl (Karikal),<note>On copper coins which bear the name of this place in Tamil characters, see <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XXI, p. 327. See also p. 295 above, note 2.</note> by M. Jules de la Fon, of Pondicherry. Professor Vinson's paper, which is based on a tracing prepared by M. de la Fon, convinced me of the importance of the inscription and induced me to apply through Government to His Excellency the Governor of the French Settlements in India for a loan of the original plates. This request was most graciously and promptly complied with. After I had transcribed the plates and prepared impressions of them, they were returned to their present owner.</p>						
                            <p>The Kaśākūḍi copper-plates, eleven in number, are strung on a ring. On this is soldered the royal seal, with the figure of a bull which faces the left and is surmounted by a <hi rend="italic">liṅga</hi>. The bull was the crest of the Pallavas,<note>See verses 9 and 24 of this inscription, and Vol. I, p. 23, note 2.</note> while their banner bore the figure of Śiva's club (<hi rend="italic">khaṭvāṅga)</hi>.<note>See verse 24, and Vol. I, p. 146.</note> The Grantha and Tamil characters of the inscription resemble those of the <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> plates (Vol. I, No. 151). The major portion of the inscription is in the Sanskrit language (lines 1 to 104). The particulars of the grant are repeated, with considerable additions, in the Tamil language (ll. 104 to 133). The concluding portion of the inscription is again in Sanskrit (ll. 133 to 138), with a short parenthetical note in Tamil (l. 137).</p>						
                            
                            <p>The immediate object of the inscription is to record the grant of a village, made in the 22nd year of the reign (ll. 80 and 105) of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> (verses 27 and 30, and l. 79). As in other Pallava copper-plate inscriptions, the grant proper is preceded by a panegyrical account of the king's ancestors, which adds a large number of new details to our knowledge of the Pallava history. After nine benedictory verses, the author names the following mythical ancestors of the Pallava dynasty:—</p>				
                            <p><!--What follows is a gealogical table-->Brahmā (v. 10).  Aṅgiras (11).  Bṛihaspati (12).  Śaṁyu (13).  Bharadvāja (14).  Drōṇa (15).  Aśvatthāman (16).  Pallava (17).  Aśōkavarman (19).</p>						
                            
                            <p>This last king can scarcely be considered a historical person, but appears to be a modification of the ancient Maurya king <hi rend="bold">Aśōka</hi>. Then follows a passage in prose, which informs us that, after this Aśōkavarman, there ruled a number of other Pallava kings, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">[S]kandavarman, Kal[i]ndavarman, Kāṇagōpa, Vishṇugōpa, Vīrakū[r]cha, Vīrasiṁha, Siṁhavarman, Vishṇusiṁha</hi> and others (l. 48 f.). Some of these names actually occur in the inscriptions of that ancient branch of the Pallavas, whose grants are dated from <hi rend="bold">Palakkada, Daśanapura</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kāñchīpura</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Skandavarman, Siṁhavarman, Vishṇugōpavarman</hi>,<note>Dr. Fleet's <hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, p. 16. Vishṇugōpa of Kāñchī was a contemporary of Samudragupta (<hi rend="italic">Gupta Inscriptions</hi>, p. 13). A Prākṛit grant of Śiva-Skandavarman, a Pallava king of Kāñchī, has been published by Dr. Bu7hler (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. I, p. 2 ff.). Another Prākṛit grant (<hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. IX, p. 100 ff.) belongs to the reign of Vijaya-Skandavarman. An archaic Chōḷa inscription at Tirukkaṛukkuṉṟam mentions Skandaśishya, who was probably a Pallava king (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 277).</note> and <hi rend="bold">Vīrakōrchavarman</hi>.<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. I, p. 397 f.</note> The <hi rend="bold">Amarāvatī</hi> pillar-inscription (Vol. I, No. 32) mentions two kings named <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavarman</hi>. But the order in which these names are enumerated, is completely different in each of the three available sources for the history of the early Pallavas, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the Amarāvatī pillar, the early copper-inscriptions, and the prose introduction of the Kaśākūḍi plates. For this reason, and on account of the summary manner in which the early kings are referred to by the author of the Kaśākūḍi inscription, it is a mistake to derive a regular pedigree from the latter, as was done by Professor Vinson (<hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>., p. 453); and it must be rather concluded that, at the time of Nandivarman, nothing was known of the predecessors of Siṁhavishṇu, but the names of some of them, and that the order of their succession, and their relation to each other and to the subsequent line of Siṁhavishṇu, were then entirely forgotten.</p>						                            
                            <p>With verse 20 we enter on historical ground. The list of kings from Siṁhavishṇu to the immediate predecessor of Nandivarman agrees with the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates of Nandivarman Pallavamalla (No. 74). <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> appears to have borne the surname <hi rend="bold">Avanisiṁha</hi>, and is stated to have defeated the <hi rend="bold">Malaya, Kaḷabhra, Mālava, Chōḷa, Pāṇḍya, Siṁhaḷa</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷa</hi> kings.</p>						                            
                            <p>His successor <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi> I. “annihilated his chief enemies at <hi rend="bold">Puḷḷalūra</hi>” (v. 21). The ‘chief enemies’ were probably the <hi rend="bold">Chalukyas</hi>, who, in their turn, considered the Pallavas their ‘natural enemies.’<note >See Vol. I, p. 146, text line 38.</note> As <hi rend="bold">Puḷḷalūr</hi> is the name of a village in the Conjeeveram tālluqa,<note>No. 182 on the <hi rend="italic">Conjeeveram Taluk Map</hi>.</note> it appears that the Chalukya army had made an inroad into the Pallava dominions, before it was repulsed by Mahēndravarman I.</p>						
                            
                            <p>His son <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> I. is reported to have conquered <hi rend="bold">Laṅkā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Ceylon, and to have captured <hi rend="bold">Vātāpi</hi>,<note>From a Tirukkaṛukkuṉṟam inscription we learn that he assumed after this conquest the surname Vātāpi-koṇḍa, ‘who took Vātāpi;’ see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 277.</note> the capital of the Western Chalukyas. The Kūram and Udayēndiram plates supply the name of the conquered Chalukya king, Pulakēśin or Vallabharāja, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Pulikēśin</hi> II.<note>See Vol. I, p. 145.</note> The conquest of Ceylon to which the Kaśākūḍi plates refer, is confirmed from an unexpected source. From the 47th chapter of the <hi rend="italic">Mahāvaṁsa</hi><note>Wijesinha's <hi rend="italic">Translation of the Mahāvaṁsa</hi>, p. 41 ff. This reference was first noticed by Mr. Venkayya; see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 277.</note> we learn that the Singhalese prince <hi rend="bold">Māṇavamma</hi> lived at the court of king <hi rend="bold">Narasīha</hi> of India and helped him to crush his enemy, king <hi rend="bold">Vallabha</hi>. The grateful Narasīha supplied Māṇavamma twice with an army to invade Ceylon. The second attack was successful. Māṇavamma occupied Ceylon, over which he is supposed to have ruled from A.D. 691 to 726. As both the Pallava inscriptions and the <hi rend="italic">Mahāvaṁsa</hi> mention the war with Vallabha and the conquest of Ceylon, the identity of Narasīha and Narasiṁhavarman I. can hardly be doubted. As, however, the latest date of Pulikēśin II. is A.D. 642,<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 2, Table.</note> the accession of Māṇavamma must have taken place about half a century before A.D. 691.<note>In my <hi rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> for 1891-92, p. 5, footnote, I have noted a similar error of about half a century in the Singhalese chronology for the period between Rājēndra-Chōḷa I. and Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa I.</note></p>	
                            
                            <p>No details are given about the reign of Narasiṁhavarman's son <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi> II. The latter was succeeded by his son <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtavarman</hi> I. who, as we know from the Kūram and Udayēndiram plates, defeated the Western Chalukya king <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi> I. at <hi rend="bold">Peruvaḷanallūr</hi>. The Kaśākūḍi plates do not contain any historical information about him, nor about his son <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> II. and his grandson <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtavarman</hi> II.</p>						
                            
                            <p>According to the Udayēndiram plates, the next king, <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, was the son of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> II. The Kaśākūḍi plates contain an entirely different account of Nandivarman's parentage. In line 72, he professes to be “engaged in ruling the kingdom of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtarāja</hi>;” and in verse 27, he is said to be ruling, at the time of the inscription, the kingdom of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtavarman</hi> II., <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, to have succeeded or supplanted the latter on the throne, and to have been “chosen by the subjects.” This plebiscite may have taken place after the death of the legitimate king; or, more probably, Nandivarman may have been an usurper who ousted and destroyed him and his family. At any rate, he was a remote kinsman of his predecessor. For, he was the son of <hi rend="bold">Hiraṇya</hi> (verses 9 and 30) by <hi rend="bold">Rōhiṇī</hi> and belonged to the branch (<hi rend="italic">varga</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Bhīma</hi> (verse 30). According to verse 28, this branch of Bhīma took its origin from <hi rend="bold">Bhīmavarman</hi>, who was the younger brother of Siṁhavishṇu. The names of three princes who intervened between Bhīmavarman and Hiraṇya, are recorded in the same verse. The name <hi rend="bold">Hiraṇyavarma-Mahārāja</hi> occurs several times in a much obliterated inscription of the <hi rend="bold">Vaikuṇṭha-Perumāḷ</hi> temple at Kānchīpuram. At the beginning of this inscription, <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarappōttaraiyar</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava-vaṁśa</hi> is mentioned as deceased (<hi rend="italic">svargastha</hi>). It is therefore not improbable that the inscription recorded the accession of Hiraṇyavarman or of his son Nandivarman after the death of Paramēśvarapōtavarman II. The latter may have been the founder of the Vaikuṇṭha-Perumāḷ temple, which is called <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara-Vishṇugṛiha</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, ‘the Vishṇu temple of Paramēśvara,’ in another inscription of the Vaikuṇṭha-Perumāḷ temple.<note>This fragment contains the date . . . . . <foreign><hi rend="grantha">rmmama</hi>hārā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>rkku yāṇṭu patineḻāvatu</foreign>, and refers immediately after to a golden vessel given to the temple by Danti[va]rma-Mahārāja. One of the Vaishṇava hymns of the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandham</hi> glorifies the temple of Paramēśvara-Viṇṇagaram at Kachchi (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Kāñchī), by which the Vaikuṇṭha-Perumāḷ temple must be meant.</note> With the addition of the new branch, the list of the later Pallavas stands as follows:—</p>
                            
                            <p><!--What follows is a gealogical table--><hi rend="italic">Unnamed ancestor</hi>.[C1]1. Siṁhavishṇu. [C1]2. Mahēndravarman I. [C2]Bhīmavarman. [C1]3. Narasiṁhavarman I. [C2]Buddhavarman. [C1]4. Mahēndravarman II. [C2]Ādityavarman. [C1]5. Paramēśvarapōtavarman or Paramēśvaravarman I. [C2]Gōvindavarman. [C1]6. Narasiṁhavarman II. [C2]Hiraṇya. [C1]7. Paramēśvarapōtavarman or Paramēśvaravarman II. [C2]8. Nandivarman.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Other forms of the name Nandivarman are <hi rend="bold">Nandipōtarāja</hi> (l. 90) and simply <hi rend="bold">Nandin</hi> (l. 88). The form <hi rend="bold">Nandipōtavarman</hi> occurs in the <hi rend="bold">Vakkalēri</hi> plates,<note>Vol. I, p. 145 f.</note> which refer to the defeat of the Pallava king by the Western Chalukya king <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi> II., and the form <hi rend="bold">Nandippōttaraiyar</hi> in an inscription of his 18th year in the <hi rend="bold">Ulagaḷanda-Perumāḷ</hi> temple at Kāñchīpuram.<note>See p. 341, note 3.</note> He bore the sovereign titles <hi rend="italic">Mahārāja</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rājādhirāja-paramēśvara</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">birudas</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kshatriyamalla, Pallavamalla</hi> (l. 78), and <hi rend="bold">Śrīdhara</hi> (verse 29). According to verse 30, he was a devotee of Vishṇu. At the request of his prime-minister (l. 89), <hi rend="bold">Brahmaśrīrāja</hi> (l. 91) or <hi rend="bold">Brahmayuvarāja</hi> (ll. 103 and 106), the king gave the village of <hi rend="bold">Koḍukoḷḷi</hi> (ll. 99, 105 f.) to the Brāhmaṇa Jyēshṭhapāda-Sōmayājin (l. 93) or (in Tamil) Śēṭṭiṟeṅga-Sōmayājin (l. 108 f.), who belonged to the Bharadvāja (l. 94) or Bhāradvāja (l. 108) <hi rend="italic">gōtra</hi>, followed the <hi rend="italic">Chhandōgasūtra</hi> (ll. 94 and 108), and resided at <hi rend="bold">Pūniya</hi> (l. 95) or <hi rend="bold">Pūni</hi> (l. 108), a village in the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍāka-rāshṭra</hi> (l. 95). The village of Koḍukoḷḷi, on becoming a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi>, received the new name <hi rend="bold">Ēkadhīramaṅgalam</hi> (l. 100). It belonged to <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāṭṭu-kōṭṭam</hi> (l. 105) or (in Sanskrit) <hi rend="bold">Undivanakōshṭhaka</hi> (l. 98), a subdivision of <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍāka-rāshṭra</hi>, and was bounded in the east and south by <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr</hi>, in the west by <hi rend="bold">Maṇaṟpākkam</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷipākkam</hi>, and in the north by <hi rend="bold">Veḷimānallūr</hi> (ll. 98 f. and 111 ff.). Connected with the gift of the village was the right to dig channels from the <hi rend="bold">Śēyāṟu</hi> or (in Sanskrit) <hi rend="bold">Dūrasarit</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Veḥkā</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Vēgavatī</hi>, and the tank of <hi rend="bold">Tīraiyaṉ</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Tīralaya</hi> (ll. 101 f. and 115 ff.).</p>
                            
                            <p>Of these geographical names, the following can be identified. Toṇḍāka-rāshṭra is,—like Toṇḍīra-maṇḍala, Tuṇḍīra-maṇḍala and Tuṇḍāka-vishaya,<note>See p. 312, note 6.</note>—a Sanskritised form of the Tamil term <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam</hi>. One of the 24 ancient divisions (<hi rend="italic">kōṭṭam</hi>) of the latter was <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāṭṭu-kōṭṭam</hi>, which owed its name to Ūṟṟukkāḍu, a village in the present Conjeeveram tālluqa.<note>No. 112 on the <hi rend="italic">Conjeeveram Taluk Map</hi>.</note> This <hi rend="italic">kōṭṭam</hi> was divided into four subdivisions (<hi rend="italic">nāḍu</hi>), one of which was <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr-nāḍu</hi>.<note>See Mr. Crole's <hi rend="italic">Chingleput District Manual</hi>, p. 438.</note> The head-village of this subdivision, <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr</hi>, appears to be identical with the village of <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr</hi>, which formed the south-eastern boundary of the granted village, and perhaps with the modern <hi rend="bold">Pālūr</hi> at the north-western extremity of the Chingleput tālluqa.<note>No. 71 on the <hi rend="italic">Chingleput Taluk Map</hi>.</note> The western boundary of the granted village, Maṇaṟpākkam, would then be represented by the modern <hi rend="bold">Mēlamaṇappākkam</hi>.<note>No. 72 on the same map.</note> For the granted village, Koḍukoḷḷi, itself and for the two remaining villages which formed its boundaries, no equivalents are found on the maps at my disposal. The village at which the donee resided, Pūni, may be the modern <hi rend="bold">Pūṇḍi</hi>, which belongs to the Conjeeveram tālluqa,<note>No. 341 on the <hi rend="italic">Conjeeveram Taluk Map</hi>.</note> but is in close proximity of Pālūr and Mēlamaṇappākkam in the Chingleput tālluqa. The proposed identification of these three villages is made more probable by the reference, made in the Kaśākūḍi plates, to two rivers near which the granted village of Koḍukoḷḷi was situated. Of these, the <hi rend="bold">Vēgavatī</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Veḥkā</hi> passes Conjeeveram and falls into the Pālāṟu near Villivalam.<note>No. 93 on the same map.</note> The <hi rend="bold">Śēyāṟu</hi> forms the southern boundary of the modern Conjeeveram tālluqa and joins the Pālāṟu opposite Mēlamaṇappākkam, which I have identified with Maṇaṟpākkam, the western boundary of Koḍukoḷḷi.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The executor (<hi rend="italic">ājñapti</hi>) of the grant was <hi rend="bold">Ghōraśarman</hi> (ll. 103 and 106), and the author of the Sanskrit portion, which, as in the <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> plates (l. 89) and the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates (ll. 101 and 105), is called a <hi rend="italic">praśasti</hi> or eulogy, was a certain <hi rend="bold">Trivikrama</hi> (verse 31). To the Sanskrit portion is affixed a Tamil endorsement (l. 104 f.), which directs the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāṭṭu-kōṭṭam</hi> to execute the order of the king. The subsequent Tamil passage (l. 105 ff.) records that, on receipt of the royal order, the representatives of Ūṟṟukkāṭṭu-kōṭṭam marked the boundaries of the granted village under the guidance of their headman, and formally assigned all rights to the donee. Another Tamil sentence (l. 132 f.) states that the grant was executed in the presence of the local authorities (?), the ministers and the secretaries.</p>
                            
                            <p>Then follow, in Sanskrit, three imprecatory verses (l. 133 ff.) and the statement that the document was written by His Majesty's great treasurer (l. 136). The inscription ends with a docket in Tamil (l. 137) and a few auspicious Sanskrit words.</p>	
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-04-19" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-04-08" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition">
                
                <!--update m to M-->
                
                <pb n="1r"/>
                
                <p xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:vernacular">                    
                    <pb n="1v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <lb n="1"/>svasti <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> jayati ja<unclear>ga</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>trayajanma<unclear>sthi</unclear>tisaṁh<supplied reason="omitted">ṛ</supplied>tikāraṇamparabrahma <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> satyamanantamanādi jñānā
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>tmakamekamamṛtapadam || <supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied> māyāvi<unclear>nā</unclear> yena padatrayārtthinā sadyaḥ pravṛddhena punarba
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>lermmakhe <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> vicakrame trirjjagatassvasātkṛt<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>au</corr></choice> sa vostu bhūtyai bhagavā<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>ṁ</corr></choice>strivikrama<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> || <supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied> maulāvi
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>ndudharaḥ phaṇa<unclear>ā</unclear>dharadhara<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> skandhe bhavānīdharo vāme kāmadharaḥ praṇā<supplied reason="omitted">ma</supplied>nirate gaṁgādharo
                    <lb n="5"/>mūrddhani <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mū<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>tt<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>au</corr></choice> dhūḷidharo gaḷe garadharaḥ keśeṣu veṇīdharaḥ pāṇ<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>au</corr></choice>  śūladharo haraḥ
                    <lb n="6"/>puraharaḥ puṣṇātu vo maṅgalam || <supplied reason="omitted">3</supplied> kaṇThe kaustubhakāḷikābharaṇ<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>yośchāyāmparāmbibhra
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>tau daityaddhvaṁsanacakrapaṭṭasadharau śyāmāvadātau rucā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> śrīgaurīvilasatkaṭākṣaviśikha
                    
                    <pb n="2r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>vyāyāmaromāñcit<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>au</corr></choice> pāyāstāmbhavatastrivikramahar<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>au</corr></choice> sampṛktadehāntarau || <supplied reason="omitted">4</supplied> pa<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>mā pa<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>m<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>sīnā pa<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>mo<supplied reason="omitted">j</supplied>jvalapāṇipa<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>mayuga<choice><sic>ḷ</sic><corr>l</corr></choice>ā vaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> prītyā paśyatu kariṇ<choice><sic>ā k</sic><corr>īk</corr></choice>aradhṛtakanakaghaṭasusnānā <supplied reason="subaudible">|| 5</supplied>
                    <lb n="10"/><unclear>dṛ</unclear>ṣṭvā lala<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>ṭe nayana<choice><sic>mbhri</sic><corr>ṁ bhi</corr></choice>yeva kāmo n<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice> yāmīśvara <unclear>I</unclear>tyupāste <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> viṣṇo<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> svasā sā bhagava
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>tyalakṣmīmāryyā kadāryyāṁ kṣiṇutā<supplied reason="omitted">t·</supplied> kṣaṇena || <supplied reason="omitted">6</supplied> kailāsagauraḥ pṛ<choice><sic>ḍ</sic><corr>th</corr></choice>unāgakakṣyaḥ
                    <lb n="12"/>prodvṛttakarṇṇo bṛhadekadantaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mātaṅgavaktro madanigghna(ne)netro bhūyādavigvnāya vina<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    <lb n="13" break="no"/>yako vaḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">7</supplied> ye devā divi dānayāgata<unclear>pa</unclear>sāṁ kāle phalantanvate ye devā bhuvi ṣaṭsu
                    <lb n="14"/>karmmasu ratāssatyāśiṣassaṁya<choice><sic>nāste</sic><corr>tāḥ | te</corr></choice> devā dvitaye kulakramabhuvā bhaktyā samārādhitāḥ pā
                    
                    <pb n="2v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="15" break="no"/>yāsuḥ parameśvarāścirataraṁ śrīpallavānāṁ ku<supplied reason="omitted">la</supplied>m || <supplied reason="omitted">8</supplied> hiraṇyagarbho jayati prajāpati<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śriyaḥ
                    <lb n="16"/>patiśśākvaraketanaḥ kṣitim <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> sahelakallolasamudravāraṇ<choice><sic>āb</sic><corr>āṁ b</corr></choice>ala<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>vipā yasya sapa<choice><sic><unclear>nna</unclear></sic><corr>tna</corr></choice>vā
                    <lb n="17" break="no"/>raṇāḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">9</supplied> svasti || namaḥ śriyai || prathamamajani vedhā<surplus>ḥ</surplus> brahmayoniḥ svayambhūrnnaḷina<add place="below" rend="mark">nayana</add>nābherulla
                    <lb n="18" break="no"/>satpuṇḍarīkā<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>t</corr></choice> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Akṛtakavacanānā<choice><sic>nt</sic><corr>ṁ t</corr></choice>a<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tvato d<choice><sic>ra</sic><corr>ṛ</corr></choice>ṣṭavartmā sakalabhuvanasarggavyāpṛti
                    <lb n="19" break="no"/>vyagrakarmmā || <supplied reason="omitted">10</supplied> tasmātsaṁgaritāntagāmicarito yajñeṁgirā jajñivāndīptāgirahunāśanādadu<note n="347-6">Read dīptāgniḥ sa hutāśaº.</note>
                    <lb n="20" break="no"/>rit<choice><sic>o</sic><corr>aḥ</corr></choice> prāṇāśanaḥ pāpmanāṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> saptarṣitvamavāptavānṛṣivṛ<unclear>ṣa</unclear>ḥ <note n="347-8">Read kāṅkṣāº.</note>kākṣvātapaḥ prāptavān putro
                    <lb n="21"/>mānasa <choice><sic>hāpa</sic><corr>Eva</corr></choice> tāmaptatarucchedārtthaṭaṁkottamaḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">11</supplied> tasmādaṁgiraso girā<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> <surplus>||</surplus> rasanidhi<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied><surplus>n</surplus>nītiprajā
                    
                    <pb n="3r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <lb n="22" break="no"/>nāmpatiścakre yaṁ gurumātmasātsukṛtināmbharttā tridhāmāgrajaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yatprajñābalasaṁśrayeṇa
                    <lb n="23"/>suratakrīḍāṁ surastrījano <choice><sic>c</sic><corr>dh</corr></choice>atte svairamasaṁsmarandinakṛtassampadvipadvyāṣṭatim || <supplied reason="omitted">12</supplied> śaṁyuśśubhaṁ<unclear>yu</unclear>
                    <lb n="24" break="no"/>ranahaṁyurajāya<unclear>tā</unclear>smādaṁhovighātakṛdaharppatitulyatejāḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Antarhite śikhini dai
                    <lb n="25" break="no"/>vatahavyavāho bhūtvā vyadhatta śikhikṛtyamapi svavīr<surplus>y</surplus>yā<choice><sic>n·</sic><corr>t·</corr></choice> <supplied reason="subaudible">|| 13</supplied> gotrasya karttā guṇagaura
                    <lb n="26" break="no"/>veṇa śrīpallavānāmmunirasya sūnuḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> jāto bharadvāja Iti trivedīṁ y<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>aḥ</corr></choice> paśyati smādrinibhānta<unclear>vo</unclear>
                    <lb n="27" break="no"/>bhiḥ<note n="347-15">Read ºnibhāṁ tapobhiḥ.</note>|| <supplied reason="omitted">14</supplied> droṇobhavadruhi[ṇa <note n="347-16">Read ºbhavaddruhiṇa eva</note> h]āva tataḥ kurūṇāndroṇābhidhānakalaśāmbujalabdhajanmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>E</unclear>ṇā
                    <lb n="28" break="no"/>jinopahitajitvaravediketurbāṇāstravedacaturarṇṇavapāradṛśvā || <supplied reason="omitted">15</supplied> tasmādyasmi<unclear>nkru</unclear>ddhyani<note n="347-17">Read ºnkrudhyati.</note>kṛṣṇā
                    
                    <pb n="3v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="29" break="no"/>rjunabhīmāśśastratyāgañcakruravighnambhayanighna<unclear>ā</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> <unclear>|</unclear><note n="347-18">Read viśvasthānāṁ viº.</note>viśvastānādviśvasanīyo munirāsīdaśvatthāmā
                    <lb n="30"/>manmathaśatroravatāraḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">16</supplied> jātastataḥ svapadaśaṁkitamānasena śakreṇa tamprati visarjji
                    <lb n="31" break="no"/><note n="347-19">Separate ºmenakāyām | Āpaº.</note>tamenakāyāmāpallavairanabhimṛṣṭasamudranemiḥ śrīpallavassapadi palla<supplied reason="omitted">va</supplied>saṁstareṣu [|| 17*]
                    <lb n="32"/>tejaḥ parambrāhmamanūrtthitopi<note n="347-20">Read brāhmakulotthitopi ?</note> sa kṣātramucc<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>rabhajatsvabhāvi <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ambhodharādapyupa<supplied reason="omitted">la</supplied>bdhaja
                    <lb n="33" break="no"/>nmā dāhātmako nanvaśaniḥ prakṛtyā || <supplied reason="omitted">18</supplied> Aśokayannānamataḥ kṣitīśā<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>n</corr></choice>saśokayansaṁyati sa
                    <lb n="34" break="no"/>mmukhīnān <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied><note n="347-23">Read yaśo 'kalaṅkaṁ dadhadindubhāso 'pyaº.</note><unclear>ya</unclear>śokalaṁkandadhasindudāso<unclear>pya</unclear>śokavarmmā tata Āvirāsī<choice><sic>n·</sic><corr>t·</corr></choice> || <supplied reason="omitted">19</supplied> tataḥ prabhṛtyakha
                    <lb n="35" break="no"/>ṇḍakalabhuvanamaṇḍalā<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>t</corr></choice>masātkaraṇākhaṇḍitavikramapa<unclear>ra</unclear>ḥ paripālitasakalavarṇṇāśramavyavasthā
                    
                    <pb n="4r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IVa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="36" break="no"/>viśeṣa<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> pra<surplus>ba</surplus>bhaviṣṇuḥ<note n="348-1">Read prabhaviṣṇurviṣṇoº.</note>viṣṇoraṁśāvatāra <choice><sic>hā</sic><corr>i</corr></choice>va vaṁśāvatāra<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> pallavānānnikhilabhuvanapāva
                    <lb n="37" break="no"/>natayā gaṁgāvatāra Iva ca nirmmalassamavarttata <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yatrodbhūtā<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> sarvvepi sarvvatrāvihataśaktayo<note n="348-3">The ta of vihata is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>
                    <lb n="38"/>mahāsenāḥ pāvakajanmānaḥ pa<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>modbhavāssubrahmaṇyāḥ kumārā Iva ye <choice><sic>g</sic><corr>bh</corr></choice>ujabalavipulapra
                    <lb n="39" break="no"/>tāpānalaśoṣitāśeṣadviṣadavāryy<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>vī<choice><sic>yy</sic><corr>ry</corr></choice>ā<add place="below" rend="mark"><choice><sic>ṇṇ</sic><corr>rṇ</corr></choice>a</add>vār<surplus>ṇ</surplus>ṇasaḥ prakīrṇṇanirmmalakīrtticandri
                    <lb n="40" break="no"/>kāniṣkālitasakalakalikālakalakakāluṣyāḥ<note n="348-7">Read ºniṣkāsitaº and ºkalaṅkakāluṣyāḥ.</note>samunnatacaritātiśayācaloda
                    <lb n="41" break="no"/>yasaṁvarddhitamitramaṇḍalānurāgā yuvatijanahṛdayahariṇa<unclear>va</unclear>āgurāyamāṇa<unclear>va</unclear>puḥ<note n="348-8">The va of vapuḥ is corrected from pu.</note>
                    <lb n="42" break="no"/>saundaryyāścandanatarava I<unclear>va</unclear><note n="348-9">The va of iva is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>dakṣi<unclear>ṇā</unclear>śāvivarddhamānasaurabhāssuratara<supplied reason="omitted">va</supplied> Ivānanyatejovilaṁ<note n="348-10">The <hi rend="italic">anusvāra</hi> of laṁ is found at the commencement of plate <hi rend="italic">IVb</hi>.</note>
                    
                    <pb n="4v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IVb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="43" break="no"/><note n="348-11">Read ºtātmaº.</note>ghitānmacchāyā<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> pūṣaṇa Iva parahitakarā <unclear>bhā</unclear>svantaśca śabdāgamā<note n="348-12">The two syllables śabdā are entered below the line, and the place at which they have to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>iva prakṛtipratyayāgamopetā
                    <lb n="44"/>nirapavāndavrirddhiguṇeśca<note n="348-13">Read nirapavādavṛddhiguṇāśca.</note>nandanā <note n="348-14">Read apyaº.</note>Avyapārijātā ghanāgamā A<choice><sic>v</sic><corr>p</corr></choice>yajaḷāścakravāḷaparvvataparyyant<unclear>āṁ</unclear><note n="348-16">The <hi rend="italic">anusvāra</hi> is found at the commencement of line 45.</note>
                    <lb n="45"/>saptadvīpasaptasāgarālaṁkṛtāṁ<note n="348-17">The ka of sakalā is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>sakalāndivamiva divapetiḥ <note n="348-18">Read divaspatirbhuvaṁ bhuº.</note>guvambhuvaspatayo <choice><sic>g</sic><corr>bh</corr></choice>uñjate <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>ye</unclear>
                    <lb n="46" break="no"/>ṣāñca<note n="348-20">Read samastaśastraśāstraº.</note>samastaśāstraśastranirjjitorjjitasamitayaḥ <note n="348-21">Read ºsamitayā 'mitaº.</note>Amitavikramāḥ kramārjjitadharmmaka
                    <lb n="47" break="no"/>rmmāṇā<note n="348-22">Read ºkarmāṇaḥ.</note>khaṇḍitakalayaḥ paṇḍitamatayaḥ <note n="348-23">Read ºmatayo.</note> lakṣitamūrttayo rakṣitakīttayassamastavasundharo<note n="348-24">Read ºkīrtayaḥ saº.</note>
                    <lb n="48" break="no"/>dvahanadhurandharaskandhāḥ<note n="348-25">Read skandavarmakalindavarmaº.</note>kanda<unclear>va</unclear>rmmakalandavarmmakāṇagopaviṣṇugopavīrakūccavīrasiṁhasiṁha<note n="348-26">Read ºvīrakūrcaº.</note>
                    <lb n="49" break="no"/>varmmaviṣṇusiṁhaprabhṛtayaśśatrudhūma(kema)ketavo<note n="348-27">The two syllables kema are already cancelled in the original by two horizontal strokes placed above them.</note>mitramānahetavaḥ sarvvamaryyādāsenavaḥ<note n="348-28">Read ºsetavaḥ.</note>
                    
                    <pb n="5r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate Va</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="50"/><unclear>ketage</unclear><note n="348-29">Read kāle gate (?) vyatīyuº.</note>vyanīyuravanipa<supplied reason="omitted">ta</supplied>yaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tadanu ka<unclear>da</unclear>nakarmmavyāvṛtaśśātravāṇā <note n="348-30">Read ºvyāpṛtaḥ śātravāṇāmabhavaº.</note> (||) Abhavadavani<unclear>siṁ</unclear> 
                    <lb n="51" break="no"/>haḥ siṁharvvijiṣṇuḥ<note n="349-1">Read siṁhaviṣṇurvijiṣṇuḥ.</note><supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> ma<unclear>ā</unclear>ḷavamatha <note n="349-2">Read malayamatha kaḷabhraṁ mālavaṁ coḷaº.</note> kaḷabhṛrmmāḷavañcoḷapāṇḍyau nijagujabalatṛptan <note n="349-3">Read nijabhujabaladṛptaṁ.</note> siṁha<unclear>ḷaṁ</unclear>
                    <lb n="52"/>keraḷāṁśca || <supplied reason="omitted">20</supplied> tato mahīmanvaśiṣanmahīndro mahendravarmmeti mahendrakīrtti[ḥ |*] Aśeṣayāmā
                    <lb n="53" break="no"/>sa viśeṣitājño yā<note n="349-4">Read yaḥ.</note>puḷḷalūre dviṣatāṁ viśeṣān || <supplied reason="omitted">21</supplied> laṁkājayādharitarāmapara<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    <lb n="54" break="no"/>kramaśrī<unclear>rudvṛ</unclear>ttaśratrukulasaṁkṣayadhūmaketuḥ<note n="349-5">Read ºśatruº.</note><supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> vātāpinirjjayaviḷambitakumbhajanmā <note n="349-6">Read ºviḍambitaº.</note> vīrastato
                    <lb n="55" break="no"/>jani jayi<note n="349-7">Read jayī.</note>narasiṁhavarmmā || <supplied reason="omitted">22</supplied> tasmādajāyata nijāyatabāhudaṇḍaścañcāśanī <note n="349-8">Read ºdaṇḍacaṇḍāśanī.</note> ripukulasya ma
                    <lb n="56" break="no"/>hendravarmmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yasmātprabhratyalamavarddhata<note n="349-9">Read ºtprabhṛtyaº.</note>dharmmakarmma devadvijanmaviṣayaṁ ghaṭikañca <note n="349-10">Read ghaṭikā ca.</note> dātu<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> || <supplied reason="omitted">23</supplied> Icchā
                    
                    <pb n="5v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate Vb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="57" break="no"/><note n="349-11">The <hi rend="italic">ē</hi> of dheya appears to be corrected from vi; read vidheya.</note>dheyasakalāvanipālaloka<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> paścādbabhūva parameśvarapotavarmmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> bhūti<note n="349-12">Read bhūtiṁ.</note>parāṁ vahati
                    <lb n="58"/>bhūtapatirvvṛṣa<unclear>āṁ</unclear>ko<note n="349-13">The engraver appears to have altered ṣāṁko into ṣāṁkaḥ; read ºṣāṅkaḥ khaṭvāṅgaº.</note>khaṭvāgaketuracalasthitiradbhuto yaḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">24</supplied> devabrāhmaṇa<unclear>sa</unclear>ātkṛtātmavibha(ā)vo
                    <lb n="59"/>ya<unclear>ḥ</unclear> kṣatracūḷāmaṇicaturvvaidyamavīvīdhan<note n="349-14">Read ºmaṇiścāturvaidyamavīviśat.</note>svasaṭikām <note n="349-15">Read svavaśagāṁ ?</note> bhūdevatāmbhaktitaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>sa</unclear>mprāpte <note n="349-16">Read saṁprāpto narasiṁhatāṁ.</note> narasiṁ
                    <lb n="60" break="no"/>ha<unclear>ta</unclear>ā svavapuṣā nāmnā ca<note n="349-17">The syllable di is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>digvyāpinā jāta<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrīparameśvarasya sakalasyāṁgā<unclear>vata</unclear>ārastataḥ [|| 25*]
                    <lb n="61"/>Etā dhanāni daitāni<note n="349-18">Read dayitāni.</note>yaśodhanāni jetā kalervvilasitāni babhūva tasmāt <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> netā nayaśya dha<note n="349-19">Read nayasya dhiº.</note>
                    <lb n="62" break="no"/>ṣaṇādhikṛtasya mārgga<note n="349-20">Read mārgaṁ.</note>pātā jagati <note n="349-21">Read jaganti.</note> parameśvarapotavarmmā [|| 26*] tasya praśāsti padamṛddhimadā samudra<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>
                    <lb n="63" break="no"/>dājñābalena jitaśatru vṛtaḥ prajābhiḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mānyo nayena manu taṁ prati<note n="349-22">Read nanu saṁprati.</note>nandivarmmā vistīrṇṇapallava<unclear>ku</unclear>
                    
                    <pb n="6r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate VIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="64" break="no"/>lārṇṇavapūrṇṇacandra<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> || <supplied reason="omitted">27</supplied> ṣaṣṭha<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrīsiṁhaviṣṇoranu patiranujaḥ prābhavadbhīmavarmmā deva<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrībuddhava
                    <lb n="65" break="no"/>rmmā budhajanamahitaḥ pañcamaḥ pallavendraḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> turyyaścādityavarmmā tulitakuli<unclear>śabhṛ</unclear>dyasya govinda
                    <lb n="66" break="no"/>varmmā tārttiyīko<note n="349-23">Read tārtīyīko.</note>dvitīyaḥ kṣitibhṛda<unclear>su</unclear>bhṛtāṁ śrīhiraṇyaśśaraṇyaḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">28</supplied> saṁgrāme vijayaḥ kalāpa
                    <lb n="67" break="no"/>ricaye karṇṇīsutaḥ kārmmuke rāmo vāraṇatantravādyaviṣaye vatseśvara<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrīdharaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> kāmo
                    <lb n="68"/>vāmavilocanāsu kavitābaddhe<note n="350-1">Read ºbandhe.</note>sa <unclear>Ā</unclear>dyaḥ kavistantrāvāpavidhau <note n="350-2">Read ºstantrālāpaº.</note> svayannayabharo dharmmaḥ prajā
                    <lb n="69" break="no"/>rañjane || <supplied reason="omitted">29</supplied> svāmī naḥ pallavānāṁ kulabharaṇapaṭussātvikassārvvabhaumo dravyo<note n="350-3">Read bhavyo.</note>vyāyāmavidyā
                    <lb n="70" break="no"/>vinayaguṇagururvvarddhate sārddhamraddhyā<note n="350-4">Read ºmṛddhyā.</note><supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> hairaṇyo bhīmavarggyo haricaraṇaparaśśurddhamātranvavā<note n="350-5">Read ºparaḥ śuddhaº.</note>
                    
                    <pb n="6v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate VIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="71" break="no"/>yo lakṣaṇyo rohiṇīja<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied><note n="350-6">Read sulabhaº.</note><unclear>svala</unclear>bhasucarito nandivarmmā narendraḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">30</supplied> tena rājādhirājaparame
                    <lb n="72" break="no"/>śva<unclear>reṇa</unclear> parameśvarapotarājapadapraśāsa<unclear>na</unclear>pareṇa<note n="350-7">rāja is corrected from varmma by the engraver.</note>paramapadaviṣaktavyāpṛtonnidrace
                    <lb n="73" break="no"/>ta<unclear>sā</unclear> parameṣṭhipadapaṁkaruhayugaḷavigaḷitadhūḷidhūsaraśirasā<note n="350-8">Read puraskṛtaº.</note>vuvaraskṛtadevabr<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    <lb n="74" break="no"/>hmaṇapūjanāsanena tiraskṛtakalikālakalikāpiḷanāvyasanena<note n="350-9">Read ºkalikālakālikapīḍanavyasanena ?</note>vivarddhamānapratā
                    <lb n="75" break="no"/>pānalapariśoṣitāmitramaṇḍalena vivarddhamānānurāgarasaparitoṣitamitramaṇḍale
                    <lb n="76" break="no"/>na <unclear>sa</unclear>kalabhuvanasāmrājyadīkṣā<unclear>da</unclear>kṣadakṣiṇakareṇa sarvvorvvībhranmakuṭamāṇikkakoṇaśāṇa<note n="350-10">Read ºbhṛnmakuṭamāṇikyaº.</note>
                    <lb n="77" break="no"/>masṛṇitacaraṇayugaḷena pallavakulanandanavanalakṣmīlatālaḷitaveṣṭanakalpavṛkṣe
                    
                    <pb n="7r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate VIIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="78" break="no"/>ṇa kṣatriyamallena pallavamallena bappabhaṭṭārakapādānuddhyānavarddhamānamahimnā
                    <lb n="79"/>nandivarmmanāmnā mahāguṇasalilanidhisalila<unclear>sa</unclear>mvarddhanasomarājena<note n="350-11">Read ºsaṁvardhanaº.</note>mahārājena sā
                    <lb n="80" break="no"/>mrājya<unclear>saṁvatsa</unclear>re<note n="350-12">The word saṁvatsare is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>dvāviṁśe <unclear>va</unclear>rttamāne chandaḥpārāvārapā<unclear>ra</unclear>gāya svarasamadhurasāma<unclear>ga</unclear>āya chandaḥkalpa
                    <lb n="81" break="no"/>vyākaraṇajyotiṣaniruktaśikṣācchandovicatiṣaḍaṁgasaṁśitasvāddhyāyāddhyaya<note n="350-13">Read ºchandovicitiº.</note>
                    <lb n="82" break="no"/>nāyapadadha<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>mavākyadharmmavastadharmmavittāya <note n="350-15">Read ºvastudharmavide.</note>śrutismṛtirasāyanapānāya karmmakāṇḍajñā
                    <lb n="83" break="no"/>nakāṇḍapaṇḍitāya lokayuktikalārakośalāpeśalāya<note n="350-16">Read ºkalākauśalapeśalāya.</note>kāvyanāṭakākhyāy<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>i</corr></choice>ke
                    <lb n="84" break="no"/>tihāsapurāṇapariṇatāya kimbahunā sarvvajñānavijñānatiṣṇātāya<note n="350-18">Read ºniṣṇātāva.</note>sarvvakarmmānuṣṭhānaniṣṭhi
                    
                    <pb n="7v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate VIIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="85" break="no"/>tāya suvṛttāya bhuvanabhavanadīpāya mānābhijan<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>sujanāya nirākṛtasamaptatamastayā<note n="350-19">Read ºsamastaº.</note>ma
                    <lb n="86" break="no"/>ddhyamalokaikamitrāya lokamitreṇa sarvvagu<supplied reason="omitted">ṇa</supplied>sārasandohasāgaragambhīreṇa śrīma
                    <lb n="87" break="no"/>tā hrīmatā vapuṣmatāyuṣmatā paruṣetarabhāṣeṇa puruṣaviśeṣeṇa brahaspati<note n="350-20">Read bṛhaspatiº.</note>
                    <lb n="88" break="no"/>neva divaspaterbbhuvaspaterjjananayanahṛdayanandino nandinaḥ pallavapatennisa<note n="350-21">Read ºpaternisarganītiº.</note>
                    <lb n="89" break="no"/>rśśanītivinītena vidvanmukhyena mukhyamantriṇ<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice> dhīreṇa vīreṇa brahmakṣatramayiṁ<note n="350-22">Read ºmayīṁ śriyaº.</note>śrīyamavi
                    <lb n="90" break="no"/>kalāmavicalāñca śrīnandipotara<unclear>āja</unclear>(na)<note n="351-1">The letter na has been already cancelled in the original by placing a horizontal stroke above it.</note>bhakti(sama)mācandramastārakambibhrāṇena bi<unclear>bhra</unclear>ā
                    <lb n="91" break="no"/>ṇena kulaṁ kulajyeṣṭhena jyeṣṭhaputreṇa brahmaśrīrājena śīlatassākṣātsoma
                    
                    <pb n="8r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate VIIIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="92" break="no"/>rājena ta<choice><sic>d</sic><corr>t</corr></choice>haiva sarvvaguṇajyoṣṭhena <note n="351-3">Read ºjyeṣṭhena.</note> jyeṣṭhena potreṇa <note n="351-4">Read ºṇāṁ pautriṇāṁ ca.</note> dhuramā
                    <lb n="93" break="no"/>ropitāya sujanmapuṇyāya dvijanmagaṇyāya<note n="351-6">Read dvijanmāgragaṇyāya.</note>brahmavedine jyeṣṭhapādasomayājine cha
                    <lb n="94" break="no"/>nda<unclear>ścha</unclear>ndānuvarttanāya chandogasūtrāya bharadvājapeyādikratugotrāya bharadvājagotrāya
                    <lb n="95"/>toṇḍākarāṣṭrabrahmalokāyamānapūniyavāstavyāya doṣadaridrāya veṣaviśiṣṭā
                    <lb n="96" break="no"/>yaikapuruṣāya dvilokacintanoya<note n="351-7">Read ºcintanāya trivargaº.</note>trivargśasādhakāya caturvvedāya pañcamahā<unclear>bhū</unclear>taparā
                    <lb n="97" break="no"/>rtthāya ṣaḍaṁgāya saptasaptipra<unclear>ti</unclear>māya suguṇāya subrāhmaṇāya svayameva prasādā
                    <lb n="98" break="no"/>dundivanakoṣṭhake tasminneva rāṣṭre <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> prāmpalayūr<note n="351-8">Read prāṅ pālaiyūr.</note><supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> dakṣiṇaśca sa Eva <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> pratyaṅ maṇatpākkaḥ ko
                    
                    <pb n="8v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate VIIIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="99" break="no"/>ḷḷipā<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kaśca <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Udaṅ veḷimānallūr <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Etadavadhicatuṣṭayāntabbhūtaḥ <note n="351-10">Read ºntarbhūtaḥ koḍuº.</note> koṭukoḷḷiriti prathamanāmā brahmade
                    <lb n="100" break="no"/>yibhāva<note n="351-11">Read ºyībhāvādekaº. The e of eka is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>ekadhīramaṁ<unclear>ga</unclear>lamiti caramanāmnā grāmassāmānyanivarttanadvayamaryyādayā nirastapurā
                    <lb n="101" break="no"/><note n="351-12">The na of dāna is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>ta<unclear>na</unclear>devadānabrahma<unclear>de</unclear>yannirastaku<supplied reason="omitted">ṭu</supplied>mbi sarvvaparihārābhyantarīkaraṇena dūrasarito vegavatyāśca t<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>ra
                    <lb n="102" break="no"/>layata<unclear>ṭā</unclear>kācca yathopapādaṁ ruddhvā c<choice><sic>a U</sic><corr>o</corr></choice>daka<unclear>bho</unclear>go g<choice><sic>ra</sic><corr>ṛ</corr></choice>haṁ kṣetramārāmo niṣkuṭañca<note n="351-16">Read niṣkuṭaṁ ceº.</note>
                    <lb n="103" break="no"/>tyetadabhyantaraṁ sarvvo brahmadeyandatta Iti vijñaptirbrahmayuvarājasya <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Ājñapti<choice><sic>gg</sic><corr>rgh</corr></choice>oraśar<surplus>m</surplus>mā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> svasti
                    <lb n="104"/>siddhirastu<surplus>ḥ</surplus> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Akṛtrimastray<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>vidhikramakratupravar<surplus>t</surplus>t<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>kaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> samastaśāstratatvavitpraśasti<supplied reason="omitted">kṛt</supplied> trivikramaḥ || <supplied reason="omitted">31</supplied>
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                    ko
                    <lb n="105" break="no"/>ṉol<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> yāṇṭirupattiraṇṭāvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ūṟṟukkāṭṭukkoṭṭattu nāṭṭāru<supplied reason="omitted">ṅ</supplied>kāṇka <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tannāṭṭukko
                    
                    <pb n="9r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IXa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="106" break="no"/>ṭukoḷḷi muṉpeṟṟārai māṟṟi <hi rend="grantha">brahma</hi><choice><sic>t</sic><corr>y</corr></choice>uvarācaṉ viṇṇappattāl kora- <hi rend="grantha">śarmma</hi>ṉṉā
                    <lb n="107" break="no"/>ṇattiyāka tevatāṉappiramate<supplied reason="omitted">ya</supplied>m nīkkikkuṭi nīkkiccāmāniyairaṇṭupaṭṭippa
                    <lb n="108" break="no"/>ṭiyāl <hi rend="grantha">bhāradvājagotrāya chandogasūtrāya pūnivāstavy</hi>āya ceṭṭiṟeṅka- <hi rend="grantha">somay<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice></hi>
                    <lb n="109" break="no"/>jikkuppiramateya<unclear>m</unclear><choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>kappaṇittaruḷi viṭut<unclear>ta</unclear>ttirumukam kaṇṭu nāṭṭom nā
                    <lb n="110" break="no"/>ṭṭu viyavaṉ colliya Ell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> poyi paṭākai valañceyitu kalluṅka<choice><sic>ṇṇ</sic><corr>ḷḷ</corr></choice>iyu
                    <lb n="111" break="no"/>nnāṭṭikkoṭuttataṟkell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> kīḻpāle<unclear>l</unclear>l<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> pāl<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yūrell<choice><sic>eI</sic><corr>aiyi</corr></choice>ṉ meṟkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    <lb n="112"/>teṉpālell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> pāl<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yūre<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied>l<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yiṉ vaṭakkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> melpālell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> maṇaṟpā<supplied reason="omitted">kka</supplied>ttel
                    
                    <pb n="9v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IXb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="113" break="no"/>l<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yiṉṉum koḷḷipā<supplied reason="omitted">kka</supplied>ttell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yiṉ<supplied reason="omitted">um</supplied> kiḻakkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> vaṭapālell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> veḷimāṉa
                    <lb n="114" break="no"/><choice><sic>laṉ</sic><corr>ll</corr></choice>ūrell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yiṉ<unclear>ṟ</unclear>eṟkkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Innāṟperell<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yuḷḷum Akappa<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭa nīrnila 
                    <lb n="115" break="no"/><unclear>ṉu</unclear>m puṉceyiyum Uṭump<unclear>o</unclear>ṭi Āmai tavaḻvate<unclear>l</unclear>lām ceyāṟṟālum ve<unclear>ḵ</unclear>kā 
                    <lb n="116" break="no"/>viṉālum tīraiyaṉeriy<unclear>ālu</unclear>nnī<unclear>rī</unclear><surplus>yi</surplus>n<unclear>ta va</unclear>ḻi Āṟṟukkālum veḷ<unclear>ḷakkā</unclear>
                    <lb n="117" break="no"/>lum toṇṭikkoṇṭuṇṇap<unclear>peṟuvār</unclear>ākavu<unclear>m</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>kkālkaḷukku kolkalamum
                    <lb n="118"/>puḻutipāṭum peṟuvatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ikk<unclear>ā</unclear>lkaḷil kūṭ<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice> <unclear>Iṟ</unclear><choice><sic><unclear>e</unclear></sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>ttuṅkuṟa<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kaṟuttum <unclear>ku</unclear>ṟ<unclear>ṟe</unclear>
                    <lb n="119" break="no"/>ttam paṇṇiyum koṇṭuṇṭār kokkoḷḷum taṇṭappaṭuvākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> ma<unclear>ṉ</unclear><choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice><unclear>yum</unclear>
                    
                    <pb n="10r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate Xa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="120"/>ma<supplied reason="omitted">ṉai</supplied>p<unclear>pa</unclear>ṭappum piṟavum Ivarum Ivar vaḻikkaṇṇārum māṭamum māḷikaiyum cū<unclear>ṭṭo</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> <note n="352-13">The large Leyden grant (l. 313) reads cuṭṭoṭṭāl.</note>
                    <lb n="121"/>l <unclear>E</unclear>ṭut<surplus><seg type="component" subtype="vowel">e</seg></surplus>tukkoṇṭirukkappe<unclear>ṟu</unclear>vārāka<unclear>vu</unclear>m <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>vvu<unclear>ḷ</unclear>ḷiṭṭa <hi rend="grantha">sarvva</hi>paricāramuḷ<unclear>ḷā</unclear>ka<unclear>p</unclear>
                    <lb n="122" break="no"/>paṇittem <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivvūr peṟṟa paricāra<unclear>m</unclear> cekku<unclear>m taṟiyum U</unclear>lliyak<unclear>kū</unclear>liyum pirāmaṇa<unclear>rā</unclear>
                    <lb n="123" break="no"/>cakkāṇamum ceṅkoṭiykkā<unclear>ṇa</unclear>mum ka<unclear>l</unclear>lā<unclear>l</unclear>kkāṇamum kaṇṇiṭṭukkāṇa
                    <lb n="124" break="no"/><unclear>mu</unclear>m katirkkāṇamum vicakkāṇamu<unclear>m</unclear> kucakkāṇamum Arikoḻiyum ne<choice><sic>yi</sic><corr>y</corr></choice>vil<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yu<unclear>m</unclear>
                    <lb n="125"/>puṭṭakavil<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum paṭṭikaikkāṇamum Iṟām<choice><sic>a<unclear>yi</unclear></sic><corr>ai</corr></choice><unclear>yum</unclear> nāyāṭikaḷum tūtuvarum kaṇikā<unclear>ra</unclear>
                    <lb n="126" break="no"/>ttikaḷum paṇṇuppāleṭuppārum putukkutir<unclear>ai</unclear>kkuṟṟatuveyiyum pullum <surplus>I</surplus>
                    
                    <pb n="10v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate Xb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="127"/><add place="below" rend="mark">Iṟām<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum</add> nallāvum nallerutum Iṟām<choice><sic>ayi</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum nāṭṭuvakai Iṟām<choice><sic>ayi</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum paṭāṅkaḻiyum kaiy<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    <lb n="128" break="no"/><unclear>ḷu</unclear>m neṭumpuṟ<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum paṉampā<surplus>k</surplus>kum Iṟām<choice><sic>ayi</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum karaṇattaṇṭamum Atikaraṇatta
                    <lb n="129" break="no"/>ṇṭamum pattūrccāṟṟum Uḻaiyavayappaḷḷivattuvum Iṟā<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied>aiyum kuvaḷ<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>naṭuva
                    <lb n="130" break="no"/>ri<supplied reason="omitted">yu</supplied>ṅku<unclear>va</unclear>ḷ<choice><sic><unclear>e</unclear></sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>kkāṇamum kamukum teṅkum Uḷḷiṭṭa palluruvil pa<choice><sic>l</sic><corr>ḻ</corr></choice>ayamaramu
                    <lb n="131" break="no"/>m Iṭṭaṉa kālko<unclear>ṭṭi</unclear>ṟām<choice><sic>ayi</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum koyiḷumuta<unclear>l</unclear>paṭi<unclear>y</unclear>āl Iṟātu Ivar tāme Uṇ
                    <lb n="132" break="no"/>ṇappeṟuvārākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> nil<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>kkaḷattārum Atikārarum <unclear>vā</unclear>yikkeṭppārum Uḷḷi
                    <lb n="133" break="no"/>runtu paratatti c<unclear>e</unclear>ṉṟatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:vernacular">  
                    
                    bhūmidānātparandānanna bhūtanna bhavi<unclear>ṣya</unclear>ti <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> tasyaiva haraṇātp<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    
                    <pb n="11r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate XI</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="134" break="no"/>panna bhūtanna bhaviṣyati || <supplied reason="omitted">32</supplied> bahubhirvvasu<surplus>d</surplus>dhā dattā bahubhiścānupālitā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yasya yasya yathā
                    <lb n="135"/>bhūmi<supplied reason="omitted">s</supplied>tasya tasya tathā phalaM || <supplied reason="omitted">33</supplied> sva<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>attā<choice><sic>mp</sic><corr>ṁ p</corr></choice>aradattāṁ vā yo haret<choice><sic>u</sic><corr>a</corr></choice> vasundharāM <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> ṣaṣ<choice><sic>ṭh</sic><corr>ṭ</corr></choice>iṁ varṣa
                    <lb n="136" break="no"/>sahasrāṇi viṣṭhāyāñjāyate krimi<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> || <supplied reason="omitted">34</supplied> svasti śrīparameśvaramahāk<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>o</corr></choice>ṣṭha<choice><sic>k</sic><corr>g</corr></choice>āriṇā likhita
                    <lb n="137" break="no"/>M <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                    I<unclear>va</unclear>ṉ peṟuma<unclear>ṉ</unclear><choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum maṉ<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>ppaṭappum Iraṇṭu paṭṭi nilaṉum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:vernacular">  
                    svasti
                    <lb n="138"/>siddhirastu namaḥ <g type="ddanda">.</g> <g type="circleLarge">.</g> <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>
                </p>
                <pb n="11v"/>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                
                <!--<app loc="0">
                    <lem>...</lem>
                    </app>-->
                
                <listApp>
                    
                    <app loc="11">
                        <lem>kṣiṇutā<supplied reason="omitted">t·</supplied></lem>
                        <note>The <foreign>kṣa</foreign> of <foreign>kṣiṇutā</foreign> is the only instance in the whole inscription, in which that group looks like <foreign>kṣa</foreign>. In all other cases it resembles <foreign>tṣa</foreign>.</note>
                    </app>
                    
                    <app loc="17">
                        <lem>°<add place="below" rend="mark">nayana</add>°</lem>
                        <note>The word <foreign>nayana</foreign> is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross (<foreign>haṁsapāda</foreign>) above the line.</note>
                    </app>
                    
                    <app loc="39">
                        <lem>°vī<choice><sic>yy</sic><corr>ry</corr></choice>ā<add place="below" rend="mark"><choice><sic>ṇṇ</sic><corr>rṇ</corr></choice>a</add>vār<surplus>ṇ</surplus>ṇasaḥ</lem>
                        <note>The <foreign>ṇṇa</foreign> of <foreign>vīyyāṇṇa</foreign> is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line; read <foreign>ºvīryārṇavārṇasaḥ</foreign>.</note>
                    </app>
                    
                    <app loc="127">
                    <lem><add place="below" rend="mark">Iṟām<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>yum</add></lem>
                        <note>This word is entered below the line, and the place at which it has to be inserted, is marked by a cross above the line.</note>
                    </app>                    
                     
                </listApp>
                
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1895_01">
                
                <p>Hail ! (<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 1.) Victorious is the supreme Brahman, which is the cause of the production, stability and destruction of the three worlds; which is true, without end (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) without beginning; which consists of knowledge (<hi rend="italic">alone</hi>); which is <hi rend="italic">one; (and</hi>) which is the abode of immortality!</p>
                
                <p>(2.) May that blessed Trivikrama (Vishṇu) grant you prosperity, who, at the sacrifice of Bali, deceitfully asked (<hi rend="italic">only</hi>) for three steps (<hi rend="italic">of land</hi>), but suddenly expanded (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) strode thrice, (<hi rend="italic">thereby</hi>) appropriating the world!</p>
                
                <p>(3.) May Hara (Śiva), the destroyer of Pura, increase your happiness, who bears the moon on his crest, who wears a serpent on his shoulder, who holds Bhavānī on his left, who bears affection to his worshipper, who bears Gaṅgā on his head, who wears ashes<note><hi rend="italic">Dhūli</hi> seems to be used in the sense of <hi rend="italic">bhūti</hi>.</note> on his body, who bears poison on his neck, who wears a braid in his hair, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who holds a spear in his hand!</p>
                
                <p>(4.) May Trivikrama and Hara protect you, whose distinct (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) united bodies (<hi rend="italic">respectively</hi>) bear on the neck the supreme splendour of two ornaments,—the <hi rend="italic">kaustubha</hi> (jewel) and the black (<hi rend="italic">poison</hi>),<note>The word <hi rend="italic">kālikā</hi>, ‘blackness,’ refers to the <hi rend="italic">kālakūṭa</hi> poison.</note> hold a discus and a spear<note>According to Dr. Gundert's <hi rend="italic">Malayāḷam Dictionary, paṭṭasa</hi> is another form of the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">paṭṭiśa</hi>, the Tamil forms of which are <hi rend="italic">paṭṭayam</hi> or <hi rend="italic">paṭṭaiyam</hi>.</note> for the destruction of the Daityas, are of black and white colour, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) thrill with joy at the expansion (<hi rend="italic">of the eyes</hi>) of Śrī and Gaurī, (<hi rend="italic">which emit</hi>) coquettish glances (<hi rend="italic">resembling</hi>) arrows !</p>
                
                <p>(5.) May Padmā (Lakshmī) regard you with fondness, who is seated on a lotus; whose pair of lotus hands is resplendent with a lotus; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) whose excellent bath (<hi rend="italic">is poured from</hi>) golden jars which are held by the trunks of (<hi rend="italic">two</hi>) female elephants!</p>
                
                <p>(6.) May that blessed Āryā (Pārvatī), the sister of Vishṇu, instantly remove dire adversity,—whom Cupid does not approach, out of fear, it seems, because he has observed the (<hi rend="italic">third</hi>) eye on (<hi rend="italic">her</hi>) forehead (<hi rend="italic">and therefore takes her</hi>) for Īśvara!</p>
                
                <p>(7.) May Vināyaka (Gaṇēśa) grant you freedom from obstacles, who is as white as the Kailāsa (<hi rend="italic">mountain</hi>), whose girdle consists of a huge serpent, who has the face of an elephant, whose ears are large, who has a single big tusk, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) whose eyes are (<hi rend="italic">half closed as if he were</hi>) under the influence of rut!</p>
                
                <p>(8.) May the race of the glorious <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi> be protected for a long time by the supreme lords, those twofold<note>The plural <hi rend="italic">dvitayē</hi> is used in the same sense in the <hi rend="italic">Raghuvaṁśa</hi>, viii. 89, as quoted in Böhtlingk and Roth's <hi rend="italic">Sanskrit-Wörterbuch</hi>, s.v. <hi rend="italic">dvitaya:</hi>— <foreign>drumasānumatāṁ kimantaraṁ yadi vāyau dvitayepi te calāḥ</foreign>. Mallinātha explains <foreign>dvitayepi</foreign> by <foreign>dviprakārā api</foreign>.</note> gods whom (they, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the Pallavas) have worshipped with traditional devotion,—(<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) the gods in heaven who timely reward gifts, sacrifices and austerities, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the gods on earth<note><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, the Brāhmaṇas (<hi rend="italic">bhūdēva</hi>).</note> who are engaged in the six duties, whose blessings are true, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who practise self-control!</p>
                
                <p>(9.) The earth, surrounded by the rolling ocean, is conquered by the lord of men, who is the son of <hi rend="bold">Hiraṇya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the lord of prosperity, whose crest is the bull, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the elephants of whose army ward off enemies.<note>This verse refers, without mentioning the name itself, to king Nandivarman, whose father was Hiraṇya; see verses 28 and 30. The epithets which the king receives in the first half of the verse, are at the same time surnames of Brahmā, Vishṇu and Śiva, and thus hint a comparison of the king to each of these three gods. As the <hi rend="italic">Sāhityadarpaṇa</hi> (pp. 103 and 107 of the Calcutta edition) expresses it, ‘the ornament of <hi rend="italic">simile</hi> is suggested’ <foreign>(upamālaṁkāro vyaṁgyaḥ);</foreign> in another place (p. 109) the term <hi rend="italic">upamā-dhvani</hi>, ‘suggestion of a <hi rend="italic">simile</hi>,’ is used for this figure.</note></p>
                
                <p>Hail! Adoration to Śrī! (10.) First, from the lotus which rose from the navel of Vishṇu, was born the creator, whose origin is the (<hi rend="italic">supreme</hi>) Brahman; who is self-existent; who fully knows the meaning of the sacred texts; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who has performed the creation of the whole world.</p>
                
                <p>(11.) From him was born at the sacrifice a son of the mind alone,<note>Compare Vol. I, No. 24, verse 2, where Aṅgiras is called the son of the mind of Brahmā.</note> <hi rend="bold">Aṅgiras</hi>, who fully carried out his promises; who was more brilliant than fire; who, being sinless, put an end to sin; who, being the chief of seers, obtained a place among the Seven Seers; who reached (<hi rend="italic">the highest degree of</hi>) austerities that can be desired; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who was the best axe for cutting the tree of ignorance.</p>
                
                <p>(12.) From this Aṅgiras (<hi rend="italic">came</hi> <hi rend="bold">Bṛihaspati</hi>), who was an ocean of speeches (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the father of politics; whom (Indra) the lord of the gods<note><hi rend="italic">Sukṛitin</hi> appears to be used for <hi rend="italic">sumanas</hi>, ‘a god.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) elder brother of Tridhāman (Vishṇu), made his preceptor (<hi rend="italic">guru); (and</hi>) relying on the power of whose intellect, the celestial women enjoy at ease amorous pleasures, without thinking of the rising and setting of the sun.</p>
                
                <p>(13.) From him was born the fortunate (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) modest <hi rend="bold">Śaṁyu</hi>, who destroyed sin (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) resembled the sun in brilliancy. When Fire had disappeared, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) became the fire of the gods and performed even the action of fire through his own power.</p>
                
                <p>(14.) His son was a sage called <hi rend="bold">Bharadvāja</hi>, who became the founder of the race (<hi rend="italic">gōtra</hi>) of the glorious <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi> by the power of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) virtues, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who mastered the three Vēdas, which resemble mountains, by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) austerities.</p>
                
                <p>(15.) From him came <hi rend="bold">Drōṇa</hi>, the preceptor<note>This meaning of <hi rend="italic">druhiṇa</hi> is not found in the dictionaries. In Vol. I, No. 24, verse 3, the corresponding word is <hi rend="italic">guru</hi>.</note> of the <hi rend="bold">Kurus</hi>, who was produced from the semen<note>The dictionaries do not contain this meaning of <hi rend="italic">ambuja</hi>.</note> (<hi rend="italic">of</hi> Bharadvāja) in a pitcher called <hi rend="italic">drōṇa</hi> The whose victorious banner was an altar painted on the skin of a black-buck; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who completely mastered (<hi rend="italic">the four branches of</hi>) the science of archery,<note><hi rend="italic">Bāṇāstra-vēda</hi> is synonymous with <hi rend="italic">dhanur-vēda</hi>.</note> which resemble the four oceans.</p>
                
                <p>(16.) From him came the sage <hi rend="bold">Aśvatthāman</hi>, who was an incarnation of (Śiva) the enemy of Cupid; who deserved the confidence of the inhabitants of the world; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) at the rising of whose anger, Kṛishṇa, Arjuna and Bhīma became terrified (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) threw down (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) weapons without any opposition.</p>
                
                <p>(17.) The glorious <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">during whose rule</hi>) the earth was untouched (<hi rend="italic">even</hi>) by the smallest calamity,<note>The same play on <hi rend="italic">Pallava</hi> and <hi rend="italic">āpal-lava</hi> occurs in the Kūram plates (line 11). The Udayēndiram plates (ll. 7 and 11) have <hi rend="italic">vipal-lava</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">āpal-lava</hi>.</note> was suddenly born to him on a litter of sprouts (<hi rend="italic">pallava)</hi><note>The same popular etymology of the name Pallava is alluded to in Vol. I, No. 32, verse 8.</note> by (<hi rend="italic">the nymph</hi>) Mēnakā,<note>According to Vol. I, No. 32, verse 5, the mother of Pallava was the nymph Madanī.</note> that had been sent to him by Śakra (Indra), who was afraid of (<hi rend="italic">losing</hi>) his position (<hi rend="italic">on account of the sage's austerities</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(18.) Though born from a race of Brāhmaṇas, he possessed in the highest degree the valour of the Kshatṟiyas, which was inherent in him. Does not the thunderbolt possess by nature the quality of burning, though it springs from the cloud ?</p>
                
                <p>(19.) From him was produced <hi rend="bold">Aśōkavarman</hi>, who removed the distress of suppliant kings, (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) who distressed those who faced (<hi rend="italic">him</hi>) in battle, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who, though bright as the moon, possessed a spotless fame (<hi rend="italic">while the moon has a spot</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 34.) From him descended the powerful, spotless race of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>, which resembled a partial incarnation of Vishṇu, as it displayed unbroken courage in conquering the circle of the world with all its parts, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) as it enforced the special rules of all castes and orders, and which resembled the descent of the Gaṅgā (<hi rend="italic">on earth</hi>), as it purified the whole world.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 37.) All (<hi rend="italic">the kings</hi>) sprung from this (<hi rend="italic">race</hi>) possessed power that was everywhere irresistible, large armies, pure descent, birth from a lotus,<note>See verse 10.</note> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) great piety, (<hi rend="italic">and therefore</hi>) resembled Kumāra, whose spear is everywhere irresistible, (<hi rend="italic">who is also called</hi>) Mahāsēna, who is the son of Fire, who invented (<hi rend="italic">the array of the army in the form of</hi>) a lotus, (<hi rend="italic">and who is also called</hi>) Subrahmaṇya. The great fierceness,—that resembled fire,—of the power of their arms dried up,—like the water of the ocean,—the irresistible valour of all enemies. The spreading moonshine of their spotless fame removed the impurity of all the sins of the Kali age. Their extremely noble conduct and constant prosperity increased the affection of the crowd of their friends.<note>This sentence has a second meaning, which refers to the sun (<hi rend="italic">mitra</hi>), but which it is useless to reproduce in the translation.</note> The beauty of their forms became the snare, in which,—like deer,—the hearts of young women (<hi rend="italic">were caught</hi>). Their fame, like the fragrance of sandal trees, was pervading the southern region. The shadow of their (<hi rend="italic">royal parasol</hi>) could not be crossed by the power of other (<hi rend="italic">kings</hi>), just as the beauty of the celestial trees cannot be surpassed by the splendour of other (<hi rend="italic">trees</hi>). They were full of splendour and kind to others, (<hi rend="italic">and therefore</hi>) resembled the sun whose rays are beneficial to men. They experienced an increase (<hi rend="italic">āgama</hi>) of the affection (<hi rend="italic">pratyaya</hi>) of (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) subjects (<hi rend="italic">prakṛiti</hi>), and possessed blameless riches (<hi rend="italic">vṛiddhi</hi>) and virtues (<hi rend="italic">guṇa), (and therefore</hi>) resembled the science of grammar, in which crude forms (<hi rend="italic">prakṛiti</hi>), affixes (<hi rend="italic">pratyaya</hi>) and augments (<hi rend="italic">āgama</hi>) are treated, (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) in which (<hi rend="italic">the rules on) guṇa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vṛiddhi</hi> are (<hi rend="italic">not</hi>) without exceptions (<hi rend="italic">apavāda)</hi>.<note>A similar <hi rend="italic">ślēsha</hi> occurs in the description of the Valabhī king Dhruvasēna II.; <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. I, p. 91, note 28. See also <hi rend="italic">Śiśupālavadha</hi>, xix. 75; <hi rend="italic">Sāhityadarpaṇa</hi>, paragraph 586; and Mr. S.P.Pandit's Preface to his edition of the <hi rend="italic">Raghuvaṁśa</hi>, p. 45, note 1.</note> They gave delight (<hi rend="italic">nandana</hi>), but were without enemies (<hi rend="italic">apa-ari-jāta</hi>); while the Nandana (<hi rend="italic">garden</hi>) contains the <hi rend="italic">pārijāta</hi> (tree). Though full of learning (<hi rend="italic">ghanāgama</hi>), they were not dull (<hi rend="italic">jaḍa</hi>); while the rainy season (<hi rend="italic">ghanāgama</hi>) brings water (<hi rend="italic">jala</hi>). As Indra the heaven, (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) lords of the earth enjoyed the whole earth, which is bounded by the Chakravāla mountain (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) adorned by the seven continents and seven oceans.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 45.) Among these have passed away in bygone times <hi rend="bold">[S]kandavarman, Kal[i]ndavarman, Kāṇagōpa, Vishṇugōpa, Vīrakū[r]cha, Vīrasiṁha, Siṁhavarman, Vishṇusiṁha</hi> and other kings, who won great battles by (<hi rend="italic">a knowledge of</hi>) the science of all weapons, whose valour was immeasurable, who had received by inheritance (<hi rend="italic">the practice of</hi>) meritorious acts, who destroyed (<hi rend="italic">the sins of</hi>) the Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>), whose minds were learned, whose bodies bore auspicious marks, who preserved (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) fame (<hi rend="italic">free from blemishes</hi>), whose shoulders were fit to bear the whole earth, who were (<hi rend="italic">evil</hi>) comets to (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) enemies, who conferred honours on (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) friends, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who were the barriers of all good conduct.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 20.) Thereafter came <hi rend="bold">Siṁha[vishṇu]</hi>, the lion of the earth (<hi rend="italic">Avanisiṁha</hi>), who was engaged in the destruction of enemies, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who vanquished the <hi rend="bold">Malaya, Kaḷabhra, Mālava, Chōḷa</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Pāṇdya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">kings</hi>), the <hi rend="bold">Siṁhaḷa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">king</hi>) who was proud of the strength of his arms, and the <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷas</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(21.) Then the earth was ruled by a king called <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi>, whose glory resembled that of Mahēndra, whose commands were respected (<hi rend="italic">by all), (and</hi>) who annihilated (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) chief enemies at <hi rend="bold">Puḷḷalūra</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(22.) From him was born the victorious hero <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi>, who surpassed the glory of the valour of Rāma by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) conquest of <hi rend="bold">Laṅkā</hi>, who was a comet (<hi rend="italic">that foreboded</hi>) destruction to the crowd of proud enemies, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who imitated the pitcher-born (Agastya) by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) conquest of <hi rend="bold">Vātāpi</hi>.<note>The same comparison occurs in the description of the reign of Narasiṁhavarman I. in the Kūram plates (line 17) and in the Udayēndiram plates (l. 14).</note></p>
                
                <p>(23.) From him was born <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi>, whose long arms were fierce thunderbolts to the crowd of enemies, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) beginning with whom, meritorious acts for the benefit of temples and Brāhmaṇas and (<hi rend="italic">the use of</hi>) the vessel of the donor<note><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, the vessel from which libations of water are poured out at donations. Compare the frontispiece of General Sir A. Cunningham's <hi rend="italic">Coins of Ancient India</hi>, where such a vessel is figured in the hand of Anāthapiṇḍika.</note> have highly prospered.</p>
                
                <p>(24.) Then came <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtavarman</hi>, to whose desires the crowd of all kings was subject. This wonderful (<hi rend="italic">king</hi>) possessed high prosperity (<hi rend="italic">bhūti</hi>), was the lord of men (<hi rend="italic">bhūta</hi>), had a bull for (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) crest (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) a club on (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) banner, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) possessed immovable firmness, [thus resembling Śiva, who wears sacred ashes (<hi rend="italic">bhūti</hi>), is the lord of goblins (<hi rend="italic">Bhūta</hi>), has a bull for his emblem and a club on his banner, and resides on the mountain].<note>This is another case of <hi rend="italic">upamā-dhvani</hi>; see p. 354, note 5. The comparison with Śiva is based on the name of the king, Paramēśvara, which is at the same time one of the names of Śiva.</note></p>
                
                <p>(25.) From him was born a complete incarnation of the blessed Paramēśvara, who equalled Narasiṁha both by (<hi rend="italic">the strength of</hi>) his body and by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) name <hi rend="bold">(Narasiṁhavarman)</hi> that spread over the world. This crest-jewel of the Kshatriyas bestowed his wealth on temples and Brāhmaṇas (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) devoutly caused the goddess of the earth, who was in his possession, to be enjoyed by those familiar with the four Vēdas.<note><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, he made grants of land to learned Brāhmaṇas.</note></p>
                
                <p>(26.) From him came <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtavarman</hi>, who obtained desired treasures, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) treasures of fame; who conquered the coquettish ways of the Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>); who led the way of policy, which had been prescribed by Dhishaṇa (Bṛihaspati); (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who protected the worlds.</p>
                
                <p>(27.) At present his prosperous kingdom, in which enemies are subdued by the power of (<hi rend="italic">mere</hi>) commands, is ruled as far as the ocean by <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, who was chosen by the subjects, who is worthy of honour on account of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) wisdom, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who is the full-moon of the race of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>, which is as extensive as the ocean.</p>
                
                <p>(28.) His sixth (<hi rend="italic">ancestor</hi>) was the lord <hi rend="bold">Bhīmavarman</hi>, who was the younger brother of, (<hi rend="italic">and reigned</hi>) after, the glorious <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi>; the fifth <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> ruler (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) the glorious king <hi rend="bold">Buddhavarman</hi>, praised by wise men; the fourth (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ādityavarman</hi>, who resembled (Indra) the bearer of the thunderbolt; the third (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Gōvindavarman</hi>; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the second lord of the earth (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) the glorious <hi rend="bold">Hiraṇya</hi>, the refuge of men.</p>
                
                <p>(29.) This <hi rend="bold">Śrīdhara</hi><note>This was evidently a <hi rend="italic">biruda</hi> of Nandivarman.</note> resembles Vijaya (Arjuna) in battle, Karṇīsuta<note>According to a quotation of the commentator on the <hi rend="italic">Kādambarī</hi> (Bombay edition of 1890, p. 40), Karṇī- suta or Karaṭaka was the author of a treatise on the art of thieving, and was, along with his two friends Vipula and Achala and his minister Śaśa, mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Bṛihatkathā</hi>. He is also referred to in the <hi rend="italic">Daśa- kumāracharita</hi> (Bombay edition of 1883, p. 48).</note> in acquaintance with the arts, Rāma in archery, the king of Vatsa<note>Compare Vol. I, No. 25, paragraph 29.</note> with respect to the science of elephants and to music, Kāma in (<hi rend="italic">the opinion of</hi>) women, the first poet (Vālmīki) in the composition of poetry, the master of policy (Bṛihaspati) himself in suggesting expedients, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) Dharma (Yudhishṭhira) in delighting the subjects.</p>
                
                <p>(30.) Increasing in prosperity is our lord, king <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, who is able to support the race of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>; who is a born emperor; who is handsome; who is a master both in the art of gymnastics and in the virtue of modesty; who is the son of <hi rend="bold">Hiraṇya</hi>; who belongs to the branch (<hi rend="italic">varga</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Bhīma</hi>; who worships the feet of Hari (Vishṇu); who is descended from a pure mother; who bears auspicious marks; who is the son of <hi rend="bold">Rōhiṇī</hi>; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) whose good deeds are numerous.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 71.) While the twenty-second year of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) reign was current, this <hi rend="italic">Rājādhirājaparamēśvara</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Mahārāja</hi> called <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, who is engaged in ruling the kingdom of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvarapōtarāja</hi>; whose mind is clinging to, engaged in, and restless in (<hi rend="italic">the desire for</hi>) supreme bliss; whose head is covered with dust that has dropped from the pair of lotus feet of the Lord (<hi rend="italic">Paramēshṭhin</hi>);<note>This expression seems to refer to Vishṇu, whose devotee Nandivarman was according to verse 30.</note> who worships the gods, the Brāhmaṇas, and (<hi rend="italic">others</hi>) who are worthy of respect; who avoids the passions that oppress the people of the Kali age; who dries up (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) enemies by the fire of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) growing valour; who refreshes (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) friends by the water of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) growing affection; whose right hand is able (<hi rend="italic">to fulfil</hi>) the vow of ruling the whole world; whose pair of feet is rubbed smooth (<hi rend="italic">as it serves as</hi>) whetstones to the edges of the rubies in the diadems of all kings; who is gracefully embraced by the fortune of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> race, (<hi rend="italic">and who therefore resembles</hi>) the celestial tree, which is gracefully entwined by the creeper of the Nandana garden; the wrestler of warriors (<hi rend="italic">Kshatriyamalla</hi>); the wrestler of the Pallavas (<hi rend="italic">Pallavamalla</hi>); whose might is increasing in consequence of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) meditations on the feet of the lord, (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) father;<note>With <hi rend="italic">bappa-bhaṭṭāraka-pād-ānudhyāna</hi> compare the similar expressions which Dr. Fleet quotes from three other Pallava inscriptions; <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XV, p. 274, 2nd column. In the Prākṛit grant of Śivaskanda- varman occurs the instrumental plural <hi rend="italic">mahārāja-bappa-sāmīhi; Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. I, p. 6, text line 11. The nominative plural <hi rend="italic">bappa-bhaṭṭārakar</hi> occurs in line 88 of the Kūram plates.</note> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who is a moon that causes to rise the water of the ocean of great virtues,—was himself pleased to give as a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya,</hi><note>The words <foreign>svayameva prasādāt</foreign> are found in line 97, and the words <foreign>brahmadeyaṁ dattaḥ</foreign> in line 103.</note>—[as requested] by <hi rend="bold">Brahmaśrīrāja</hi>,<note>The occurrence of the words <hi rend="italic">vijñapti</hi> and <hi rend="italic">viṇṇappam</hi> in lines 103 and 106 and the analogy of the Kūram and Udayēndiram plates make it probable that the word <hi rend="italic">vijñaptēna</hi> has to be supplied in connection with the instrumental <hi rend="italic">Brahmaśrīrājēna</hi> in line 91.</note> who is a friend of men; who is filled with all virtues, as the ocean with a heap of gems; who is famous (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) modest, handsome (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) long-lived, of soft speech (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the best of men; who, just as Bṛihaspati (<hi rend="italic">is the minister</hi>) of (Indra) the lord of heaven, is the chief minister of the handsome <hi rend="bold">Nandin</hi>, the lord of the earth (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) chief of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>; who is refined both by nature and through education;<note>With <hi rend="italic">nisarga-nīti-vinīta</hi> compare <hi rend="italic">nisarga-saṁskāra-vinīta, Raghuvaṁśa</hi>, iii. 35; and <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, x. 79.</note> who is the first of the wise, firm (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) brave; who possesses the full splendour of the Brāhmaṇa and Kshatriya castes, and a loyalty to the glorious <hi rend="bold">Nandipōtarāja</hi>, which does not cease as long as the moon and the stars endure; who supports (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) family; who is the chief of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) family; who is an eldest son; who resembles the moon in beauty; who excels in all virtues; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who is an eldest grandson,—to <hi rend="bold">Jyēshṭhapāda-Sōmayājin</hi>, who has mastered the ocean-like Vēdas; who chants the <hi rend="italic">Sāman</hi> (hymns) which are pleasant on account of their melodies (<hi rend="italic">rasa</hi>); who has completed the rehearsal and the study of the six auxiliary works, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) the ritual of the Vēda, grammar, astronomy, etymology, phonetics and metrics;<note>This enumeration of the six <hi rend="italic">Aṅgas</hi> of the Vēda agrees literally with Āpastamba's <hi rend="italic">Dharmasūtra</hi>, ii. 4, 8, 11.</note> who knows the properties of words, sentences and subjects; who has drunk the elixir of the <hi rend="italic">Śruti</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Smṛiti</hi>; who is learned in the portion referring to rites (<hi rend="italic">karma-kāṇḍa</hi>) and the portion referring to knowledge (<hi rend="italic">jñānakāṇḍa</hi>); who is skilled in the ways of the world and in the knowledge of the arts; who is versed in poems, dramas, stories, epics and legends; in short, who is skilled in all (<hi rend="italic">branches of</hi>) holy and profane knowledge; who is expert in the performance of all rites; who is of good conduct; (<hi rend="italic">who illumines</hi>) the world, as a lamp (<hi rend="italic">does</hi>) a house; who is courteous (<hi rend="italic">in spite of</hi>) the honour (<hi rend="italic">paid to him</hi>) and of noble birth; who is the only sun of the middle world (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the earth), because he has dispelled all ignorance (<hi rend="italic">or darkness</hi>);<note>In the original, the description of the donee is here (l. 86) interrupted by that of the minister, and is continued in line 92.</note> who is considered the best of fathers and grand-fathers; whose good deeds (<hi rend="italic">in former births are the reason of his present</hi>) noble birth; who ranks first among the twice-born; who knows the Vēdas; who conforms to the precepts of the Vēda; who follows the <hi rend="italic">Chhandōgasūtra</hi>; who has performed the <hi rend="italic">Vājapēya</hi> and a number of other sacrifices; who belongs to the Bharadvāja <hi rend="italic">gōtra</hi>; who resides at <hi rend="bold">Pūniya</hi>, an excellent settlement of Brāhmaṇas<note>The literal meaning of <hi rend="italic">brahmalōka</hi> is ‘the world or heaven of Brahman.’</note> in the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍāka-rāshṭra</hi>; who is poor in sins; who is distinguished by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) dress (?);<note>In the Sanskrit original, the next seven epithets begin successively with the numbers <hi rend="italic">one, two, three, four, five, six</hi> and <hi rend="italic">seven</hi>.</note> who is a unique person; who cares for both worlds;<note><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, for heavenly as well as earthly prosperity.</note> who accomplishes the three objects of human life (<hi rend="italic">trivarga</hi>); who knows the four Vēdas; whose chief objects are the five primary elements (<hi rend="italic">pañcha-mahābhūta</hi>);<note>This appears to mean that he studied philosophy.</note> who knows the six auxiliary works;<note>This accomplishment of the donee was already stated in full in line 80 f.</note> who resembles the sun; who possesses good qualities; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who is an excellent Brāhmaṇa,—a whole village, the original name of which was <hi rend="bold">Koḍukoḷḷi</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) which, on becoming a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya, (received</hi>) the new name <hi rend="bold">Ēkadhīramaṅgalam</hi>,<note>The word Ēkadhīra, from which the new name of the village is derived, must be taken as a <hi rend="italic">biruda</hi> either of the king or of his minister. Thus the village of Paramēśvaramaṅgalam, which is the object of the Kūram grant, received its name from king Paramēśvaravarman I.; and in the Udayēndiram plates, the village granted was named after Udayachandra, the king's general.</note> in <hi rend="bold">Undivana-kōshṭhaka</hi>,<note>This is a Sanskrit rendering of the Tamil name <foreign>ūṟṟukkāṭṭukkōṭṭam</foreign>, which occurs in line 105. <hi rend="italic">Kōshṭhaka</hi> corresponds to <hi rend="italic">kōṭṭam; vana</hi> is the Sanskrit equivalent of <hi rend="italic">kāḍu</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">undi</hi>, which appears to be formed from the root <hi rend="italic">und</hi>, ‘to spring,’ is intended for an equivalent of <hi rend="italic">ūṟṟu</hi>, ‘a spring.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of the same <hi rend="italic">rāshṭra,</hi><note>This refers to the Toṇḍāka-rāshṭra in line 95.</note> enclosed by the following four boundaries:—in the east, <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr</hi>; in the south, the same; in the west, <hi rend="bold">Maṇatpākka</hi><note>In this word, the letter <hi rend="italic">t</hi> represents the letter <foreign>ṟ</foreign>, which is unknown to Sanskrit, of the Tamil name Maṇaṟpākkam, line 112.</note> and <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷipākka</hi>; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) in the north, <hi rend="bold">Veḷimānallūr,</hi><note>In the Tamil portion (line 113), this name is spelt with the Tamil <foreign>ṉa</foreign> instead of the <hi rend="italic">na</hi>.</note>—to the extent of altogether two <hi rend="italic">nivartanas;</hi><note><foreign>sāmānyanivartanadvayamaryādayā</foreign> is a literal translation of <foreign>cāmāniya iraṇṭupaṭṭippaṭiyāl</foreign> in line 107 f. Accor- dingly, the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">nivartana</hi> (= 40,000 square <hi rend="italic">hastas</hi>) and the Tamil <hi rend="italic">paṭṭi</hi> (‘a measure of land sufficient for a sheep-fold’) are synonymous. <hi rend="italic">Nivartana</hi> occurs in line 38 of the grant of Śivaskandavarman, and <hi rend="italic">paṭṭi</hi> in the Kūram plates.</note> excluding previous grants to temples and grants to Brāhmaṇas; excluding (<hi rend="italic">the houses of</hi>) the ryots;<note><foreign>nirastakuṭumbi</foreign> corresponds to <foreign>kuṭi nīkki</foreign> in line 107.</note> with all exemptions (<hi rend="italic">parihāra); (and</hi>) including <note>The substantives from <foreign>udakabhogaḥ</foreign> to <foreign>niṣkuṭaṁ ca</foreign> depend on <foreign>ityetadabhyantaram</foreign>.</note> the use of the water by digging channels at convenience from the <hi rend="bold">Dūrasarit</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Vēgavatī</hi>, and the tank of <hi rend="bold">Tīralaya</hi>,<note>These three topographical names are again mentioned in line 115 f. <foreign>dūrasarit</foreign> is a Sanskrit translation of <foreign>cēyāṟu</foreign>, the name of the river which forms the southern boundary of the Conjeeveram tālluqa. <foreign>vegavatā</foreign> is the Sanskrit name of the river <foreign>veḵkā</foreign> or <foreign>kampai</foreign>, which passes Conjeeveram on the south. The tank of Tīralaya is identical with the tank of Tīraiyaṉ in line 116.</note> houses, fields, gardens and groves.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 103.) This (<hi rend="italic">grant was made at</hi>) the request (<hi rend="italic">vijñapti</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Brahmayuvarāja</hi>. The executor of the grant (<hi rend="italic">ājñapti) (was</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ghōraśarman</hi>. Hail! Let there be success!</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 31.) The author of the (above) <hi rend="italic">praśasti (was</hi>) the honest <hi rend="bold">Trivikrama</hi>, who knew the truth of all sciences (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) performed sacrifices according to the rules of the three Vēdas.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 104.) (<hi rend="italic">The above is</hi>) an order of the king (<hi rend="italic">kōṉ-ōlai), (dated in</hi>) the twenty-second year (<hi rend="italic">of his reign</hi>). Let the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāṭṭu-kōṭṭam</hi> see (<hi rend="italic">it) !</hi></p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 105.) Having seen the order (<hi rend="italic">tirumugam</hi>), which was issued after (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) had been pleased to give <hi rend="bold">Koḍukoḷḷi</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a village</hi>) of our country,—having expropriated the former owners, at the request of <hi rend="bold">Brahmayuvarāja</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">having appointed</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ghōraśarman</hi> as <hi rend="italic">ājñapti (āṇatti</hi>), having excluded (<hi rend="italic">previous</hi>) grants to temples and grants to Brāhmaṇas, having excluded the houses (<hi rend="italic">of the ryots</hi>), to the extent of altogether two <hi rend="italic">paṭṭi</hi>,—as a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Śēṭṭiṟeṅga-Sōmayājin</hi>, who belongs to the Bhāradvāja <hi rend="italic">gōtra</hi>, follows the <hi rend="italic">Chhandōgasūtra</hi> and resides at <hi rend="bold">Pūni</hi>,—we, the inhabitants, went to the boundaries which the headman (<hi rend="italic">viyavaṉ</hi>) of the district (<hi rend="italic">nāḍu</hi>) pointed out, circumambulated the village (<hi rend="italic">paḍāgai</hi>) from right to left, and planted stones and milk-bush (<hi rend="italic">round it</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 111.) The boundaries of (<hi rend="italic">this village are):</hi>—The eastern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the west of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr</hi>; the southern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the north of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Pālaiyūr</hi>; the western boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the east of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Maṇaṟpākkam</hi> and of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷipākkam</hi>; and the northern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the south of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Veḷimāṉallūr</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 114.) (<hi rend="italic">The donee</hi>) shall enjoy the wet land and the dry land included within these four boundaries, wherever the iguana runs and the tortoise crawls,<note>A similar phrase is used in line 305 of the large Leyden grant.</note> (<hi rend="italic">and shall be permitted</hi>) to dig river channels and inundation channels for conducting water from the <hi rend="bold">Śēyāṟu</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Veḥkā</hi>, and the tank of <hi rend="bold">Tīraiyaṉ</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) shall obtain . . . . . . . . . .<note>Here two technical terms are omitted. One of them, <foreign>puḻutipāṭu</foreign>, occurs in line 79 of the Kūram plates.</note> for these channels. Those who take and use (<hi rend="italic">the water</hi>) in these channels by pouring out baskets, by cutting branch channels (?),<note><foreign>kuṟaṅkaṟuttu</foreign> occurs in No. 5, paragraph 14.</note> or by employing small levers,<note>The same implement is mentioned in line 81 of the Kūram plates. Each of the three terms <foreign>kuṟaṅku, kuṟṟēttam</foreign> and <foreign>kūṭai</foreign> occurs in line 310 f. of the large Leyden grant. On the irrigation basket and lever see Dr. Grierson's <hi rend="italic">Bihār Peasant Life</hi>, paragraph 949, and Dr. Buchanan's <hi rend="italic">Journey through Mysore</hi>, Madras reprint, Vol. I, p. 183.</note> shall pay a fine to be taken by the king. He and his descendants shall enjoy the houses, house gardens and so forth (<hi rend="italic">and shall have the right</hi>) to build houses and halls of burnt tiles. (<hi rend="italic">The land</hi>) included within these (<hi rend="italic">boundaries</hi>) we have endowed with all exemptions.<note>Here and in the next sentence, <foreign>paricāram</foreign> appears to be used for <foreign>parikāram</foreign> (<hi rend="italic">parihāra</hi>). Compare <foreign>sarvaparihārābhyantarīkaraṇena</foreign> in line 101.</note> He himself shall enjoy the exemptions obtaining in this village without paying for the oil-mills and looms, the hire of the well-diggers (<hi rend="italic">ulliyar</hi>), the share (<hi rend="italic">kāṇam</hi>) of the Brāhmaṇas and of the king, the share of <hi rend="italic">śeṅgoḍi,</hi><note>According to Winslow, <foreign>ceṅkoṭivēli </foreign> is ‘a running plant whose root is a powerful caustic, rose coloured lead-wort, <hi rend="italic">Plumbago Zeylanica</hi>, L.’</note> the share of <hi rend="italic">kallāl,</hi><note>According to the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Tamoul-Français</hi>, this is the tree <hi rend="italic">Ficus Mysorensis</hi>.</note> the share of <hi rend="italic">kaṇṇiṭṭu</hi> (?), the share of corn ears (<hi rend="italic">kadir</hi>), the share of the headman, the share of the potter,<note><foreign>vicakkāṇam</foreign> and <foreign>kucakkāṇam</foreign> are derived from <foreign>vicavaṉ</foreign>, another form of <foreign>viyavaṉ</foreign> (Vol. I, p. 116, note 7), and <foreign>kucavaṉ</foreign>.</note> the sifting of paddy, the price of ghee, the price of cloth (<hi rend="italic">puṭṭagam</hi>), the share of the cloth (<hi rend="italic">paṭṭigai</hi>), the hunters (?), messengers, dancing-girls, . . . . . . . . . .<note>The two obscure terms which are here omitted, contain the words <foreign>paṇṇu</foreign> (which may be connected with <foreign>paṇṇuvar </foreign>, ‘riders on horses or on elephants,’) and <foreign>kutirai</foreign>, ‘a horse,’ and may therefore correspond to the terms <foreign>āṉaikkūṭam</foreign> (‘elephant-stalls’) and <foreign>kutiraippanti</foreign> (‘horse-stables’) on page 115, text line 11.</note> the grass, the best cow and the best bull, the share of the district (<hi rend="italic">nāṭṭuvagai</hi>), cotton threads (<hi rend="italic">paḍāṅ-gaṛi</hi>), servants, <hi rend="italic">neḍumbuṟai</hi>, palmyra molasses, the fine to the accountant (<hi rend="italic">karaṇam</hi>) and the fine to the minister,<note><foreign>atikaraṇam</foreign> appears to be used for <hi rend="italic">adhikārin</hi>, as <foreign>atikārar</foreign> in line 132 and <foreign>atikāram</foreign> in Vol. I, p. 94. Compare <hi rend="italic">pradhāni-jōḍi</hi>, Vol. II, p. 119.</note> <hi rend="italic">pattūr-śāṟṟu</hi>, . . . . . . . . . .<note>The obscure term <foreign>uḻaiyavayappaḷḷivattu</foreign> contains the words <foreign>uḻaiyaṉ </foreign>, ‘a servant,’ and <foreign>paḷḷi</foreign>, ‘a temple.’</note> the tax (<hi rend="italic">vari</hi>) on planting water-lilies, the share of the water-lilies, the fourth part of the trunks, which is given of old trees of various kinds,<note>Compare <foreign>palluruvil paḻamaraṅkaḷ</foreign>, ‘old trees of various kinds,’ in Vol. I, No. 40, text line 38.</note> including areca palms and cocoanut trees . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 132.) The grant (<hi rend="italic">para-datti</hi>) was made in the presence of the local authorities (?), of the ministers,<note>See note 2.</note> and of the secretaries.<note>Literally, ‘those who hear (the words of) the mouth (of the king).’ The term <hi rend="italic">kīṛ-vāy-kkēḷppāṉ</hi>, ‘an under-secretary,’ occurs at the end of the Cochin plates of Bhāskara Ravivarman; <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 69.</note></p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 133.) [Three of the usual imprecatory verses.]</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 136.) Hail! Written by His Majesty's great treasurer (<hi rend="italic">Śrī-Paramēśvara-mahākōshṭhāgārin</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">L</hi>. 137.) He (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the donee) shall obtain the houses, the house-gardens, and two <hi rend="italic">paṭṭi</hi> of land.<note>Compare line 107.</note></p>
                
                <p>Hail! Let there be success! Adoration!</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 2.73 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1895_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1895_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">342-361</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">73</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
