<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.82: original edition by V. Venkayya</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 82. ON THE BASE OF THE SOUTH ENCLOSURE. No. 29 of 1897.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0082</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 7th year of <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷa</hi> I. The king's conquests end with the subjugation of the island of <hi rend="bold">Śāndimattīvu</hi>. As we know that the invasion of the “many ancient islands” immediately preceded this event and that it took place in the 6th year,<note n="402-3">See above, p. 92.</note> it may be concluded that the conquest of <hi rend="bold">Śāndimattīvu</hi> must have taken place in the 7th year of the king's reign = A.D. 1018-19. The <hi rend="bold">Tiruvālaṅgāḍu</hi> plates<note n="402-4">See my <hi rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> for 1905-06, Part II, paragraph 17.</note> tell us that <hi rend="bold">Rā0jē0ndra-Choḷa</hi> advanced against the Western Country because he had heard of the disgrace which the kings of the earth had suffered at the hands of <hi rend="bold">Paraśurāma</hi>. Not finding him on earth the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> king desired to conquer the country reclaimed by him, which was protected against foreign invasion by the greatness of Paraśurāma's penance. It is evident that the conquest of the island of <hi rend="bold">Śāndimattīvu</hi> was the most important event of the campaign against <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷa</hi> which must have taken place in A.D. 1018-19.</p>						

						<p>The subjoined inscription registers an endowment in money in favour of the image of <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṇṭhamūrtigaḷ</hi> set up by <hi rend="bold">Pṛithivīmahādēviyār</hi>, queen of <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi>. The money was lent out on interest to the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅga-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Āvūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, a subdivision of <hi rend="bold">Nittavinōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>. The interest was to be paid in kind and amounted to thirty-seven <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>, one <hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">padakku</hi> of paddy.</p>						

						<p>This and the next record belong to a class of Tanjore inscriptions which are dated during the reign of <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷa</hi> I. and register endowments by groups of men. To each of these groups a shrine in the temple was “attached” by order of the king.<note n="402-5">To the same class belong Nos. 9, 11 to 19 and No. 54 above.</note> </p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrīḥ</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tiru manti vaḷara Irunila<unclear>maṭantaiyum por</unclear>ccaya<unclear>p</unclear>pāvaiyuñcīrttaṉiccelvi<unclear>yu</unclear>ntan peruntevi<unclear>yarā</unclear>kiyiṉapuṟa n<unclear>eṭutuyalū</unclear>ḻiyuḷ Iṭ<unclear>aitu</unclear>ṟaināṭu<unclear>n</unclear>toṭarvaṉav<unclear>e</unclear>lippa<unclear>ṭar</unclear> vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻmatiṭkoḷḷippākkaiyu- naṇṇaṟkarumuraṇ maṇṇaikkaṭa<unclear>ka</unclear>mum<note n="403-1">ṇo. 9 above has also the reading maṇṇaikkaṭakamum.</note> poruta<unclear>ṭa</unclear>rīḻattaraicartamuṭiyumāṅkavar teviyaroṅkeḻilmuṭiyum muṉṉavar <unclear>pa</unclear>kkal tennavar vaitta cuntaramuṭiyum Intiraṉāramum teṇṭi<unclear>r</unclear>ai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟipaṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>kkeraḷarmuṟaimaiyiṟcū<unclear>ṭu</unclear>ṅkulatanamākiya <unclear>pa</unclear>larpu<unclear>ka</unclear>ḻmuṭiyuñceṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>tirmālaiyu<unclear>ñca</unclear>ṅkatirvelaittolperuṅkāval pa<unclear>lapaḻantī</unclear>vuñceruvi<unclear>ṟ</unclear>ciṉa<unclear>vil Irupa</unclear>tt<unclear>o</unclear>rukāl Araicukaḷai kaṭṭa paracu<unclear>r</unclear>āmaṉ mevaruñcāntimattivvaraṇ karutiyiruttiya cempoṟṟiruttaku muṭiyumāpporuta<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭāṟkkoṇṭa koppara<hi rend="grantha">kesari</hi>va[ <hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>r] Āṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷa</hi>
<lb n="2" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vark<unclear>ku</unclear> yāṇṭu Eḻ<unclear>ā</unclear>vatu Uṭai[ yār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendraco</hi>] <hi rend="grantha">ḷade</hi>var pe<unclear>ru</unclear>ntanattu<unclear>k</unclear>ka<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>rmmi</unclear></hi>kaḷ karaṇattārkaḷu<unclear>k</unclear>ku Aṭaitta <hi rend="grantha">śrī<unclear>rā</unclear>jarā<unclear>jīśvaram</unclear></hi> U<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ai<unclear>yār ko</unclear>yilil Uṭaiyā<unclear>r</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var nampirāṭṭiyā[ r <hi rend="grantha">pṛ</hi>] <hi rend="grantha">thi</hi>vi<hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>viyār Eḻunta<unclear>ru</unclear>ḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kaṇṭamūrttikaḷukkuttirua<unclear>mu</unclear>tu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunnivantaṅkaḷukku Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>varkku yā<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭu <unclear>Eḻā</unclear>vatu varai vaitta kācu <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>ttiniteḻuntaruḷi Irunta <hi rend="grantha">para<unclear>ma</unclear>svāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>mū</unclear>la<unclear>bhṛtya</unclear>-</hi> nā<unclear>ki</unclear>ya <hi rend="grantha">ca<unclear>ṇḍeśva</unclear>rad<unclear>e</unclear></hi>var pakkal policaikku koṇṭa Ūruṅkallil veṭṭiṉa <g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g><hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kaṇṭamūrttikaḷukkupperuntanattukka<hi rend="grantha">rmi</hi>kaḷ <unclear>kara</unclear>ṇattārkaḷ Ivar<unclear>kku</unclear>tti<unclear>ruamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭu</unclear>nnivan<unclear>taṅkaḷukku vai</unclear>tta kācu nitta<unclear>viṉ</unclear>otavaḷanāṭṭu <unclear>Āvūrk</unclear>kūṟṟattu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m</hi> nara[ ciṅka<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu] <hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>va<unclear>rk</unclear>ku yāṇṭu Eḻāvatu mutal koṇṭa kā<unclear>cu</unclear> nū<unclear>ṟ</unclear>ṟaimpatināl kācu O
<lb n="3" break="no"/>ṉṟukku Āṭṭaivaṭṭaṉ muk<unclear>kuṟuṇi nellu poli</unclear>caiy<unclear>āka</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">candrā<unclear>di</unclear>ttya</hi>val Āṭṭāṇṭut<unclear>oṟu</unclear>ntañcāvūr Uṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>y<unclear>ār</unclear> p[erumpaṇṭārat ?]te <hi rend="grantha">rājakesa<unclear>ri</unclear>-</hi> yoṭ<unclear>ok</unclear>kum Āṭavallāṉeṉṉum marakkāl<unclear>ā</unclear>l Aḷakkakkaṭava nellu muppatteḻukalaney tūṇippatakku <g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Venkayya1913_01">

<p>Hail! Prosperity! In the seventh year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who,—in (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) life of high prosperity<note n="403-2">Nos. 9 to 19 above and No. 83 below read <ta>neṭutiyal</ta>.</note> , while fortune, having become constant, was increasing, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) while the goddess of the great earth, the goddess of victory in battle, and the matchless goddess of fame rejoiced in having become his great queens,—conquered, with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) great warlike army, <hi rend="bold">Iḍaituṟai-nāḍu; Vaṉavāśi</hi>, whose unbroken hedge of forest (<hi rend="italic">trees</hi>) was extending; <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷippākkai</hi>, whose walls were surrounded by ‘śuḷḷi’ (<hi rend="italic">trees</hi>); the camp of <hi rend="bold">Maṇṇai</hi>, whose strength (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> fortifications) was unapproachable; the crown of the king of <hi rend="bold">Īṛam</hi>, who came to close quarters in fighting; the exceedingly beautiful crown of the queen of that (<hi rend="italic">king</hi>); the beautiful crown and <hi rend="bold">Indra's</hi> pearl-necklace which the king of the South (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi>) had previously deposited with that (king of <hi rend="bold">Īṛam</hi>); the whole <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi> on the transparent sea; the crown praised by many and the garland (<hi rend="italic">emitting</hi>) beautiful rays,—family treasures, which the (<hi rend="italic">kings of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷa</hi>, whose armies overcame (<hi rend="italic">opponents</hi>), rightfully wore; many ancient islands, whose old and great guard was the sea, which resounds with conches; the crown of pure gold, worthy of Lakshmī, which <hi rend="bold">Paraśurāma</hi>, having thought of the fortifications of the impregnable <hi rend="bold">Śāndimattīvu</hi>, had deposited (<hi rend="italic">there</hi>) when, enraged in battle, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) bound the kings twentyone times,—there was engraved on stone (<hi rend="italic">the name of</hi>) the village which had received on interest from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—the first servant of the supreme lord who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,—the money which had been deposited until the seventh year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi> on account of the offerings and other expenses required for (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṇṭhamūrtigaḷ</hi>, which <hi rend="bold">Pṛithivīmahādēviyār</hi>, the consort of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>, had set up in the temple of <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvaramuḍaiyār</hi> and which the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi> had attached to the artisans (<hi rend="italic">karmigaḷ</hi>) of the <hi rend="italic">Perundaṉam (and</hi>) the accountants.<note n="404-1">It is also possible that the “accountants of the artisans” is intended.</note> </p>

<p>2. The members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅga-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Āvūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittavinōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have received at the beginning of the seventh year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, one hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāśu (out of</hi>) the money which the artisans of the <hi rend="italic">Perundaṉam (and</hi>) the accountants had deposited on account of the offerings and other expenses required for this (<hi rend="italic">image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṇṭhamūrtigaḷ</hi>. For (<hi rend="italic">these one hundred and fifty kāśu, the former</hi>) have to make over every year, as long as the moon and the sun (<hi rend="italic">endure</hi>), thirty-seven <hi rend="italic">kalam, (one) tūṇi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) padakku</hi> of paddy into the big treasury of the lord at <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi> which is equal to a <hi rend="italic">rājakēsari</hi>—the rate of interest being three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuni</hi> of paddy per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.82 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Venkayya1913_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Venkayya1913_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">402-404</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">82</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
