<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.12: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 12. ON THE SOUTH WALL, FIRST TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0012</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription, which is dated in the same year as No. 10, records endowments to an image, the name of which is lost, but can be supplied with certainty from No. 13, and to the image of <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>, which had been set up by a person, that is also mentioned in the large Leyden grant.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="7"/><note n="97-1">Continued from page 96.</note> tiru maṉṉi vaḷara Irunilamaṭantaiyum poṟcayappāvaiyuñcīrttaṉiccelviyuntaṉ perunteviyarākiyiṉpuṟa neṭutiyalūḻiyuḷiṭaituṟaināṭuntuṭarvaṉavelippaṭar vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻ<unclear>ma</unclear>tiḷ k<unclear>o</unclear>ḷḷippākkaiyunaṇṇaṟkarumaraṇ maṇṇaikkaṭakkamum porutaṭarīḻa<unclear>ttaraicar ta</unclear>muṭiyumāṅkavar teviyaroṅkeḻil muṭiyumuṉṉavar pakkal teṉṉavar <unclear>v</unclear>aitta cuntaramuṭi<unclear>yu</unclear>m Intiraṉāramunteṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟipaṭaikk<unclear>e</unclear>raḷar muṟaimaiyiṟcūṭuṅkulataṉamākiya palar pukaḻ muṭiyuñceṅkatir mālaiyuñcaṅkatirvelaittolperuṅkāval palapaḻantīvuñceruviṟciṉaviyirupattorukāl Araicukaḷai kaṭ<unclear>ṭa pa</unclear>racurāmaṉ m<unclear>e</unclear>varuñcāntimattīvaraṇ karutiyiruttiya cempoṟṟiruttaku muṭiyum payaṅkoṭu paḻi mika muyaṅkiyil mutukiṭṭoḷi
</p>

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Second section</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1" break="no"/><unclear>tta cayaciṅkaṉ A</unclear>ḷa<unclear>pparum pu</unclear>kaḻoṭu pīṭiyaliraṭṭapāṭiyeḻarai Ilakkamum na<unclear>vanetik</unclear>kulapperumalaikaḷumāpporutaṇṭāṟ<unclear>k</unclear>o<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭa k<unclear>o</unclear>p<unclear>parak</unclear>e<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>riva- <hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>rāṉa Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi><unclear>va</unclear>rkku yāṇṭu pattāvatu Aruḷmoḻi<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vavaḷa<unclear>n</unclear>āṭṭu n<unclear>e</unclear>ṉmalināṭṭuppaḷḷiyiṟ<hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yār tañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājī</hi>[ <hi rend="grantha">śvara</hi>ttiṉi] teḻu<unclear>n</unclear>taruḷiyirunta <hi rend="grantha">paramasvāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha">mūlabhṛtya</hi>ṉākiya <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>var pakkal Uṭai[ yār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>muṭaiy] Ārk<unclear>ku Aṭ</unclear>ait<unclear>ta niyāyam</unclear> p<unclear>eruntaṉat</unclear>tu <unclear>vala</unclear>ṅ<unclear>kaive</unclear>ḷaikkāṟappaṭaikaḷil paṇṭitacoḻatterintavillikaḷ Ivarkku v<unclear>eṇṭum nivantaṅka</unclear>ḷukku vaitta kācil kācu muppattoṉṟu<unclear>m</unclear> Ivarkke nittaviṉotatterintavalaṅkaiveḷaikkāṟar meṟpaṭikku vaitta kācu patiṉ mūṉṟum peruntaṉam Īrāyiravaṉ pa<unclear>llavayaṉā</unclear>ṉa mummaṭicoḻapocaṉāṉa Uttamacoḻappallavaraiyaṉ Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>varkku Aṭaitta niyāyam Uttamacoḻatterinta Antaḷakattāḷār Ivarkku ve<unclear>ṇṭum niva</unclear>ntaṅkaḷukku <unclear>v</unclear>aitta kācu Aṟupatum Āka yāṇṭu pattāvatu pacāṉ mutal koṇṭa kācu nūṟṟu nālu <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied></hi> Ikkācu nūṟṟu nāliṉāluṅkācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vīṭṭaṉ policai kācu Araikkālāka <unclear>yāṇ</unclear>ṭu pattāvatu pacāṉ mutal <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">t</hi> Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>muṭaiyār paṇṭārattu Iṭakkaṭava policai kācu patiṉ mūṉṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. After (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who, <hi rend="italic">etc.,</hi><note n="98-1">The historical part of this inscription is identical with that of No. 10.</note> the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Paḷḷiyil</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Neṉmali-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Aruḷmoṛidēva-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have received from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—who is the first servant of the supreme lord, who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>,—one hundred and four <hi rend="italic">kāśu, viz</hi>., thirty-one <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> out of the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Paṇḍita-Śōṛa-terinda-villigaḷ</hi>,<note n="98-2"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the chosen archers of Paṇḍita-Chōḷa.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of the <hi rend="bold">[Niyāyam P]e[rundaṉat]tu [Vala]ṅ[gai-vē]ḷaikkāṟa-paḍaigaḷ</hi>,<note n="98-3"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the troops of servants of the right hand of the large treasure.’ <ta>vēḷaikkāṟaṉ</ta> seems to be a corruption of <ta>vēlaikkāraṉ</ta>.</note> who were attached to the lord [of the <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>)], had deposited for the expenses required by this (<hi rend="italic">image</hi>); thirteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which the <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-terinda-valaṅgai-vēḷaikkāṟar</hi> had deposited for the above (<hi rend="italic">requirements</hi>) of this (<hi rend="italic">image</hi>); and sixty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which the <hi rend="bold">Niyāyam Uttama-Śōṛa-terindaandaḷagattāḷār</hi>,—<note n="98-4"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the chosen knights of Uttama-Chōḷa.’ <ta>antaḷakattāḷār </ta> may be dissolved into <ta>antaḷakattu</ta>, the genitive case of <ta>antaḷakam </ta>,—which seems to be another form of <ta>antaḷam</ta>, ‘a coat of mail,’—and <ta>āḷu</ta>, ‘to possess.’</note> who were attached to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>, which had been set up by <hi rend="bold">Perundaṉam Īrāyiravaṉ Pa[llavayaṉ]</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Mummaḍi-Śōṛa-Pōśaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Śōṛa-Pallavaraiyaṉ</hi>,—<note n="98-5">The same person is mentioned in lines 132 f., 163 f. and 439 f. of the large Leyden grant.</note> had deposited for the expenses required by this (<hi rend="italic">image</hi>).</p>

<p>2. For these one hundred and four <hi rend="italic">kāśu, (they</hi>) have to pay every year from (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, an interest of thirteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the treasury of the lord of the <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>),—the rate of interest being one eighth <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.12 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">97-98</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">12</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
