<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.11: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 11. ON THE SOUTH WALL, FIRST TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0011</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>The date of this inscription is the same as that of No. 10. It records endowments to the two last of the images, which were mentioned in No. 10, and to the images of <hi rend="bold">Kalyāṇasundarar</hi> and his consort, the first of which had been set up by <hi rend="bold">Trailōkyamahādēvī</hi>, a queen of <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="6"/><note n="95-3">Continued from page 94.</note> tiru manni vaḷara Irunilamaṭantaiyum poṟcayappāvai<unclear>yuñ</unclear>cīrttaṉiccelviyuntaṉ perunteviyarākiyiṉpuṟa neṭutiyalūḻiyuḷ I<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aituṟaināṭuntuṭarvaṉavelippaṭar vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻmatiḷ koḷḷippākkaiyum naṇṇaṟkarumuraṇ maṇṇaikkaṭakkamum porutaṭarīḻattaraicar tamuṭiyum Āṅkavar teviyaroṅkeḻil muṭiyum muṉṉavar pakkal teṉṉavar vaitta cuntaramuṭiyum Intiraṉāramunteṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟipaṭaikkeraḷar muṟaimaiyiṟcūṭuṅkulataṉamākiya palar pukaḻ muṭi<unclear>yu</unclear>ñceṅkatir mālaiyuñcaṅkatirvelaittolperuṅkāval palapaḻantīvuñceruviṟciṉaviyirupattorukālaraicukaḷai kaṭṭa paracurāmaṉ mevaru<unclear>ñ</unclear>cāntimattīvaraṇ karutiyiruttiya cempoṟṟiruttaku muṭiyum payaṅkoṭu paḻi mika muyaṅkiyil mutukiṭṭoḷitta cayaciṅka<unclear>ṉ Aḷa</unclear>pperum pukaḻoṭu pīṭiyaliraṭṭapāṭi Eḻarai Ilakkamum navanetikkulapperumalaika<unclear>ḷum māppo</unclear>rutaṇṭāṟkoṇṭa kopparake<hi rend="grantha">sari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>rāṉa Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷad</hi>[ <hi rend="grantha">E</hi>varkku yāṇṭu pa] ttā<unclear>va</unclear>tu Arumoḻi<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vavaḷanāṭṭuppuṟaṅkarampaināṭṭu Arumoḻi<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār tañcāvūr <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>ttiṉiteḻuntaruḷiyirunta <hi rend="grantha">paramasvāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha">mūlabhṛtya</hi>ṉākiya <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>var pakkal Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">mahāmeru-</hi> viṭaṅkarkku<unclear>m</unclear> nampirāṭṭiyārkkum Aṭaitta niyāyam ciṟutaṉattuppaṇimakkaḷ <unclear>I</unclear>varkaḷukku veṇṭum nivantaṅkaḷukku vaitta kācil kācu Irunūṟṟutto
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ṇṇūṟṟu nālum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var <unclear>na</unclear>mpirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">trailokhya</hi><note n="96-1">Read <hi rend="grantha">trailokya</hi>.</note> <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>viyār Eḻuntaruḷu<unclear>vi</unclear>tta <hi rend="grantha">kalyā</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">sundara</hi>rkkum nampirāṭṭiyārkkum Aṭaitta niyāya<unclear>ṅkaḷi</unclear>lār Ivarkaḷukku veṇṭu<unclear>m</unclear> nivantaṅkaḷukku vaitta kācil keraḷāntakavācaṟtirumeykāppar kācu nūṟṟorupatteṭṭum Aṇukkavācaṟtirum<unclear>e</unclear>ykāppar kācu Eṭṭum keraḷāntakatterintaparivārattār kācu muppattaiñcu<unclear>m</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>nanātatterintaparivārattār kācu Aiñcum ciṅkaḷāntakatterintapa<unclear>ri</unclear>vārattār kācu Oṉṟum teṉkaraināṭṭupparivārameykāpparkaḷ kācu munnūṟṟu muppattoṉpatum Āka yāṇṭu pat<unclear>tā</unclear>vatu pacāṉ mutal koṇṭa kācu Eṇṇūṟu <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied></hi> Ikkācu Eṇṇūṟiṉālum kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vīṭṭaṉ policai kācu Araik<unclear>k</unclear>ālāka yāṇṭu pattāvatu pacāṉ mutal <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">t</hi> Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvaram</hi> Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">bhaṇḍā</hi>rattu Iṭakkaṭa<unclear>va</unclear> policai kācu nūṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. [In the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of] <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷa[dēva]</hi>, who, <hi rend="italic">etc.,</hi><note n="96-2">The historical part of this inscription is identical with that of No. 10.</note> the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Arumoṛidēvachaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Puṟaṅgarambai-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Arumoṛidēvavaḷanāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">have received</hi>) from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—who is the first servant of the supreme lord, who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>,—two hundred and ninety-four <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> out of the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Niyāyam<note n="96-3">The technical meaning of <hi rend="italic">niyāyam</hi> (Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">nyāya</hi>) is not apparent. Perhaps it stands for <hi rend="italic">niyāśam</hi> (Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">nyāsa</hi>), ‘a deposit, pledge, mortgage,’ and has to be translated by ‘dedicated (<hi rend="italic">to the god</hi>).’</note> Śiṟudaṉattu Paṇimakkaḷ</hi>,—<note n="96-4">See page 95. note 2.</note> who were attached to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahā-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, which had been set up by the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>, and to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) his consort,—had deposited for the expenses required by these (<hi rend="italic">images</hi>). And, out of the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Niyāya[ṅgaḷi]lār</hi>,—who were attached to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kalyāṇasundarar</hi>, which had been set up by <hi rend="bold">Trailōkyamahādēvī</hi>, the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>, and to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) his consort,—had deposited for the expenses required by these (<hi rend="italic">images</hi>), the <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷāntaka-vāśal-tirumeykāppar</hi><note n="96-5">Literally, ‘the body-guard of the gate of Kēraḷāntaka.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">have received</hi>) one hundred and eighteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>; the <hi rend="bold">Aṇukka-vāśal-tirumeykāppar</hi> eight <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>; the <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷāntakaterinda-parivārattār</hi><note n="96-6"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the chosen retinue of Kēraḷāntaka.’</note> thirty-five <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>; the <hi rend="bold">Jananātha-terinda-parivārattār</hi> five <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>; the <hi rend="bold">Śiṅgaḷāntaka-terinda-parivārattār</hi> one <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>; and the <hi rend="bold">Parivāra-mey- kāppargaḷ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Teṉkarai-nāḍu</hi> three hundred and thirty-nine <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>. Altogether, eight hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>) were received after (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi>) in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>).</p>

<p>2. For these eight hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu, (they</hi>) have to pay every year from (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), as long as the moon and the sun endure, an interest of one hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the treasury of the lord of the <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>),—the rate of interest being one eighth <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.11 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">95-97</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">11</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
