<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 2.98: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
                <title type="alt">No. 98. VELURPALAIYAM PLATES OF VIJAYA-NANDIVARMAN (III).</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0098</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>These plates were discovered in 1911 by the late Rai Bahadur V.Venkayya, M.A., in the village <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi>, about 7 miles north-west of Arkonam in the North Arcot district. They have since been purchased by the Government for deposit in the Madras Museum. A detailed description of the plates and their contents has appeared in the Epigraphical Report for 1911, Part II, paragraphs 5 to 12. Mr. Venkayya also, has published a valuable note on them in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society</hi> for 1911, pp. 521 ff.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The plates are five in number and consist of eight written sides, the outer faces of the first and last being completely blank. They vary in length from 9(5/8)" to 9(3/4)", and are slightly convex on their right and left sides. The breadth of each plate is about 3(1/2)". The ring which holds the plates together is oval-shaped, and measures 7" x 6(1/4)", while the circular seal in whose massive bottom the edges of the ring are firmly fixed, is 3(1/4)" in diameter. The seal bears on a depressed surface an elongated figure of a <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> bull in a recumbent posture facing the proper right with an ornamental lamp-stand on either side of it. The bull and the lamp-stands are placed on a straight line which is perhaps to be taken for the surface of a pedestal. Below this latter, there appear the faint traces of an expanded lotus flower. Above the bull are engraved in one row, eight symbols of which a goddess (perhaps Lakshmī), flanked by two lamp-stands occupies the centre. Another symbol which is recognisable is the <hi rend="italic">svastika</hi>. The remaining four are indistinct. Above these again are the insignia of royalty, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">chauris</hi> mounted on handles and a parasol between them. Right round the margin of the seal is a defaced legend in Pallava-Grantha characters of which the syllables . . . . . . <hi rend="italic">va-nāthasya Nan[tipa]ṉmas[ya] bhū[pa*]tēḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> viśva-[vi]śva[ṁ]bharāpāla śrīḥ</hi>, are visible. The plates including ring and seal weigh 394 <hi rend="italic">tolas</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The inscription on the plates is engraved partly in <hi rend="bold">Grantha</hi> and partly in <hi rend="bold">Tamil</hi> characters. The writing discloses two different scripts, the first of which (ll. 1 to 28) is somewhat less deeply cut and slanting. The <hi rend="italic">virāma</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">puḷḷi</hi> in the Tamil portion of the inscription is marked almost regularly throughout, by a zigzag line resembling the final <hi rend="italic">m</hi> of Grantha or by the usual dot. The grant consists of 31 <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi> verses intercepted in the middle by a prose passage in Tamil from lines 47 to 63, and including at the end a short Tamil sentence in lines 68 and 69. Verses 1 and 2 are invocations addressed to the Supreme Being and to <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṇṭha (Śiva)</hi>. The two next supply the legendary origin of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi> from <hi rend="bold">Vishṇu</hi>, down to the eponymous king <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi>, through <hi rend="bold">Brahmā, Aṅgiras, Bṛihaspati, Śaṁyu, Bharadvāja, Drōṇa</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Aśvatthāman</hi>, and eulogise the family as being very powerful. From verses 5 to 8, we learn the names of some probably historical kings. One of them was <hi rend="bold">Aśōkavarman</hi> in whose family was born <hi rend="bold">Kāḷabhartṛi</hi>. His son was <hi rend="bold">Chūtapallava</hi>; his son, <hi rend="bold">Vīrakūrcha</hi>; from him came <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi>; from him, <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> and after him, <hi rend="bold">Buddhavarman</hi>. It is evident, as Professor Hultzsch has remarked, (above, p. 342), that <hi rend="bold">Aśōkavarman</hi> “can scarcely be considered a historical person, but appears to be a modification of the ancient <hi rend="bold">Maurya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Aśōka</hi>.” <hi rend="bold">Kāḷabhartṛi</hi> is a possible synonym of <hi rend="bold">Kāṇagōpa</hi>, who is mentioned in the <hi rend="bold">Kāśākuḍi</hi> plates, in the group of kings that ruled after <hi rend="bold">Aśōkavarman</hi>. Vīrakūrcha, the grandson of <hi rend="bold">Kāḷabhartṛi (Kāṇagōpa)</hi>, must be the <hi rend="bold">Vīrakōrchavarman</hi> whose name occurs as that of the great grandfather (of the donor) in an odd <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> plate published by Professor Hultzsch in the <hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi> (Vol. I, p. 397 f.) and the same as Vīravarman of the Pīkira, Māṅgaḷūr, Uruvupalli and the Chendalūr grants, all of which belong practically to the same period. Vīrakūrcha is stated to have married the daughter of a Nāga chief<note>The account of the Pallava connection with a Nāga princess, here attributed to Vīrakūrcha, is already mentioned of the progenitor Aśvatthāman himself, in the Rāyakōṭa plates of Skandaśishya-Vikramavarman (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. V, p. 52). A similar story of the early Chōḷa king Kiḷḷi having taken to wife a Nāga princess, is related in the <hi rend="italic">Perumbāṇāṟṟuppaḍai</hi>. The mythical account given in the <hi rend="italic">Mahābhārata</hi>, of the epic hero Arjuna marrying a Nāga queen, combined with what is stated of the Nāga connections in inscriptions and literature, confirms the accepted belief, that the Nāgas were the original indigenous rulers of Southern India and that they were subdued in course of time by foreign invaders from the North, eventually losing their individuality by intermarriages with them.</note> and through her, to have acquired the insignia of royalty. Their son <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi> seized from king <hi rend="bold">Satyasēna</hi> the <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi> of the Brāhmaṇas. The reference to a <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi> at this early period is very interesting. It occurs also in the Tālagunda inscription of Kakusthavarman which is ascribed by Professor Kielhorn to about the first half of the 6th century A.D.<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. VIII, p. 26. According to the Kāñchī inscription of Vikramāditya II, Conjeeveram continued to be the seat of a <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi> in the beginning of the 8th century A.D. (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Vol. III, p. 360, note 4). The hill at Sholinghur in the North Arcot district is known as Ghaṭikāchala, perhaps on account of its having also been the seat of a <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi>.</note> <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi> is perhaps identical with the Pallava king of the same name, who is referred to in one of the <hi rend="bold">Tirukkaṛukkuṉṟam</hi> inscriptions<note><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> Vol., III, p. 277 f.</note>, as having made a gift to the holy temple of <hi rend="bold">Mūlasthāna</hi> at that village. If <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi> is synonymous with <hi rend="bold">Skandavarman</hi> as suggested by Mr. Venkayya in his article on the Tirukkaṛukkuṉṟam inscription, we shall have to identify him with Skandavarman II, particularly because the two generations after him supplied by the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates would, in this case, be the same as those found in the <hi rend="bold">Chendalūr</hi> plates of Kumāravishṇu II.<note><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Vol. VIII, p. 233 f.</note> Satyasēna, the king from whom <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi> seized the <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi>, remains unidentified. Kumāravishṇu, the son of <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi>, is next stated to have captured <hi rend="bold">Kāñchī</hi>, and his son <hi rend="bold">Buddhavarman</hi> to have been the conqueror of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷas</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Mr. Venkayya mentions two distinct periods in early <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> history, viz. (1) the period in which their grants are recorded in the <hi rend="bold">Prākṛit</hi> language and (2) that in which the grants are in <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi>.<note><hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey Report</hi> for 1906-7, pp. 217—43.</note> The first has been tentatively assigned to the beginning of the 4th century A.D. Evidently, the break suggested at the beginning of verse 5 in the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates with the words “<hi rend="bold">Aśōkavarman</hi> and others,” included this earlier period of the <hi rend="bold">Prākṛit</hi> charters, and counted within it such names as <hi rend="bold">Śivaskandavarman, Vijayaskandavarman, Vijayabuddhavarman, Buddhyaṅkura</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Vishṇugōpa</hi>. The <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi> charters, which are to be referred probably to the 5th and the 6th centuries of the Christian era, supply the names of a number of <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> kings who may now be arranged in order of succession, with the help of the information given in the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates. The capture, or rather the re-capture of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchī</hi> attributed to <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> in these plates confirms Mr. Venkayya's suggestion that that town was not the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> capital for some time during the interval between the <hi rend="bold">Prākṛit</hi> period and the later <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi> period. <hi rend="bold">Kāḷabhartṛi (Kāṇagōpa)</hi> may have been the first of the kings of the second period which lasted down to <hi rend="bold">(Kāṇagōpa)</hi> may have been the first of the kings of the second period which lasted down to <hi rend="bold">Buddhavarman</hi> according to our plates, or down to his son <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> II according to the <hi rend="bold">Chendalūr</hi> plates. The question however arises whether <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> (I) of the <hi rend="bold">Chendalūr</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates has to be identified with <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Yuvamahārāja</hi> Vishṇugōpavarman</hi> or to be treated as still another son of <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi> (<hi rend="bold">Skandavarman</hi> II). The former alternative was suggested by Mr. Venkayya together with the further supposition that <hi rend="bold">Buddhavarman</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavarman</hi> II may have been brothers.<note><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XXXVII, p. 284, foot-note 48.</note> But as the names <hi rend="bold">Vishṇugōpa</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> are mentioned simultaneously together among <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> ancestors, as for instance, in the <hi rend="bold">Vāyalūr</hi> pillar inscription of the time of <hi rend="bold">Rājasiṁha</hi>,<note>Madras Epigraphical Report for 1909, Part II, paragraph 17.</note> we may presume, perhaps tentatively, <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> I to be a third son of <hi rend="bold">Skandavarman</hi> II. The following revised pedigree of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> kings based on the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates and the <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi> charters of Pīkira, Māṅgaḷūr, Uruvupalli and Chendalūr, is given provisionally, subject to the identifications and suggestions made above:—</p>						
                            
                            <p><!--what follows is a table-->[C1]Kāḷabhartṛi (Kāṇagōpa) [C1]Chūtapallava (perhaps, a surname of Skandavarman I mentioned in the Uruvupalli grant) [C1]Vīrakūrcha (Vīrakōrchavarman or Vīravarman) [C1]Skandaśishya (Skandavarman II) [C1]Siṁhavarman I [C2]<hi rend="italic">Yuvamahārāja-</hi> Vishṇugōpa or Vishṇugōpavarman [C3]Kumāravishṇu I [C1]Skandavarman III [C2]Siṁhavarman II [C3]Buddhavarman [C1]Nanḍivarman<note>The names Nandivarman, Skandavarman III, and Siṁhavarman I are taken from a grant published by Professor Kielhorn (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, pp. 142 ff.) and suspected by him to be a spurious document.</note> [C2]Kumāravishṇu II</p>						
                            
                            <p>After v. 8 we are again introduced to another gap in the succession in which were included a host of kings such as <hi rend="bold">Vishṇugōpa</hi><note>A Pallava copper-plate grant from the Guntur district recently examined, belongs to the time of a certain Vishṇugōpavarman II whose father was Siṁhavarman, a son of Vishṇugōpavarman I and grandson of Kandavarman. I have assigned this to the period subsequent to Kumāravishṇu II of the Chendalūr plates (Madras Epigraphical Report for 1914, p. 82).</note> and others. Then appeared a king named <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> I who brought under his control a powerful snake apparently called <hi rend="italic">Dṛishṭivisha</hi>.<note>The influence of the Nāgas who, as already suggested, must have been the original rulers of Southern India apparently continued down to the time of Nandivarman of about the 6th century A.D. In later times the Sindas of Yelburga (Dr. Fleet's <hi rend="italic">Dynasties of the Kanarese districts</hi>, p. 572) and the Chhindas of Bastar traced their origin to the serpents (<hi rend="italic">nāga</hi>).</note> In verse 10, <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavarman</hi>, the father of <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi>, is introduced,—no connection being specified between himself and the <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> just mentioned. <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> was the conqueror of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> country which was fertilized by the river Cauvery.</p>						
                            
                            <p>What follows of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> genealogy is not new. It is a repetition of the account already supplied by the <hi rend="bold">Kāśākuḍi, Kūram</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates. Stone inscriptions written in the <hi rend="bold">Pallava-Grantha</hi> characters commence from this period,—a fact which suggests that, with the conquest of <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi> must have extended their dominion further south of Kāñchī into the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> country and adopted the Dravidian language generally found mixed up with Sanskṛit in the later stone inscriptions. From <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu's</hi> son <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi> I was born <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> I. This King whose conquest of <hi rend="bold">Vātāpi (Bādāmi)</hi> and the Western Chalukya <hi rend="bold">Pulakēśin</hi> II has frequently been described, is stated in verse 11 to have defeated his enemies and to have taken from them the pillar of victory standing at <hi rend="bold">Vātāpi</hi>.<note>It is not unlikely that this pillar of victory had been set up there by one of the ancestors of Narasiṁhavarman himself. The fragmentary rock inscription at Bādāmi published by Dr. Fleet (<hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. IX, p. 99f.) refers to Vātāpi, [Narasiṁ]havishṇu and to a pillar of victory (<hi rend="italic">jayastambha</hi>). Dr. Fleet is of opinion that Bādāmi (Vātāpi) “was originally the Western India stronghold of the Pallavas and that it was from them that the Chalukyas wrested it. It is probable that Vātāpi was temporarily recovered by the Pallavas from the Western Chalukyas after the reign of Pulakēśin II”.</note> Then came <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> I, an enemy of the <hi rend="bold">Western Chalukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi> I, whom, according to the <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates, he defeated at <hi rend="bold">Peruvaḷanallūr. Paramēśvara's</hi> “son's son” was <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> II, who re-organised the <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi> of the Brāhmaṇas, and built a temple for <hi rend="bold">Śiva</hi> “comparable with the mountain <hi rend="bold">Kailāsa</hi>”. This is a clear reference to the building of the <hi rend="bold">Kailāsanātha</hi> temple at Conjeeveram by <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> II.<note>Recorded in an inscription round the central shrine of the temple; above, Vol. I, No. 24.</note> The latter's son was <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> II. The usurpation of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> throne by <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> II, subsequent to the death of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> II, is clearly stated in verse 15. The distant relation that existed between the usurper <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> II and <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> II is described in the <hi rend="bold">Kāśākuḍi</hi> plates.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Two points in the account given above are worthy of note: (1) the omission of the name <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi> II after <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> I and (2) the statement that <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> II was the “son's son”<note>The actual word <hi rend="italic">putra-sūnu</hi> though used, very peculiarly, in place of the more common <hi rend="italic">pautra</hi>, leaves no doubt that the composer could not have intended any other term of relationship.</note> of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> I. The latter is probably an error, since all the three published <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> accounts agree in saying that <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> II was the <hi rend="italic">son</hi>, not the <hi rend="italic">grandson</hi>, of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> I. The former, however, may be different. For although the <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> plates call <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> I, the grandson of <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> I, still the doubtful way in which this relationship is expressed in the <hi rend="bold">Kāśākuḍi</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates, taken together with the statement of the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates, makes it appear as if <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi> II and <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> I were both sons of <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> I, thus reducing the seven generations between <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> II, to six. The usurper <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> II who, according to the <hi rend="bold">Kāśākuḍi</hi> plates, was sixth in descent from a brother of <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> could not at the time of his usurpation be a generation older than <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> II whose kingdom he usurped. Indeed, as hinted in the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates, he must have been much younger to justify his being called there the <hi rend="italic">son</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi>. Consequently it appears probable that <hi rend="bold">Mahēndravarman</hi> II and <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvaravarman</hi> I were actually brothers and that the succession after <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> I passed on directly to the latter, the former having, perhaps, died before him. Two successions after the usurper <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman (Pallavamalla)</hi> are further supplied for the first time by the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates. <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> II's son by <hi rend="bold">Rēvā</hi> was the <hi rend="bold">Pallava-Mahārāja Dantivarman</hi> (verse 18). His queen was the <hi rend="bold">Kadamba</hi> princess <hi rend="bold">Aggaḷanimmaṭī</hi>; from these, was born king <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> III, or according to the Tamil portion of the inscription, <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Nandivarman</hi>, in the sixth year of whose reign the subjoined grant was made. No specific historical facts are mentioned in connection with these kings. <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> III is stated to have “acquired the prosperity of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> kingdom by the prowess of his (own) arms” (verse 20). From this we may infer that the sovereignty over the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> kingdom had now been keenly contested either by outsiders or by some direct descendents of the <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> line.</p>						
                            
                            <p>In the Chingleput, North Arcot, South Arcot and Trichinopoly districts, there have been discovered a number of stone records (more or less of the same age as the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates) which refer themselves to the reigns of <hi rend="bold">Dantivarman, Dantivarma-Mahārāja, Dantippōttaraśar</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Dantivikramavarman</hi>, and also of <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> with similar variations in the name. Again, the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates<note>See Postscript.</note> supply the names <hi rend="bold">Dantivarman</hi>, (his son) <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> and (his son) <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅgadēva</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi>, as members of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> family, among whose ancestors were <hi rend="bold">Vimala, Koṅkaṇika</hi> and others. From this latter statement Professor Hultzsch concluded that the kings mentioned in the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates were different from the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchī</hi> and were only “<hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> by name but <hi rend="bold">Western Gaṅga</hi> by descent.” It is now, therefore, diffcult to say if the <hi rend="bold">Dantivarmans</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Nandivarmans</hi> of the stone records mentioned above, are to be identified with those mentioned in the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates, or with those of the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> plates or with both. Mr. Venkayya is inclined to connect the names in the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates with those of the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpaḷaiyam</hi> plates, and suggests that <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi> of the former was apparently the son of <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> III of the latter. Against this the only objection is the ancestry which, in the one case includes the clear <hi rend="bold">Western Gaṅga</hi> name (or surname) <hi rend="bold">Koṅkaṇika</hi>, while in the other it does not. If, however, Mr. Venkayya's suggestion is accepted, we must presume two facts to arrive at a concurrent genealogy, and to connect the kings of stone records with those mentioned in the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates. The prefix <hi rend="italic">kō-vijaya</hi> and the suffix <hi rend="italic">vikramavarman</hi> which are invariably found appended to the names of the kings in this series must have been introduced for the first time by the usurper <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman Pallavamalla</hi>, who, we know, literally won the kingdom by victory (<hi rend="italic">vijaya</hi>) and by prowess (<hi rend="italic">vikrama)</hi><note><hi rend="italic">Vijaya</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vikrama</hi> as prefixes and suffixes of Pallava names occur in much earlier records <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> in names like Vijaya-Buddhavarman, Vijaya-Īśvaravarman and Mahēndravikramavarman; but here they do not signify any distinct branch of kings.</note>, and that <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi> who was decidedly the most powerful<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. VIII, p. 293 and foot-note 3.</note> of this last branch of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>, and a son of the <hi rend="bold">Rāshṭrakūṭa</hi> princess Śaṅkhā, must have contracted new relations with the <hi rend="bold">Western Gaṅgas</hi> to justify the insertion of one or more of the names of that dynasty among his <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> ancestors. Even with these suppositions granted, the identification of kings mentioned in stone records with the <hi rend="bold">Nandivarmans</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Dantivarmans</hi> of the copper-plate grants presents peculiar difficulties. The script of the copper-plates, though of the same age with that of the stone inscriptions often differs from it,<note>See the remarks of Professor Hultzsch on the alphabet of the Rāyakōṭa plates in <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. V, p. 49.</note> and the information supplied by the latter is so meagre that hardly any points of contemporaneous nature that could help us in such identification, are forthcoming. In the present state of our knowledge therefore, it may be hypothetically presumed that kings of names <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Dantivarman</hi> with or without the prefix <hi rend="italic">kō-vijaya</hi> and the suffix <hi rend="italic">vikramavarman</hi>, may be taken to be one or the other of the immediate ancestors of <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga-Vikramavarman</hi>; while kings described as <hi rend="bold">Dantivarma-Mahārāja</hi> of the Bhāradvāja-<hi rend="italic">gōtra,</hi><note>See below, p. 513, footnote 1.</note> <hi rend="bold">Dantivarman</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Pallava-tilaka-kula,</hi><note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. XI, p. 157.</note> and <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> “who conquered [his enemies] at <hi rend="bold">Teḷḷāṟu</hi>,”<note>This was the hero of the Tamil work <hi rend="italic">Nandikkalambagam; Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XXXVII, p. 171.</note> have to be kept distinct.</p>						
                            
                            <p>In conclusion it may be stated, by way of a resume4, that the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> history covers four separate periods extending from about the 4th to the 9th century A.D. with three gaps which remain yet to be filled up satisfactorily by later researches. These are (1) the period of the <hi rend="bold">Prākṛit</hi> charters; (2) after a gap of a little more than a century, the period of the <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi> charters; (3) after another gap (or rather two gaps) of about the same length the period of stone inscriptions when, the <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> line was predominant; and (4) the last period when the <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> line (developing later, into what has been called the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅga-Pallava</hi> line) was powerful until it was completely crushed by the Chōḷas. A table of the kings of the <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> line and of the collateral branch of <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman Pallavamalla</hi> down to <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates is appended below:—</p>						
                            
                            <p><!--what follows is a table-->[C1]Nandivarman I [C1]Siṁhavarman [C1]Siṁhavishṇu [C2]Bhīmavarman [C1]Mahēndravarman I [C2]Buddhavarman [C1]Narasiṁhavarman I [C2]Ādityavarman [C1]Mahēndravarman II [C2]Paramēśvaravarman I [C3]Gōvindavarman [C1]Narasiṁhavarman II [C2]Hiraṇya (I) [C1]Paramēśvaravarman II [C2]Mahēndravarman III [C3]Nandivarman II Pallavamalla [C1]Dantivarman or Vijaya-Dantivikramavarman (Hiraṇyavarman II)<note>See below, p. 518.</note> [C1]Nandivarman III, Vijaya-Nandivarman or Vijaya-Nandivikramavarman [C1]Nṛipatuṅgavarman or Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</p>						
                            
                            <p>The object of the <hi rend="bold">Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</hi> grant was the gift of the village <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> to a temple of Śiva built at that village by a certain <hi rend="bold">Yajñabhaṭṭa</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Śaṉṉakkuṟi Yajñabhaṭṭa</hi>, surnamed <hi rend="bold">Bappa-Bhaṭṭāraka</hi>,<note>This surname occurs in early Sanskṛit charters of the Pallavas and has been translated “lordfather”. Perhaps the term was one of high respect applied to spiritual preceptors, and it is not unlikely that Yajñabhaṭṭa stood in this relation to king Nandivarman III. The spiritual preceptor of Nandivarman Pallavamalla is also called Bappa-Bhaṭṭāraka in the Kāśākuḍi plates (text, 1. 78).</note> in the sixth year of the reign of king <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi> III. The request (<hi rend="italic">vijñapti</hi>) was made by the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa-Mahārāja<note>The Chōḷas at this period must have been occupying a subordinate position. Neither literature nor inscriptions afford any clue to the identification of this Chōḷa-Mahārāja Kumārāṅkuśa, who was evidently a feudatory of king Nandivarman III. The name Kumārāṅkuśa-Gāvuṇḍa occurs among the signatories in a record of Parāntaka I (No. 457 of the Madras Epigraphical collection for 1911).</note> Kumārāṅkuśa</hi>, while the executor (<hi rend="italic">ājñapti</hi> or <hi rend="italic">āṇatti</hi>) was the minister <hi rend="bold">Namba</hi> (in Tamil, <hi rend="bold">Iraiyūr-uḍaiyāṉ-Nambaṉ</hi>) of the <hi rend="bold">Agradatta</hi> family. The donee was the <hi rend="bold">Mahādēva (Śiva)</hi> temple of <hi rend="bold">Yajñēśvara</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi>. Verse 28 informs us that the composer of the <hi rend="italic">praśasti</hi><note>Strangely enough this series of the latest Pallava grants have all been registered as <hi rend="italic">praśasti</hi>; see above, p. 345.</note> was the <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvara</hi> <hi rend="bold">Manōdhīra</hi>. Verse 31 and the <hi rend="bold">Tamil</hi> sentence following it, supply the name of <hi rend="bold">Pēraya</hi>, a clever carpenter of <hi rend="bold">Maṉaichchēri</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> (Conjeeveram), who engraved the writing on these plates.</p>						
                            
                            <p>One point of great interest in the Tamil portion of the grant is the long list of exemptions (<hi rend="italic">parihāra</hi>) and the written declaration (<hi rend="italic">vyavasthā</hi>) with which <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> was made over to the temple assembly (<hi rend="italic">paraḍai</hi>, Skt. <hi rend="italic">parishad</hi>). The former included items of collection whose significance is not quite clear, but which, as the inscription says, the king “could receive and enjoy.” It appears as though most of the items here mentioned were not necessarily sources of revenue to the State, as now understood, but only obligatory services which the king could enforce on the people for the benefit of the community. By the written declaration the donee was permitted to build (without any special license) mansions of burnt brick; to grow <hi rend="italic">Artimissia, Andropogan Muricatum</hi>, red lilies and <hi rend="italic">uḷḷi</hi> in gardens; to plant cocoanut trees in groves; to sink reservoirs and wells; to use large oil-presses; and to prohibit toddy-drawers from tapping for toddy, the cocoanut and the palmyra trees planted within the four boundaries of the village.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The village <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> is identical with <hi rend="bold">Kāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> in the Poṉṉēri tāluk of the Chingleput district; <hi rend="bold">Nāyaṟu-nāḍu</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Puṛaṟ-kōṭṭam</hi>, in which the village is stated to have been situated, takes its name from the village Nāyar of the same tāluk, about 8(1/2) miles south-west of <hi rend="bold">Kāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi>. In the British Museum plates of the <hi rend="bold">Vijayanagara</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Sadāśivarāya</hi> of the 16th century A.D., <hi rend="bold">Nāyattu-nāḍu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Nāyaṟu-nāḍu</hi>) is described as being a sub-division of <hi rend="bold">Puḷali-kōṭaka</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Puṛaṟ-kōṭṭam</hi>).<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>, Vol. IV., p. 8f.</note></p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-04-29" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-04-29" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:vernacular">
                
                <!--check miniature letters
                    split words
                -->
                
                <p>
                    <pb n="1v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <lb n="1"/>svasti śrīḥ namaśśivāya <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>nityam vyāpi nirāmayam paramayā bhaktyādhigamyaṁ śivam vācāndūramaci
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>ntyamakṣayamiti prodgīyamānam budhaiḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> saṁyamyendriyavāhinīṁ yativarairyyanmṛ<unclear>gya</unclear>te santa
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>ta<unclear>m</unclear> tejastatparamārtthasaccirataranniśreyasāyāstu va<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied> śarvvāṇīkucakuṁkumāṁka<unclear>śu</unclear>bhakasubha
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>gāḥ proddāmadarppāmaradveṣivrātavadhūprasādhanaparāmṛṣṭiprasaṁgocitāḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yuṣmānpāntu yu
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>gāntavahnivilasaddīprāstracakrāśriraṁ śrīkaṇṭhasya śikhaṇḍaratnaruciravyāḷāṁgadā bāha
                    <lb n="6" break="no"/>vaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Āsīdaṁbujanābhanābhikamalā<unclear>dbra</unclear>hmā tatopyaṁgirā<unclear>sta</unclear>smāddevagurustataśśubhamatiśśaṁyu
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>stataśśāṁ<unclear>yava</unclear>ḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <surplus>s</surplus>tasmātku<unclear>m</unclear>bhasamudbhava<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> smararipo<unclear>rdrau</unclear>ṇistatoṁśaḥ kramādasmādvismayanīyakīrttira
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>khila<unclear>kṣmā</unclear>vallabhaḥ pallavaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 3</supplied> vaṁśastatova<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>ttata pallavānāṁ rakṣāvidhidhvastavipalla<unclear>vā</unclear>nā<unclear>m</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> bhū
                    
                    <pb n="2r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>bhārakhedālasapannagendrasāhāyyaniṣṇātabhujārggaḷānām <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 4</supplied> Aśokavarmmādiṣu devabhūyaṁ ga
                    <lb n="10" break="no"/>te<unclear>ṣu vaṁśye</unclear>ṣvatha pārtthiveṣu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> vaṁśasyacū<choice><sic>ḷ</sic><corr>ḍ</corr></choice>āmaṇirāvirāsīdbharttendirāyā Iva kāḷabharttā <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g><supplied reason="omitted">5</supplied>
                    <lb n="11"/>tatsutādajani cūtapallavādvīrakūrcca Iti viśrutāhvayaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yaḥ phaṇīndrasutayā sahāgrahīdrāja
                    <lb n="12" break="no"/>cihnamakhilaṁ yaśodhanaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 6</supplied> Anvavāyanabhaśrandra<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> skandaśiṣyastatobhava<choice><sic>tv</sic><corr>t | d</corr></choice>ijānāṁ ghaṭikāṁ rājñassatya
                    <lb n="13" break="no"/>senā<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>j</corr></choice>jahāra yaḥ <g type="danda">.</g><supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g> 7</supplied> gṛhītakāñcīnagarastatobhūtkumāraviṣṇussamareṣu ji<unclear>ṣṇu</unclear>ḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> bharttā bhuvo
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>bhūdatha buddhava<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>mmā yaścoḷasainyārṇṇava<choice><sic>v</sic><corr>b</corr></choice>āḍabāgniḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 8</supplied> saviṣṇugope ca narendrabṛnde gate
                    <lb n="15"/>tatojāyata nandivarmmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Anugrahādyena pinākapāṇeḥ<note n="508-6">Read praṇātato.</note>pranarttito dṛṣṭiviṣaḥ phaṇīndraḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 9</supplied> Atha prathitavikra
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>mo jagati siṁhavarmmāhvayānnṛpātparamadāpahādajani siṁhaviṣṇu<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>jayī<surplus>ḥ</surplus> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> lasatkramukamaṇḍalāḥ ka<choice><sic>ḷ</sic><corr>l</corr></choice>ama
                    <lb n="17" break="no"/>kānanālaṁkṛtāḥ kavīratanayāñcitāssapadi yena coḷā hṛtāḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 10</supplied> tadā<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>t</corr></choice>majādāvirabhūnmahendrādupe
                    
                    <pb n="2v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>--><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="18" break="no"/>ndrakīrtti<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>nnarasiṁhavarmmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> vātāpimaddhye vijitāriva<unclear>rgga</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> sthitañjayastambhamalambhayadyaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 11</supplied> tataḥ paramadaddhvaṁ<note>The <hi rend="italic">anusvāra</hi> stands at the beginning of the next line.</note>
                    <lb n="19" break="no"/>sī babhūva parameśvaraḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> cāḷukyakṣitibhṛtsainyadhvāntadhvaṁsadivākaraḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 12</supplied> tatputrasūnurnnarasiṁhavarmmā pu
                    <lb n="20" break="no"/>nar<choice><sic>y</sic><corr>v</corr></choice>yadhādyo ghaṭikāṁ dvijānāṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> śilāmayaṁ veśma-śaśāṁkamauleḥ kailāsakatpañca<note n="508-13">Read ºkalpañca mahendrakalpaḥ.</note>mahendraka
                    <lb n="21" break="no"/>tpaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 13</supplied> tatsūnurbhūbhṛtāṁ <unclear>m</unclear>ānyo babhūva parameśvaraḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mānavena krameṇorvvīmaśādyaḥ kaliśāsanaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 14</supplied> tada
                    <lb n="22" break="no"/>nantaramanvayasya lakṣmīñcatura<unclear>mbho</unclear>nidhivāsasā sahorvvyā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> samavāpadaśeṣapūrvva<unclear>bhū</unclear>
                    <lb n="23" break="no"/><note n="508-14">Read ºsemalanaº.</note>bhṛdguṇasaṁmeḷanadhāma nandivarmmā <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 15</supplied> tasyāṁburāśeriva vāhinīnānnāthasya nānāguṇara<unclear>tna</unclear>
                    <lb n="24" break="no"/>dhāmnaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> dhīrasya bhūbhṛdvaralabdhajanmā reveva revā mahiṣī babhūva <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 16</supplied><note n="508-15">Read ºbhūttriº.</note>tasyāmāvirabhūtrilokaparira
                    <lb n="25" break="no"/><unclear>kṣā</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>tthaḥ kṣamānandanaḥ<note n="508-17">Read ºnandanassākṣāº.</note>sākṣādaṁburuhekṣaṇassvayamiha śrīdantivarmmā nṛpaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> śauryyatyāgakṛtajña
                    <lb n="26" break="no"/>tādiramalo yasminguṇānāṁ gaṇaḥ pra<unclear>ā</unclear>pta<unclear>ā</unclear>nyonyasamāgamotsava Iva prāpatpra<supplied reason="omitted">ti</supplied>ṣṭhāñci
                    
                    <pb n="3r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>--><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIIa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <lb n="27" break="no"/>rāt <supplied reason="omitted"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 17</supplied> prakhyātasya kada<unclear>mba</unclear>vaṁ<supplied reason="omitted">śa</supplied>tilakasyorvvīpaterātmajā vīrāṇāṁ prathamasyaṁ pallavamahārāja
                    <lb n="28" break="no"/>sya tejasvinaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ākhyāmaggaḷanimmaṭīti <supplied reason="omitted">da</supplied>dhatī śuddhānvavāyocitā <unclear>bha</unclear>rttustasya bhuvo
                    <lb n="29"/>babhūva mahiṣī gaurīva jetuḥ pura<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>m <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">18</supplied> śrīnandivarmmāṇamasūta seyaṁ sandhyeva te
                    <lb n="30" break="no"/>jasvinamambikeva <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> kumāramatyadbhutaśaktiyuktaṁ yathā jayantaṁ jayinaṁ śacīva <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">19</supplied> Utkhāta
                    <lb n="31" break="no"/>khaḍganihatadvipakumbhamuktāmuktāphalaprapāsite<note n="508-18">Read ºprahasite.</note>samarāṁgaṇe yaḥ <unclear><g type="danda">.</g></unclear> śatrū
                    <lb n="32" break="no"/>nnihatya samavāpadananyalavyāṁ<note n="508-19">Read ºlabhyāṁ rājyaśriyaṁ.</note>rājyaśiśrayaṁ svabhujavikramadarppaśālī <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">20</supplied> U<unclear>dya</unclear>ānaṁ ma
                    <lb n="33" break="no"/>dhunā guṇaiḥ kulabhuvaḥ<note n="508-20">Read ºbhūvaśśīlena vāmekṣaṇā.</note>śīlena vāmertṣaṇā tyāgenārtthapatiśśrutena vinaya
                    <lb n="34" break="no"/>ssūryyeṇa pa<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>mākaraḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> prāleyadyutinā payodasamayāpāye nabhaḥprāṁgaṇannai
                    <lb n="35" break="no"/>vaṁ <unclear>bhā</unclear>ti tathā yathā jagadidaṁ yena <choice><sic>t</sic><corr>k</corr></choice>ṣamābandhunā <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g> 21</supplied> pṛthvīpālasya tasya<note n="509-3">Read prāthataº.</note>pradhitagu
                    
                    <pb n="3v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>--><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IIIb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <lb n="36" break="no"/>ṇaga<unclear>ṇo</unclear> bappabhaṭṭārakāgyaśśāstre<note n="509-4">Read kākhyaº.</note>vede ca sāṁkhye prakaṭitamahimā yajña
                    <lb n="37" break="no"/>bhaṭṭābhidhāna<choice><sic>ś ś</sic><corr>ḥ | ś</corr></choice>rīkaṭṭuppa<seg xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">ḷḷi</seg>nāmni śrutavina<supplied reason="omitted">ya</supplied>dharastuṁgakailāsakalpaṁ grā
                    <lb n="38" break="no"/>mebālendumauler<surplus>bh</surplus>bhavanamakṛta yadbhaktiyogapra<unclear>tī</unclear>taḥ <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">22</supplied> pitābhavadyasya
                    <lb n="39"/>viśuddhabuddhirggirāmiveśaśśivadāsanāmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mātābhavadyasya guṇaissama<choice><sic>ś</sic><corr>g</corr></choice>rai
                    <lb n="40" break="no"/>rggarīyasī <unclear>dre</unclear>ṇamaṇirmmahīva <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">23</supplied> pitāmaho yasya viśuddhavṛttirdvijāgragaṇya
                    <lb n="41" break="no"/>stamasānnipāntā<note n="509-8">Read ºnnihantā.</note><supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> nidhiḥ kalānāmi<unclear>va</unclear> yajñanāmā babhūva vikhyātayaśaḥprakāśaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 24</supplied> tasmai
                    <lb n="42"/>devāya śarvvāya pūjāsatrādikarmaṇe <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied><note n="509-9">Read ºsodādgāº.</note>sodāggrāmanti<seg xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">rukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</seg>nāmāna
                    <lb n="43" break="no"/>mīśvaraḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">25</supplied> vijñaptimatrākṛta coḷavaṁśacū<choice><sic>ḷ</sic><corr>ḍ</corr></choice>āmaṇirvviśrutavikramaśrīḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> dhīraḥ kumā
                    <lb n="44" break="no"/>rāṁkuśanāmadheyastyāgena rādheyasamaḥ kṛtajñaḥ <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">26</supplied> Atrājñaptirabhūnmantrī na
                    
                    <pb n="4r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>--><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IVa</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="45" break="no"/><seg xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">m</seg>panāmā mahīpateḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Agradattānvayavyomaśarannīhāradīdhiti<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">27</supplied> vāgmanaḥ<unclear>ka</unclear>ā
                    <lb n="46" break="no"/>yakarmmāṇi parārtthānyeva yasya saḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>māheśvaro manodhīraḥ praśastiṁ kṛta
                    <lb n="47" break="no"/>vānima<unclear>ām</unclear> <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">28</supplied> 
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                    puḻaṟkoṭṭattu nāyaṟunāṭṭuttirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷippañcavaram Āirakkā
                    <lb n="48" break="no"/>ṭi Itu kovicaiya <hi rend="grantha">nantivarmma</hi>ṟku yāṇṭu Āṟāvatu coḻa<hi rend="grantha">ma</hi>hārājar viṇṇappattā
                    <lb n="49" break="no"/>l Iraiyūr Uṭaiyāṉ nampaṉāṇattiyākattirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷiccaṉṉa
                    <lb n="50" break="no"/>kkuṟi ya<hi rend="grantha">jñabhaṭṭa</hi><unclear>r</unclear>eṭuppitta ya<hi rend="grantha">jñeśva</hi>rattu <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>varkku nāṭṭu nīṅkalā
                    <lb n="51" break="no"/>y Uṭpuravāy tevar<hi rend="grantha">dā</hi>ṉamākap peṟṟataṟkup peṟṟa <hi rend="grantha">parihāra</hi>m nāṭāṭciyum
                    <lb n="52"/>Ūrāṭciyum puravupoṉṉum tirumukkāṇamum vaṭṭināḻiyum putāḻiyum taṭṭu
                    <lb n="53" break="no"/>kāyamum Īḻampūṭciyum Iṭaippūṭciyum maṉṟupāṭum<surplus>t</surplus> tarakum taṟikkū<unclear>ṟ</unclear>ai
                    
                    <pb n="4v"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate IVb</hi>.</h4>-->
                    
                    <lb n="54" break="no"/>yum kūlamum nallāvum nallerutum nallāṭum nāṭukāvalum Ūṭupokkum
                    <lb n="55"/>kallāṇakkāṇamum kucakkāṇamum pāṟaikkāṇam paṭṭiṉaceriyum maṟṟumivvū
                    <lb n="56" break="no"/>r<choice><sic>ai</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>ll<choice><sic>ai</sic><corr>e</corr></choice> U<supplied reason="omitted">ḷ</supplied>ḷakappaṭṭatu kottoṭṭuṇṇappālatellām Ev<unclear>vak</unclear>aippaṭṭa
                    <lb n="57" break="no"/>tum kok<unclear>k</unclear>oḷḷappeṟāte Ivya<hi rend="grantha">jñeśva</hi>rattu <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>vareyi<note n="509-13">Read <foreign>ºrēy</foreign>.</note> koḷḷappe
                    <lb n="58" break="no"/>ṟṟataṟkuppeṟṟa <hi rend="grantha">vyavasthai<supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></hi> cuṭṭoṭṭāl māṭamāḷikai Eṭukkappeṟuvatā
                    <lb n="59" break="no"/>kavum tamaṉakamum Iruveliyum ceṅkaḻunīrum Uḷḷiyum naṭappeṟuvatākavum kāvute
                    <lb n="60" break="no"/>ṅkiṭappeṟuvatākavum turavukiṇaṟiḻittappeṟuvatākavum peruñcekkiṭappeṟu
                    <lb n="61" break="no"/>vatākavum Ivvūrellai U<supplied reason="omitted">ḷ</supplied>ḷiṭṭa teṅkum paṉaiyum Ivarkaḷ maṉamiṉṟi Īḻavareṟap
                    <lb n="62" break="no"/>peṟātārākavum Ivvakaippaṭṭa <hi rend="grantha">vyavasthai</hi>yiṉūṭu<note n="509-14">Read <foreign>ºṉōṭu</foreign>.</note> <hi rend="grantha">yajñeśvara</hi>ttu <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>vark                    
                    <pb n="5r"/><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>.</h4>--><!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>.</h4>-->
                    <lb n="63" break="no"/>kuttevatāṉamāy <hi rend="grantha">sarvvaparihāramāka paraṭa<!--EF: da in fact-->tti</hi> ceṉṟatu <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:vernacular">                    
                    sukṛtamidamajasraṁ ra<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>k</corr></choice>ṣate
                    <lb n="64" break="no"/>ti <choice><sic>t</sic><corr>k</corr></choice>ṣitīśāssakalanṛpatiketussoyamāgāmino vaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> haracaraṇasaro<unclear>jo</unclear>
                    <lb n="65" break="no"/>ttaṁsacihnena mūrddhnā mukuḷitakara<unclear>pa</unclear><choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>mo vandate nandivarmmā <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">29</supplied> sarvvānetānbhāvinaḥ
                    <lb n="66"/>pā<unclear>rtthi</unclear>vendrānbhūyo bhūyaḥ prārtthayatyeṣa rāmaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> sāmānyoyandharmmasetu<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>nnṛpāṇāṁ kā
                    <lb n="67" break="no"/>lekāle pa<unclear>ā</unclear>lanīyo bhav<choice><sic>an</sic><corr>īd</corr></choice>bh<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>ḥ <unclear><g type="danda">.</g></unclear><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">30</supplied> karakauśalakṛtayaśasā <seg xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">ciṟṟa</seg>yaputre
                    <lb n="68" break="no"/>ṇa patrasaṁghoyam· <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> likhita<choice><sic>ṁ</sic><corr>ḥ</corr></choice> perayanāmnā sthapatikulavyomacandreṇa <unclear><g type="danda">.</g></unclear><g type="dashLong">.</g> <supplied reason="omitted">31</supplied> 
                </p>
                
                <p xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                    kaccip
                    <lb n="69" break="no"/>peṭṭaimmaṉaiccerikkā<hi rend="grantha">ṣṭha</hi>kārimakaṉ perayaṉ Eḻuttu <g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>           
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation">
                
                <p>Hail! Prosperty! Adoration to Śiva !</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 1.) May that effulgence which is the existence absolute, which is sung by the wise to be eternal, universal, infallible, accessible (<hi rend="italic">only</hi>) to highest devotion, benevolent, beyond the reach of words and thoughts, and endless and which, the best of sages ever strive to attain by putting a restraint upon the currents of (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) sense-perceptions,—grant you permanent bliss !</p>
                
                <p>(V. 2.) May (<hi rend="italic">they</hi>) always protect you, the arms of <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṇṭha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śiva</hi>), which are lovely by bearing on them the marks of saffron from the breasts of <hi rend="bold">Śarvāṇī</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Pārvatī</hi>), which delight themselves in the work of removing the ornaments (<hi rend="italic">from the body</hi>) of the wives of the highly conceited hoards of the enemies of gods,<note>This is an elegant expression for saying that the enemies of gods (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the demons) were destroyed by Śiva. It is usual with Hindu women to remove their ornaments and to give up their toilet after the death of their husbands.</note> which (hold) a number of weapons that shine with the brilliance of the fire at the end of the world and wear armlets of serpents radiant with gems in (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) crests !</p>
                
                <p>(V. 3.) From the lotus-(like) navel of the lotus-navelled <hi rend="bold">(Vishṇu)</hi>, was (<hi rend="italic">produced</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Brahmā</hi>; from him (<hi rend="italic">was born</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Aṅgiras</hi>; from him, the preceptor of the gods <hi rend="bold">(Bṛihaspati)</hi>; from him, the good-natured <hi rend="bold">Śaṁyu</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Śāṁyava</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Bharadvāja); from him the pitcher-born (Drōṇa); from him <hi rend="bold">Drauṇi</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Aśvatthāman</hi>), who is of the essence of <hi rend="bold">(Śiva)</hi>, the enemy of Cupid; and from him in (<hi rend="italic">the same</hi>) order (<hi rend="italic">came</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi>, the lord of the whole earth, whose fame was bewildering.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 4.) Thence, came into existence the race of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>, who by the law of protection (<hi rend="italic">which they adopted</hi>) removed (<hi rend="italic">even</hi>) the slightest distress (<hi rend="italic">of their subjects</hi>); and whose bar-like arms were skilled in rendering assistance to the lord of serpents who was fatigued by the labour of (<hi rend="italic">carrying on his head</hi>) the burden of the earth.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 5.) After kings, such as <hi rend="bold">Aśōkavarman</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and others</hi>), born in that family, had attained god-hood (<hi rend="italic">i.e. died</hi>), was born <hi rend="bold">Kāḷabhartṛi</hi>, the head-jewel of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) family, like <hi rend="bold">(Vishṇu)</hi> the husband of <hi rend="bold">Indirā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Lakshmī</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 6.) From his son <hi rend="bold">Chūtapallava</hi>, was produced <hi rend="bold">Vīrakūrcha</hi>, of celebrated name, who simultaneously with (<hi rend="italic">the hand of</hi>) the daughter of the chief of serpents grasped also the complete insignia of royalty and became famous.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 7.) From him came <hi rend="bold">Skandaśishya</hi>, the moon in the sky of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) family, who seized from king <hi rend="bold">Satyasēna</hi> the <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi> of the twice-born (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Brāhmaṇas).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 8.) From him came <hi rend="bold">Kumāravishṇu</hi> who captured the city of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchī</hi> and was victorious in battles. Then became king, <hi rend="bold">Buddhavarman</hi>, the submarine fire to the ocean-like army of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷas</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 9.) And after a host of kings including <hi rend="bold">Vishṇugōpa</hi> had passed away, was born <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, who with the favour of (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pinākapāṇi (Śiva)</hi> caused to dance a powerful snake whose poison was in (<hi rend="italic">its</hi>) eyes (<hi rend="italic">Dṛishṭivisha</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 10.) Then from the king named <hi rend="bold">Śiṁhavarman</hi>, who wiped off the pride of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) enemies, was born the victorious <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> whose prowess was widely known on earth. He quickly seized the country of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷas</hi>, embellished by the daughter of <hi rend="bold">Kavīra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the river Kāvērī), whose ornaments are the forests of paddy (<hi rend="italic">fields</hi>) and where (<hi rend="italic">are found</hi>) brilliant groves of areca (<hi rend="italic">palms</hi>). </p>
                
                <p>(V. 11.) From his son <hi rend="bold">Mahēndra</hi> was born <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> (I), famous (<hi rend="italic">like</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Upēndra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Vishṇu), who, defeating the host of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) enemies, took (<hi rend="italic">from them</hi>) the pillar of victory standing in the centre of (<hi rend="italic">the town of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Vātāpi</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 12.) From him came <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> (I) who crushed the conceit of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) enemies, (<hi rend="italic">and was</hi>) a sun in destroying the darkness which was the army of the <hi rend="bold">Chāḷukya</hi> king.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 13.) His son's son (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Narasiṁhavarman</hi> (II) who, equal to Mahēndra, once again organised the <hi rend="italic">ghaṭikā</hi> of the twice-born (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Brāhmaṇas) and built of stone a house for the moon-crested (Śiva) which was comparable with the (<hi rend="italic">mountain</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kailāsa</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 14.) His son who was respected by kings, was <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> (II). This chastiser of the dark age (<hi rend="italic">Kali</hi>) governed the earth according to the rules laid down by <hi rend="bold">Manu</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 15.) After him, <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, the repository of the aggregate (<hi rend="italic">good</hi>) qualities of all ancient kings, got possession of the prosperity of the family together with the earth whose garments are the four oceans.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 16.) Of this heroic lord of battalions (<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, of rivers), and the home of many virtues (<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, of gems), as of the ocean, the chief queen was <hi rend="bold">Rēvā</hi> who, like (<hi rend="italic">the river</hi>) Rēvā, had (<hi rend="italic">her</hi>) birth from a great king (<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, from a high mountain).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 17.) To her was born on this (<hi rend="italic">earth</hi>) the glorious king <hi rend="bold">Dantivarman</hi>, a manifestation of the lotus-eyed <hi rend="bold">(Vishṇu)</hi> himself, who was the delight of the earth, whose (<hi rend="italic">sole</hi>) object (<hi rend="italic">of life</hi>) was the protection of the three worlds and in whom the group of pure qualities such as prowess, charity and gratitude attained eminence, as it were, after a long time (<hi rend="italic">enjoying</hi>) the pleasure of each other's company.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 18.) Just as <hi rend="bold">Gaurī</hi> (<hi rend="italic">was the wife</hi>) of the conqueror of the (<hi rend="italic">three</hi>) cities (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śiva</hi>), the suitable chief queen of that lord of the earth, the foremost of heroes, the powerful <hi rend="bold">Pallava-Mahārāja</hi>, was (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) of a spotless race, who bore the name <hi rend="bold">Aggaḷanimmaṭī</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and was</hi>) the daughter of the celebrated king—a crest-jewel of the <hi rend="bold">Kadamba</hi> family.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 19.) As the (<hi rend="italic">morning</hi>) twilight (gives birth to) the resplendent one (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the sun); as <hi rend="bold">Ambikā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Pārvatī</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">to the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kumāra (Skanda)</hi> possessed of the marvellous (weapon) <hi rend="italic">Śakti</hi> (<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, of strength); as Śachī, to the victorious Jayanta; so did this <hi rend="bold">(Aggaḷanimmaṭī)</hi> give birth to (the glorious) <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 20.) This <hi rend="bold">(Nandivarman)</hi> puffed up with the prowess of his arms, acquired the prosperity of the <hi rend="bold">(Pallava)</hi> kingdom, not easy for others to obtain, by killing (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) enemies on the battle-field which was laughing (<hi rend="italic">as it were</hi>) with pearls dropping from the frontal globes of elephants slain by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) unsheathed sword.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 21.) Never shone so (<hi rend="italic">thoroughly</hi>) a garden with (<hi rend="italic">the advent of</hi>) spring, nor men of high birth with (<hi rend="italic">good</hi>) qualities, nor women with morality, nor a millionaire with charity, nor humility with knowledge, nor a lotus-tank with the sun, nor the expanse of the sky with the moon at the end of the rainy season, as (<hi rend="italic">the people of</hi>) this earth (<hi rend="italic">shone</hi>), with that king.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 22.) (<hi rend="italic">A subject</hi>) of that king who was learned, modest and of established virtues, who was named <hi rend="bold">Yajñabhaṭṭa</hi> and surnamed <hi rend="bold">Bappa-Bhaṭṭāraka</hi>, was widely famous (<hi rend="italic">for his knowledge</hi>) in the <hi rend="italic">Śāstra</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Vēda</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Sāṅkhya</hi> and was celebrated for (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) persistent devotion to (Śiva), built in the village named <hi rend="bold">Śrīkaṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> a temple for <hi rend="bold">Śiva</hi> similar to the high <hi rend="bold">Kailāsa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">mountain</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 23.) His (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Yajñabhaṭṭa's</hi>) father was named <hi rend="bold">Śivadāsa</hi>, who like the lord (<hi rend="italic">of the goddess</hi>) of speech (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Brahmā) was possessed of pure intelligence. His mother was <hi rend="bold">[Drē]ṇamaṇi</hi> who like the (<hi rend="italic">goddess</hi>) earth was great for the exhuberance of her (<hi rend="italic">good</hi>) qualities.<note>A pun on the words <hi rend="italic">guṇa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">garīyasī</hi> is intended. The earth has all the <hi rend="italic">guṇas</hi> such as form, taste, <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>. and is also heavy.</note></p>
                
                <p>(V. 24.) His grandfather was named <hi rend="bold">Yajña</hi> who, like the repository of the <hi rend="italic">kalās</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the moon), is the abode of sciences (<hi rend="italic">kalā</hi>),<note>For a correct understanding of the sense, the phrase <hi rend="italic">nidhiḥ kalānām</hi> has to be repeated twice.</note> has spotless character<note><hi rend="italic">Viśuddha-vṛittaḥ</hi> would have been more apt.</note> (<hi rend="italic">as the moon, a white disc</hi>), is the best of the twice-born (<hi rend="italic">dvija</hi>), the expeller of ignorance (<hi rend="italic">as the moon, of darkness</hi>) and shines with wide-spread fame.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 25.) To that god <hi rend="bold">Śarva (Śiva)</hi>, the king granted the village called <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> for (<hi rend="italic">maintaining</hi>) the services (<hi rend="italic">connected with</hi>) worship, feeding, <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 26.) The heroic head-jewel of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> race named <hi rend="bold">Kumārāṅkuśa</hi>, the glory of whose prowess was well-known, whose liberality was equal to that of <hi rend="bold">Rādhēya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Karṇa</hi>) and whose conduct was upright, made the (<hi rend="italic">necessary</hi>) request (<hi rend="italic">vijñapti</hi>) for (<hi rend="italic">securing</hi>) this (<hi rend="italic">grant</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 27.) The executor (<hi rend="italic">ājñapti</hi>) here, was the king's minister named <hi rend="bold">Namba</hi>, the autumnal moon in the firmament of the <hi rend="bold">Agradatta</hi> family.</p>
                
                <p>(V. 28.) The <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvara</hi> <hi rend="bold">Manōdhīra</hi>, the act of whose words, thoughts and body were (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) for the benefit of others, composed this <hi rend="italic">praśasti</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(Lines 47 to 63.) Whereas in the sixth year of <hi rend="bold">Kōvijaya-Nandivarman</hi>, at the request (<hi rend="italic">made by</hi>) Chōḷa-Mahārāja and the <hi rend="italic">āṇatti</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Iraiyūr-uḍaiyāṉ Nambaṉ</hi>, this (<hi rend="italic">village</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi> of <hi rend="italic">pañchavaram āyirakkāḍi</hi><note><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> whose yield under the head <hi rend="italic">pañchavaram</hi>, was one thousand <hi rend="italic">kāḍi</hi> of paddy. <hi rend="italic">Pañchavaram</hi> may be a mistake for <hi rend="italic">pañchavāram</hi> ‘the five <hi rend="italic">vārams</hi> or income in grain’; cp. the terms <hi rend="italic">mēl-vāram, kuḍi-vāram</hi>, etc., which are still in use. See also <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. V., p. 138, foot-note 7.</note>, in <hi rend="bold">Nāyaṟu-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a sub-division</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Puṛaṟ-kōṭṭam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) excluded from the district (<hi rend="italic">nāṭṭu-nīṅgal</hi>) (and) has been assigned as an <hi rend="italic">uṭpuravu dēvadāna</hi> in favour of (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahādēva</hi> of (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Yajñēśvara</hi> built by <hi rend="bold">Śaṉṉakkuṟi Yajñabhaṭṭa</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</hi>, the immunities (<hi rend="italic">parihāra</hi>) secured (<hi rend="italic">therefor) viz. nāḍāṭchi, ūrāṭchi, puravu-poṉ, tirumukkāṇam,<note>This term corresponds to <hi rend="italic">tirumugakkāṇam</hi> of the Taṇḍantōṭṭam plates; see below, page 531, note 2. The following other terms, <hi rend="italic">viz., vaṭṭi-nāṛi, pudāṛi, taṭṭukāyam, īṛam-pūṭchi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">iḍai-ppūṭchi</hi> also occur in the Taṇḍantōṭṭam plates.</note> vaṭṭi-nāṛi, pudāṛi, taṭṭukāyam, īṛam-pūṭchi, iḍai-ppūṭchi, maṉṟupāḍu</hi>, brokerage, tax on looms, <hi rend="italic">kūlam</hi>, good cow, good bull, good sheep, watch-fee of the district, <hi rend="italic">ūḍupōkku</hi>, taxes on marriages, potters and quarries, <hi rend="italic">paṭṭina-śēri</hi> and all other (<hi rend="italic">income</hi>) of any kind which the king could receive and enjoy within the boundary of this village, shall not (<hi rend="italic">henceforth</hi>) be collected by the king but by this Mahādēva of (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) Yajñēśvara only. The (<hi rend="italic">following</hi>) written declaration (<hi rend="italic">vyavasthā</hi>) is (<hi rend="italic">also</hi>) granted (<hi rend="italic">for the guidance of the donee):</hi> Mansions of burnt tiles (<hi rend="italic">bricks ?</hi>) may be built (<hi rend="italic">without special permission</hi>); artimissia (<hi rend="italic">damanagam</hi>), andropogan muricatum (<hi rend="italic">iruvēli</hi>), red-lilies (<hi rend="italic">śeṅgaṛunīr</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">uḷḷi</hi> may be grown (<hi rend="italic">in gardens ?</hi>); cocoanut (<hi rend="italic">trees</hi>) may be planted in groves; reservoirs and wells may be sunk; large oil-presses may be used and the toddy-drawers (<hi rend="italic">īṛavars</hi>) may not climb, without the consent of this (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Mahādēva of Yajnēśvara), the cocoanut and the palmyra (<hi rend="italic">trees</hi>) planted within the boundaries of (this village). With the written declaration thus defined (<hi rend="italic">the village</hi>) was placed in the (<hi rend="italic">hands of the</hi>) assembly (<hi rend="italic">paraḍatti,</hi>) as a <hi rend="italic">dēvadāna</hi>, with all immunities, to the (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahādēva</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Yajñēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(V. 29.) O ! Future rulers of earth ! He, <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>, the banner among all kings, with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) lotus-like hands folded, bows down to you with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) head which is marked by the headjewel (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) the lotus-feet of Hara <hi rend="bold">(Śiva)</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and requests you</hi>) to protect this good deed always !</p>
                
                <p>(V. 30.) Thus does <hi rend="bold">Rāma</hi> request again and again, all the present and future lords of the earth: “This bridge of (<hi rend="italic">religious</hi>) charity is common to (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) kings; you must (<hi rend="italic">therefore</hi>) protect (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>) at all times.”</p>
                
                <p>(V. 31.) This set of (<hi rend="italic">copper-</hi>)sheets was engraved by the moon in the sky of the family of carpenters, named <hi rend="bold">Pēraya</hi>, the son of <hi rend="bold">Śiṟṟaya</hi>, who has won (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) reputation for skill in workman-ship.</p>
                
                <p>(LI. 68 and 69.) The writing of <hi rend="bold">Pērayaṉ</hi> son of the carpenter (<hi rend="italic">kāshṭhakārin</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Maṉaichchēri</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    
                    <!--<app loc="0">
                        <lem>...</lem>
                    </app>-->
                        
                    <app loc="3">
                        <lem>°<unclear>śu</unclear>bhaka°</lem>
                        <note>The three letters <foreign><unclear>śu</unclear>bhaka</foreign>, which were evidently written by mistake, are to be cancelled.</note>
                    </app>
                    
                </listApp>
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
                <p>TEXT. <note>From the original plates and a set of ink-impressions.</note></p>
                
                <p>POSTSCRIPT.</p>
                
                <p>On pages 180 and 181 of the <hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi>, Vol. IV., Professor Hultzsch gives an extract of a set of five copper-plates of <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi> which were discovered at <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> near Pondicherry by M.J. de la Fon. The originals are not available but appear to be in the possession of some person at Paris. A transcript of the inscription prepared by a Tamil Paṇḍit was supplied by the discoverer to Professor Hultzsch some year ago. It is in many places defective. Still as the information conveyed appears to be important for the study of the collateral branch of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> family, known as <hi rend="bold">Gaṅga-Pallavas</hi>, I append below the <hi rend="bold">Sanskṛit</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Tamil</hi> texts as transcribed by the Paṇḍit.</p>
                
                <p>It may be added by way of supplementing Professor Hultzsch's remarks that in V. 16 reference is made to a victory gained by a <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king with the help of <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga</hi>. It is not stated who this <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> was or where he fought the battle in which <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga</hi> could have helped him. The <hi rend="bold">Ambāsamudram</hi> inscription of <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. IX, pp. 84 to 94) states that that king advanced as far north as <hi rend="bold">Araiśūr</hi> on the Pennar in <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam</hi>. Mr. Venkayya distinguishes this <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</hi> from his grandson <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇavarman</hi> who fought the battle of <hi rend="bold">Śrīpurambiyam</hi> with <hi rend="bold">Pṛithivīpati</hi> I and his ally <hi rend="bold">Aparājitavarman</hi>, the last of the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅga-Pallava</hi> kings (Madras Epigraphical <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> for 1906-7, Part II, paragraph 21). It is not definitely known what relation existed between this <hi rend="bold">Aparājita</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates. Anyhow <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</hi> who flourished two generations before <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇavarman</hi>, about the beginning of the 9th century A.D., and who pushed his campaign in the north up to the bank of the river Pennar cannot be far distant in time from <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi>. Consequently, the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> referred to in V. 16 of the <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> plates may probably be <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</hi>. The enemy against whom <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga</hi> fought to help his friend <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</hi> was very likely a king of the <hi rend="bold">Siṁhavishṇu</hi> line who was ruling simultaneously with <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga</hi> in some portion of the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam</hi>.<note>Dantivarma-Mahārāja of the Bhāradvāja-<hi rend="italic">gōtra</hi> mentioned in the Triplicane inscription is supposed to have been the first of a line of kings who “spoke of themselves as belonging to the family of <hi rend="italic">Pallava-tilaka</hi> in order to distinguish themselves from the Gaṅga-Pallavas” (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. VIII., pp. 290-6). Nandippōttaraiyaṉ was another king of the same family whose queen Māṟambāvai figures as the donor in two inscriptions at Tiruchcheṉṉampūṇḍi, Tanjore district, which are dated in the 18th and 22nd years of the reign of Nṛipatuṅga (Nos. 303 and 300 of the Madras Epigraphical collection for 1901). This subordinate position of Māṟambāvai suggests evidently either the defeat or the death of her husband at the hands of Nṛipatuṅga. Consequently, Nandippōttaraiyaṉ of the <hi rend="italic">Pallava-tilaka</hi> family must have been the enemy against whom Varaguṇa-Mahārāja and Nṛipatuṅga jointly fought.</note></p>
                
                <p>The object of the grant was the donation of the three villages <hi rend="bold">Cheṭṭuppākkam Viḷāṅgāṭṭaṅkaḍuvaṉūr</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Iṟaippuṇaichchēri</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">vidyāsthāna</hi> (V. 23) at <hi rend="bold">Bāhugrāma</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi>) (V. 25), by a member of the <hi rend="bold">Baśāli</hi> family and a descendant of the <hi rend="bold">Kuru</hi> race (V. 18). This chief was the minister of <hi rend="bold">Tuṅgavarman</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga</hi>) (V. 28) who issued the necessary order for the grant of the villages (V. 21). The college (<hi rend="italic">vidyāsthāna</hi>) at <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> consisted of 14 <hi rend="italic">gaṇas</hi><note>The Paṇḍit who supplied the transcript of the grant remarks that the 14 <hi rend="italic">guṇas</hi> were the fourteen divisions of learning and consisted of—the <hi rend="italic">Vēdas</hi> (4), the <hi rend="italic">aṅgas</hi> (6), <hi rend="italic">Mīmāṁsā</hi> (1), <hi rend="italic">Nyāya</hi> (1), <hi rend="italic">Purāṇa</hi> (1) and the <hi rend="italic">Dharmaśāstra</hi> (1).</note> and was controlled by the learned men of that village, being organised and maintained by them “as the <hi rend="bold">Ganges (Mandākinī)</hi> descending from the sky with all the fury of its rushing waves is borne by the god Śiva on one of his matted locks” (Vv. 24 and 25). The composer of the <hi rend="italic">praśasti</hi> was <hi rend="bold">Dāśaya</hi> (V. 30). The Tamil portion of the grant refers to the 8th year of <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</hi> and states that at the request of <hi rend="bold">Baśāli-Pērarayaṉ</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">āṇatti (ājñapti</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Viḍōlaiviḍugu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Viḍēlviḍugu</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kāḍupaṭṭi-Tamiṛappēraraiyaṉ</hi>,<note>See below Vol. III, p. 92.</note> the grant of the three villages already mentioned was announced to the residents of <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr-nāḍu</hi>, a sub-division of <hi rend="bold">Aruvā-nāḍu</hi>, on its eastern side. As usual, the villages were granted after excluding previous donations and expropriating former owners, for the sole benefit of the <hi rend="italic">vidyāsthāna</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi>. The order was communicated to the assembly of Bāhūr-nāḍu (<hi rend="italic">nāṭṭār)</hi><note>See Madras Epigraphical Report for 1913, Part II, paragraph 23.</note> who on receiving it, obeyed it placing the order on their heads, circumambulated the village, planted stones and milk bush and drew up the necessary document (<hi rend="italic">aṟaiy-ōlai</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>Among the boundaries described occur the names <hi rend="bold">Teṉmalippākkam, Nelvāyēppākkam, Uṟattūr, Māmbākkam, Neriñjikkuṟumbu</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Śiṟimāṉpātti</hi>. The land comprised within the described boundaries of the three villages was given away to the members of the <hi rend="italic">vidyāsthāna</hi> for the advancement of learning, after including these in <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> and giving them the same exemptions (<hi rend="italic">parihāra</hi>) and written declarations (<hi rend="italic">vyavasthā</hi>) as in the case of <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi>. The goldsmith (<hi rend="italic">suvarṇakṛit</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Nṛipatuṅga</hi>, a jewel of the <hi rend="bold">Uditōdita</hi> family and a faithful servant of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>, wrote the grant (V. 32). The Tamil passage at the end of the inscription states that this goldsmith's father was <hi rend="bold">Mādēvipperudaṭṭāṉ</hi>, son of <hi rend="bold">Uditōdaya-Perudaṭṭāṉ</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> (Conjeeveram).</p>
                
                <p>Of the villages mentioned, <hi rend="bold">Bāhūr</hi> is the only place that can be identified. It is the head-quarters of a commune in the French territory and was the site of a battle between the French and the English troops in A.D. 1752.</p>
                
                <p>TEXT.<note>From the transcript prepared by a Tamil Pandit.</note></p>
                
                <p>svasti śrīḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></p>
                
                <lg><l>diśatu va<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śriyamaṁbujalocanastridaśamaulinisṛṣṭapadāṁbujaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>sakalalokabhayaṁkararākṣasapraśamaheturajo madhusūdanaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 1</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l><note>The metre is faulty. The three first feet are Praharshiṇī with a long and a short missing. The last foot is Anushṭubh.</note>śrībhartuśśayanaparasya netre yatteja<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> sthitilayasūtihetuḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tannābherajani samastabījamabjamātmayonistato['*]bhavat <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 2</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>aṁgirāstata utpanno lokanāthāccaturmukhāt <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>bṛhaspatistato mantrī śakrasya valabhedinaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 3</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tataśśaṁyustato jajñe bharadvājasamāhvayaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tato droṇo maheṣvāsassamare śakravikramaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 4</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tato droṇānmahābāhussarvāyudhaviśāradaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>Aśvatthāmā kilāṁśena saṁbabhūva pinākinaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 5</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>aśvatthāmnastato rājā pallavākhyo babhūva ha <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>rarakṣa navakhaṇḍasthān bhūpatīn sakṛṣīvalān <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 6</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>vimalakoṁkaṇikādi tadanvayādajani bṛndamaripramadānataṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>nihitaśāsanamanyanṛpeṣvapi priyatamaṁ jayaghoṣamanārataṁ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 7</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>bhutkvā bhuvaṁ svavīryeṇa catussāgaramekhalāṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tatassvargaṁ vimānena gateṣu vimalādiṣu <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 8</supplied> AsIt</l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>purandarasamo rājā dṛḍhabhaktirmuradviṣi <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l><choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>antivarmā mahābāhuḥ kṣmāpālamakuṭīnataḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 9</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>dharmmeṇa pālanā<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>bhūmiṁ kalāvapi yuge nṛpaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>varṣaṇādapi dānasya parjanya iva nirbabhau <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 10</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>ātmano bandiyuktān tān yamālayadidṛkṣayā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>pā<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>th</corr></choice>eyamiva kṛtvārīn khaṇḍāni vi<unclear>sa</unclear>sarja yaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 11</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>nandivarmā mahābāhussañjāto <choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>antivarmmaṇaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>samare vijitā bhūmirasahāyena yena saḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 12</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>āsīt<note n="515-5">Read āsīcchaṁkhāº.</note>śakhāhvayā devī tanvaṁgī nandivarmaṇaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>rāṣṭrakūṭa<unclear>ku</unclear>le jātā lakṣmīriva muradviṣaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 13</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>kṣamāvatī dharitrīva mā<unclear>tṛ</unclear>vajjagataḥ priyā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>babhau śaṁkhāhvayā devī rājña<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrīriva rūpiṇī <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 14</supplied></l></lg>               
                
                <lg><l>tasyāṁ babhūva matikāntikalādimatyāṁ mānyaḥ kulena guṇavān bhuvanatrayeśaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>Utpadyamānatapanādhipatulyatejā jiṣṇuḥ kalāvān samare nṛpatuṁgadevaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 15</supplied><note>The last foot of this Vasantatilaka verse is faulty.</note></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>yatprasādājjitā senā pāṇḍyena samare purā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l><note>In the word pārericit must be found the reference to the place where the enemy was defeated by Nṛipatuṅga. Literally translated, it means ‘on the other bank of Arichit.’ I am not able to identify (the river ?) Arichit.</note>pārericitsarājyaśrīrdadāha ripusaṁhatiṁ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 16</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>nṛpatuṁga iti khyāto bālopi bhuvaneśvaraḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>khyāto na kevalaṁ bhūmāvamuṣminnapi rāmavat <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 17</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tasyopakārasaṁyukto rājñaḥ kurukulo<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>bhavaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>baśālivaṁśamārttāṇḍaḥ prajānāṁ śaraṇe rataḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 18</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>śaśivattilako loke gāṁbhīryādessamudravat <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>sūryavadrakṣaṇāllokān lokānāṁ nilayo nṛpaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 19</supplied></l></lg>
                
                
                <lg><l>tasmāttasyocitannāmni tulyatā bhāti devavat <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>āthava sutarānnāma pratyakṣatvādviśāṁpateḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 20</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>grātra yaṁ svarāṣṭre saḥ kuruvaṁśavivarddhanaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>vijñāpya nṛpatuṁgeśāllabdhamājñaptipūrvakaḥ<note n="516-1">Read ºpūrvakaṁ.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 21</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>ceṭuppākkaṁ phalādhāraṁ grāmamekamathāparaṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>grāmaṁ<note>In the Tamil portion this village is called Viḷāṅgāṭṭaṅkaḍuvaṉūr. I cannot explain how this full name could be got out of the Sanskṛit verse.</note> vidyādviḷāṁgādirephāntapadanāmakaṁ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 22</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tasmādi <seg xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">ṟaippuṇaiccērī</seg>ntritIyyaM<note n="516-3">Read ºntṛtīyaṁ.</note> sarvasaMpadaM <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>evaṁ grāmatrayaṁ labdhvā vidyāsthānāya dattavān <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 23</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>mandākinīṁ samāyāntīmūrmivaṁśasamākulāṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>saṁbabhāra yathā devo dhūrjaṭirjaṭayaikayā <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 24</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>vidyānadī tathāgāthā caturdaśagaṇākulā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>bāhugrāmajuṣāṁ sthānaṁ vyāpya yasmādvyavasthitā <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 25</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tatsthānamevaṁ viduṣāṁ vidyāsthānaṁ pracakṣate <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>tebhyo datvā sa bhūpālo grāmānājñaptipūrvakān <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 26</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>hastisañcārisīmāntānātmānaṁ bahumanyate <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>yuktān sarvaparīhārairākaratvena rakṣitān <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 27</supplied></l></lg>                
                
                <lg><l>ājñābhīrurddharmmaśīlastrailokyeśvarapūjitaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>mantrī bṛhaspatiprakhyaḥ rājña<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrītuṁgavarmmaṇaḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 28</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>āgāminaḥ prajāpālān yācate kurunandanaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>dharmmasya tasya sāmānyāt pālanīya iti svayaṁ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 29</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>dāsa<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> sthānasya vidyāyāḥ bāhugrāmajuṣāmayaṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>kṛtavān śāstratatvajñaḥ praśastindāśayassvataḥ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 30</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <p xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                    kovicaiya nirupatoṅkavarumaṟku yāṇṭu eṭṭāvatu <hi rend="grantha">ba</hi>cālipperarayaṉ viṇṇappattāl viṭōlaiviṭuku kāṭupaṭṭittamiḻapperarayaṉ āṇattiyāka aruvānāṭṭukkiḻvaḻi vākūrnāṭṭu nāṭṭār kāṇka <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tannāṭṭu ceṭṭuppākkamum viḷāṅkāṭṭaṅkaṭuvaṉūrum iṟaippuṇaicceriyumāka immūṉṟūrum paḻayavaṟamum piramateyamum nīkki muṉpeṟṟārai māṟṟi yāṇṭu eṭṭāvatu pākūr vittiyāstāṉattārkku vittiyāṉupokamākappaṇittom <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tāṅkaḷum paṭākai naṭantu kalluṅkaḷḷiyum nāṭṭi aṟaiyolai ceytu viṭutakaveṉṟu nāṭṭārkkuttirumukam viṭa nāṭṭār tirumukaṅkaṇṭu toḻutu talaikku vaittu paṭākai naṭantu kalluṅkaḷḷiyum nāṭṭi aṟaiyōlai ceytu nāṭṭārviṭutta aṟaiyōlaippaṭi nilattukkellai <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> viḷāṅkāṭṭaṅkaṭuvaṉūrkkum ceṭṭuppākkattukkumāka iraṇṭūrukkum kīḻpāṟkellai kāṭṭu ellai oṉṟum teṉmalipākkattu yellaiyiṉ meṟkum teṉpāṟkellai teṉmalipākkattellai oṉṟum nelvāyēppākkattellai oṉṟum uṟattūrellaikku vaṭakkum melpāṟkellai māmpākkattellai oṉṟum ivviḷāṅkāṭṭaṅkaṭuvaṉūr<unclear>p</unclear>pāṟ piramateyamāyiṉa aṟupatu ceṟuvukkukkiḻakkum vaṭapāṟkellai vākūrellaiyiṉṟeṟkum <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Iṟaippuṇaiccerikkellai kiḻpāṟkellai nattamuḷḷiṭṭa kāṭṭukku meṟkum teṉpāṟkellai neriñcikkuṟumpiṉ ellaiyiṉ vaṭakkum melpāṟkellai vākūrellaiyiṉ kiḻakkum vaṭapāṟkellai ciṟimāṉpātti ellaiyiṉ ṟeṟkumāka ivvicaitta perunāṉkellaikaḷilumakappaṭṭa nilaṉ nirnilaṉum puñceyum ūrum ūrirukkaiyum maṉaiyum maṉaippaṭappum māṭuṅkaṉṟumēypāḻum kuḷamum kōṭṭakaramum kiṭaṅkum kēṇiyum kāṭuṅkaḷarum ōṭaiyum uṭaippum uḷḷiṭṭu nīrpūci neṭumparamapeṟintu uṭumpōṭi āmaitavaḻntatellām uṇṇilaṉoḻiviṉṟi vākūr vittiyāstāṉattārkku vittiyāṉupokamāy pākūrōṭē ēṟṟi vākūrpeṟṟa parikāramum <hi rend="grantha">vya</hi>vastaiyum peṟṟu carvaparikāramāy pirammateyamāy piracitti<note>This word was perhaps <foreign>paraṭatti</foreign> in the original as in the Vēlūrpāḷaiyam plates, text, l. 63.</note> ceṉṟatu <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></p>
                
                <lg><l>puṇyaṁ samaṁ kṛtavatāṁ parirakṣatāñcet tadrakṣateti nṛpatirnnṛpatuṁgavarmmā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>āgāminaḥ kṣitipatīn praṇamatyajasraṁ mūrdhnā mukundacaraṇāṁbujaśekhareṇa <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 31</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>uditoditakulatilakaḥ suvarṇakṛtsarvaśāstraniṣṇātaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></l></lg>
                
                <lg><l>alikhannṛpatuṁgākhyaḥ pallavakulamūlabhṛtyotra <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g> 32</supplied></l></lg>
                
                <p><seg xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">kaccippeṭṭukkiḻppaicārattu utitotayapperutaṭṭāṉ makaṉ mātevipperutaṭṭāṉ makaṉ nirupatoṅkaṉ eḻuttu <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></seg></p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 2.98 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1916_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1916_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">501-517</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">98</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
