<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.22: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 22. ON THE SOUTH WALL, FIRST AND SECOND TIERS.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0022</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated on the 64th day of the 35th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Tribhuvanachakravartin Kōnēriṉmai-koṇḍāṉ</hi> and records the grant of the village of <hi rend="bold">Suṅgandavirtta-Śōṛaṉallūr</hi>,<note n="112-7"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the good village (<hi rend="italic">called after</hi>) Śuṅgandavirtta-Chōḷa.’ An inscription at Pallāvaram, the beginning of which is found on page 111, note 3, mentions a king of the name Śuṅgandavirtta-Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Tribhuvanachakravartin Kōnērimmai-koṇḍāṉ.</note> which formed part of the town of <hi rend="bold">Karundiṭṭaikuḍi,</hi><note n="112-8">This is a northern suburb of Tanjore; see the Index of the <hi rend="italic">Tanjore Manual</hi>, where it is spelled “Karundattāngudi.”</note> and which was situated on both banks of the <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Śōṛa-Vaḍavāṟu</hi><note n="112-9">According to the map of irrigation works, which accompanies the <hi rend="italic">Tanjore Manual</hi>, the “Vadavāru” is the first river, which is crossed on the north of Tanjore by the road to “Tiruvādi” (Tiruvaiyāṟu).</note> and on the north- western extremity of the city of <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>. The village was divided into 108 shares, of which 106 were to be enjoyed by the Brāhmaṇas of the village of <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇachaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> near <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>, and 2 by the temple of <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇa-Viṇṇagar-Emberumāṉ</hi> in this village. Both this village and this temple had been called after his own name, and the granted village had been purchased from its former owners, by a person, who is designated in the text as the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉār</hi>, but whose proper name must accordingly have been <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇa</hi>. He was apparently a feudatory or high officer of the king, who made the grant at his instance and on his behalf. At the present time the title of <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi> is borne by the chiefs of the state of <hi rend="bold">Pudukkōṭṭai</hi> in the Trichinopoly district. Their ancestor is reported to have ousted one <hi rend="bold">Pallavarāyaṉ Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi> about 1680 A.D.<note n="113-1">Mr. Sewell's <hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. II, p. 225.</note> This chief was probably a descendant of <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇa Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi> and of <hi rend="bold">Karuṇākara Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi>, who, according to the Tamil poem <hi rend="italic">Kaliṅgattu-Paraṇi,</hi><note n="113-2"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XIX, p. 337.</note> was king of the <hi rend="bold">Pallavas</hi>, resided at <hi rend="bold">Vaṇḍai</hi><note n="113-3">Mr. Kanakasabhai Pillai, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 340, has satisfactorily identified Vaṇḍai or Vaṇḍainagaram with Vaṇḍalūr, a Railway station south of Pallāvaram in the Chingleput district.</note> and was the prime minister of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga</hi>. The title <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi> means the king of <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍai</hi><note n="113-4">Compare <ta>cēramāṉ</ta>, ‘the Chēra king,’ which occurs in No. 1, paragraphs 34, 51, 52 and 107.</note> or <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimaṇḍalam</hi>, the Tamil name of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> country, the ancient capital of which was <hi rend="bold">Kāñchīpuram</hi>. The numerous Chōḷa inscriptions found at this town prove that the Pallava kingdom must have fallen a prey to the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷas</hi>. From the <hi rend="italic">Kaliṅgattu-Paraṇi</hi> it further appears, that the former rulers of Toṇḍaimaṇḍalam were allowed to retain possession of their dominions as feudatories. In the subjoined inscription they appear in the same position during the time of <hi rend="bold">Kōnēriṉmai-koṇḍāṉ</hi>.</p>						

						<p>The chief difficulty in this inscription are the numerous fiscal terms mentioned in connection with the grant. A good many of them had to be left untranslated,<note n="113-5">The English meanings which are assigned to some of these terms by Mr. S.M.Naṭēśa Śāstrī in Dr. Burgess' <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey of Southern India</hi>, Vol. IV, p. 186, are purely fanciful.</note> while the translation of others is only tentative.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">First tier, first section</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tribhu</hi>vaṉaccak<hi rend="grantha">ra</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rtti</hi> koneri<unclear>ṉ</unclear>
<lb n="2" break="no"/>maikoṇṭāṉ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> pāṇṭiku<unclear>la</unclear>pativaḷanāṭ
<lb n="3" break="no"/>ṭuttañcāvūrkkūṟṟattuttañcāvūri<unclear>l</unclear> toṇṭ
<lb n="4" break="no"/>aimāṉār tam perāl vaitta A<unclear>ka</unclear>ram cāman
<lb n="5" break="no"/>tanārāyaṇaccatu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedi</hi>maṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>lattu<hi rend="grantha"> A<unclear>dhī</unclear></hi>
<lb n="6" break="no"/><unclear>ta</unclear>ve<hi rend="grantha">daśāstrarā</hi>y viyā<note n="113-6">Read <hi rend="grantha">vyā</hi>.</note> <hi rend="grantha">khyā</hi>tāk<unclear>kaḷ</unclear>āyirukkum
</p>

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">First tier, second section</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">ca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>rvve</unclear>dibha</hi>ṭṭa<unclear>r</unclear>kaḷ per nūṟṟāṟukkuppaṅku nūṟṟāṟum Ivvaka<unclear>ra</unclear>ttu Iva<unclear>r</unclear> perāl Eḻuntaru<unclear>ḷi</unclear>vitta cāmantanārā<unclear>ya</unclear>ṇaviṇṇakaremperumāṉukkuppa
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ṅku <unclear>Ira</unclear>ṇṭum <unclear>Ā</unclear>ta<note n="113-7">Read āka.</note> ppaṅku nūṟṟe<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭukkum muppattaiñcāvatu k<unclear>ār</unclear> mutal kuṭutta pāṇṭikulapativaḷanāṭṭuttañ<unclear>c</unclear>āvūrkkūṟṟattuttañcāvūrppaṟṟil
<lb n="3"/>teṉṉakaṅkatevaṉum ciṉattaraiyaṉum Uḷḷiṭṭār pakkal toṇṭaiymānār vilai koṇṭa nakaram karuntiṭṭaiykuṭi Āṉa cuṅkantavir
<lb n="4" break="no"/>ttatoḻa<note n="114-1">Read coḻa.</note> ṉallūrkku kiḻpārkkellai karuntiṭṭaikuṭiyāṉa kulottu<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kacoḻaṉ Aḷ<unclear>ḷu</unclear>r<note n="114-2">Read coḻaṉallūr.</note> Ellaikkum karuntiṭṭaikuṭi Āṉa
<lb n="5"/>keṅkaikoṇṭacoḻaṉ tiruṉantavaṉa Ellaikkumeṟkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>vī</unclear>racoḻavaṭavāṟṟukkutteṟku<note n="114-3">Corrected from tekku by the engraver himself.</note> kiḻpārkkellai tañcāvūr nantava
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ṉappaṟṟu Ellaikku meṟkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> teṉpāṟkel<unclear>lai</unclear> mummaṭicoḻaṉ matiḷukkukkiḻakku nantavaṉappaṟṟu Ellaikku vaṭakkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> matiḷu
<lb n="7" break="no"/>kku meṟku tañcāvūrppalataḷippaṟṟu Ellaikku va<unclear>ṭa</unclear>kkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> melpāṟkellai koṭivaṉamuṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>yāḷ peruvaḻikkukkiḻakkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
<lb n="8"/>viracoḻavaṭavāṟṟukku vaṭakarai Ivvāṟṟukkukkiḻakkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> vaṭapāṟkellai kāṭavaṉ<hi rend="grantha">mahā<unclear>d</unclear>e</hi>vi Āṉa virutarā<hi rend="grantha">jabha</hi>yaṅkaracca
<lb n="9" break="no"/>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedi</hi>maṅkalattu Ellaikkutteṟkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Āka Iṉṉāṉkellaikku Uḷḷakappaṭṭa Ava kama<unclear>l</unclear>lakuḷamāṉa <hi rend="grantha">jagade</hi>kavīra<hi rend="grantha">su</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">r</hi>namaṅ
</p>

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">Second tier</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1" break="no"/>kalam viḷainilamum puṉceyyum palataḷippaṟṟu viḷai<unclear>ni</unclear>lamum pu<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ceyyum ṉantavaṉappaṟṟu viḷai<unclear>ni</unclear>lamum puṉceyyum nik<unclear>ki</unclear> Innāṉk<unclear>e</unclear>llaikkuḷppaṭṭa karai Ai<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied>pa<unclear>tiṉā</unclear>lppaḻantevatānam
<lb n="2"/>nikkippottakappaṭi paṭukaiiṟaitta<unclear>la</unclear>varam<unclear>pi</unclear>ṟai <unclear>U</unclear>ṭppaṭa naṉce<unclear>ni</unclear>lam Aṟupatiṟṟu veliyum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> paṇimakkaḷ<hi rend="grantha">vṛtti</hi>nilam Oṉṟe mukkāle mūṉṟu māvum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> puṉceynilam patiṉā<unclear>lu</unclear> veliyum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Akaranattamum
<lb n="3"/><hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vaya<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">bhūmi</hi>yum <hi rend="grantha">gopracārabhūmi</hi>yum nilam <unclear>Ā</unclear>ṟu veliyum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> veḷḷāṉ nattaṅka<unclear>ḷ</unclear> kuḷaṅkaḷ vāykkālkaḷ tiṭalkaḷ kāṭu meṭu Uṭpaṭa nilam paṉṉiraṇṭe kāle Araikkā<unclear>lum</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Āka naṉcey puṉcey Akara
<lb n="4" break="no"/>nattam <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vaya<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">gopracār(ā)bhūmi</hi> v<unclear>e</unclear>ḷḷāṉ nattaṅkaḷ kuḷaṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>ḷ vāykkālkaḷ tiṭalkaḷ kāṭu meṭu Uṭpaṭa potta<unclear>ka</unclear>ppaṭi nilam toṇṇūṟṟu nāle kāle Arai mā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Iti<unclear>l t</unclear>eṉṉakaṅkatevaṉ kāṇi
<lb n="5" break="no"/>yāṉa karai Oṉpatukkum viḻukkāṭu <unclear>ni</unclear>lam patiṉāṟe mukkāle nālu mākkāṇi Araikkāṇi nikkikkarai nāṟpattoṉṟukku nilam Eḻupatteḻe Āṟu māvaraikkāṇi <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Iṉṉi<unclear>la</unclear>m Eḻupatteḻe Āṟu mā
<lb n="6" break="no"/>varaikkāṇiyum Eṟṟakkuṟaittal <unclear>U</unclear>ṭpa<unclear>ṭa</unclear> Innilamum Innilaṅkaṉil<note n="114-4">Read kaḷil.</note> melnokkiṉa maraṅkaḷum kiḻnokkiṉa kiṇaṟukaḷum maṟṟum Epperppaṭṭa <hi rend="grantha">samastaprāpti</hi>kaḷum <unclear>U</unclear>ḷpaṭappaṇṭuṭaiyārai
<lb n="7" break="no"/><unclear>yu</unclear>m <unclear>pa</unclear>ḻaṅkā<unclear>ṇi</unclear>yā<unclear>ḷa</unclear>raiyu<unclear>m</unclear> mutaliṟtaviṟ<unclear>tu</unclear> Ivvakara<hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṭṭarkaḷ per nūṟṟāṟukkum cāmantanā<hi rend="grantha">r<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice></hi>yaṇaviṇṇakaremperumaraṉukku<unclear>p</unclear>paṅku Iraṇṭukkum kāṇiyum Iṟaiyiliyumākakk<unclear>o</unclear>ṇṭu k<unclear>ār</unclear> maṟu<unclear>vu</unclear>m Orupūvum
<lb n="8"/>kaṭaippūvum <unclear>A</unclear>mpum <unclear>pu</unclear>ṉpayirum ceṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>ḻanirum<note n="114-5">Read ceṅkaḻunīrum.</note> kamukum koḻun<unclear>tu</unclear>m mañcaḷiñci vāḻai karumpu Uḷḷiṭṭa Aṉaittuppayirum ceytu koḷḷavum kaṭamai kuṭimai kācukaṭamai Oṭukkumpaṭi Uṟaināḻi veṭṭimeṟpāṭi
<lb n="9" break="no"/>kāval A<unclear>ḷa</unclear>kkuṅkara<unclear>ṇam</unclear> k<unclear>ār</unclear>ttikai<unclear>p</unclear>paccai taṟiiṟai cekki<unclear>ṟ</unclear>ai ceṭṭiṟai taṭṭoli taṭṭā<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>ppāṭṭam māvaṭ<unclear>ai</unclear> kuḷavaṭai Oḻukkunirppāṭṭam vaḻiāyam Inavari Iṭaivari Aḻukalccarakku Aṅkā
<lb n="10" break="no"/><unclear>ṭi</unclear>ppāṭṭam Uppāyam<note n="115-1">ṭhis word is injured by cracks and looks like vippirayam.</note> <unclear>U</unclear>ḷ<unclear>ḷi</unclear>ṭṭa A<unclear>ṉai</unclear>ttāyavaṟkaṅkaru<note n="115-2">Read vaṟkaṅkaḷum.</note> pañcu<unclear>pi</unclear>li<note n="115-3">This term occurs frequently in the Tirupparaṅkuṉṟam inscription (see page 110, note 7), where it is perfectly distinct, though in the published transcript it is read pañcumili.</note> cantivikkirakappeṟu Ilāñciṉaippeṟu vā<unclear>ca</unclear>lviniyokam paṭaiilārmuṟaimai kūṟṟilakkai ka<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aikkūṭṭilakkai taṇṭali
<lb n="11" break="no"/>la<unclear>k</unclear>k<unclear>ai</unclear> viṭaipper <unclear>m</unclear>āta<unclear>p</unclear>pa<unclear>ṭi A</unclear>r<unclear>ai</unclear>kkālvāci Ūci<unclear>v</unclear>āci vilai<unclear>t</unclear>tuṇṭam nirāṇi kāverikkulai tevaikuṭimai n<unclear>ā</unclear>ṭṭupāti Āṉaikkūṭam kutiraippanti Uḷḷiṭṭa Aṉai<unclear>ttu</unclear> vaṟkaṅkaḷum Uṭpaṭa
<lb n="12"/>muppattaiñcāvatu kā<unclear>r</unclear> mutal <hi rend="grantha">dharmma<unclear>d</unclear>ā</hi>namāka U<hi rend="grantha">da</hi>ka<hi rend="grantha">pūrvvamā</hi>ka <hi rend="grantha">dā</hi>nā<hi rend="grantha">dhama-</hi> navik<hi rend="grantha">ra</hi>yaṅkaḷukku yo<hi rend="grantha">gyamā</hi>ka <hi rend="grantha">bhūdā</hi>naiṟ<unclear>ai</unclear>yiliyāka<hi rend="grantha">ccandrāditya</hi>vaṟcelvatākattantom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ip<unclear>pa</unclear>ṭikku Ivvolai piṭipā
<lb n="13" break="no"/><unclear>ṭ</unclear>ākakkoṇṭu kallilum cempilum veṭṭikkoḷka <g type="ddanda">.</g> yāṇṭu muppattaiñcāvatu nāḷ Aṟupattu nālu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai miḻalaikkūṟṟattu tuñcalūruṭaiyāṉ kāṅkayaṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> I<unclear>v</unclear>ai mi<unclear>ḻa</unclear>laikkūṟṟattu tuñ
<lb n="14" break="no"/>calū<unclear>ru</unclear>ṭaiyāṉ pallavarāyaṉ <unclear>E</unclear>ḻuttu <hi rend="grantha">U</hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>Hail ! Prosperity ! (<hi rend="italic">The following is an order of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tribhuvanachakravartin Kōnēriṉmai-koṇḍāṉ</hi>.</p>

<p>“From the rainy season (<hi rend="italic">kār</hi>) in the thirty-fifth (<hi rend="italic">year of our reign), (the village of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śuṅgandavirtta-Śōṛaṉallūr</hi>,—which forms part of the town (<hi rend="italic">nagara</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Karundiṭṭaikuḍi</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr-paṟṟu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr-kūṟṟam</hi><note n="115-4">The same subdivision is mentioned in No. 1, paragraph 2.</note> in <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍikulapativaḷanāḍu</hi>,<note n="115-5">This designation corresponds to Pāṇḍyakulāśani-and Pāṇḍikulāśaṉi-vaḷanāḍu in No. 1, paragraph 2, and No. 21, paragraph 2, respectively.</note> and which the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉār</hi> had purchased from <hi rend="bold">Teṉṉagaṅgadēvaṉ, Śiṉattaraiyaṉ</hi> and other partners (<hi rend="italic">uḷḷiṭṭār</hi>),—was given for (<hi rend="italic">providing</hi>) one hundred and eight shares (<hi rend="italic">paṅgu), viz</hi>., one hundred and six shares for one hundred and six <hi rend="italic">Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭas</hi>, who had studied the <hi rend="italic">Vēdas</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Śāstras</hi> and were able to interpret (<hi rend="italic">them), (and who lived</hi>) at <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇa-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>,—a village (<hi rend="italic">agaram</hi>) in (<hi rend="italic">the neighbourhood of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a city</hi>) in <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍikulapativaḷanāḍu</hi>,—which the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉār</hi> had bestowed (<hi rend="italic">on them and called</hi>) after his own name; and two shares for (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇa-Viṇṇagar-Emberumāṉ,</hi><note n="115-6"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘our lord of the Vishṇu temple (<hi rend="italic">called after</hi>) Sāmantanārāyaṇa.’ <hi rend="italic">Viṇṇagar</hi> is another form of <hi rend="italic">Viṇṇagaram</hi>, which, to judge from a Kāñchīpuram inscription (Vol. I, p. 87, note 1), seems to be a popular corruption of <hi rend="italic">Vishṇu-gṛiha</hi>. It occurs in inscriptions at Poygai and Kaṇiyaṉūr; in Vol. I, p. 87, line 1, and in paragraph 1 of the <hi rend="italic">Progress Report</hi> quoted on page 110, note 6, read <hi rend="italic">Viṇṇagar</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">Viṇṇagara</hi>.</note> which he had set up in this village (<hi rend="italic">and called</hi>) after (<hi rend="italic">his own</hi>) name. The eastern boundary of (<hi rend="italic">this village</hi>) is to the west of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Śōṛaṉallūr</hi>, which forms part of <hi rend="bold">Karundiṭṭaikuḍi</hi>, and of the boundary of the sacred flower-garden (<hi rend="italic">called after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Geṅgaikoṇḍa-Śōṛaṉ</hi>,<note n="115-7">See No. 21. paragraph 3.</note> which forms part of <hi rend="bold">Karundiṭṭaikuḍi</hi>; (<hi rend="italic">that part of</hi>) the eastern boundary, which is to the south of the <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Śōṛa-Vaḍavāṟu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">river</hi>), is to the west of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Nandavaṉappaṟṟu</hi>,<note n="115-8"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the quarter of flower-gardens.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">a quarter of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">That part of</hi>) the southern boundary, which is to the east of the wall (<hi rend="italic">madiḷ</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Mummaḍi-Śōṛaṉ</hi>, is to the north of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Nandavaṉappaṟṟu</hi>; (<hi rend="italic">that part of the southern boundary, which is</hi>) to the west of the (<hi rend="italic">same</hi>) wall, is to the north of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Palataḷippaṟṟu</hi>,<note n="116-1"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, ‘the quarter of many temples.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">a quarter of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>. The western boundary is to the east of the high-road (<hi rend="italic">peru-vaṛi</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Koḍivaṉam-uḍaiyāḷ</hi>; (<hi rend="italic">that part of the western boundary, which is on</hi>) the northern bank of the <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Śōṛa-Vaḍavāṟu</hi>, is (<hi rend="italic">at the same time</hi>) to the east of this river.<note n="116-2">This queer description may be explained by assuming that the river which passes the village from east to west, takes a northerly bend on leaving it.</note> The northern boundary is to the south of the boundary of <hi rend="bold">Kāḍavaṉ-mahādēvī</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Virudarājabhayaṁkara-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>.<note n="116-3">This village might have received its name from the Chōḷa king Kulōttuṅga, one of whose <hi rend="italic">birudas</hi> was, according to Mr. Kanakasabhai Pillai's abridged translation of the <hi rend="italic">Kaliṅgattu-Paraṇi</hi>, ‘he who was a terror to Virutarāja;’ <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XIX, p. 332.</note> Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the land</hi>) included within these four boundaries,—excluding the cultivated land (<hi rend="italic">viḷai-nilam</hi>) and the dry land (<hi rend="italic">puṉśey) (of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ava. .kamallakuḷam</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Jagadēkavīra-Suvarṇamaṅgalam</hi>, the cultivated land and the dry land of <hi rend="bold">Palataḷippaṟṟu</hi>, and the cultivated land and the dry land of <hi rend="bold">Nandavaṉappaṟṟu</hi>,—(<hi rend="italic">is divided into</hi>) fifty blocks (<hi rend="italic">karai)</hi>.<note n="116-4">On this division of land see Mr. H.Stokes' paper ‘The custom of “Kareiyīḍ” or periodical redistribution of land in Tanjore,’ <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. III, pp. 65 ff.</note> Of (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>), the wet land (<hi rend="italic">naṉśe[y]-nilam</hi>),— excluding ancient gifts to temples (<hi rend="italic">dēvadāna), (and</hi>) including the portion on the bank of the river (<hi rend="italic">paḍugai-iṟai</hi>) and the portion consisting of the causeways between fields (<hi rend="italic">talavaramb-iṟai),—(contains</hi>), according to the book (<hi rend="italic">pottagam</hi>),<note n="116-5">This expression must refer to the land-register, which is called <hi rend="italic">kaṇakku</hi> in No. 21, second section, line 3.</note> sixty <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>; the land on which the (<hi rend="italic">village</hi>) servants subsist, (<hi rend="italic">contains</hi>) one (<hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>), three quarters and three twentieths; the dry land (<hi rend="italic">puṉśey-nilam) (contains</hi>) fourteen <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>; the land (<hi rend="italic">which is occupied by</hi>) the villagesite (<hi rend="italic">agara-nattam</hi>), the place used for sacrificing to the gods (<hi rend="italic">dēva-yajana-bhūmi</hi>), and the place used as pasture for the cows (<hi rend="italic">gō-prachāra-bhūmi),<note n="116-6">Compare the fiscal term <hi rend="italic">sva-sīmā-tṛiṇa-yūti-gōchara-paryanta; Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XIV, p. 161, note 26, and Vol. XV. p. 309, note 36.</note> (contains</hi>) six <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>; the land which includes the houses of the cultivators (<hi rend="italic">Veḷḷāṉ</hi>), the ponds, channels, hills, jungles and mounds, (<hi rend="italic">contains</hi>) twelve (<hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>), one quarter and one eighth. Altogether, the land which includes the wet land and dry land, the site of the village, the places used for sacrificing to the gods and as pasture for the cows, and the houses of the cultivators, the ponds, channels, hills, jungles and mounds, (<hi rend="italic">contains</hi>), according to the book, ninety-four (<hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>), one quarter and one fortieth. Deducting from this nine blocks in possession (<hi rend="italic">kāṇi</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Teṉṉagaṅgadēvaṉ</hi>, which contain sixteen (<hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>) of land, three quarters, four twentieths, one eightieth and one hundred-and-sixtieth, (<hi rend="italic">there remain</hi>) forty-one blocks, containing seventy-seven (<hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>) of land, six twentieths and one hundred-and-sixtieth.<note n="116-7">The whole manipulation is as follows:— <table>Wet land .. .. 60 <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>. Land of the village-servants 1(3/4), (3/20) <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>. Dry land .. .. 14 <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>. Village-site, etc. .. .. 6 <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>. Miscellaneous .. .. 12(1/4), (1/8) <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>. Total 94(1/4), (1/40) <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> = 50 blocks. Deduct 16(3/4), (4/20), (1/80), (1/160) <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>. = 9 blocks. Remainder 77(6/20), (1/160) <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> = 41 blocks.</table></note> These seventy-seven, six two tieths and one hundred-and-sixtieth (<hi rend="italic">vēli</hi>) of land, which may be more or less,<note n="116-8">This clause seems to provide for possible mistakes in the measurement.</note> we gave,—including the trees overground and the wells underground in this land, and all other benefits (<hi rend="italic">prāpti</hi>) of whatever kind,<note n="117-1">Compare <ta>ivvērinīr</ta><hi rend="grantha">prāpti</hi> <ta>āṟṟukkāl</ta><hi rend="grantha">prāpti</hi> <ta>vāykkāl</ta><hi rend="grantha">prāpti</hi> in Vol. I, p. 103, text line 19.</note> having first excluded the former owners and the hereditary proprietors, and having purchased (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>) as tax-free property (<hi rend="italic">kāṇi</hi>) for the one hundred and six <hi rend="italic">Bhaṭṭas</hi>) of this village and for the two shares (<hi rend="italic">of the image</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Sāmantanārāyaṇa-Viṇṇagar-Emberumāṉ</hi>,—from the rainy season in the thirty-fifth (<hi rend="italic">year of our reign</hi>), as a meritorious gift (<hi rend="italic">dharmadāna</hi>), with libations of water, with the right to bestow, mortgage or sell (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>), as a tax-free grant of land, to last as long as the moon and the sun. (<hi rend="italic">This grant</hi>) includes all kinds (<hi rend="italic">varga</hi>) of taxes (<hi rend="italic">kaḍamai</hi>) and rights (<hi rend="italic">kuḍimai), viz., (the right</hi>) to cultivate <hi rend="italic">kār,<note n="117-2">According to the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Tamoul-Français</hi>, this is an inferior kind of paddy, which grows in some localities during the rainy season (<hi rend="italic">kār</hi>) and in others after that season.</note> maṟuvu,</hi><note n="117-3"><ta>maṟuvu</ta> is perhaps the same as <ta>maruku</ta>, ‘a fragrant plant, <hi rend="italic">Origanum majoranum</hi>’ (Winslow).</note> single flowers (<hi rend="italic">? oru-pū</hi>), flowers for the market (<hi rend="italic">kaḍai-pū</hi>), limetrees, dry crops, red water-lilies, areca-palms, betel-vines, saffron, ginger, plantains, sugarcane and all other crops (<hi rend="italic">payir</hi>); all kinds of revenue (<hi rend="italic">āya</hi>), including the tax in money (<hi rend="italic">kāśu-kaḍamai), oḍukkum-paḍi, uṟai-nāṛi,<note n="117-4">On <ta>paṭi</ta> or <ta>nāḻi</ta> see page 48, note 5.</note> (the share of</hi>) the village-watchman (<hi rend="italic">? pāḍi-kāval) (who is placed</hi>) over the <hi rend="italic">Veṭṭis,<note n="117-5">See Vol. I, p. 82, note 3, and p. 108. note 6.</note> (the share of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">Karaṇam</hi> who measures (<hi rend="italic">the paddy ?</hi>), the unripe (<hi rend="italic">fruit ?</hi>) in <hi rend="italic">Kārttigai</hi>, the tax on looms (<hi rend="italic">taṟi-iṟai</hi>), the tax on oil-mills (<hi rend="italic">śekk-iṟai</hi>), the tax on trade (<hi rend="italic">śeṭṭ-iṟai), taṭṭoli</hi>, the tax on goldsmiths (<hi rend="italic">taṭṭār-pāṭṭam), (the dues on</hi>) animals and tanks,<note n="117-6">With <ta>māvaṭai kuḷavaṭai</ta> compare the terms <ta>māviṭai maraviṭai</ta>, ‘the animals and trees,’ which the Tamil dictionaries quote from a deed of sale.</note> the tax on water-courses (<hi rend="italic">oṛukku-nīr-pāṭṭam</hi>), tolls (<hi rend="italic">vaṛi-āyam), inavari,</hi><note n="117-7">The term <ta>inavari</ta> or <ta>iṉavari</ta> occurs in Vol. I, Nos. 61, 62 and 78.</note> the tax on weights (<hi rend="italic">iḍai-vari), (the fine for</hi>) rotten drugs (<hi rend="italic">aṛugal-śarakku</hi>), the tax on <hi rend="italic">bāzārs (aṅgāḍipāṭṭam), (and</hi>) the salt-tax (<hi rend="italic">upp-āyam</hi>); • • • • • the elephant-stalls (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the horse-stables. Thus, in accordance with this order (<hi rend="italic">ōlai</hi>), it shall be engraved on stone and copper. On the sixty-fourth day of the thirty-fifth year (<hi rend="italic">of our reign</hi>).”</p>

<p>This is the signature of <hi rend="bold">Gāṅgayaṉ</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Tuñjalūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Miṛalai-kūṟṟam</hi>. This is the signature of <hi rend="bold">Pallavarāyaṉ</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Tuñjalūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Miṛalai-kūṟṟam</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.22 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">112-117</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">22</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
