<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.83: original edition by V. Venkayya</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 83. ON THE BASE OF THE SOUTH ENCLOSURE. This is a continuation of No. 82 above.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0083</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the tenth year of <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷa</hi> I. and registers an endowment in money in favour of the image of <hi rend="bold">Mahāmēru-Viṭaṅka</hi>, set up by <hi rend="bold">Rāja rājadēva</hi>, and of that of his consort. The money was lent out on interest to the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅga-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> mentioned in No. 82. In this case too, the interest was payable in kind and amounted to fifty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy which had to be delivered into <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viḍaṅgaṉ</hi>, the big treasury at <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/>tiru manni vaḷara Iru<unclear>nila</unclear>maṭan<unclear>tai</unclear>yum p<unclear>o</unclear>rccaya<unclear>p</unclear>pāvaiyuñcīrttaṉiccelviyuntaṉ perunteviyarā<unclear>ki</unclear> Iṉpuṟa neṭutiyalūḻi<unclear>yuḷ Iṭaituṟainā</unclear>ṭuntoṭarvaṉaveli<unclear>ppaṭa</unclear>r vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻmatiṭakoḷ<unclear>ḷip</unclear>pākkai<unclear>yuna</unclear>ṇṇaṟkaru<unclear>mura</unclear>ṇ ma<unclear>ṇṇaikkaṭakkamum porutaṭar Ī</unclear>ḻattaraicartammuṭiyumāṅkavar teviyaroṅkeḻil muṭiyum munnavar <unclear>pa</unclear>kkal tennavar vaitta cuntaramuṭiyu<unclear>ma</unclear> Intiraṉāra munteṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum E<unclear>ṟi</unclear>paṭaikkera<unclear>ḷa</unclear>r <unclear>muṟai</unclear>m<unclear>aiyiṟcūṭuṅkulataṉamākiya palar pukaḻ muṭiyuñceṅkatir</unclear> mā<unclear>laiyuñ</unclear>caṅkatirve<unclear>lai</unclear>ttolp<unclear>e</unclear>ruṅk<unclear>āva</unclear>l <unclear>pa</unclear>lapaḻan<unclear>tī</unclear>(y)vuñ<unclear>ceruvi</unclear>ṟciṉaviyirupattorukālarai<unclear>cukaḷai kaṭṭa paracurāma</unclear>ṉ mevaruñcāntimattivavara<unclear>ṇ</unclear> karutiyiruttiya cem<unclear>poṟṟi</unclear>ruttaku muṭiyum payaṅkoṭu paḻimika muyaṅkiyil mutukiṭṭoḷitta ca<unclear>ya</unclear>ciṅkaṉ Aḷapperum pukaḻoṭu <unclear>pi</unclear>ṭi
<lb n="2" break="no"/>yal Iraṭṭapāṭi Eḻarai Ilakkamu<unclear>m</unclear> navanetikkulapperumalaikaḷum māpporutaṇaṭāṟkoṇṭa koppara<hi rend="grantha">kesari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>r<unclear>āṉa</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu pattāvatu Uṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>yār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">mahāmeru</hi>viṭaṅkarkkum <unclear>I</unclear>var nampirāṭṭiyārkkum Aṭaitta ciṟutaṉattup<unclear>pa</unclear>ṇimakkaḷ I<unclear>va</unclear>rkaḷukkuttiruvamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunnivantaṅkaḷukku Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>varkku <unclear>y</unclear>āṇṭu pattāvatu varai vaiytta kācil <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>ttiṉiteḻuntaruḷi Irunta <hi rend="grantha">paramasvāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha">mūlabhṛtya</hi>nākiya <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>var pakkal policai<unclear>k</unclear>kukk<unclear>o</unclear>ṇṭa Ūr kallil veṭṭiṉa <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>uṭai<unclear>y</unclear>ār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">mahāmeru</hi>viṭaṅkarkkum Ivar nampirāṭṭiyārkkuñciṟutaṉattuppaṇi<unclear>ma</unclear>kkaḷ Ivarkaḷukkuttiruvamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunnivantaṅkaḷukkuppattā<unclear>va</unclear>tu varai v<unclear>aiy</unclear>tta kācil nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭu Āvūrkkūṟṟattu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">m</hi> na<unclear>ra</unclear>ciṅka<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvve<unclear>di</unclear>maṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yār <unclear>U</unclear>ṭai<unclear>yār</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu pattāva<unclear>tu</unclear> pa<unclear>c</unclear>āṉamutal koṇṭa kācu Irunūṟiṉāl kācu Oṉ<unclear>ṟu</unclear>kku Āṭṭaivaṭṭa<unclear>ṉ</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">rājakesari</hi>y<unclear>o</unclear>ṭokkum Āṭa<unclear>vallāṉe</unclear>ṉṉum marakkālāl mukkuṟuṇi nelluppolicaiyāka<hi rend="grantha">cca<unclear>ndr</unclear>āditya</hi>val<note n="404-3">The letter ṭu of āṭṭāṇṭu appears to have been added subsequently below the line.</note> Āṭṭāṇṭutoṟu<unclear>n</unclear>tañcāvūr
<lb n="3"/>Uṭaiyār perumpaṇṭārantañcai<unclear>vi</unclear>ṭaṅkaṉiley <hi rend="grantha">rājakesari</hi>yoṭokku<unclear>m</unclear> Āṭavallāṉeṉ<unclear>ṉum ma</unclear>rakkālāl <unclear>A</unclear>ḷakkakka<unclear>ṭa</unclear>va nellu Aiympa<unclear>ti</unclear>ṉ kalam [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>*]
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Venkayya1913_01">

<p>In the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who, <hi rend="italic">etc.,</hi><note n="405-1">The historical introduction of this inscription is almost identical with that of No. 10 above.</note> —there was engraved on stone (<hi rend="italic">the name of</hi>) the village which had received on interest from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—the first servant of the supreme lord, who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,—(<hi rend="italic">part</hi>) of the money which the servants of the minor treasure (<hi rend="italic">śiṟudaṉattuppaṇimakkaḷ)</hi><note n="405-2">Another portion of the endowment made by these people was lent out to the assembly of Irumbudal <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Manukulachūḷāmaṇi-chaturvēdimaṅgalam in the same <hi rend="italic">kūṟṟam</hi>; see No. 10, above. The term <hi rend="italic">śiṟudaṉattuppaṇimakkaḷ</hi> may also mean ‘servants (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> officers) of the king when he was young (<hi rend="italic">siṟudaṉam</hi>).’</note> had deposited until the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi> on account of the offerings and other expenses required for these, (<hi rend="italic">viz.) (the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahāmēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi> set up by the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">that of</hi>) his consort— to both of whom (<hi rend="italic">they i.e.</hi> the servants of the minor treasure) had been attached.</p>

<p>2. The members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅga-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Āvūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have received from the beginning of (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉam</hi> in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, two hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> out of the money which the servants of the minor treasure had deposited, until the tenth (<hi rend="italic">year</hi>), on account of the offerings and other expenses required for these, (<hi rend="italic">viz.) (the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahāmēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi> set up by the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">that of</hi>) his consort. For (<hi rend="italic">these two hundred kāśu, the former</hi>) have to measure every year, as long as the moon and the sun endure, fifty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy into <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viḍaṅgaṉ</hi>, the big treasury of the lord at <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi>, by the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>, which is equal to a <hi rend="italic">rājakēsari</hi>—the rate of interest being three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu (measured</hi>) by the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>, which is equal to a <hi rend="italic">rājakēsari</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.83 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Venkayya1913_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Venkayya1913_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">404-405</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">83</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
