<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.17: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 17. ON THE SOUTH WALL, FIRST TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0017</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the same year as No. 10 and records an endowment to the same image as Nos. 14 to 16.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="6"/><note n="102-2">Continued from the end of the text of No. 16.</note> tiru maṉṉi vaḷara Irunilamaṭantaiyum poṟcayapapāvaiyuñcāttaṉiccelviyuntaṉ perunteviyarākiyiṉpuṟa neṭutiyalūḻiyuḷiṭatuṟaināṭuntuṭarvaṉavelippaṭar vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻmatiḷ koḷḷippākkaiyum naṇṇaṟkarumaraṇ maṇṇaikkaṭakkamum porutaṭarīḻattaraicar tam muṭiyum Āṅkavar <supplied reason="omitted">teviyaroṅkeḻil mu</supplied>
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ṭiyum muṉṉava<unclear>r</unclear> pakkal <unclear>t</unclear>eṉṉa<unclear>var</unclear> vaitta cuntaramuṭiyum Intiraṉāramunteṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟipaṭaikkeraḷar muṟaimaiyiṟcūṭuṅkulataṉa- mākiya palar pukaḻ muṭiyuñc<unclear>e</unclear>ṅkatir mālaiyuñcaṅka<unclear>tir</unclear>velaittolperuṅkāval palapaḻan<unclear>tīvu</unclear>ñceruvil <unclear>ciṉaviyirupat</unclear>t<unclear>o</unclear>rukāl Araicukaḷai kaṭṭa paracurāmaṉ mevaruñcāntimattīyvara<unclear>ṇ karutiyiruttiya cempoṟṟiruttaku muṭiyum paya</unclear>ṅkoṭu paḻi mika mucaṅkiyil mutukiṭṭoḷitta cayaciṅkaṉ Aḷapparum pu<unclear>kaḻoṭu pīṭiyal Iraṭṭapāṭiyeḻa</unclear>rai Ilakkamum navanetikkulapperumalaikaḷum māpporutaṇṭāl koṇṭa kopparake<hi rend="grantha">sari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>rāṉa Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi><unclear>var</unclear>kku yāṇṭu pattāvatu Arumoḻi- <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vavaḷanāṭṭu Iṭaiyaḷanāṭṭu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>yam Aṟiñcikai<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sabhai</hi>yoṅkaiyeḻuttu <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied></hi> Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇameruviṭaṅkarkkuttiruvāy moḻintaruḷiyaṭaitta niyāyañciṟutaṉattu valaṅkaiveḷaikkāṟappaṭaikaḷilār Ivarkku veṇṭuvaṉavaṟṟukku vaitta kācil <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarāja</hi><note n="103-1">Read <hi rend="grantha">jī</hi>.</note> <hi rend="grantha">śvara</hi>ttiṉiteḻuntaruḷi Irunta <hi rend="grantha">paramasvāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha">mūlabhṛtya</hi>ṉākiya <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>var pakkal yāṇṭu pattāvatu pacāṉ mutal koṇṭa <unclear>kācu</unclear> Eṇṇūṟiṉāl kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vīṭṭaṉ polic[ Ai kācu Araikkālāka <hi rend="grantha">candrādi*</hi>]
<lb n="8" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">tya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">t</hi> Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">bhaṇḍā</hi>rattu <unclear>Iṭakka</unclear>ṭava policai kācu nūṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. In the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who, <hi rend="italic">etc.,<note n="103-2">The historical part of this inscription is identical with that of No. 10.</note> (the following</hi>) written agreement (<hi rend="italic">kaiyeṛuttu) (was entered into</hi>) by us, the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Aṟiñjigai-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Iḍaiyaḷa-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Arumoṛidēva-vaḷanāḍu</hi>.</p>

<p>2. (<hi rend="italic">We</hi>) have received after (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>) from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—who is the first servant of the supreme lord, who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,—eight hundred <hi rend="italic">[kāśu]</hi> out of the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Niyāyam Śiṟudaṉattu Valaṅgai-vēḷaikkāṟapaḍaigaḷilār</hi>,—who had been attached by order of the king to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, which had been set up by the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>,—had deposited for the requirements of this (<hi rend="italic">image</hi>). For (<hi rend="italic">these eight hundred kāśu), (we</hi>) have [to pay] every year, as long as [the moon and] the sun endure, an interest of one hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> into the treasury of the lord,—[the rate of] interest [being one eighth <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>] per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.17 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">102-103</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">17</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
