<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.9: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 9. ON THE SOUTH WALL, FIRST TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0009</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>The following eleven inscriptions (Nos. 9 to 19) are engraved continuously in two large sections, the first of which consists of seven, and the second of ten lines.</p>						

						<p>No. 9 is dated in the 6th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, and fixes the interest to be paid to the temple by certain villagers for a sum of money, which had been contributed by several donors and by the temple treasury. The interest was to be used for the chief idol of the temple (paragraph 2) and for the images of <hi rend="bold">Krātārju[nī]yadēvar</hi><note n="90-5">This image is called <hi rend="bold">Krātārjunadēvar</hi> in No. 10. The two names are no doubt corruptions of <hi rend="bold">Kirātārjuna-</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kirātārjunīya-dēva</hi>.</note> and of <hi rend="bold">Pichchadēvar</hi><note n="90-6">The Sanskrit original of this word may be <de>picchadeva</de> or <de>bhikṣādeva</de>.</note> (paragraphs 3 and 4). The first of the two latter had been set up by a minister, who is also mentioned in the large Leyden grant, and the second by <hi rend="bold">Lōkamahādēvī</hi>, a queen of <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">First section</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrīḥ</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tiru manni vaḷaravirunilamaṭantaiyum porccayappāvaiyuñcīrttaniccel<supplied reason="omitted">vi</supplied>yuntan perun<unclear>teviya</unclear>rākiyiṉpuṟa neṭutiyalūḻiyuḷiṭaitu<unclear>ṟai</unclear>nāṭuntoṭarvaṉavelippaṭar vaṉa<unclear>vā</unclear>ciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻmatiṭkoḷḷippākk<unclear>aiyum na</unclear>- ṇṇaṟkarumuraṇ maṇṇaikkaṭakamu<unclear>m po</unclear>rutaṭa<unclear>rī</unclear>ḻattaraicar tamuṭiyu<unclear>mā</unclear>ṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>va<unclear>r</unclear> teviyaroṅkeḻil muṭiyumunnavar pakkal tennavar<note n="91-1">Nos. 15 and 16 read teṉṉavaṉ.</note> vaitta cuntaramuṭiyum Intiraṉāramum teṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟipaṭaikkeraḷar<note n="91-2">No. 20 reads keraḷaṉ.</note> muṟaimaiyiṟcūṭuṅkulatanamākiya palar pukaḻ <unclear>muṭiyu</unclear>ñceṅkatir mālaiyuñcaṅkatirvelaitt<unclear>olperuṅkā</unclear>val palapaḻantīvumāpporutaṇṭāṟk<unclear>oṇ</unclear>ṭa koppara<hi rend="grantha">kesari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>rāṉa Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrāj<unclear>endrac</unclear>oḷade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu Āṟāva<unclear>tu</unclear> kurukkaḷ Ī<hi rend="grantha">śā</hi>na<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>śi</unclear>vapaṇḍi</hi>ta<hi rend="grantha">r</hi> policaiyūṭṭukku yāṇṭu Āṟāvatu varai vaitta kācum Atikārikaḷ kāñcivāyiluṭaiyār Utaiyativāka<unclear>ra</unclear>ṉ tillai<unclear>yāḷi</unclear>yārāṉa <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>rā</unclear>jarāja</hi>mūventaveḷār policaiyūṭṭukku yāṇṭu Ā<unclear>ṟāva</unclear>tu <unclear>varai vait</unclear>ta kācum va<unclear>laṅ</unclear>k<unclear>aippaḻampa</unclear>
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ṭaikaḷilār policaiyūṭṭukku yāṇṭu Āṟāvatu varai vait<unclear>ta</unclear> kācum paṇṭārattuppolic<unclear>aiyūṭṭukku y</unclear>āṇṭu Āṟāvatu varai kuṭutta kācum Ikkācu policaiyūṭṭukku koṇṭa Ūruṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>llil veṭṭiṉa <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied></hi> kuru<unclear>kka</unclear>ḷ Ī<hi rend="grantha">śā</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">śi</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">paṇḍi</hi>ta[ <hi rend="grantha">r</hi> Uṭ] Aiyārkku mūṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sandhi</hi>yum Amutu cey<unclear>yu</unclear>m potu Amutu ceyvikka Oru<hi rend="grantha">sandhi</hi>kku kaṟpūramañcāṭiyāka Orunāḷaikku kaṟpūra<unclear>mū</unclear>ṉṟu mañcāṭiyāka Orāṭṭaikku kaṟpūram Aimpattu nāṟkaḻañcum periyatiru<hi rend="grantha">utsa</hi>vattirunāḷ Oṉpatinukkuppaṭi mel Eṟṟam nicatam kaṟpūram kālāka kaṟpūram I<unclear>rukaḻañc</unclear>e<unclear>y k</unclear>ālum Āka kaṟpūram Aimpattaṟukaḻa<unclear>ñc</unclear>e <unclear>kālukkuk</unclear>kācu Oṉṟukku kaṟpūram Irukaḻañcaraiyāka <unclear>kā</unclear>cu <unclear>Irupa</unclear>ttiraṇṭaraikkukkācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭ<unclear>ṭaṉ A</unclear>raikkāṟkācu policaiyāka vai<unclear>tta</unclear> kācu nūṟṟeṇpa<unclear>tu</unclear>m <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi> Atikārikaḷ kāñcivāyiluṭaiyār Utaiyativākaraṉ tillaiyāḷiyārāṉa <hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>mūventaveḷār tām Eḻuntaruḷuvit[ ta <hi rend="grantha">kr</hi>] Ātā<hi rend="grantha">rjju <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> <unclear>ya</unclear></hi><note n="91-3">Read <hi rend="grantha">krā</hi>tā<hi rend="grantha">rju</hi>nīya.</note> <hi rend="grantha">d<unclear>e</unclear></hi>varkkuttiruamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭuvaṉavaṟṟu<unclear>k</unclear>ku vaitta kācu pa<unclear>tin</unclear> mūṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">[<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>] <supplied reason="omitted">3</supplied></hi> <unclear>Uṭai</unclear>yār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājar<unclear>āja</unclear>de</hi>var na<unclear>mpirāṭṭi</unclear>
<lb n="3" break="no"/>yār Oloka<hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>viy<unclear>ā</unclear>r Eḻuntaruḷuvitta picca<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkku Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var tiruvāy mo<unclear>ḻintaruḷi</unclear> Aṭaitta valaṅkaippaḻampaṭaikaḷil<unclear>ār</unclear> Ivarkkutti<unclear>ru</unclear>amutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭuva<unclear>ṉa</unclear>vaṟṟukku vaitta kācil kācu Irunūṟṟaimpattu <unclear>Iraṇ</unclear>ṭum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrībhaṇḍā</hi>rattukkācu Eṇṇū<unclear>ṟṟai</unclear>ñcum Ākakkācu Āyirattirunūṟ<unclear>ṟ</unclear>aimpatu <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">4</supplied></hi> Ikkācil <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>ttiniteḻuntaruḷi Irunta <hi rend="grantha">paramasvāmi</hi>kku <hi rend="grantha">mū</hi>la<hi rend="grantha">bhṛtya</hi>nākiya <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>var pakkal Arumoḻi<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vavaḷanāṭṭu neṉmalināṭṭu neṭumaṇalākiya matanamañcari<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedimaṅgala<unclear>ttu sabhai</unclear></hi>y<unclear>ā</unclear>r yāṇṭu Āṟāvatu pacān mutal koṇ<unclear>ṭa</unclear> kā<unclear>cu Āyiratt</unclear>eḻupatināl kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭa<unclear>ṉ</unclear> muk<unclear>ku</unclear>ṟuṇi neṟpolicaiyāka <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>ca</unclear>ndrāditya</hi>val Āṭṭā<unclear>ṇṭu to</unclear>ṟuntañcāvūr Uṭaiyār peru<unclear>m pa</unclear>ṇṭāratte<unclear>y</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">rājakesari</hi>yoṭokkum Āṭavallāṉeṉṉum marakkālāl Aḷakkakkaṭava nellu Irunūṟṟaṟupa(pa)tteḻukalaṉe tūṇippatakku <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">5</supplied></hi> Ivarkaḷe kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ Araikkāṟkācu palicaiyāka yāṇṭu Āṟāvatu pacāṉ mutal ko<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭa
<lb n="4"/>kācu nūṟṟeṇpatiṉāl <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>val Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟunta<unclear>ñc</unclear>āvūr Uṭaiyār paṇṭārattu vaikkak<unclear>kaṭava</unclear> kācu Irupattu Iraṇṭarai <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">6</supplied></hi> 
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. Hail ! Prosperity ! In the sixth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who,—in (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) life of high prosperity,<note n="92-1"><ta>neṭutiyal</ta> stands perhaps for <ta>neṭu+utiyal</ta>.</note> (<hi rend="italic">during which he</hi>) rejoiced that, while Fortune, having become constant, was increasing, the goddess of the great earth, the goddess of victory in battle, and the matchless goddess of fame had become his great queens,—<note n="92-2">The same four goddesses, who are here represented by the poet as the wives of the king, are enumerated in inverse order at the commencement of the inscriptions of Kō-Rājakēsarivarman, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva, under the names of Pugar-mādu (the goddess of fame), Jaya-mādu (the goddess of victory), Nila-magaḷ (the goddess of the earth) and Malar-magaḷ (the goddess with the (<hi rend="italic">lotus</hi>) flower, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Lakshmi).</note> conquered with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) great and warlike army <hi rend="bold">Iḍaituṟai-nāḍu; Vaṉavāśi</hi>, whose warriors (<hi rend="italic">were protected by</hi>) walls of continuous forests; <hi rend="bold">Kollippākkai</hi>, whose walls were surrounded by <hi rend="italic">śuḷḷi (trees</hi>); <hi rend="bold">Maṇṇaikkaḍagam</hi><note n="92-3">Nos. 10 to 20 read Maṇṇaikkaḍakkam.</note> of unapproachable strength; the crown of the king of <hi rend="bold">Īṛam</hi>, who came to close quarters in fighting;<note n="92-4"><ta>porutaṭar</ta> stands for <ta>porutu+aṭar</ta>.</note> the exceedingly beautiful crown of the queen of the king of that (<hi rend="italic">country</hi>); the crown of <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi> and the pearl-necklace of <hi rend="bold">Indra</hi>, which the king of the South (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the Pāṇḍya) had previously given up to that (<hi rend="italic">king of</hi> Īṛam); the whole <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi> on the transparent sea; the crown praised by many and the garland of the sun, family-treasures, which the arrow-shooting<note n="92-5">The Chēra king had the device of a bow (<hi rend="italic">vil</hi>) on his banner and was therefore called Villavaṉ, ‘the bearer of the bow.’</note> (<hi rend="italic">king of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷa</hi> rightfully wore; and many ancient islands, whose old and great guard was the sea, which resounds with conches;—there was engraved on stone the money (<hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>), which the <hi rend="italic">guru</hi> <hi rend="bold">Īśānaśiva-paṇḍita</hi> had deposited until the sixth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>), to be put out to interest; the money, which the minister (<hi rend="italic">adhikārin</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Udayadivākaraṉ Tillaiyāḷiyār</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Mūvēnda-Vēḷār</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchivāyil</hi>,<note n="92-6">The same person is mentioned in lines 96 ff. of the large Leyden grant.</note> had deposited until the sixth year, to be put out to interest; the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Valaṅgai-paṛambaḍaigaḷilār</hi><note n="92-7">This term, the real application of which is not apparent, means literally: ‘those belonging to the old troops of the right hand.’ Similar terms occur in the following inscriptions.</note> had deposited until the sixth year, to be put out to interest; the money, which had been given out of the (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) treasury until the sixth year, to be put out to interest; and the village, which had received this money on interest.</p>

<p>2. The <hi rend="italic">guru</hi> <hi rend="bold">Īśānaśiva-paṇḍita</hi> deposited one hundred and eighty <hi rend="italic">kāśu, (to be put out</hi>) at an interest of one eighth <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, so as to realize twenty-two and a half <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>) for (<hi rend="italic">purchasing</hi>),—at the rate of two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half of camphor (<hi rend="italic">karpūra</hi>) for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>,—fifty-six <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and [a quarter] of camphor, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, (1) (<hi rend="italic">one) mañjāḍi</hi> of camphor for feeding the god, when he takes his food (<hi rend="italic">amudu</hi>), at each of the three times (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>), altogether three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of camphor per day, or fifty-four <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> of camphor per year, and (2) a quarter (<hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>) of camphor in excess (<hi rend="italic">ēṟṟam</hi>) of the daily rate (<hi rend="italic">paḍi</hi>) on each of the nine sacred days of the great sacred festival (<hi rend="italic">utsava</hi>), altogether two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a quarter of camphor.</p>

<p>3. The minister <hi rend="bold">Udayadivākaraṉ Tillaiyāḷiyār</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Mūvēnda-Vēḷār</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchivāyil</hi>, deposited thirteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> for the sacred food and other requirements (<hi rend="italic">of the image</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Krātārju[nī]yadēvar</hi>, which he had set up himself.</p>

<p>4. (<hi rend="italic">Adding to these amounts</hi><note n="93-1"><hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, 180 <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> (paragraph 2) and 13 <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> (paragraph 3).</note> ) eight hundred and five <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> out of the sacred treasury (<hi rend="italic">śrī-bhaṇḍāra</hi>) of the lord, and two hundred and fifty-two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> out of the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Valaṅgai-paṛambaḍaigaḷilār</hi>,—who had been attached by order of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi> to (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pichchadēvar</hi>, which had been set up by <hi rend="bold">Lōkamahādēvī</hi>, the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>,—had deposited for the sacred food and other requirements of this (<hi rend="italic">image</hi>),—the total is one thousand two hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>5. Out of this money, the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Neḍumaṇal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Madanamañjari-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, in <hi rend="bold">Neṉmali-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Arumoṛidēvavaḷanāḍu</hi>, have received after (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi><note n="93-2">See page 74, note 1.</note> in the sixth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>) from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—who is the first servant of the supreme lord, who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,—one thousand and seventy <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>. For (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) they have to measure every year, as long as the moon and the sun endure, two hundred and sixty-seven <hi rend="italic">kalam, (one) tūṇi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) padakku</hi> of paddy into the large treasury of the lord (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>, which is equal to a <hi rend="italic">rājakēsari</hi>,—the rate of interest being three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuni</hi> of paddy per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>6. The same (<hi rend="italic">villagers</hi>) have to pay every year, as long as the moon and the sun endure, into the treasury of the lord (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> twenty-two and a half <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>) for (<hi rend="italic">the remaining</hi>) one hundred and eighty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>, which they have received after (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the sixth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>),—the rate of interest being one eighth <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>) per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.9 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">90-93</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">9</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
