<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 2.75: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">No. 75. ON A PILLAR AT UYYAKKONDAN-TIRUMALAI.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0075</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>This short inscription is engraved on a pillar in the south-east corner of the veranda which surrounds the shrine of the <hi rend="bold">Ujjīvanātha</hi> temple at <hi rend="bold">Uyyakkoṇḍāṉ-Tirumalai</hi>, a village 3 miles west of Trichinopoly. It records the gift of a perpetual lamp in the 34th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Madirai-koṇḍa Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, of the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I.<note>See p. 365, note 5.</note> The donor was <hi rend="bold">Pirāntakaṉ-Mādēvaḍigaḷār</hi>, a queen of <hi rend="bold">Pirāntakaṉ-Kaṇḍarādittadēvar</hi>. The only king with a similar name, of whom we know, is <hi rend="bold">Gaṇḍarādityavarman</hi>, the second son of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I.<note>See lines 38, 48 and 60 of the large Leyden grant.</note> As the inscription belongs to the time of Parāntaka I. himself, and as it prefixes the word <hi rend="italic">Pirāntakaṉ</hi> to the name of Kaṇḍarādittadēvar,<note>Compare <hi rend="italic">Parāntakaṉ-Kundavaiyār, i.e.</hi>, ‘Kundavai, (the daughter of) Parāntaka (II.),’ in No. 6, p. 68.</note> it is evident that Gaṇḍarādityavarman, the son of Parāntaka I., is actually meant here. The name Parāntaka also forms the first member of the name of the queen of Kaṇḍarādittadēvar; Pirāntakaṉ-Mādēv-aḍigaḷār probably means ‘the devotee (of the temple) of Mahādēva, (founded by) Parāntaka (I.).’</p>						
                            
                            <p>The hitberto published inscriptions of Parāntaka I. are dated in the 13th,<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 280 f.</note> 15th,<note>Vol. I, Nos. 82 and 83, and Vol. II, No. 76.</note> 24th<note><hi rend="italic">Madras Christian College Magazine</hi>, Vol. VIII, p. 104 ff.</note> and 26th<note><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>., Vol. III, p. 147, and the endorsement of No. 74 above.</note> years of his reign. The latest sure date hitherto found is the 40th year in an inscription of the Pañchanadēśvara temple at Tiruvaiyāṟu.<note>No. 232 of 1894 in my <hi rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> for 1894-95.</note> </p>						
                            
                            <p>The large Leyden grant (l. 48 ff.) states that Gaṇḍarādityavarman, the second son of Parāntaka I., “founded, for the sake (of bliss) in another (world), a large village, (called) by his own name, in the country on the northern bank of Kavēra's daughter (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Kāvērī</hi> river).” This village appears to be identical with <hi rend="bold">Gaṇḍarāditya-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, which is mentioned in several Tanjore inscriptions<note>No. 6, paragraph 14; No. 69, 78; and No. 70, 65.</note> as belonging to a district on the northern bank (of the Kāvērī), and with the modern <hi rend="bold">Kaṇḍarādityam</hi> in the Uḍaiyārpāḷaiyam tālluqa.<note>See Vol. I, p. 112, note 6.</note> The fifth of the nine Śaiva hymns known as <hi rend="italic">Tiruviśaippā</hi> was composed by <hi rend="bold">Kaṇḍarādittaṉ</hi>, who calls himself ‘king of the people of <hi rend="bold">Tañjai</hi>,’ <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Tanjore, and must be accordingly identified with the Chōḷa king Gaṇḍarādityavarman.<note>See Mr. P. Sundaram Pillai's valuable article on the Age of Tiruñāṉaśambandar in the <hi rend="italic">Madras Christian College Magazine</hi>, Vol. IX, pp. 344 and 511; and <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. III, p. 280 f.</note> The carpenter <hi rend="bold">Kaṇḍarāditta-Perundachchaṉ</hi> in No. 66, paragraph 505, is apparently named after Gaṇḍarādityavarman, the grand-uncle of the then reigning king Rājarājadēva.</p>						
                            
                            <p>According to the subjoined inscription, the ancient name of Uyyakkoṇḍāṉ-Tirumalai was <hi rend="bold">Nandipanmamaṅgalam</hi>, which suggests that the place may have been founded by one of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> kings named <hi rend="bold">Nandivarman</hi>. The temple was called <hi rend="bold">Tirukkaṟkuḍi-Paramēśvara</hi>. This enables us to identify it with <hi rend="bold">Kaṟkuḍi</hi>, a shrine which is referred to in the <hi rend="italic">Periyapurāṇam</hi> as situated in the Chōḷa country to the south of the Kāvērī river.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-07-17" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-06-24" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/>matirai koṇṭa koppara
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>kecari<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>pa</unclear>nma</hi>rkku yāṇṭu mu
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/><unclear>p</unclear>pattunālāvatu ten
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>karai <hi rend="grantha">bra<unclear>hma</unclear></hi>teyam nan=tipa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>ma
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>ṅkalattu tirukkaṟkkuṭi<hi rend="grantha">para</hi>
                    <lb n="6" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">mesvara</hi>ṟkku pirāntakan kaṇ
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>ṭarātittatevar teviyār
                    <lb n="8"/>maḻaperumāḷ makaḷār pirā
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>ntakaṉmātevaṭikaḷār
                    <lb n="10"/>Orutirunontāviḷakku I
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>ravum pakalum Erivatāka nica
                    <lb n="12" break="no"/>tam cūlauḻakkāl Uḻakku
                    <lb n="13"/>neyaṭṭi cantirātittava
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>l Erip<unclear>pa</unclear>tāka vaitta cāvā
                    <lb n="15"/>m<choice><sic>u</sic><corr>ū</corr></choice>vāpperāṭu toṇṇū
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>ṟu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>panm</unclear>āheśvara<supplied reason="omitted">ra</supplied>kṣai</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1895_01">
                
                <p>In the thirty-fourth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Madirai-koṇḍa Kō-Parakēsarivarman,— Pirāntakaṉ-Mādēvaḍigaḷār</hi>, the daughter of <hi rend="bold">Maṛa-Perumāḷ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) queen of <hi rend="bold">Pirāntakaṉ-Kaṇḍarādittadēvar</hi>, gave ninety full-grown ewes, which must neither die nor grow old,<note><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, which have to be replaced by fresh ones when they die or grow old; <hi rend="italic">see</hi> Vol. I, p. 114, note 1.</note> to (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tirukkaṟkuḍi-Paramēśvara</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Nandipanmamaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> on the southern bank (<hi rend="italic">of the</hi> Kāvērī <hi rend="italic">river</hi>), for supplying, every day as long as the moon and the sun endure, (<hi rend="italic">one) uṛakku</hi> of ghee (<hi rend="italic">measured</hi>) by the <hi rend="italic">uṛakku (stamped with</hi>) a trident,<note><hi rend="italic">Śūla</hi> is used for <hi rend="italic">triśūla</hi>.</note> in order to feed one sacred perpetual lamp which shall burn day and night. (<hi rend="italic">This charity is placed under</hi>) the protection of all <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvaras</hi>.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 2.75 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1895_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1895_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">374-375</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">75</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
