<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.68: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 68. ON THE OUTSIDE OF THE NORTH ENCLOSURE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0068</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 4th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷadēva</hi>, and records that the king assigned an allowance to a person who measured the paddy in the <hi rend="bold">Rājarājēśvara</hi> temple and in the villages belonging to it. This man was evidently a controlling officer who had to check the supplies of paddy, which, according to many of the inscriptions published in this volume, had to be delivered into the temple stores.</p>						

						<p>The order of the king is preceded by a poetical account of his deeds. Though this passage is, on the whole, of a purely panegyrical character, it contains a few statements which appear to be based on historical facts. While still a youth,—probably only heirapparent,—Vikrama-Chōḷa is said to have put to flight the <hi rend="bold">Teliṅga Bhīma</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kuḷam</hi>, to have burnt the <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi> country, and to have stayed in the <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgai-maṇḍalam</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgī</hi> country. In my <hi rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> for 1893-94, page 6, I have noticed some inscriptions of the chiefs of <hi rend="bold">Kamalākarapura</hi> or (in Telugu) <hi rend="bold">Kolanu</hi>, which is probably the modern <hi rend="bold">Ellore</hi><note n="308-1">The identity of Kolanu with Ellore is suggested by seven inscriptions of Kēśava and Sōmaya of Kolanu on a pillar in the <hi rend="italic">māsjid</hi> at Ellore (Nos. 527 to 533 of 1893). These inscriptions record gifts of lamps to the Sōmēśvara temple at Kolanu, of which no other trace remains and which appears to have been destroyed by the Musalmāns.</note> on the bank of the Kolleru lake in the Gōdāvarī district. The earliest known member of this family is <hi rend="bold">Kāṭama-Nāyaka</hi>, who is mentioned in two inscriptions of Śaka 1062 and 1070 at <hi rend="bold">Drākshārāma</hi> (Nos. 204 and 347 of 1893). The same chief is the donor of a copper-plate grant of Śaka 1056, which has been published by Dr. Fleet.<note n="308-2"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XIV, p. 55.</note> He is there stated to have been the lord of <hi rend="bold">Sarasīpurī</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Kolanu</hi><note n="308-3">In Kolani-Kāṭama-Nāyaka (<hi rend="italic">l.c.), kolani</hi> is the Telugu genitive of <hi rend="italic">kolanu</hi>; see Arden's <hi rend="italic">Telugu Grammar</hi>, Madras, 1873, paragraph 659.</note> on the bank of a great lake (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Kolleru</hi> lake) in the <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgī-maṇḍala</hi> and to have been a vassal of <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga</hi> II. As the Tañjāvūr inscription of Vikrama-Chōḷa connects the Vēṅgai-maṇḍalam with <hi rend="bold">Kuḷam</hi>, whose lord <hi rend="bold">Bhīma</hi> was put to flight by the king, and as the Tamil word <hi rend="italic">kuḷam</hi>, ‘a tank,’ is etymologically identical with the Telugu <hi rend="italic">kolanu</hi>, ‘a lake,’ it may be safely concluded that the Teliṅga Bhīma of the Tañjāvūr inscription belonged to the same dynasty as Kāṭama-Nāyaka of Kolanu.</p>						

						<p>After his stay in the Vēṅgai-maṇḍalam, the subjoined inscription informs us, Vikrama-Chōḷa went to the South and claimed the crown of the country on the banks of the <hi rend="bold">Kāvērī</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> country. The passage which conveys this information, is also met with in the inscriptions of <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga</hi> I.<note n="308-4">The words <ta>vaṭa ticai vākai cūṭitteṉṟicaittemarukamalappūmakaḷ potumaiyum poṉṉiyāṭai naṉṉilappāvaiyiṉ taṉimaiyuntavirttu puṉitattirumaṇimakuṭamuṟaimaiyiṟcūṭi</ta> (line 1 f.) are almost identical with lines 4 to 9 of No. 58.</note> As none of the predecessors of Kulōttuṅga I. bore the name Vikrama-Chōḷa, it is clear that the passage in question was taken over by the composer of Vikrama-Chōḷa's inscriptions from those of Kulōttuṅga I., and that, in trying to identify the Vikrama-Chōḷa of the present inscription, we must look for him among the successors of Kulōttuṅga I. The only Vikrama-Chōḷa who is known from other sources but the subjoined inscription, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, from a copper-plate grant<note n="308-5"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XIV, p. 55.</note> and from a Tamil chronicle,<note n="308-6"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Vol. XXII, p. 142, note 8.</note> was the immediate successor of Kulōttuṅga I. I have no hesitation in identifying this <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷa</hi>, who reigned from Śaka 1034 to 1049,<note n="308-7"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, Vol. I. p. 32, and <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XX, p. 282.</note> with the king of the same name to whose reign the Tañjāvūr inscription belongs. A confirmation of the identity of both may be derived from verse 24 of the third inscription<note n="308-8">No. 492 of 1893 in my <hi rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> for 1893-94.</note> on the <hi rend="bold">Piṭhāpuram</hi> pillar:—</p>						

						<l n="2:308:68:0"><de>tasmiṁstyāgasamudrāparanāmani coḍamaṁḍalaṁ trātuṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied></de></l>						

						<l n="2:308:68:0"><de>gatavati vegībhūmirnāyakarahitā tadaṁtare jātā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></de></l>						

						<p>“When he (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḍa</hi>), whose other name was <hi rend="bold">Tyāgasamudra</hi>, had gone to protect the <hi rend="bold">Chōḍa-maṇḍala</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgī</hi> country became devoid of a ruler in that interval.”</p>						

						<p>Here we have an independent variant of the statement, made in the Tañjāvūr inscription, that Vikrama-Chōḷa originally resided in <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgī</hi> and that he left it to ascend the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> throne. Another point of agreement is still more decisive: Mr. Venkayya informs me that, in his copy of the Tanjore MS. of the <hi rend="italic">Vikkirama-Śōṛaṉ-Ulā</hi>, the surname <hi rend="bold">Tyāgasamudra</hi> is twice applied to <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷa</hi>.<note n="309-1">Those portions of the poem, in which the surname Tyāgasamudra occurs, are not included in the extracts published by Mr. Kanakasabhai.</note> </p>						

						<p>Finally the Tañjāvūr inscription acquaints us with the names of two queens, <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiṛānaḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Tyāgapatākā</hi>. The former, whom the poet compares to the goddess Pārvatī, was evidently Vikrama-Chōḷa's chief queen, and the second, who is compared to Gaṅgā, his favourite.</p>						

						<p>The text of the historical introduction has been compared with that of two similar inscriptions of <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷa</hi>, one of the 5th year of his reign in the Tyāgarāja temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruvārūr</hi> in the Negapatam tālluqa (No. 164 of 1894) and another of the 11th year in the Āpatsahāyēśvara temple<note n="309-2">In its inscriptions and in the <hi rend="italic">Periyapurāṇam</hi>, this temple is called Irumbūḷai, a name which is even now remembered at Ālaṅguḍi.</note> at <hi rend="bold">Ālaṅguḍi</hi> in the Kumbhakōṇam tālluqa (No. 165 of 1894). Other inscriptions of <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷa</hi> open with a much shorter historical introduction, the first words of which are <ta>pūmātu puṇara</ta>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, one of the 9th year in the Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruvattiyūr</hi> or Little Conjeeveram (No. 33 of 1893), one of the same year and one of the 14th year at <hi rend="bold">Pallāvaram</hi> in the Chingleput tālluqa. These inscriptions mention the burning, or conquest, of the <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi> country<note n="309-3">One of the Pallāvaram inscriptions reads <ta>kaliṅkameriya</ta>, while the other Pallāvaram one and the Tiruvattiyūr one read <ta>kaliṅkamiriya</ta>.</note> and the name of one of Vikrama-Chōḷa's queens, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiṛānaḍi</hi>, and must, accordingly, belong to the time of the same king as the other set, the introductions of which open with the words <ta>pūmālai miṭaintu </ta>.</p>						

						<p>Thanks to the calculations of Mr. S.B.Dikshit and Professor Kielhorn, I am able to state the probable day of the accession of <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷa</hi>. The third line of the <hi rend="bold">Tiruvārūr</hi> inscription to which reference was made in the preceding paragraph, contains the following date:—</p>						

						<p> <ta>koppara</ta><hi rend="grantha">k[e]sari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmmarā</hi>na<hi rend="grantha"> tribhu</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">[na]cakra</hi>va[ <hi rend="grantha">rtti</hi><ta>ka</ta>] <ta>ḷ</ta> <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vi<hi rend="grantha">kramacoḷa[de]</hi><ta>varkku [y]ā[ṇ]ṭu aiñcā[vatu]</ta> <hi rend="grantha">mi[thu]</hi><ta>nanāyaṟṟu</ta> <hi rend="grantha">pū[r]vvapakṣa</hi><ta>ttu</ta> <hi rend="grantha">saptami</hi>yu<hi rend="grantha">m</hi> <ta>nā[yi]ṟṟukkiḻamaiyum attamumāna nāḷ munnūṟṟunāṟ[pa]ti[n]āl</ta>.</p>						

						<p>“In the fifth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the emperor of the three worlds, <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Vikrama-Chōḷadēva</hi>,—on the three-hundred-and-fortieth day, which was (<hi rend="italic">the day of</hi>) Attam (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi> Hasta), a Sunday, and the seventh <hi rend="italic">tithi</hi> of the first fortnight of the month of Mithuna.”</p>						

						<p>On this date Mr. Dikshit remarks as follows<note n="309-4">See <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>., Vol. XXIII, p. 299.</note> :—“Assuming that Vikrama-Chōḷa began to reign in A.D. 1112, his 5th year would be about A.D. 1116. Having made calculations for 1115, 1116 and 1117, I find that A.D. 1116 is the only year which corresponds with the details of the given date. In that year, Āshāḍha <hi rend="italic">śukla</hi> 7 ended on Sunday, the 18th June, at about 21 hours after sunrise. This was the 25th day of the solar month Mithuna. On this day, at sunrise, the <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi> was Uttara-Phalgunī, which ended at 7 hours 48 minutes after sunrise, when the <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi> Hasta commenced.”</p>						

						<p>In his important paper on ‘dates of Chōḷa kings,’ which will appear in Vol. IV of the <hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi>, Professor Kielhorn adds the following remark:—“If the above were the day of the date, the 1st day of the 5th year of Vikrama-Chōḷa's reign would be the 15th July, A.D. 1115; and the 1st day of the 1st year [<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the day of his accession to the throne] would be Saturday, the 15th July, A.D. 1111.”</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi> pūmālai miṭain<unclear>tu</unclear> poṉmālai <unclear>ni</unclear>kaḻtara<unclear>p</unclear>pāmālai mali<unclear>n</unclear>ta parumaṇi<unclear>t</unclear>tiraḷ puyattirunilamaṭantaiyoṭu <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yama<unclear>ka</unclear>ḷiruppattanṟuṇai<note n="310-1">Read taṉṟuṇai mārpan.</note> mā<unclear>r</unclear>vaṉtaṉatenap<unclear>p</unclear>eṟṟuttirumakaḷḷorutaniyiruppakkalaimakaḷ coṟṟiṟam puṇarnta kaṟpiṉa<unclear>ḷ</unclear>āki viruppoṭu <unclear>nā</unclear>vakattiruppat<unclear>ti</unclear>cai toṟu<unclear>m ti</unclear>kiriyoṭuñceṅkol naṭappa Akilapuvaṉamuṅka<unclear>vi</unclear>ppatoruputumati pol veṇkuṭai <unclear>mī</unclear>micai niṟpakkaruṅkali O<unclear>ḷi</unclear>t<unclear>tu</unclear> vaṉ<unclear>pi</unclear>la<unclear>t</unclear>tiṭaikkiṭappakkuḷatteliṅkavimaṉ<note n="310-2">Read vīmaṉ. Instead of kuḷa two other inscriptions read kuḷattiṭai.</note> vilaṅkal micaiyeṟa<unclear>vu</unclear>ṅkaliṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>pūmiy<unclear>ai</unclear>k<unclear>kaṉai</unclear>yeri <unclear>parukavu</unclear>m Aimpa<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aip<unclear>paruvattu</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> [paṭai<note n="310-3">Read vempaṭai .</note> tāṅki v]eṅk<unclear>ai</unclear>ma<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭa<unclear>la</unclear>ttut<unclear>tā</unclear>ṅkiniti<unclear>ru</unclear>ntu<note n="310-4">Two other inscriptions read correctly maṇṭalattāṅki.</note> vaṭaticai vākai cūṭitten<note n="310-5">Read teṉ.</note> 
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ṟicaitte<unclear>ma</unclear>ruka<unclear>ma</unclear>la<unclear>p</unclear>pūmakaḷ potum<unclear>ai</unclear>yum po<unclear>ṉi</unclear>niyāṭai<unclear>y</unclear><note n="310-6">Read poṉṉiyāṭai.</note> naṉni<unclear>la</unclear>ppāvai<unclear>yu</unclear>n<note n="310-7">Read pāvaiyiṉ.</note> tanimaiyun<unclear>ta</unclear>vuntu<note n="310-8">Read tavirttu. The Tañjāvūr inscription of Kulōttuṅga I. (No. 58, p. 233) reads tavira.</note> <unclear>pu</unclear>nitaṟṟiri<note n="310-9">Read puṉitattiru .</note> ma<unclear>ṇi</unclear>ma<unclear>ku</unclear>ṭamu<unclear>ṟaim</unclear>aiyiṟcū<unclear>ṭi</unclear>t<unclear>taṉ</unclear>naḷi parappittanitta<unclear>ni</unclear> paran<unclear>tu</unclear> maṇ muḻutuṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>ḷippa maṇi ṉāv<unclear>o</unclear>ṭuṅka vicaiyamu<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> pukaḻumel<supplied reason="omitted">me</supplied><unclear>l</unclear>oṅkacceḻiyar ve<unclear>ñ</unclear>curam puka ce<unclear>ra</unclear>lar kaṭal puka <unclear>A</unclear>ḻitaru ciṅka<unclear>ḷa</unclear>ra<unclear>ñ</unclear>ci neñcalamākakkaṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>r tiṟaiyi<unclear>ṭa</unclear>k<unclear>kaṉ</unclear>naṭar<note n="310-10">Read kaṉṉaṭar venniṭa.</note> veṉniṭakk<unclear>o</unclear>ṅkarotuṅkakkoṅkaḷar<note n="310-11">Two other inscriptions read koṅkaṇar.</note> cāya <unclear>ma</unclear>ṟṟet<unclear>ti</unclear>cai<note n="310-12">Read maṉṉarun .</note> <unclear>maṉ</unclear>narun<unclear>tanta</unclear>makkaraṇenattirumalaṟcevaṭi Urimaiyil<note n="310-13">The Ālaṅguḍi inscription reads tirumalarccevaṭiyuri[m*]aiyiliṟ[ai]ñca.</note> ni<unclear>ṟṟa</unclear>ñcattollaiyeḻulakuntoḻuteḻatton<unclear>ṟi</unclear>ya<note n="310-14">Read toṉṟiya.</note> mullaivāṇak<unclear>ai</unclear>y mukkokki<unclear>ḻ</unclear>ānaṭi Umaiyoṭu<unclear>ñ</unclear>ca<unclear>ṅka</unclear>raṉ Im<unclear>ai</unclear>yat<unclear>ti</unclear>runtāne<unclear>ṉa</unclear>pp<unclear>o</unclear>runti Iṉitirup<unclear>pa</unclear> Āṅkava[ṉ<note n="310-15">Read makiḻu.</note> ma]kuḻuṅkaṅkaiyoppākiya terivaiyar tila<unclear>ta</unclear>m tiyākapatā
<lb n="3" break="no"/><unclear>kai pu</unclear>rikuḻal <unclear>ma</unclear>ṭap<unclear>pi</unclear>ṭi <unclear>pu</unclear>ṉitakuṇa<unclear>va</unclear>ṉit<unclear>ai ti</unclear>ri<unclear>pu</unclear>vana<unclear>muḻu</unclear>tuṭ<unclear>aiyā</unclear>ḷivaṉ<note n="310-16">Read tiruvuḷa.</note> <unclear>ti</unclear>ru<unclear>vi</unclear>ḷattaru<unclear>ḷ</unclear> muḻu<unclear>tuṭai</unclear>yāḷeṉa <unclear>A</unclear>m<unclear>ai</unclear>n<unclear>ti</unclear>ṉitiruppacce<unclear>m</unclear>poniṉ<note n="310-17">Read poṉṉiṉ or poṉ.</note> <unclear>vī</unclear>ra <hi rend="grantha">siṁ</hi>h[ā<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>]ṉa<unclear>ttu vī</unclear>ṟṟiru<unclear>ntaruḷiya</unclear> k<unclear>o</unclear>pparakecari<unclear>pa</unclear>ṟ<unclear>ma</unclear>r<unclear>āṉa</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">tri</hi>puvanacca<unclear>kkarava</unclear>ṟ<unclear>tika</unclear>ḷ [<hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vi]<hi rend="grantha">kra</hi>macoḻate<unclear>va</unclear>ṟ<unclear>ki</unclear> y<unclear>āṇ</unclear>ṭu ṉālāva<unclear>tu</unclear> [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied></hi> <unclear>U</unclear>ṭ<unclear>aiyā</unclear>r <hi rend="grantha">śrī<unclear>rā</unclear>ja[rājīśvara</hi>muṭ]ai<unclear>y</unclear>ār ko<unclear>yilil kāra</unclear>ḷak[ kum <hi rend="grantha">rā</hi>] <hi rend="grantha">ja<unclear>rā</unclear>ja</hi><unclear>ppa</unclear>llavaraya<unclear>nuk</unclear>ku ta<unclear>ṉ p</unclear>ā<unclear>ṭṭaṉ nilaiy</unclear>āy <unclear>va</unclear>rukiṟa k<unclear>āṇi kāra</unclear>ḷa<unclear>vuk</unclear>ku <unclear>kāṇiy</unclear>ā<unclear>ka</unclear> ku<unclear>ṭu</unclear>tt<unclear>om</unclear>e- <supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied><unclear>ṟu tiruv</unclear>āy m<unclear>o</unclear>ḻintaru<unclear>ḷi Uṭ</unclear>aiyār <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>śrī</unclear>rājarā<unclear>jī</unclear>śvaram</hi> Uṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>y<unclear>ār k</unclear>oyil cīkā<unclear>ri</unclear>yañceyvānuk<unclear>ku</unclear>m pari<unclear>y</unclear>āra<unclear>mū</unclear>la<unclear>p</unclear>paṭṭu<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ai<unclear>p</unclear>pa<unclear>ñc</unclear>ācā<unclear>riya</unclear>ttevar<unclear>kaṉ</unclear>mikaḷu<unclear>k</unclear>kum <hi rend="grantha">prasā</hi>tam ceytu vanta tiru<unclear>mu</unclear>kappa<unclear>ṭi</unclear> kal<unclear>li</unclear>l v<unclear>eṭṭi</unclear>ya<unclear>tu</unclear> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi> <unclear>muṉ</unclear>pu kāra<unclear>ḷan</unclear>tu va<unclear>ruki</unclear>ṟa putuvuṭ<unclear>aiyā</unclear>ṉ A<unclear>ra</unclear>
<lb n="4" break="no"/><unclear>yaṉ</unclear> U<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aiyāṉ marittam<unclear>aiyil I</unclear>van <unclear>ma</unclear>ka<unclear>ṉā</unclear>na Uṭ<unclear>aiy</unclear>ān <unclear>ka</unclear>l<unclear>lālai</unclear>k<unclear>ku</unclear> ta<unclear>ñc</unclear>ā<unclear>vū</unclear>rtt<unclear>e</unclear>varkku <unclear>Aṭai</unclear>t<unclear>ta</unclear> nāṭṭup<unclear>paṇ</unclear>ṭāraṅ<unclear>kaḷu</unclear>m <unclear>Aḷa</unclear>ntu Itt<unclear>ā</unclear>l va<unclear>ṉta</unclear> kāra<unclear>ḷa</unclear>vu <unclear>m</unclear>ā<unclear>ṭam</unclear> U<unclear>ḷḷi</unclear>tu O<unclear>ṭu</unclear>k<unclear>ki va</unclear>rukiṟa pa<unclear>ri</unclear>cu t<unclear>e</unclear>var <unclear>paṇ</unclear>ṭāratte Oṭuk<unclear>ka kaṭavan</unclear>ā<unclear>kavu</unclear>m <unclear>ta</unclear>ṉakkum <unclear>tan va</unclear>rk<unclear>ka</unclear>ttā<unclear>r</unclear>kkum ca<hi rend="grantha">ntr]ā<unclear>di</unclear></hi>t[ tava <hi rend="grantha">t</hi> c] Ella vaitta paṅku Oṉṟu [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">3</supplied></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1895_01">

<p>1. Hail! Prosperity! (<hi rend="italic">The king</hi>) was resplendent with golden chains, combined with garlands of flowers. In (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) arms, which were covered with large jewels, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) which (<hi rend="italic">formed the subject of</hi>) a great number of poems, rested the goddess of Victory, along with the goddess of the great Earth. Having obtained as her own (<hi rend="italic">possession) (his</hi>) breast, (<hi rend="italic">which was</hi>) her support, the goddess of Prosperity exclusively abided (<hi rend="italic">there</hi>). As a chaste woman that possessed great eloquence, the goddess of Learning resided with delight in (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) tongue. (<hi rend="italic">His</hi>) sceptre, along with the wheel (<hi rend="italic">of his authority</hi>), swayed over all regions. (<hi rend="italic">His</hi>) white parasol was raised on high, like a matchless second moon, overspreading the whole world. The dark Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>) hid itself and lay in the deep pit.</p>

<p>At the time of love<note n="311-1"><ta>aimpaṭai</ta> is synonymous with <ta>aiṅkaṇai</ta>, which is a translation of the Sanskrit <de>pañcabāṇa</de>.</note> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, in his youth), (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) grasped the cruel weapon, so that the <hi rend="bold">Teliṅga</hi> Vīmaṉ (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Bhīma</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kuḷam</hi><note n="311-2">Two other inscriptions read “at Kuḷam.” The manner in which the word <ta>kuḷam</ta> is employed, shows that it cannot be taken in its usual sense, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ‘a tank,’ but must be the proper name of a locality.</note> ascended the mountains (<hi rend="italic">as refuge</hi>), and so that intense fire consumed the country (<hi rend="italic">bhūmi</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) joyfully stayed (<hi rend="italic">awhile</hi>) in the <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgai-maṇḍalam</hi> and put on the garland of (<hi rend="italic">the victory over</hi>) the Northern region.</p>

<p>(<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) stopped the prostitution of the goddess with the sweet and excellent lotus-flower (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Lakshmī) of the Southern region, and the loneliness of the goddess of the good country whose garment is the <hi rend="bold">Poṉṉi</hi> (Kāvērī), and put on by right (<hi rend="italic">of inheritance</hi>) the pure royal crown of jewels.</p>

<p>While (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) diffused his kindness, (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>) spread to every individual. The whole earth rejoiced; the tongue of the bell<note n="311-3"><ta>maṇi</ta> stands for <ta>ārāyccimaṇi</ta>, “a bell attached to a royal palace, rung by those who seek for justice from the king” (Winslow).</note> became silent; (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) victory and fame rose higher and higher.</p>

<p>The Śeṛiyas (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍyas</hi>) entered hot jungles (<hi rend="italic">as refuge</hi>); the Śēralas (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Chēras</hi>) entered the sea; the Śiṅgaḷas (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Siṁhalas</hi>), who deal destruction, became afraid and agitated in mind; the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgas</hi> paid tribute; the <hi rend="bold">Kaṉṉaḍas</hi> turned (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) backs; the <hi rend="bold">Koṅgas</hi> retreated; the <hi rend="bold">Koṅkaṇas</hi> fled; the kings of all other regions duly worshipped (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) red lotus-feet as their protection.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiṛānaḍi</hi>, the jewel among the inhabitants of the forest-country,<note n="311-4"><ta>vāṇakai</ta> stands for <ta>vāḻ+nakai</ta>.</note> who was born to be worshipped by the seven ancient worlds, joyfully dwelt in harmony (<hi rend="italic">with him</hi>), just as Śaṁkara dwells with Umā on the Imaiyam (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Himālaya).</p>

<p>Tiyāgapadāgai (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Tyāgapatākā</hi>), the ornament of women, (<hi rend="italic">who had</hi>) curly hair, (<hi rend="italic">who possessed the gait of</hi>) a female elephant, a lady of pure virtues, the mistress of the whole of the three worlds, joyfully dwelt in harmony (<hi rend="italic">with him</hi>) as mistress of the full favour of his royal heart, resembling Gaṅgā at whom he (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, Śiva) rejoices.</p>

<p>In the fourth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the emperor of the three worlds, <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Vikrama-Śōṛadēva</hi>, who was graciously seated on the throne of heroes (<hi rend="italic">which consisted</hi>) of pure gold.</p>

<p>2. The king having ordered:—“We have given the allowance which was permanently enjoyed by his grandfather, as an allowance for measuring the paddy (<hi rend="italic">kār</hi>),<note n="312-1">See page 117, note 2.</note> to <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Pallavarayaṉ</hi>, who measures the paddy in the temple of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,”— (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) was engraved on stone in accordance with a royal order (<hi rend="italic">to this effect</hi>), which had reached the manager, the • • • • • <hi rend="italic">Pañchāchārya,<note n="312-2">I have omitted in the translation the terms preceding <ta>pañcācāriya</ta>, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>, <ta>pariyāramūlappaṭṭuṭai</ta>, because their meaning is obscure, and because I do not now believe in the correctness of the translation of them which was given on page 112. Instead of <ta>pariyāra</ta>, two other inscriptions read <ta>patipāta;</ta> see page 111, note 3.</note> (and</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">Pūjārīs (dēvar-kaṉmi</hi>) of the temple of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>.</p>

<p>3. Whereas <hi rend="bold">Puduvuḍaiyāṉ A[rayaṉ] Uḍaiyāṉ</hi>,<note n="312-3">This appears to be another name of the person who is styled Rājarāja-Pallavarayaṉ in paragraph 2.</note> who previously used to measure the paddy, is dead, one share was assigned, for as long as the moon and the sun endure, to his son <hi rend="bold">Uḍaiyāṉ K[a]l[lāl]ai</hi> himself and to his family (<hi rend="italic">under the condition that</hi>) he should also measure (<hi rend="italic">the contents of</hi>) the up-country treasuries belonging to the <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> temple, and that he should pay into the temple treasury all fees (?), <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>., which are paid to him (<hi rend="italic">for</hi>) measuring the paddy on these occasions.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.68 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1895_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1895_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">307-312</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">68</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
