<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.8: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 8. ON THE WALLS OF THE PORTICO, SECOND TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0008</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription engraved on the south, east and north walls of a portico, which forms the main entrance on the east of the central shrine. The published text, which consists of three sections of nine lines each, ends in the middle of paragraph 26 with the statement, that the inscription is continued at the bottom of the south wall of the portico. Of this portion no copy could be taken, as the present pavement of the temple court rises to its level.</p>						

						<p>Like the preceding inscription, this one describes a number of ornaments of gold and jewels, which were presented by <hi rend="bold">Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi> until the 3rd year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>. The donees were the images which she had set up herself. Among these, the published part of the inscription mentions the consort of <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi> (paragraph 2) and the consort of <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viṭaṅkar</hi> (paragraphs 8 and 24).</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">A. South wall</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrīḥ</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> koppara<hi rend="grantha">kesari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>rāṉa Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>śrī</unclear>rājendra</hi>coḻa<hi rend="grantha">de-</hi> varkku yāṇṭu mūṉṟāvatu varai Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>śrī</unclear>rājarājade</hi>var <unclear>ti</unclear>ruttamakkaiyār vallavaraiyar va<hi rend="grantha">ndyade</hi>var <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi><unclear>vi</unclear>yār Āḻvār parāntakaṉ kuntavaiyār taram Eḻunta
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ruḷuvitta tirumenikaḷukkukkuṭutta poṉ Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉuṅkuṭiñaikkallāl niṟai Eṭuttum <hi rend="grantha">ratna</hi>ṅkaḷ caraṭuñcaṭṭamuñceppāṇikaḷum Arakkum piñcum nīkki niṟaiyuḷḷaṉa niṟai Eṭuttum Arakkum piñcuṅkūṭa <hi rend="grantha">ratna</hi>ṅkaṭṭi ve
<lb n="3" break="no"/>ṟu niṟaiyaṟiya Uṇṇātaṉa Arakkum piñcum Uṭpaṭa <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkan</hi> Eṉṉuṅkācukallāl niṟai Eṭuttuṅkallil veṭṭiṉa <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied> dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭa<hi rend="grantha">ṅkar</hi> nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yārkkukkuṭuttaṉa <g type="danda">.</g>— <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi> tiruppaṭṭikai <unclear>O</unclear>ṉ
<lb n="4" break="no"/>ṟu poṉ toṇṇūṟṟeḻukaḻañcaraiye nālu mañcāṭiyum Oṉpatu māvuṅkaṭṭiṉa vayiram maṭṭatārai poṟivum muṟivum <hi rend="grantha">raktabindu</hi>vum <hi rend="grantha">kākabindu</hi>vum ventaṉavum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭappariyaṉavum neriyaṉavum Āka A
<lb n="5" break="no"/>ṟunūṟṟu Aṟupatteḻiṉāl niṟai Irukaḻañce kāle Āṟu māvum māṇikkam <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷa</hi>ṅkuṇaviyaṉ Irupattiraṇṭum <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷam</hi> Irupatuṅkomaḷam Irupatum nīlakanti Oṉpatuñcaṭṭam Iraṇṭuntaḷam pattum Ā
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ka māṇikkaṅkuḻivum <hi rend="grantha">prahara</hi>mum ve<hi rend="grantha">jja</hi>mum <hi rend="grantha">laśu</hi>niyun<hi rend="grantha">trāsamu</hi>ṅkaṟpaṟṟum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭappariyaṉavum neriyaṉavum Āka Eṇpattu mūṉṟiṉāl niṟai patiṉ kaḻañce mukkāle mūṉṟu mañcāṭiyum Iraṇṭu māvum
<lb n="7"/>kottaṉavuntaiyttaṉavum Āka muttu vaṭṭamum Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttuṅkuṟumuttum nimpoḷamum Ampumutuṅkuḷirnta nīruñcivanta nīrum Ippippaṟṟu Arāviṉavum varaiyuṅkaṟaiyuṅkuruvuñcuppiramuntiraṅkalum
<lb n="8"/>Uṭpaṭa Irunūṟṟorupattiraṇṭiṉāl niṟai patiṉ Eṇkaḻañce Iraṇṭu mañcāṭiyum Āka niṟai nūṟṟu Irupattoṉpatiṉ kaḻañce Eḻumāvukku vilai kācu nālāyirattu Aiññūṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">3</supplied></hi> tiruvaṭikkāṟai Oṉṟu poṉ Eḻu
<lb n="9" break="no"/>pattu mukkaḻañce mūṉṟu mañcāṭiyum Aṟumāvaraiyuṅkaṭṭiṉa vayiram maṭṭatārai nāṉūṟṟu nāṟpat<unclear>t</unclear>oṉpatum maṭṭatāraiccappaṭi Āṟum Āka vayiram poṟivum muṟivum <hi rend="grantha">raktabindu</hi><unclear>vu</unclear>ṅ<hi rend="grantha">kākabindu</hi>vum ventaṉavum
</p>

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">B. East wall</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/>Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭa Āka nāṉūṟṟu Aimpattaiñciṉāl niṟai kaḻañcaraiye Iraṇṭu mañcāṭiyum Aimmāvaraiyum māṇikkam <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷa</hi>ṅkuṇaviyaṉ pattum <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷam</hi> pattuṅkomaḷam Eṭṭum nīlakanti mūṉṟuntaḷam Eṭṭum Āka māṇikkaṅkuḻivum <hi rend="grantha">prahara</hi>mum ve<hi rend="grantha">jja</hi>mum <hi rend="grantha">laśu</hi>niyun<hi rend="grantha">trāsamu</hi>ṅkaṟpaṟṟum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭappariyaṉavum neriyaṉavum Āka muppattoṉpatiṉāl niṟai nāṟkaḻañce Āṟu māvum Āka niṟai
<lb n="2"/>Eḻupatteṇkaḻañce mukkāle mañcāṭiyum Eṭṭu māvukku vilai kācu Aiññūṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">4</supplied></hi> tiruvaṭikkāṟai Oṉṟu poṉ Eḻupattorukaḻañcaraiye Iraṇṭu mañcāṭiyum kaṭṭiṉa vayiram maṭṭatārai nāṉūṟṟu Aimpatum maṭṭatāraiccavakkam neriyaṉa Oṉpatum Āka vayiram poṟivum muṟivum <hi rend="grantha">raktabindu</hi>vuṅ<hi rend="grantha">kākabindu</hi>vum ventaṉavum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭa Āka nāṉūṟṟu Aimpattoṉpatiṉāl niṟai kaḻañcaraiye mūṉṟu mañcāṭiyum
<lb n="3"/>Oṉpatu māvum māṇikkam <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷa</hi>ṅkuṇaviyaṉ pattum <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷam</hi> Eṭṭuṅkomaḷam Oṉpatum nīlakanti mūṉṟuntaḷam Oṉpatum Āka māṇikkaṅkuḻivum <hi rend="grantha">prahara</hi>mum ve<hi rend="grantha">jja</hi>mum <hi rend="grantha">laśu</hi>niyun<hi rend="grantha">trāsamu</hi>ṅkaṟpaṟṟum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭappariyaṉavum neriyaṉavum Āka muppattoṉpatiṉāl niṟai mukkaḻañce mukkāle <unclear>mū</unclear>ṉṟu mañcāṭiyum Aṟumāvum Āka niṟai Eḻupatteḻukaḻañce nālu mañcāṭiyuṅkuṉṟi
<lb n="4" break="no"/>kku vilai kācu Aiññūṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">5</supplied> śrīpādaś[ā</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">]lam</hi> Oṉṟu poṉ muppatteḻukaḻañce mukkāle mūṉṟu mañcāṭiyum nāṉku māvuṅkaṭṭiṉa vayiram poṟivum muṟivum <hi rend="grantha">raktabindu</hi>vuṅ<hi rend="grantha">kākabindu</hi>vum ventaṉavum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭa muṉṉūṟṟu Aṟupatiṉāl niṟai mukkāle nālu mañcāṭiyum māṇikkam <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷa</hi>ṅkuṇaviyaṉ patiṉaiñcum <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷam</hi> Irupatuṅkomaḷam Irupattiraṇṭum nilakanti <unclear>mū</unclear>ṉṟuntaḷam paṉṉiraṇṭum Āka māṇikkaṅkuḻi
<lb n="5" break="no"/>vum <hi rend="grantha">prahara</hi>mum ve<hi rend="grantha">jja</hi>mum <hi rend="grantha">laśu</hi>niyun<hi rend="grantha">trāsamu</hi>ṅkaṟpaṟṟum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭappariyaṉavum neriyaṉavum Āka Eḻupattiraṇṭiṉāl niṟai Irukaḻañcaraiye Iraṇṭu mañcāṭiyum Āṟu māvuṅkottaṉavuntaiyttaṉavum Āka muttu vaṭṭamum Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttuṅkuṟumuttum nimpoḷamum payiṭṭamuṅkuḷirnta nīruñcivanta nīrum varaiyuṅkaṟaiyuṅ<unclear>ku</unclear>ruvum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭa muttu nāṟpattiraṇṭiṉāl
<lb n="6"/>niṟai Irukaḻañce Eṭṭu mañcāṭiyuṅkuṉṟiyum Āka niṟai nāṟpattu mukkaḻañce mukkāle <unclear>mū</unclear>ṉṟu mañcāṭiyuṅkuṉṟikku vilai kācu muṉ<unclear>ṉū</unclear>ṟṟaimpatu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">6</supplied> śrīpādaśā</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">lam</hi> Oṉṟu poṉ muppa<unclear>t</unclear>teḻukaḻañce Iraṇṭu mañcāṭiyum nāṉku māvuṅkaṭṭiṉa vayiram maṭṭatārai poṟivum muṟivuṅ<hi rend="grantha">kākabindu</hi>vum <hi rend="grantha">raktabindu</hi>vum ventaṉa<unclear>vu</unclear>m Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭa muṉṉūṟṟu <unclear>A</unclear>ṟupatiṉāl niṟai mukkāle nālu mañcāṭiyum māṇikkam
<lb n="7"/><hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷa</hi>ṅkuṇavi<unclear>ya</unclear>ṉ patiṉaiñcum <hi rend="grantha">haḷahaḷam</hi> Irupatuṅ<unclear>k</unclear>omaḷam patiṉaiñcum nilakanti pattuntaḷam paṉṉiraṇṭum Āka māṇikkaṅ<unclear>ku</unclear>ḻivum <hi rend="grantha">prahara</hi>mum ve<hi rend="grantha">jja</hi>mum <hi rend="grantha">laśu</hi>niyun<hi rend="grantha">trāsamu</hi>ṅkaṟpaṟṟum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭappariyaṉavum neriyaṉavum Āka Eḻupattiraṇṭiṉāl niṟai Irukaḻañcaraiye nālu mañcāṭiyum Orumāvuṅkottaṉavuntaiyttaṉavum Āka muttu vaṭṭamum Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttuṅkuṟu
<lb n="8" break="no"/>muttum nimpoḷamum payiṭṭamuṅkuḷirnta nīruñcivanta nīrum varai<unclear>yu</unclear>ṅkaṟai<unclear>yuṅ</unclear>kuruvum Uṭaiyaṉavum Uṭpaṭa muttu nāṟpattu Iraṇṭiṉāl niṟai Irukaḻañce kāle kuṉṟiyum Āka niṟai nāṟpattu mukkaḻañce mañcāṭikku vilai kācu muṉṉūṟṟu Aimpatu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">7</supplied></hi> Ivare tañcaiviṭaṅkar nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari</hi>yārkku Āṭavallāṉ Eṉṉuṅkuṭiñaik<unclear>ka</unclear>llāl niṟai Eṭuttukkuṭutta poṉṉiṉ tiruvā<hi rend="grantha">bhara</hi>ṇaṅkaḷ <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">8</supplied></hi> tiru<unclear>ma</unclear>kuṭam Oṉṟu <unclear>poṉ nū</unclear>ṟṟuttoṇṇūṟṟu E
<lb n="9" break="no"/>ḻukaḻañcarai [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">9</supplied></hi> tūkkam Oṉṟu poṉ I<unclear>ru</unclear>patteḻukaḻañce mukkāl [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="10"><g type="numeral">10</g></num>*]</hi> <unclear>v</unclear>āḷi Oraṇaiyāṟp<unclear>o</unclear>ṉ Irukaḻañcaraiye mūṉṟu mañcāṭi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="11"><g type="numeral">10</g> 1</num>*]</hi> Iraṭṭaiuḻuttu Oraṇaiyāṟpoṉ mukkaḻañcarai <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="12"><g type="numeral">10</g> 2</num>*]</hi> tirukkampi Oraṇaiyāṟpoṉ Aiṅkaḻañcaraiye kuṉṟi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="13"><g type="numeral">10</g> 3</num>*]</hi> tālimaṇivaṭam Oṉṟu tāli Uṭpaṭappoṉ Irukaḻañce mukkāle kuṉṟi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="14"><g type="numeral">10</g> 4</num>*]</hi> vayi<hi rend="grantha">raśā</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">lam</hi> Oṉṟu poṉ I<unclear>ru</unclear>pa<unclear>t</unclear>teḻukaḻañcarai <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="15"><g type="numeral">10</g> 5</num>*]</hi> mūṉṟ<unclear>oṉṟā</unclear>ka viḷakkiṉa kaṇṭattuṭar Oṉṟu poṉ Irupattorukaḻañcu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="16"><g type="numeral">10</g> 6</num>*]</hi> <unclear>pu</unclear>ṟattuṭar
</p>

<!--<h4><hi rend="italic">C. North wall</hi>.</h4>-->

<p>
<lb n="1"/>Oṉṟu poṉ patiṉ kaḻañce mukkāle nālu mañcāṭi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="17"><g type="numeral">10</g> 7</num>*]</hi> tirukkaippoṭṭu Oraṇaiyāṟkotta nāṇ nālu Uṭpaṭappoṉ Aimpattoṉpatiṉ kaḻañce Eḻumañcā<unclear>ṭi</unclear>yuṅkuṉṟi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="18"><g type="numeral">10</g> 8</num>*]</hi> tirukkaikkaṭakam Oraṇai<unclear>y</unclear>āṟ<unclear>p</unclear>oṉ <unclear>mu</unclear>ppattoṉpati<unclear>ṉ</unclear>
<lb n="2"/>kaḻañce Eḻumañcāṭi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="19"><g type="numeral">10</g> 9</num>*]</hi> tirukkaikkāṟai Oraṇaiyāṟpoṉ Aṟupattu nāṟkaḻañce mukkāl <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="20">2 <g type="numeral">10</g></num>*]</hi> tiruvaṭikkāṟai Oraṇaiyāṟpoṉ Eḻupattu nāṟka<unclear>ḻa</unclear>ñce mukkāl<unclear>e</unclear> kuṉṟi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="21">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 1</num>*] śrīpādaśāyalam</hi> Oraṇaiyāṟpoṉ Aṟupatteḻukaḻañce Oṉpatu
<lb n="3"/>mañcāṭi <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="22">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 2</num>*]</hi> tiruvaṭikkālmotiram pattiṉāl poṉ patiṉorukaḻañce kāl <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="23">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 3</num>*]</hi> tañcaiviṭaṅkar nampirāṭṭiyār <hi rend="grantha">Umāparameśvari-</hi> yārkku Ivare kuṭutta <hi rend="grantha">ratna</hi>ttiṉ tiruv<unclear>ā</unclear><hi rend="grantha">bhara</hi>ṇaṅkaḷ caraṭuñcaṭṭamum Arakkum piñcum nīkki <hi rend="grantha">dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">meru</hi>viṭaṅkaṉ Eṉ<unclear>ṉu</unclear>ṅk<unclear>ā</unclear>cu<unclear>ka</unclear>llāl niṟai
<lb n="4"/>Eṭuttukkallil veṭṭiṉa <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="24">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 4</num>*]</hi> tirumakuṭam Oṉṟu poṉ Irunūṟṟu Eḻukaḻañce Eṭṭu mañcāṭiyum Iraṇṭu māvum kaṭṭiṉa paḷikkuvayiram Aiññūṟṟu Irupattañciṉāl niṟai Irukaḻañce mūṉṟu mañcāṭiyum Aimmāvaraiyum
<lb n="5"/>paḷiṅku Iru<unclear>nū</unclear>ṟṟu Irupatteḻiṉāl niṟai Aiṅkaḻañce nālu mañcāṭiyum Arai māvum kaṭṭiṉa muttu vaṭṭamum Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttuṅkuṟumuttum nimpoḷamum payiṭṭamuṅkuḷirnta nīruñcivanta nīruñcup<unclear>pi</unclear>ramum varai
<lb n="6" break="no"/>yum Uṭaiyaṉa patiṉāṟiṉāl niṟai kaḻañcaraiye nālu mañcāṭiyum Oṉpatu māvaraiyum vīrapaṭṭattu Iraṇṭarukiluṅkotta vaṭam Ira<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭum Itaṉ mel vāyvaṭam Oṉṟuntaṉivaṭam cavi nāluntaṉittūkkam Iraṇṭu
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ṅkoṭaṅkaḷiluṅkaṟaṇṭikaiyiṟkotta <unclear>va</unclear>ṭam mūṉṟilum<unclear>ā</unclear>kakkotta muttu vaṭṭamum Aṉuvaṭṭamum Oppumuttuṅkuṟumuttum nimpoḷamum Ippippaṟṟu Arāviṉavuṅkuḷirnta niruñcivanta nīrum varai
<lb n="8" break="no"/>yuṅkaṟaiyuñcuppiramuntiraṅkalum Uṭaiyaṉa Uṭpaṭa muṉṉūṟṟe<unclear>ṇ</unclear>pattaiñciṉāl niṟai patiṉ mukkaḻañce Eḻumañcāṭiyum Āka niṟai <unclear>I</unclear>runūṟṟu Irupattu Oṉpatiṉ kaḻañce mukkāle Iraṇṭu mañc<unclear>ā</unclear>ṭiyum Eḻumāvarai
<lb n="9" break="no"/>kku vilai kācu Eḻunūṟu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="25">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 5</num>*]</hi> mālai Oṉṟu poṉ nāṟpattu <unclear>A</unclear>ṟukaḻañce <unclear>E</unclear>ṭṭu mañcāṭiyum <unclear>mukkā</unclear>ṇiyum kaṭṭiṉa paḷikku<unclear>vayi</unclear>ram Irunūṟṟeṇpatteṭṭiṉāl niṟai Araikkaḻañce <unclear>mū</unclear>ṉṟu mañcāṭiyu<unclear>m</unclear> Eḻumāvum paḷiṅku
<lb n="10"/>Itiṟkuṟai <hi rend="grantha">ca<unclear>tuṣki</unclear>kai</hi><unclear>yil</unclear> teṉ<unclear>ca</unclear>turattu <unclear>U</unclear>ttirat<unclear>ti</unclear>ṉ kīḻkkaṇṭappaṭaiyil veṭṭiccu <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">[<num value="26">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 6</num>*]</hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. Hail ! Prosperity ! Until the third year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Śōṛadēva,—Āṛvār Parāntakaṉ Kundavaiyār</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the venerable elder sister of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the great queen of <hi rend="bold">Vallavaraiyar Vandyadēvar</hi>, gave to the images which she had set up herself,—gold which was weighed by the stone (<hi rend="italic">used in</hi>) the city and called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>, and jewels which were weighed by the jewel weight called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkaṉ</hi>. Those (<hi rend="italic">jewels</hi>), which could be weighed (<hi rend="italic">separately</hi>), were weighed without the threads, the frames, the copper nails, the lac and the <hi rend="italic">piñju</hi>. Those jewels, the net weight of which could not be ascertained, as they were united with the lac and the <hi rend="italic">piñju, (were weighed</hi>) together with the lac and the <hi rend="italic">piñju. (The amount of this gold and these jewels</hi>) was engraved on stone (<hi rend="italic">as follows):</hi>—</p>

<p>2. To (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">she</hi>) gave:—</p>

<p>3. One sacred girdle (<hi rend="italic">tiruppaṭṭigai), (containing</hi>) ninety-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half, four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and nine tenths of gold. Six hundred and sixty-seven large and small diamonds with smooth edges, set (<hi rend="italic">into it</hi>),—including such as had spots, cracks, red dots, black dots, and marks as of burning,—weighed two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a quarter and six tenths (<hi rend="italic">of a mañjāḍi</hi>). Eighty-three large and small rubies, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, twenty-two <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi> of superior quality, twenty <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi>, twenty smooth rubies, nine bluish rubies, two <hi rend="italic">śaṭṭam</hi> and ten unpolished rubies,— including such as had cavities, cuts, holes, white specks, flaws, and such as still adhered to the ore,—weighed ten <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters, three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and two tenths. Two hundred and twelve pearls, strung or sewn on,—including round pearls, roundish pearls, polished pearls, small pearls, <hi rend="italic">nimboḷam, ambumudu, (pearls</hi>) of brilliant water and of red water, such as had been polished while still adhering to the shell, (<hi rend="italic">and pearls with</hi>) lines, stains, red dots, white specks and wrinkles,—weighed eighteen <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and two <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>. Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the girdle</hi>) weighed one hundred and twenty-nine <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and seven tenths (<hi rend="italic">of a mañjāḍi</hi>), corresponding to a value of four thousand and five hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>4. One ring for the foot of the goddess (<hi rend="italic">tiruvaḍikkāṟai), (containing</hi>) seventy-three <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>, six tenths and one twentieth of gold. Four hundred and fifty-five diamonds, set (<hi rend="italic">into it), viz</hi>., four hundred and forty-nine diamonds with smooth edges, and six flat diamonds with smooth edges,—including such as had spots, cracks, red dots, black dots, and marks as of burning,—weighed (<hi rend="italic">one) kaṛañju</hi> and a half, two <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>, five tenths and one twentieth. Thirty-nine large and small rubies, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ten <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi> of superior quality, ten <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi>, eight smooth rubies, three bluish rubies and eight unpolished rubies,— including such as had cavities, cuts, holes, white specks, flaws, and such as still adhered to the ore,—weighed four <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and six tenths (<hi rend="italic">of a mañjāḍi</hi>). Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the ring</hi>) weighed seventy-eight <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters, (<hi rend="italic">one) mañjāḍi</hi> and eight tenths, corresponding to a value of five hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>5. One ring for the foot of the goddess, (<hi rend="italic">containing</hi>) seventy-one <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half and two <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold. Four hundred and fifty-nine diamonds, set (<hi rend="italic">into it), viz</hi>., four hundred and fifty diamonds with smooth edges, and nine small square diamonds with smooth edges,— including such as had spots, cracks, red dots, black dots, and marks as of burning,—weighed (<hi rend="italic">one) kaṛañju</hi> and a half, three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and nine tenths. Thirty-nine large and small rubies, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ten <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi> of superior quality, eight <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi>, nine smooth rubies, three bluish rubies and nine unpolished rubies,—including such as had cavities, cuts, holes, white speeks, flaws, and such as still adhered to the ore,—weighed three <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters, three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and six tenths. Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the ring</hi>) weighed seventy-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi>, corresponding to a value of five hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>6. One <hi rend="italic">śāyalam</hi> for the foot of the goddess (<hi rend="italic">śrī-pāda-śāyalam), (containing</hi>) thirty-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters, three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and four tenths of gold. Three hundred and sixty diamonds, set (<hi rend="italic">into it</hi>),—including such as had spots, cracks, red dots, black dots, and marks as of burning,—weighed three quarters (<hi rend="italic">of a kaṛañju</hi>) and four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>. Seventy-two large and small rubies, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, fifteen <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi> of superior quality, twenty <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi>, twenty-two smooth rubies, three bluish rubies and twelve unpolished rubies,—including such as had cavities, cuts, holes, white specks, flaws, and such as still adhered to the ore,—weighed two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half, two <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and six tenths. Forty-two pearls, strung or sewn on,— including round pearls, roundish pearls, polished pearls, small pearls, <hi rend="italic">nimboḷam, payiṭṭam, (pearls</hi>) of brilliant water and of red water, (<hi rend="italic">and pearls</hi>) with lines, stains and red dots,— weighed two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, eight <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi>. Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the śāyalam</hi>) weighed forty-three <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters, three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi>, corresponding to a value of three hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>7. One <hi rend="italic">śāyalam</hi> for the foot of the goddess, (<hi rend="italic">containing</hi>) thirty-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and four tenths of gold. Three hundred and sixty diamonds with smooth edges, set (<hi rend="italic">into it</hi>),—including such as had spots, cracks, black dots, red dots, and marks as of burning,—weighed three quarters (<hi rend="italic">of a kaṛañju</hi>) and four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>. Seventy-two large and small rubies, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, fifteen <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi> of superior quality, twenty <hi rend="italic">haḷahaḷam</hi>, fifteen smooth rubies, ten bluish rubies and twelve unpolished rubies,—including such as had cavities, cuts, holes, white specks, flaws, and such as still adhered to the ore,—weighed two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half, four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and one tenth. Forty-two pearls, strung or sewn on,—including round pearls, roundish pearls, polished pearls, small pearls, <hi rend="italic">nimboḷam, payiṭṭam, (pearls</hi>) of brilliant water and of red water, (<hi rend="italic">and pearls</hi>) with lines, stains and red dots,—weighed two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a quarter and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi>. Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the śāyalam</hi>) weighed forty-three <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) mañjāḍi</hi>, corresponding to a value of three hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>8. The same (<hi rend="italic">princess</hi>) gave to (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) sacred ornaments (<hi rend="italic">ābharaṇa</hi>) of gold, which were weighed by the stone (<hi rend="italic">used in</hi>) the city and called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ:</hi>—</p>

<p>9. One sacred crown (<hi rend="italic">makuṭa), (consisting of</hi>) one hundred and ninety-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half of gold.</p>

<p>10. One pendant (<hi rend="italic">tūkkam), (consisting of</hi>) twenty-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters of gold.</p>

<p>11. One pair of ear-rings (<hi rend="italic">vāḷi</hi>), consisting of two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half and three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>12. One pair of double <hi rend="italic">uṛuttu</hi>, consisting of three <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half of gold.</p>

<p>13. One pair of sacred ear-rings (<hi rend="italic">tirukkambi</hi>), consisting of five <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>14. One string of beads for the marriage-badge (<hi rend="italic">tāli-maṇi-vaḍam), (consisting of</hi>) two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi> of gold,—including the marriage-badge (<hi rend="italic">itself</hi>).</p>

<p>15. One <hi rend="italic">śāyalam</hi> of diamonds (<hi rend="italic">vayira-śāyalam), (containing</hi>) twenty-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a half of gold.</p>

<p>16. One necklace (<hi rend="italic">kaṇṭha-tuḍar</hi>) of three (<hi rend="italic">chains</hi>) soldered into one, (<hi rend="italic">consisting of</hi>) twenty-one <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>17. One outer chain (<hi rend="italic">? puṟattuḍar), (consisting of</hi>) ten <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters and four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>18. One pair of <hi rend="italic">poṭṭu</hi> for the arms of the goddess, consisting of fifty-nine <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, seven <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi> of gold,—including four strings (<hi rend="italic">nāṇ</hi>) on which (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>) was strung.</p>

<p>19. One pair of bracelets (<hi rend="italic">kaṭaka</hi>) for the arms of the goddess, consisting of thirty-nine <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and seven <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>20. One pair of rings for the arms of the goddess (<hi rend="italic">tirukkaikkāṟai</hi>), consisting of sixtyfour <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters of gold.</p>

<p>21. One pair of rings for the feet of the goddess (<hi rend="italic">tiruvaḍikkāṟai</hi>), consisting of seventyfour <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters and (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṉṟi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>22. One pair of <hi rend="italic">śāyaḻam</hi> for the feet of the goddess (<hi rend="italic">śrī-pāda-śāyalam</hi>), consisting of sixty-seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and nine <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold.</p>

<p>23. Ten rings for the toes of the goddess (<hi rend="italic">tiruvaḍikkāl-mōdiram</hi>), consisting of eleven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and a quarter of gold.</p>

<p>24. To (<hi rend="italic">the goddess</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Umāparamēśvarī</hi>, who is the consort of our lord <hi rend="bold">Tañjai-Viṭaṅkar</hi>, the same (<hi rend="italic">princess</hi>) gave (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) sacred ornaments of jewels, which were weighed by the jewel weight called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Dakshiṇa-Mēru-Viṭaṅkaṉ</hi> without the threads, the frames, the lac and the <hi rend="italic">piñju</hi>, and engraved on stone:—</p>

<p>25. One sacred crown (<hi rend="italic">makuṭa), (containing</hi>) two hundred and seven <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, eight <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and two tenths of gold. Five hundred and twenty-five diamond crystals, set (<hi rend="italic">into it</hi>), weighed two <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>, five tenths and one twentieth. Two hundred and twenty-seven crystals (<hi rend="italic">paḷiṅgu</hi>) weighed five <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and one twentieth. Sixteen pearls, set (<hi rend="italic">into it), (viz</hi>.) round pearls, roundish pearls, polished pearls, small pearls, <hi rend="italic">nimboḷam, payiṭṭam, (pearls</hi>) of brilliant water and of red water, (<hi rend="italic">and pearls</hi>) with white specks and lines, weighed (<hi rend="italic">one) kaṛañju</hi> and a half, four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>, nine tenths and one twentieth. Three hundred and eighty-five strung pearls,—including round pearls, roundish pearls, polished pearls, small pearls, <hi rend="italic">nimboḷam</hi>, such as had been polished while still adhering to the shell, (<hi rend="italic">pearls</hi>) of brilliant water and of red water, (<hi rend="italic">and pearls</hi>) with lines, stains, white specks and wrinkles,—weighed thirteen <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and seven <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi; (these pearls</hi>) were strung on two strings (<hi rend="italic">vaḍam</hi>) on both sides of the front-plate (<hi rend="italic">vīra-paṭṭa</hi>),<note n="90-1">Literally, ‘the diadem of heroes.’ The technical meanings of <hi rend="italic">vāy-vaḍam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kaṟaṇḍigai</hi> as parts of a crown are not found in the dictionaries.</note> one <hi rend="italic">vāy-vaḍam</hi> over it, four bundles (<hi rend="italic">śavi</hi>) of single strings, two single pendants (<hi rend="italic">tūkkam</hi>), and three strings on the ornamental curves (<hi rend="italic">kōḍam)<note n="90-2">See Winslow, <hi rend="italic">s.v</hi>. <ta>kōṭakam</ta>.</note> (and</hi>) on the <hi rend="italic">kaṟaṇḍigai</hi>. Altogether, (<hi rend="italic">the crown</hi>) weighed two hundred and twenty-nine <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> and three quarters, two <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>, seven tenths and one twentieth, corresponding to a value of seven hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

<p>26. One garland (<hi rend="italic">mālai), (containing</hi>) forty-six <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, eight <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and three fortieths of gold. Two hundred and eighty-eight diamond crystals, set (<hi rend="italic">into it</hi>), weighed half a <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi>, three <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> and seven tenths. Crystals,—The continuation of this (<hi rend="italic">inscription</hi>) is engraved on the panel (<hi rend="italic">kaṇḍappaḍai)</hi><note n="90-3">Compare <hi rend="grantha">upapīṭha</hi>ttu<ta>kkaṇṭappaṭai</ta> in No. 3. second section, ll. 10 f.</note> underneath the projecting stone (<hi rend="italic">? uttiram)</hi><note n="90-4">According to Winslow, <ta>uttiram</ta> means ‘a beam, a cross beam in a building.’</note> on the southern side (<hi rend="italic">? śaduram</hi>) of the portieo (<hi rend="italic">chatushkikā</hi>).</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.8 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">84-90</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">8</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
