<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 2.10: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 10. ON THE SOUTH WALL, FIRST TIER.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv02p0i0010</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 10th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, and fixes the interest, which the inhabitants of a certain village had to pay for the benefit of the image of <hi rend="bold">Krātārjunadēvar</hi><note n="93-3">See page 90, note 5.</note> and of the images of <hi rend="bold">Mahā-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi> and his consort. The first of these three images had been set up by the minister, who is mentioned in the preceding inscription, and the second by king <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="4"/><note n="93-4">Continued from page 91.</note> <hi rend="grantha">svasti śrīḥ</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tiru maṉṉi vaḷara Iruni<unclear>lamaṭan</unclear>taiyum poṟcayappā<unclear>v</unclear>aiyuñcīrttaṉiccelviyuntaṉ perunteviyarākiyiṉpu<unclear>ṟa ne</unclear>ṭutiyalūḻiyuḷ Iṭaituṟaināṭuntoṭarvaṉavelippaṭar vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻmatiḷ koḷḷippākkaiyum naṇṇaṟkarumuraṇ maṇṇaikkaṭakkamum porutaṭarīḻattaraicar tamuṭiyum Āṅkavar teviyaroṅkeḻil muṭiyum muṉṉavar pakkal teṉṉavar vaitta cuntaramuṭiyum Intiraṉāramunteṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟipaṭaikkeraḷar muṟ<unclear>aimaiyi</unclear>ṟcūṭuṅkulataṉamākiya palar pukaḻ muṭiyuñceṅkatir mālai<unclear>yu</unclear>ñ<unclear>caṅka</unclear>ti<unclear>r</unclear>velaittolperuṅkāval palapaḻantīvuñceruviṟ<unclear>ci</unclear>ṉavi<unclear>yi</unclear>rupattorukālaraicukaḷai kaṭṭa paracurāmaṉ mevaruñcāntima<unclear>ttīvara</unclear>ṇ karutiyiruttiya cempoṟṟiruttaku <unclear>muṭi</unclear>yum <unclear>payaṅk</unclear>oṭu paḻi <unclear>mi</unclear>ka muyaṅkiyi<unclear>l</unclear> mutukiṭṭoḷitta cayaciṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>ṉ Aḷapperum<note n="93-5">Nos. 12 to 20 read aḷapparum, which comes to the same.</note> pukaḻoṭu pīṭiyal Iraṭṭapāṭi Eḻarai Ilakkamum navanetikkulapperumalaikaḷum māpporutaṇṭāṟkoṇṭa kopparake<hi rend="grantha">sari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi>rāṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu pattāvatu Atikārikaḷ kāñcivāyiluṭaiyār Utai<unclear>ya</unclear>tivākaraṉ tillai
<lb n="5" break="no"/>yāḷiyārāṉa <hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>mūventaveḷār Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">krā</hi>tā<hi rend="grantha">rjju</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var<unclear>k</unclear>kuttiruvamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunnivantaṅkaḷu<unclear>k</unclear>kuñciṟutaṉattuppaṇimakkaḷ Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>var Eḻunta<unclear>ruḷuvi</unclear>tta <hi rend="grantha">mahāmeru</hi>viṭaṅkar<unclear>k</unclear>kum nampirāṭṭiyārkkuntiruvamu<unclear>tu</unclear> Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunni<unclear>va</unclear>ntaṅkaḷukkum Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu pattāvatu varai Ivarkaḷ vaiytta kācil <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājīśvara</hi>ttiṉiteḻuntaruḷi Irunta <hi rend="grantha">paramasvāmi</hi>kku mula<hi rend="grantha">bhṛtya</hi>nākiya <hi rend="grantha">caṇḍeśvarade</hi>var pakkal policaiūṭṭukkukkoṇṭa Ūruṅkallil veṭṭiṉa <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">1</supplied></hi> nittaviṉotavaḷanāṭṭu Āvūrkkūṟṟattu <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>yam Irumputalākiya <hi rend="grantha">ma</hi>nu<hi rend="grantha">kulacūḷāma</hi>ṇi<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvedimaṅgala</hi>ttu<hi rend="grantha"> sa<unclear>bh</unclear>ai</hi>yār Atikārikaḷ kāñcivāyiluṭaiyār Utai<unclear>ya</unclear>tivākaraṉ tillaiyāḷiyār<unclear>āṉa</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi><unclear>mū</unclear>ventaveḷār Eḻuntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">krā</hi>tā<hi rend="grantha">rjju</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkkuttiruvamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunnivantaṅkaḷukku vaiytta k<unclear>ācil ko</unclear>ṇṭa kācu toṇṇūṟṟu nālum Uṭaiyā<unclear>r</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">śrī<unclear>r</unclear>ājarā[jade</hi>var Eḻu]ntaruḷuvitta <hi rend="grantha">mahāmeru</hi>viṭaṅkarkkum nampirāṭṭiyārkkuntiruvamutu Uḷḷiṭṭu veṇṭunnivantaṅkaḷukkucciṟutaṉattuppaṇimakkaḷ vaiytta kācil koṇṭa kācu Aiññūṟṟāṟum Āka yāṇṭu pattāvatu pacāṉ mutal koṇṭa kācu Aṟunūṟiṉāl kācu Oṉṟukku Āṭṭai vaṭṭaṉ palicai nellu mukkuṟuṇiyāka <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha"/>
<lb n="6" break="no"/>l Āṭṭāṇṭu toṟum <hi rend="grantha">rājakesari</hi>yoṭokkum Āṭavallāṉeṉṉum marakkālāl tañcāvūr Uṭaiyār perum paṇṭārattey Aḷakkakkaṭava nellu nūṟṟaimpatiṉ kalam <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">2</supplied></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1891_01">

<p>1. Hail ! Prosperity ! In the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kō-Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who,—in (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) life of high prosperity, (<hi rend="italic">during which he</hi>) rejoiced that, while Fortune, having become constant, was increasing, the goddess of the great earth, the goddess of victory in battle, and the matchless goddess of fame had become his great queens,—conquered with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) great and warlike army <hi rend="bold">Iḍaituṟai-nāḍu;<note n="94-1">Nos. 17 to 19 read Iḍatuṟai-nāḍu.</note> Vaṉavāśi</hi>, whose warriors (<hi rend="italic">were protected by</hi>) walls of continuous forests; <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷippākkai</hi>, whose walls were surrounded by <hi rend="italic">śuḷḷi (trees</hi>); <hi rend="bold">Maṇṇaikkaḍakkam</hi> of unapproachable strength;<note n="94-2">Instead of <ta>naṇṇaṟkarumuraṇ</ta>, Nos. 12 to 19 read <ta>naṇṇaṟkarumaraṇ</ta>, ‘the fortifications of which were unapproachable.’</note> the crown of the king of <hi rend="bold">Īram</hi>, who came to close quarters in fighting; the exceedingly beautiful crown of the queen of the king of that (<hi rend="italic">country</hi>); the crown of <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi> and the pearl-necklace of <hi rend="bold">Indra</hi>, which the king of the South had previously given up to that (<hi rend="italic">king of</hi> Īṛam); the whole <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi> on the transparent sea; the crown praised by many and the garland of the sun, family-treasures, which the arrow-shooting (<hi rend="italic">king of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷa</hi> rightfully wore; many ancient islands, whose old and great guard was the sea, which resounds with conches; the crown of pure gold, worthy of Lakshmī, which <hi rend="bold">Paraśurāma</hi>, having considered the fortifications of <hi rend="bold">Śāndimattīvu</hi><note n="94-3"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>, the island of Śāntimat (?).</note> impregnable, had deposited (<hi rend="italic">there</hi>), when, raging with anger, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) bound the kings twenty-one times; the seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-pāḍi</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">which was</hi>) strong by nature, (<hi rend="italic">the conquest of which was accompanied</hi>) with immeasurable fame, (<hi rend="italic">and which he took from</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi>, who, out of fear (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) full of vengeance, turned his back at <hi rend="bold">Muyaṅgi</hi><note n="94-4">Instead of <ta>muyaṅki</ta>, No. 17 and two inscriptions at Tirumalai near Pōlūr (Vol. I, pp. 98 and 100) read <ta>mucaṅki </ta>. As the Drāviḍians generally pronounce initial <hi rend="italic">u</hi> as <hi rend="italic">vu</hi>, and as the change of <hi rend="italic">v</hi> into <hi rend="italic">m</hi>, which is frequent in Malayāḷam (see Dr. Caldwell's <hi rend="italic">Comparative Grammar</hi>, 2nd edition, p. 58), occurs in Tamil too (<hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>, in <ta>māṉam</ta> for <ta>vāṉam</ta>, ‘the sky’), Muśaṅgi might be identical with Uchchaṅgi-durga, an ancient hill-fort in the Harpanahaḷḷi tālluqa of the Bellary district.</note> and hid himself; and the principal great mountains, (<hi rend="italic">which contained</hi>) the nine treasures;—<note n="95-1"><ta>navaneti</ta> seems to be a corruption of the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">nara-nidhi</hi>, ‘the nine treasures (of Kuvēra).’</note> there was engraved on stone (<hi rend="italic">the name of</hi>) the village, which had received on interest from <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍēśvaradēva</hi>,—who is the first servant of the supreme lord, who has been pleased to take up gladly his abode in (<hi rend="italic">the temple called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājēśvara</hi>,—(<hi rend="italic">part</hi>) of the money, (<hi rend="italic">which had been deposited</hi>) until the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva</hi> for the sacred food and other expenses required by (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Krātārjunadēvar</hi>,—which had been set up by the minister <hi rend="bold">Udayadivākaraṉ Tillaiyāḷiyār</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Mūvēnda-Vēḷār</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchivāyil</hi>,—and (<hi rend="italic">of the money</hi>), which the <hi rend="bold">Śiṟudaṉattu Paṇimakkaḷ</hi><note n="95-2">The literal meaning of this term would be: ‘the servants of the minor treasure.’</note> had deposited for the sacred food and other expenses required by (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahā-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>,—which had been set up by the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>,—and by (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) his consort.</p>

<p>2. The members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Irumbudal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Manukulachūḷāmaṇichaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Āvūr-kūṟṟam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Nittaviṉōda-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, have received after (<hi rend="italic">the harvest of</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paśāṉ</hi> in the tenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the king's reign</hi>) six hundred <hi rend="italic">kāśu, viz</hi>., (1) ninety-four <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> taken out of the money, which had been deposited for the sacred food and other expenses required by (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Krātārjunadēvar</hi>, which had been set up by the minister <hi rend="bold">Udayadivākaraṉ Tillaiyāḷiyār</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Mūvēnda-Vēḷār</hi>, a native of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchivāyil</hi>, and (2) five hundred and six <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> taken out of the money, which the <hi rend="bold">Śiṟudaṉattu Paṇimakkaḷ</hi> had deposited for the sacred food and other expenses required by (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahā-Mēru-Viṭaṅkar</hi>,—which had been set up by the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>,—and by (<hi rend="italic">the image of</hi>) his consort. For (<hi rend="italic">these six hundred kāśu</hi>), they have to measure every year, as long as the moon and the sun endure, one hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy into the large treasury of the lord (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tañjāvūr</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi>) called (<hi rend="italic">after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āḍavallāṉ</hi>, which is equal to a <hi rend="italic">rājakēsari</hi>,—the rate of interest being three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per year for each <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 2.10 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1891_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">93-95</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">10</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
