<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 3.128: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
                <title type="alt">XIV.—INSCRIPTIONS OF PARAKESARIVARMAN UTTAMA-CHOLA. No. 128.—MADRAS MUSEUM PLATES OF UTTAMA-CHOLA.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0128</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>These copper-plates belong to the Madras Museum. A full description of them together with that of the huge ring and seal on which they are hung and a short abstract of contents, have been given by Professor Hultzsch in his <hi rend="italic">Report on Epigraphy</hi> for the halfyear ending March 1891, page 4, paragraph 9<note>For a facsimile of the seal see <hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi>, Vol. III, plate facing page 104, No. 3.</note> . The plates are published below for the first time with text and translation. Mr. Sewell does not mention them in the list of copperplate grants which he gives at the beginning of his <hi rend="italic">Lists of Madras Antiquities</hi>, Volume II. It cannot be ascertained how and when the plates were acquired by the Museum.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Early <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> copper-plate grants published so far are only two in number. These are known as the large and the small Leyden grants which belong to the time of <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷa</hi> I. Hence the subjoined plates which bear on them the record of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman Uttama-Chōḷadēva</hi>, the uncle of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I., and the grandfather of <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷa</hi> I., will be the earliest Chōḷa record<note >The late Mr. T.A. Gopinatha Rao has discovered a set of still earlier copper-plates of the time of Sundara-Chōḷa Parāntaka II., the father of Rājarāja I., which is being published in the <hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi>.</note> published.</p>						
                            
                            <p>A few plates of the set are missing at the beginning and one at least at the end. The portion of the record on the existing five copper-plates consists of a short Sanskrit prose passage (ll. 1 to 6), three Sanskrit verses (ll. 6 to 11) and Tamil prose (ll. 11 to 121). The construction of the Tamil portion is often involved and irregular<note>See Mr. Venkayya's remarks on the history of Tamil Philology of the Tanjore inscriptions in <hi rend="italic">South- Indian Inscriptions</hi>, Vol. II, Introduction, page 15.</note> . The word <hi rend="italic">nēra</hi> in l. 87, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>, is used in the still current commercial sense of adjustment of receipts and payments and the meaning of <hi rend="italic">viśam</hi> in l. 111 is not quite intelligible<note>This word must be different from <hi rend="italic">viśaṉ</hi> which in a record of Vīrarājēndradēva is used in the sense of a servant.</note> . As regards the palaeography and orthography of the plates the following may be noted. The initial vowels <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ē</hi> are not distinguished, though in other inscriptions of this period the distinction is marked by adding the sign of length <foreign>(kāl)</foreign> to the short <hi rend="italic">e</hi>. This method of distinguishing the long from the short is however observed in <hi rend="italic">o</hi>, in ll. 52 and 53. The secondary <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ī</hi> signs are distinguished, the latter by a loop attached to the end of the semi-circular cap which represents the former, <hi rend="italic">e.g., nī</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vī</hi> in ll. 22 and 23 respectively. The <hi rend="italic">i</hi> super-added to <hi rend="italic">ḍa</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ṭa</hi> is, as usual, marked by the semi-circular cap; but in certain cases as in ll. 26, 34, <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>., it is shown by the head of the letter itself being bent and drawn out almost into a loop. The vowel signs <hi rend="italic">u</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ū</hi> added to <hi rend="italic">m</hi> are distinguished, the former by a plain curve bent towards the left and attached to the prolonged vertical of <hi rend="italic">ma</hi> from its middle and the latter by the same curve doubled like the English numeral 3. The same remarks apply as well to <hi rend="italic">ḷu</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ḷū</hi>. When added to <hi rend="italic">ka</hi> the <hi rend="italic">u</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ū</hi>-signs are doubled in either case, the distinction, however, being that in the former the curve bends to the left and in the latter to the right. In <hi rend="italic">ya, va</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pa</hi> these signs are marked as at present by a vertical line attached to the right limb of the letter in the one case, and by a curve affixed to the latter, in the other. In the case of the letters <foreign>na, ṉa, la</foreign> and <foreign>ña</foreign> the <hi rend="italic">ū</hi>-sign is denoted by adding to the <hi rend="italic">u</hi>-sign a detached <foreign>kāl </foreign>-symbol which at present however is joined to the <hi rend="italic">u</hi>-sign of the letter. <hi rend="italic">Sandhi (puṇarchchi</hi>) is but optionally adopted. The doubling of consonants has been omitted evidently by mistake in ll. 68, 70, 71, <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>. Case terminations are added to the last word of a group (<hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>, ll. 16f, 82). In l. 44 <foreign>aiñkaḻañcu</foreign> is written for <foreign>aiṅkaḻañcu</foreign>. The forms <foreign>nicatam</foreign> and <foreign>nicata</foreign> both occur. So also the forms <foreign>ukaccakaḷ, uvaccarkaḷ</foreign> and <foreign>uvaccar</foreign> (ll. 54, 64, 86).</p>						
                            
                            <p>The Sanskrit portion states that 200 pieces of gold were deposited with two classes of <hi rend="italic">paṭṭaśālins</hi> residing in the quarters (of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>) known as <hi rend="bold">Karuvuḷānpāṭi, Kaṁsahappāṭi, Atimānappāṭi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ēṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> and that the residents of two of the above-said quarters were appointed managers of the temple by the king <hi rend="bold">(Uttama-Chōḷa)</hi>. Also this same Chōḷa king ‘who destroyed <hi rend="bold">Madhurā</hi>’ is stated to have ordered that the residents of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi>, another quarter of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, should give to the god at <hi rend="bold">Ūraka</hi> two <hi rend="italic">prastha</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">kuḍubaka</hi> of rice and one <hi rend="italic">prastha</hi> of oil and thus be exempted from all other taxes payable to the king. These residents of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> together with the managers appointed from among the weavers who made cloths for the king and lived in the four quarters mentioned above, were further required to write out by turns the accounts of the temple of <hi rend="bold">Vishṇu</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The Tamil portion which begins in line 11 is dated in the 16th year of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Chōḷadēva</hi> and records that while the king was seated in the <hi rend="bold">Chitra</hi>-<hi rend="italic">maṇḍapa</hi> inside his palace (<hi rend="italic">kōyil</hi>) at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, his officer <hi rend="bold">Śōḻamūvēndavēḷār</hi> whose name was <hi rend="bold">Nakkaṉ Kaṇichchaṉ</hi> of Śikkal (l. 25 f.) requested that the income of the god of the temple of <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi> which consisted of (1) <hi rend="italic">kōlniraikūli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kālaḷavu-kūli</hi> collected at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, (2) of the (produce from) lands purchased at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Tuṇḍuṇukkachchēri</hi> and (3) of interest (in paddy and in money) accruing on investments by the temple, might be apportioned for the several services in the main temple and in the two shrines of the hall called <hi rend="bold">Karikālateṟṟi</hi> (l. 65) and that the residents of the two quarters of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kambuḻānpāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Atimānappāḍi</hi> (l. 23) may be appointed to supervise and carry out this apportionment. The king entrusted the matter in the hands of the chief who made the request and the latter settled the required apportionment of income.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The lands purchased and the investments made are detailed with reference to the original documents written on stone. These were:—(1) document dated in the 22nd year of king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, by which the assemblies of <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ariyar-Perumbākkam</hi> having received 250 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold from the temple had agreed to measure every year as interest thereon 500 <hi rend="italic">kāḍi</hi> of paddy; (2) document dated in the same year by which the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Uḻai-ūr</hi> received 50 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and agreed to measure annually an interest thereon of 150 <hi rend="italic">kāḍi</hi> of paddy; (3) document dated in the 9th year of king <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Kampavarman</hi>, by which the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Oḻukkaippākkam</hi> received 24 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and agreed to pay an interest every year of one <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold.</p>						
                            
                            <p>With line 72 commences a fresh grant made in the 16th year of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman (Uttama-Chōḷa)</hi>, to the temple of <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> for maintaining the <hi rend="italic">Śittirai-tiruviḻā</hi> festival of that god. For this purpose 200 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold were deposited with the residents of <hi rend="bold">Kambuḻāṉpāḍi, Atimānappāḍi, Kañjagappāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ēṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> on perpetual interest of 30 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> for one year, at the rate of one <hi rend="italic">piḷavu</hi> on each <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> per month. This money (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, 30 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi>) being fully adjusted (<foreign>nēr</foreign>) for expenses detailed in lines 81 to 89, the lamp-holders for the festival and the flaghoisters had to be secured by the residents of the four quarters mentioned above (<hi rend="italic">free of cost</hi>).</p>						
                            
                            <p>Lines 99 to 100 register a few other items of expense apparently in connexion with the same festival. It is stated that in the 18th year of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, ‘who took <hi rend="bold">Madirai</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Īḻam</hi>’ (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I), a concession had been granted, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, exemption from municipal taxes, to the residents who had newly settled down in the quarter called <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> (of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>) in consideration of their giving certain fixed quantities of oil and rice to the temple of <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi>, which the <hi rend="bold">Tōḷāchcheviyār</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Ēlākkaiyar</hi> the former residents of this quarter were regularly contributing but had discontinued on account of their decline. This concession. was now (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, in the 16th year) ratified by king <hi rend="bold">(Uttama-Chōḷa)</hi>. It was further ordered that the residents of this quarter, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi>, must provide also an accountant who would be given every day from the temple treasury 2 <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy and every year 2 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold.</p>						
                            
                            <p>According to lines 100 to 103 a further grant of 23 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> was made to the residents in the three Śaiva quarters <hi rend="bold">(Śaṅkarappāḍi)</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Raṇajayappāḍi, Ēkavīrappāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Vāmanaśaṅkarappāḍi</hi>, in order to maintain a perpetual lamp in the temple and to burn twilight lamps from the oil supplied by the residents of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> mentioned in the previous paragraph.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Other miscellaneous items of provision (ll. 103 to 108) included the cost of the sacred festivals of <hi rend="bold">Uttarāyaṇa-Saṁkrānti</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Chitrā-Vishu</hi>, the organization of the <hi rend="italic">gōshṭhī</hi> of devotees, etc. The president of the City Corporation, the members of the Annual Supervision Committee and the residents of <hi rend="bold">Ēṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kañjagappāḍi</hi> were required to check the accounts at the end of each festival, while the residents of these two quarters were to supply also the watchman of the temple (ll. 110 ff.). (<hi rend="italic">The city assembly</hi>) was further entrusted with the authority of appointing the managers for carrying out the temple business, the watchman and the accountant and of exempting these from payment of all municipal taxes (l. 113 f.). The document was drawn up by <hi rend="bold">Nārppatteṇṇāyiramaṅgalādittaṉ</hi>, an arbitrator (<hi rend="italic">madhyastha</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Vīrappāḍi</hi>, a quarter of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> (l. 119 f.).</p>						
                            
                            <p>From the above abstract of contents it is clear that the preserved Sanskrit portion of the grant refers in brief to what has been elaborately detailed in ll. 72 to 115 of the Tamil portion. Consequently the contents covered by lines 11 to 71 of the Tamil portion together with the genealogical portion of the grant, if any—all in Sanskrit—should have been lost in the missing plates at the beginning of the record. The reference to previous kings in the body of the Tamil portion is very interesting inasmuch as it enables us to identify king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman Uttama-Chōḷa</hi>, the 16th year of whose reign is quoted twice in ll. 11 f. and 72 f., with the uncle and immediate predecessor of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I. These references as stated already are the 22nd year of a certain <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> (l. 28 f.), the 9th year of <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Kampavarman</hi> (l. 34 f.) and the 18th year of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, ‘who took <hi rend="bold">Madirai (Madura)</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Īḻam (Ceylon)</hi>’ (l. 96 f.). <hi rend="bold">Vijaya-Kampavarman</hi> has been attributed to the 9th century A.D. by Professor Hultzsch, and <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, ‘who took <hi rend="bold">Madirai</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Īḻam</hi>’ is <hi rend="bold">Madiraikoṇḍa Parāntaka</hi> I.<note>Parāntaka I. was the first of the Chōḷa kings of Tanjore who crushed the power of the Pāṇḍya and captured their capital Madura. The title <hi rend="italic">‘who conquered Madura and Ceylon’</hi> was not assumed by him till a very late period in his reign (see <hi rend="italic">Madras Epigraphical Report</hi> for 1907, paragraphs 32 to 34). The mention of this latter title early in the 18th year of his reign becomes explicable when it is understood that it is only a quotation.</note> whose reign extended over the first half of the 10th century A.D. Consequently the unidentified Parakēsarivarman referred to in l. 28 f. appears to be no other than <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman Vijayālaya</hi>, who was the first of the resuscitated line of the Tanjore Chōḷas and to whom Professor Kielhorn doubtfully attributes certain Chōḷa records from Conjeeveram, Ukkal and Śuchīndram ranging in date from the 4th to the 34th years of his reign<note><hi rend="italic">List of Inscriptions of Southern India</hi>, page 113, Nos. 672 to 675. There is nothing in these records to show definitely that the king Parakēsarivarman referred to is Vijayālaya. The statement in our grant that a stone inscription (<hi rend="italic">śilā-lēkha</hi>) of his 22nd year did provide for permanent income to a temple at Kachchippēḍu is proof enough to show that though he was the first of the new line, Vijayālaya had a peaceful, long and prosperous rule like any of his powerful successors. It is not possible, however, to say that as early as his time the Chōḷa rule extended so far south as Śuchīndram in the Pāṇḍya country.</note> .</p>						
                            
                            <p>The inscription also supplies some valuable information about the town <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the modern Conjeeveram). Four quarters are referred to, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kambuḻāṉpāḍi</hi> (ll. 74 and 88) spelt in the Sanskrit text as Karuvuḷānpāṭi (ll. 1 and 3); <hi rend="bold">Atimāṉappāḍi</hi> (ll. 2 and 75); <hi rend="bold">Kañjagappāḍi</hi> (Sanskrit <hi rend="bold">Kaṁsahappāṭi</hi>) (ll. 1f. and 75 f.) and <hi rend="bold">Eṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> (ll. 2 and 76) which were mostly inhabited by weavers who were patronised by the king (l. 10) and consisted of two sections of <hi rend="italic">paṭṭaśālins</hi>. The appointment of these <hi rend="italic">paṭṭaśālins</hi> as the managers of the temple and the royal patronage extended them suggests the high social status which they must have been enjoying at this early period. Even now the name <hi rend="bold">Piḷḷaipāḷaiyam</hi> given to the weavers’ quarters suggests the favourite position which these weavers occupied either with reference to the temple or to the king—the word <hi rend="italic">piḷḷai</hi> or <hi rend="italic">piḷḷaiyār</hi> being frequently applied in this sense. Mr. Thurston under the heading Śāliyans<note><hi rend="italic">Castes and Tribes</hi>, Vol. VI, page 279.</note> mentions the two main divisions of that class, one of which was <hi rend="italic">paṭṭaśāliyaṉ</hi> evidently the <hi rend="italic">paṭṭaśāliṉ</hi> mentioned above. The Śaiva quarters <hi rend="bold">Raṇajayappāḍi, Ekavīrappāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Vāmanaśaṅkarappāḍi</hi> of Conjeevaram are also mentioned. <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> seems to have been still another such quarter of Conjeeveram in which according to lines 89 to 93 the inhabitants were exempted from all taxes in consideration of their payment of fixed quantities of rice and oil to the temple of <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi>. In this connexion it is also interesting to learn that this quarter of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> was at first inhabited by a class of people known as <hi rend="bold">Tōḷāchcheviyar</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Ēlākkaiyar</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Tōlāchcheviyar</hi> literally means ‘those whose ears are not bored’ and <hi rend="italic">Ēlākkaiyar</hi> ‘those whose hands would not accept gifts’. The first is perhaps the opposite of <hi rend="italic">Karṇaprāvṛitas</hi> mentioned in a Tanjore inscription<note><hi rend="italic">South-Indian Inscriptions</hi>, Vol. II, p. 202, footnote 2.</note> and of <hi rend="italic">Toḷḷaikkādar</hi> a term applied to the tribes of Maravaṉ, Kaḷḷaṉ, Śāṇāṉ, etc., according to Winslow's <hi rend="italic">Tamil Dictionary</hi>. Two other <hi rend="italic">chēris</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> which we learn from the inscription were <hi rend="bold">Tuṇḍuṇukkachchēri</hi> whose lands were watered by the two irrigation channels named respectively ‘the high-level sluice’ and ‘the low level-sluice’ and <hi rend="bold">Vīrappāḍi</hi>. Whether these several quarters (<hi rend="italic">pāḍi</hi> or <hi rend="italic">chēri</hi> in Tamil and <hi rend="italic">vāṭī</hi> or <hi rend="italic">vāṭaka</hi> in Sanskrit) were suburban villages adjoining Conjeeveram or the different quarters of that city cannot be ascertained<note>The names Atimāṉappāḍi, Raṇajayappāḍi and Ēkavīrappāḍi were evidently named after the titles <hi rend="italic">Atimāna, Raṇajaya</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ēkavīra</hi> which were commonly held by Pallava kings. Ēkavīrappāḍi as the name of a <hi rend="italic">chēri</hi> of Kachchippēḍu occurs already in an inscription of Parāntaka I. in the temple of Rājasiṁhēśvara (<hi rend="italic">South- Indian Inscriptions</hi>, Vol. I, No. 145).</note> Conjeeveram must have also been the seat of the king<note>It was the chief capital of the early Chōḷa kings long before the time of Vijayālaya. During the reign of Vijayālaya and his successors, however, it must have been recognized second only to Tanjore.</note> whose palace is referred to in l. 13. The temple of Ūragam (Sanskrit Ūraka) at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> is mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandham</hi> and has been identified by Professor Hultzsch with the present <hi rend="bold">Ulagaḷanda-Perumāḷ</hi> some of whose inscriptions mention the temple by that name. The <hi rend="italic">Karikāla-teṟṟi</hi> hall which formed an important portion of the temple must have been so called after the ancient <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Karikāla</hi>. The present temple of <hi rend="bold">Ulagaḷanda-Perumāḷ</hi> which is in a badly neglected condition shows that the surrounding hall, if at all contemporaneous with the central shrine, must have been renovated in a much later period and could not represent the old <hi rend="italic">Karikāla-teṟṟi</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Kōlnirai-kūli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kālaḷavu-kūli</hi> which were assigned to the temple of Ūragam (l. 15 f.) are explained in the Sanskrit portion (l. 4) as ‘tolls on (<hi rend="italic">articles</hi>) measured by weight (<hi rend="italic">tulā</hi>) and by capacity (<hi rend="italic">prastha</hi>)’. The city had a strong guild of merchants (<hi rend="italic">nagara</hi> l. 110, <hi rend="italic">nagarattār</hi> l. 119, or <hi rend="italic">mānagarattōm</hi> l. 120 f.) who apparently represented the city council with a chief person (<hi rend="italic">mānagaramāḷvāṉ</hi>) at their head. The guild was given full liberty to supervise the proper management of the temple business, to appoint the watchman and clerks of the temple and to exempt these latter from payment of (municipal) taxes. An item of interesting information supplied by the record is that a Brāhmaṇa knowing the <hi rend="italic">Vēdas</hi> was appointed for worship in the temple of Ūragam, only in case a man conversant with the <hi rend="bold">Vaishṇava</hi> system of temple-worship (<hi rend="italic">kōyil-nambu)</hi><note>Dr. Winslow states that <hi rend="italic">nambi</hi> is the son of a Brahman father and a Kshatriya mother and a worshipper of Vishṇu.</note> was not available. Vedic Brāhmaṇas as a rule do not appear to have had anything to do with temple-worship from early times. The details of expenditure recorded in the grant on account of the several festivals were audited by the Chief Merchant and the Annual-Supervision Committee and all difficulties in way of the proper conduct of the charities were to be removed by the Vaishnava devotees of the temple, in the 18 <hi rend="italic">nāḍus</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The geographical names that occur in the inscription, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kūram, Ariyar Perumbākkam, Uḻai-ūr</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Oḻukkaipākkam</hi>, are all situated in the Chingleput district and are respectively identical with <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Āriyaperumbakkam</hi> in the Conjeeveram taluk and <hi rend="bold">Oḻaiyūr</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Oḻukarai</hi> (?) in the Madurantakam taluk. <hi rend="bold">Śikkal</hi> the native village of the officer <hi rend="bold">Śōḻamūvēndavēḷāṉ</hi> is identical with Śikkil near Negapatam in the Tanjore district.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
               
                <p xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:grantha maturity:vernacular">
                    <pb n="1r"/><lb n="1"/>yati sma <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> sa ca teṣāṁ yugmavaṁśapaṭṭaśālinānteṣveva karuvuḷānpāṭikaṁsahappā
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>dyatimānappādy<seg rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">eṟṟuvaḻicce</seg>rītyākhyāteṣu vāṭakeṣu tathā taddhemaśatadvayannyadha
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>tta teṣv<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>va vāṭakeṣvatimānappāṭikaruvu<seg rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">ḷā</seg>npāṭītivāṭakadvayajātāṁstantuvā<unclear>y</unclear>ā
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>ntasyaiva harestulāprasthādimānasambhūtepvarttheṣu hemavṛddhyupanateṣvartthe<supplied reason="omitted">ṣu</supplied>
                    <lb n="5"/>cāyavyayālokināṁ śrīkāryyakṛtāmabhāvāt sa E<supplied reason="omitted">va</supplied> rājā śrīkāryyakara
                    <lb n="6" break="no"/>ṇāya tāneva sva<supplied reason="omitted">ya</supplied>nnyayuṅkta<surplus>ḥ</surplus> <g type="ddanda">.</g> dātavyammāsamātre kuḍubakasahitantaṇḍu
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>laprasthayugmantailaprasthañca <seg rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">coḻā</seg>niyamanilayanairūrakasthatridhāmne <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> nā
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>deyaṁ rājabhāvyaṁ karamiti madhuronmāthinā śūnyabhāvāccoḷenājñāpitai
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>stairatha nagarajanairapyanujñātametat <g type="ddanda">.</g> Āyavyayāvathālikhya co<seg rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">ḻā</seg>niyamavā
                    <lb n="10" break="no"/>sibhiḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> māsakrameṇa caikaikandarśanīyau kuḍumbibhiḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> rājavastrakṛtāmeṣāñcatu
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>rvvāṭanivāsinām <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> hareḥ kāryyaniyuktaiśca sārddhamūrakavāsinaḥ <g type="ddanda">.</g> 
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    
                    <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> koppara
                    <lb n="12" break="no"/>kecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>rāṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>uttamacoḻa<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkku yāṇṭu patiṉāṟāvatu Uṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>
                
                
                    <pb n="1v"/><lb n="13" break="no"/>yār kaccippeṭṭu koyiliṉuḷaḷāl teṟkil cittiramaṇṭapatteḻun
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>taruḷi Irukka Atikārikaḷ coḻamūventaveḷār Emperumāṉ I<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kaccippeṭṭu
                    <lb n="15"/>Ūrakattu niṉṟaruḷiṉa <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkku Ikkaccippeṭṭuk kolniṟaikūliyum kāla
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>ḷavukūliyum Ivarkku pokamāy varum maṟṟum Ittevarkke kaccippeṭṭum tu
                    <lb n="17" break="no"/>ṇ<unclear>ṭu</unclear>ṇukkacceriyilum vilaikoṇṭuṭaiya <hi rend="grantha">bhūmi</hi>yum maṟṟum poli
                    <lb n="18" break="no"/>ūṭṭuḷḷaṉavum muṉpu Ittevarkku nivantañceytilām<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yi
                    <lb n="19" break="no"/>l nivantañ ceyyavum Ikkaccippeṭṭu Iraṇṭu ceri Ittevaruṭai
                    <lb n="20" break="no"/>ya <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāriyaṅ kaṭaikkāṇavum Aruḷicceyvateṉṟu viṇṇappañceyya <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> I
                    <lb n="21" break="no"/>kkaccippeṭṭu Ūrakattu niṉṟaruḷiṉa <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkku Ivvūr kolniṟaikūliyum kālaḷa
                    <lb n="22" break="no"/>vukūliyum vilaikoṇṭuṭaiya <hi rend="grantha">bhūmi</hi>kaḷum poliūṭṭuḷḷaṉavum nīy<unclear>e</unclear>y ni
                    <lb n="23" break="no"/>van=tañceyavīyeṉṟum Ivvūrkkampuḻāṉpāṭiyum Atimāṉappāṭiyum I
                    <lb n="24" break="no"/>vviraṇṭu ceri<unclear>yu</unclear>m I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāriyamā<unclear>r</unclear>āya<unclear>vu</unclear>m Ipparicu nivan<supplied reason="omitted">ta</supplied>ñ ceykave
                    
                    
                    <pb n="2r"/><lb n="25" break="no"/>ṉṟum Aruḷicceyya <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>atikāri cikkaruṭaiyāṉ nakkaṉ kaṇiccaṉāṉa co
                    <lb n="26" break="no"/>ḻamūventaveḷāṉ viṇṇappattāl nivan=tañ ceyvittapaṭi kālaḷa
                    <lb n="27" break="no"/>vukūliyum kolniṟaikūliyum I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var vilaikoṇṭuṭaiya nilaṅkaḷil
                    <lb n="28"/>pokamum I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var poliūṭṭu <hi rend="grantha">śilālekhai</hi>ppaṭi kopparakecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>ṟku
                    <lb n="29"/>yāṇṭu Irupatti<hi rend="grantha">ra</hi>ṇṭāvatu kūrattu <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yārum Ariyaṟperumpākkattu
                    <lb n="30"/><hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yārum koṇṭa poṉ Iruṉūṟṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>mpatiṉ kaḻañciṉukku
                    <lb n="31"/>taṅkaḷūr Eṇṇāḻippoṟkālāl Orāṭṭaināḷaikku Aṭṭakka
                    <lb n="32" break="no"/><supplied reason="omitted">ṭa</supplied>va policai nellu Aiññūṟṟuk kāṭiyum Uḻaiyūr <hi rend="grantha">sabh</hi>aiyār <hi rend="grantha">śilā</hi>
                    <lb n="33" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">le<unclear>kh</unclear>ai</hi>ppaṭi koṇṭa poṉ Aimpatiṉ kaḻañciṉāl Orāṭṭaināḷai
                    <lb n="34" break="no"/>kku <unclear>A</unclear>ḷakka<supplied reason="omitted">ka</supplied>ṭava polic<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>nellu ṉūṟṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>mpatiṉ kāṭiyum ko vi
                    <lb n="35" break="no"/>c<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yakampapa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>ṟku yāṇṭu Oṉpatāvatu Oḻukkai<supplied reason="omitted">p</supplied>pākkattu <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>
                    <lb n="36" break="no"/>yār <hi rend="grantha">śilālekhai</hi>ppaṭi koṇṭukaṭava poṉ Irupattunāṟkaḻañciṉāl Orā
                
                
                    <pb n="2v"/><lb n="37" break="no"/>ṭṭaināḷaikkiṭakkaṭava polic<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>ppoṉ kaḻañce nālumañcāṭiyum ni
                    <lb n="38" break="no"/>vantañ ceytapaṭi <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> tiruvamirtu mūṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku nel mukkuṟuṇi Aṟunāḻiyu
                    <lb n="39" break="no"/>m kaṟiyamutu I<hi rend="grantha">ra</hi>ṇṭukku mūṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku nel nāṉāḻiyum neyyaḻutu nicatam
                    <lb n="40"/>Uḻakkiṉukku nel Aiññāḻiyum tayiramutu potu Uriyāka mūṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku <unclear>ta</unclear>
                    <lb n="41" break="no"/>yiramutu nāḻi Urikku nel muṉṉāḻiyum Aṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>kkāyamutu mūṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku
                    <lb n="42"/>nel muṉṉāḻiyum viṟakiṉukku nel Iru nāḻiyum Ārātikkum
                    <lb n="43"/>veta<hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇaṉ Oruvaṉukku nel patakkum Ivaṉukku puṭavai mutal
                    <lb n="44"/>Orāṭṭaināḷaikku poṉ Ai<unclear>ñ</unclear>kaḻañcum paricārakañ ceyyu māṇi Oruvaṉukku
                    <lb n="45"/>nel Aṟunāḻiyum Ivaṉukku puṭavaimutal Orāṭṭaināḷaikku poṉ
                    <lb n="46"/>kaḻañcum tirumeykāppāṉ Oruvaṉukku nicata nel kuṟuṇiyum Ivaṉu
                    <lb n="47" break="no"/>kku puṭavaimutal Orāṭṭai nāḷaikku po<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied>ṉirukaḻañcum nan=taṉavaṉam Uḻap
                    <lb n="48" break="no"/>pār Iruvarkku nicata nel kuṟuṇi nāṉāḻiyum Ivarkaḷukku puṭavaikku poṉ
                
                
                    <pb n="3r"/><lb n="49"/>kaḻañcum caṅkirān=ti Oṉṟiṉukku <hi rend="grantha">Ācāryya</hi>pūcaṉai Uṭpaṭa poṉ kaḻañceykālā
                    <lb n="50" break="no"/>ka caṅkirān=ti paṉṉiraṇṭiṉukku poṉ patiṉaiṅkaḻañcum tirumeyppūccu
                    <lb n="51" break="no"/>kkum tirupukaikkum tiṅkaḷ Araikkāl poṉṉāka Orāṭṭaināḷaikku
                    <lb n="52"/>poṉ kaḻañcaraiyum tirunamaṉikai mūṉṟukku Ōrāṭṭaināḷaikku po
                    <lb n="53" break="no"/>ṉ mukkālum tiruparicaṭṭam mūṉṟukku Ōrāṭṭaināḷaikku poṉ kaḻañ
                    <lb n="54" break="no"/>cum Ukaccakaḷ talaippaṟai Oṉṟum mattaḷi Iraṇṭum kaṟaṭik<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi> Oṉ
                    <lb n="55" break="no"/>ṟum tāḷam Oṉṟum cekaṇṭikai Oṉṟum kāḷam Iraṇṭum k<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>
                    <lb n="56" break="no"/>maṇi Oṉṟumāka Āḷ Oṉpatiṉukku puṭavaimutaluṭpaṭa Uḻaiūr poli
                    <lb n="57" break="no"/>ūṭṭu nel ṉūṟṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>mpatiṉ kāṭiyum kaccippeṭṭu nakarattār pakkal vilaiko
                    <lb n="58" break="no"/>ṇṭuṭaiya nilattil cittiravallipperuñceṟuvāṉa paṭṭiyum tuṇṭu
                    <lb n="59" break="no"/>ṇukkacceriyil vilaikoṇṭuṭaiya nilattil meṭṭumatakāṟu pāñca
                    <lb n="60"/>cen=taṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>ppottaṉ nilattukku vaṭakkil taṭi muṉṟum<note n="270-1">Read mūṉṟu</note> kāṭāṭikuṇ
                
                
                    <pb n="3v"/><lb n="61" break="no"/>ṭiliṉ vaṭakkil ceṟuvu voṉṟum paḷḷamatakāṟu p<unclear>ā</unclear>ñca nilattuḷ
                    <lb n="62"/>koṉeriyār pokattil vaṭakkil kuṇṭilumāka taṭi Aiñciṉāl pa
                    <lb n="63" break="no"/>ṭṭi nilamumāka Innilam Iraṇṭupaṭṭiyum Ippoliyūṭṭu nel ṉūṟ
                    <lb n="64" break="no"/>ṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>mpatiṉ kāṭiyum Uvaccarkaḷ Oṉpatiṉmarkku nivan=tamākavum tirume
                    <lb n="65" break="no"/>ḻukkiṭuvārkku nicata nel muṉṉāḻiyum karikālateṟṟiyil Iruvar <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>va<unclear>r</unclear>k
                    <lb n="66" break="no"/>ku muṉṟu<note type="repeated" n="270-1"/> <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku nicatamariciyaṟunāḻiyāka nicatamarici kuṟuṇi nā
                    <lb n="67" break="no"/>ṉāḻikku nel mukkuṟuṇi Aṟunāḻiyum kaṟiyamutu muṉṟu<note type="repeated" n="270-1"/> <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=ti<hi rend="grantha"/>
                    <lb n="68" break="no"/>kku nel nāṉāḻiyum viṟakukku nel muṉṉāḻiyum muṉṟu<note type="repeated" n="270-1"/> <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku ney<supplied reason="omitted">ya</supplied>
                    <lb n="69" break="no"/>mutu Uḻakkiṉukku nel <supplied reason="omitted">Ai</supplied>ññāḻiyum Iruvar <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkkum tirunon=tāviḷakki
                    <lb n="70" break="no"/>raṇṭiṉukku ne<supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied>yurikku nel kuṟuṇi nāṉāḻiyum tirumeyppūccukkum
                    <lb n="71"/>tirupukai<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kum tiṅkaḷ mañcāṭippoṉṉāka Orāṭṭaināḷaikku poṉ paṉ
                    <lb n="72" break="no"/>ṉiraṇṭu mañcāṭiyum Ivviruvar <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkkum niva<hi rend="grantha">ndha</hi>mākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> kopparakecaripa
                
                
                    <pb n="4r"/><lb n="73" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>ṟku yāṇṭu patiṉāṟāvatu kaccippe<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭu Ūrakattu niṉṟaruḷiṉa <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varpakkal I
                    <lb n="74" break="no"/>vvūr kampuḻāṉpāṭiyār koṇṭa poṉ Eḻupattumukkaḻañcaraiyum A
                    <lb n="75" break="no"/>timāṉappāṭiyār koṇṭa poṉ Eḻupattumukkaḻañcaraiyum kañ<supplied reason="omitted">ca</supplied>ka
                    <lb n="76" break="no"/>ppāṭiyār koṇṭa poṉ muppattaiṅkaḻañcum Eṟṟuvaḻicceriyār
                    <lb n="77"/>koṇṭa poṉ patiṉeṇkaḻañcum Ākap poṉ Irunūṟṟukkaḻañ
                    <lb n="78" break="no"/>ciṉukku kaḻañciṉvāy piḷavu policaiyāka Orāṭṭainā
                    <lb n="79" break="no"/>ḷaikku van=ta policaippoṉ muppatiṉ kaḻañcu Ippo
                    <lb n="80" break="no"/>ṉ muppatiṉ kaḻañcum I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var cittiraitiruviḻāvukku nivan=tañceyta
                    <lb n="81" break="no"/>paṭi tiruviḻā Eḻunāḷaikkum Eṇṇaikku pon Eḻu kaḻañcum Eḻunāḷaikku nā
                    <lb n="82" break="no"/>ṟupūvum nāṟucāntukkum poṉ Irukaḻañcum Eḻunāḷum koṭṭi cey
                    <lb n="83" break="no"/>yum <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varaṭiyarkku koṟṟukkum pūcaṉaikkumāka poṉ Aiṅkaḻañcum Eḻu
                    <lb n="84" break="no"/>nāḷum <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha">bhoja</hi>ṉattukku Aṉṟāṭa+kattāl<note n="271-1">The symbol + cannot be read as <foreign>ka</foreign> (<foreign>ka</foreign>) nor could it stand for the numeral one (<foreign>ka</foreign>). Probably it is a mark to indicate that the space between <foreign>ṭa</foreign> and <foreign>ka</foreign> left by the engraver by mistake has to be cancelled.</note> neṟkoṇṭu 
                
                
                    <pb n="4v"/><lb n="85"/>Ūṭṭuvatāṉa poṉ patiṉ(k) kaḻañcum <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var paḷḷiccivikai kāvuñcivi
                    <lb n="86" break="no"/>k<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yārkkum ciṟappuvanta Uvaccarkkum Eḻunāḷaikku poṉ kaḻañcum
                    <lb n="87"/>kaṇṭaḻivu poṉ Aiṅkaḻañcu<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> Ākap poṉ ner<supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> tiruviḻāvukku viḷakku pi
                    <lb n="88"/>ṭippārum koṭi Eṭuppārum kampuḻāṉpāṭiyārum Atimāṉappāṭiyārum
                    <lb n="89"/>Eṟṟuvaḻicceriyārum kañcakappāṭiyārum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var ceriyāṉa coḻāniya
                    <lb n="90" break="no"/>mattu muṉpuḷḷa toḷācceviyarāṉa Elākk<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yar Eccaṟṟam<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>
                    <lb n="91" break="no"/>yil Ivvelākk<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yyar <hi rend="grantha">pūrvvamarjjā</hi>ti Iṟai Iṟukka<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kaṭavarallām<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>
                    <lb n="92" break="no"/>yil Iccerikku puṟattuniṉṟu vanteṟiṉa kuṭikaḷai maṉaiyāl tiṅkaḷ nāḻi
                    <lb n="93"/>Uḻakkeṇṇaiyum Irunāḻi Arici<supplied reason="omitted">yu</supplied>m I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkke yiṟaiyāka koṇṭu maṟṟu Inna
                    <lb n="94" break="no"/>karañcuṭṭiṉa Iṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi> Eppeṟpaṭṭatum koḷḷātitākavum Ivarkaḷai Itaṉṟi maṟ
                    <lb n="95" break="no"/>ṟu Iṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi> kāṭṭiṉār keṅk<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi> Iṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>kumari Iṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi> ceytār ceyta pāvaṅ koḷva
                    <lb n="96" break="no"/>tākavum Eṉṟu Ipparicu matir<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yum Īḻamuṅkoṇṭa <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>parakecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>ṟku
                
                
                    <pb n="5r"/><lb n="97"/>yāṇṭu patiṉeṭ<unclear>ṭ</unclear>āvatu Ikkaccippeṭṭu nakarattār ceyta <hi rend="grantha">vya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">sthai</hi>paṭiyey <unclear>I</unclear>
                    <lb n="98"/><hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varum Ivakkaḷai<note n="271-2">Read ivarkaḷai.</note> I<supplied reason="omitted">v</supplied>viṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yeya koḷvatākavum Icceriyār I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>varkku
                    <lb n="99"/>kaṇakku Iṭuvatākavum Ivaṉukku I<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var paṇṭāratte nicatam kuṟuṇi nellum
                    <lb n="100"/>Āṇṭuvarai Irukaḻañcu poṉ Iṭuvatākavum Ivvūr Iraṇa<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yappāṭi Ekavirap
                    <lb n="101"/>pāṭi vāmaṉacaṅkarappāṭiyumāka mūṉṟu cericcaṅkarappāṭiyārum koṇṭa poṉ
                    <lb n="102"/>Irupatiṉ kaḻañciṉāl muṉpu niṉṟa ceriyāre kaṭava non=tāviḷakkon
                    <lb n="103" break="no"/>ṟum coḻ<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>niyamattāraṭṭum Eṇṇai <hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tiviḷakkerippatākavum Iṟa
                    <lb n="104" break="no"/>ṇṭu <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>koyiluḷ tevarkaḷai Uttaramayana<hi rend="grantha">saṅgrā</hi>n=tiyum cittir<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>vi<hi rend="grantha">ṣu</hi>vum <hi rend="grantha">sna</hi>
                    <lb n="105" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">pa</hi>ṉamāṭṭuvataṟkum tiruviḻāviṟku viḷakku piṭippāṟkum koṭi Eṭukkumāḷuk
                    <lb n="106" break="no"/>kum tirumuṟṟam pukunta <hi rend="grantha">paruṣai</hi>nāyaṉmāṟku Arici<note n="271-3">Read tūṇi.</note> tuṇiyum ko<hi rend="grantha">ṣṭi</hi> ceytāṉu
                    <lb n="107" break="no"/>kku Arici<note type="repeated" n="271-3"/>tuṇippatakkum <hi rend="grantha">pūja</hi>ṉaippoṉ Ar<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>kkaḻañcum maṟṟum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>koyiluḷ
                    <lb n="108"/>kuṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>vuḷḷaṉa nivantam pārāte kaṇṭḻivile ceyvatākavum Ittevar <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>k<unclear>ā</unclear>
               
               
                    <pb n="5v"/><lb n="109" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">ryya</hi>m Iṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>yūṟuḷḷaṉa patiṉeṭṭunāṭaṭiyārumē kaṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>kkaṇṭu <note n="271-4">Read tīrttu.</note>tirantukuṭup<unclear>pā</unclear>
                    <lb n="110" break="no"/>rākavum Iññakarattu nakaramāḷvāṉum Āṭṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>vāriyarum Eṟṟuvaḻicceriyārum
                    <lb n="111"/>kañcakappāṭiyārum Ittevar vicam Aḻintatu Āṇṭutoṟum tiruviḻāc ceyta
                    <lb n="112" break="no"/>vaḷave kaṇakku kāṇpatākavum Iccuṭṭappaṭṭa Iraṇṭu ceriyārume tevarpaṇ
                    <lb n="113" break="no"/>ṭārattu vaitta nivantaṅ koṇṭu tirume<supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied>kāppu Iṭuvatākavum Ittevar <hi rend="grantha">śrīkāryya</hi>
                    <lb n="114" break="no"/>m kaṭ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>kkāṇpāraiyum tirumeykāppāṉaiyum kaṇakkeḻutuvāṉai
                    <lb n="115" break="no"/>yum nakarame <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">sthai</hi>ceytu Iṟaikoḷḷappeṟātatākavum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>koyi
                    <lb n="116" break="no"/>lukku <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>koyil nampā<unclear>y</unclear> nirampiṉār<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>p piṟātuviṭil<note n="271-5">Read ppeṟā tuviṭil.</note> vetamva<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied>la <hi rend="grantha">brā</hi>
                    <lb n="117" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">hma</hi>ṇaṉaiye Ārātikka Iṭuvatākavum Ipparicu Atikārañceyvāreva Aṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi><unclear>ō</unclear>
                    <lb n="118" break="no"/>lai ceyteṉ Iññaka<supplied reason="omitted">ra</supplied>ttir virappāṭi <hi rend="grantha">madhyasta</hi>ṉ nāṟpa<supplied reason="omitted">ta</supplied>te<supplied reason="omitted">ṇ</supplied>ṇāyiramaṅkalātitta
                    <lb n="119" break="no"/>neṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ikkaccippeṭṭu nakarattārpakkal vilaikoṇṭa nilam Oloka
                    <lb n="120" break="no"/>mārāyapperuñceṟuvil kiḻakkil meṟ mikutikkuṟ<hi rend="grantha">ai</hi>vu Uṭpaṭa viṟṟukkuṭuttom mā
                    <lb n="121" break="no"/>ṉakarattom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Inta <hi rend="grantha">śāsa</hi>nam Eḻuttu veṭṭiṉa Aṟantāṅki porm<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>u</corr></choice>kaviraṉā 
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app loc="1">
                        <lem>yati sma</lem>
                        <note>It cannot be definitely stated how many plates may be missing before this. The genealogical account, if any, is altogether lost.</note>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="6">
                        <lem><g type="ddanda">.</g></lem>
                        <note>The punctuation is represented by a floral device; see Plate IX.</note>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="9">
                        <lem><g type="ddanda">.</g></lem>
                        <note>The punctuation is represented by a floral device; see Plate IX.</note>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="11">
                        <lem><g type="ddanda">.</g></lem>
                        <note>The punctuation is represented by a floral device; see Plate IX.</note>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="121">
                        <lem>pormikaviraṉā</lem>
                        <note>Read <foreign>pōrmuka</foreign>. Only a few lines are wanting to complete the record; consequently a single plate appears to have been lost at the end.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01">
                
                <p>(Line 1.) . . . . . . . . . and he likewise invested (<hi rend="italic">for interest</hi>) these two hundred pieces of gold in those same quarters (<hi rend="italic">vāṭaka</hi>) called <hi rend="bold">Karuvuḷāṉpāṭi, Kaṁsahappāṭi, Atimāṉappāṭi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ēṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> of those <hi rend="italic">paṭṭasālins</hi> of the two families. There being no managers (<hi rend="italic">śrīkāryakṛit</hi>) to supervise the receipts and expenses of that same (<hi rend="italic">temple of</hi>) Hari (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Vishṇu),—of the income arising out of the interest on gold (<hi rend="italic">invested</hi>) and the tolls on (<hi rend="italic">things</hi>) measured by weight, capacity, <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>., that same king himself appointed for doing the work of (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) management (<hi rend="italic">śrīkārya</hi>) those same weavers born in the two quarters, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Atimāṉappāṭi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Karuvuḻāṉpāṭi</hi> of those same (<hi rend="italic">four</hi>) quarters.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 6.) The Chōḷa (<hi rend="italic">king</hi>) who was the destroyer of <hi rend="bold">Madhurā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Chōḷa Madhurāntaka</hi>) commanded that the residents of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> must give per month two <hi rend="italic">prasthas</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">kuḍubaka</hi> of rice and (<hi rend="italic">one) prastha</hi> of oil to (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tridhāmam</hi> (Vishṇu) standing in (<hi rend="italic">the temple</hi> of) <hi rend="bold">Ūraka</hi> and that no taxes which may be levied by the king be collected (<hi rend="italic">from these</hi>) in consideration of (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) poverty. Thereupon the city-magnates also authorized this. Consequently the house-holders residing in <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi> together with the managers of (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Hari</hi> whose abode is in <hi rend="bold">Ūraka</hi>, must write out in turn one after another the (<hi rend="italic">accounts of</hi>) income and expenditure and show (<hi rend="italic">them</hi>) every month to these weavers of royal garments living in the four quarters (<hi rend="italic">mentioned above</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(L. 11.) In the sixteenth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the glorious king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Chōḷadēva</hi>, when (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) lord was pleased to remain in the (<hi rend="italic">hall called</hi>) Chitra-<hi rend="italic">maṇḍapa</hi> on the southern side within (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) palace<note>Sometimes <foreign>kōyil</foreign> is also taken for a temple; it is doubtful if the king's palace always adjoined a temple or was otherwise connected with it.</note> at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, the officer (<hi rend="italic">adhikāri</hi>). <hi rend="bold">Śōḻamūvēndavēḷār</hi> seeing that no provision for expenses (<hi rend="italic">nibandam</hi>) was previously made for this god, made the request that the king (<hi rend="italic">emberumāṉ</hi>) may be pleased to order that the <hi rend="italic">kōlniṟai-kūli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kālaḷavu-kūli</hi> of this <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> together with the proceeds in the enjoyment of this (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>) from the lands purchased for this same god in <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Tuṇḍuṇukkachchēri</hi> and other (<hi rend="italic">income</hi>) derived by interest (<hi rend="italic">poliyūṭṭu), (may be used</hi>) to provide for the <hi rend="italic">nibandam</hi> of the god who is pleased to stand in (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi><note>This is the name of one of the old temples at Kāñchī mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandham</hi> and refers to the present Ulagaḷanda-Perumāḷ temple (<hi rend="italic">Madras Epigraphical Report</hi> for 1893, page 6).</note> at this <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> and that the two <hi rend="italic">chēris</hi> of this <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> may manage the business (<hi rend="italic">śrīkārya</hi>) of this god.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 21.) (<hi rend="italic">The king</hi>) was pleased to order (<hi rend="italic">as follows):</hi>—“You shall yourself have the (<hi rend="italic">necessary</hi>) provision made for the <hi rend="italic">nibandam</hi> of the god who is pleased to stand in (<hi rend="italic">the temple</hi> <hi rend="italic">of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi> at this <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">from</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">kōlniṟai-kūli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kālaḷavu-kūli</hi> of this village, (<hi rend="italic">from</hi>) the lands acquired (<hi rend="italic">by the temple</hi>) by purchase and (<hi rend="italic">from</hi>) the income derived by interest. The two <hi rend="italic">chēris</hi> of this village, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kambuḻāṉpāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Atimāṉappāḍi</hi>, shall manage the business of this god. In this way shall you carry out the <hi rend="italic">nibandam</hi>.”</p>
                
                <p>(L. 25.) (<hi rend="italic">Thus</hi>) at the request of the officer <hi rend="bold">Nakkaṉ Kaṇichchaṉ</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Mūvēndavēḷāṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Śikkal</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">nibandam</hi>, which was caused to be made (<hi rend="italic">from</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">kālaḷavu-kūli</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">kōlniṟai-kūli</hi>; from the income from the lands purchased by this god; from the five hundred <hi rend="italic">kāḍi</hi> of paddy which (<hi rend="italic">being the income</hi>) as interest of this god according to the investment deed (<hi rend="italic">engraved</hi>) on stone in the 22nd year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> was measured out by (<hi rend="italic">the measure called) eṇṇāḻippoṟkāl</hi> of their village for one year, (<hi rend="italic">as interest</hi>) on the 250 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold deposited with the members of the assemblies of <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ariyar Perumbākkam</hi>; from the one hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāḍi</hi> of paddy which was measured out as interest for one year on fifty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold received by the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Uḻaiyūr</hi> (<hi rend="italic">in the same year of the same king</hi>) according to the deed (<hi rend="italic">engraved</hi>) on stone; and from one <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and four <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold which was paid as interest, for one year, on the twenty-four <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold received by the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Oḻukkaipākkam</hi>, according to the deed (<hi rend="italic">engraved</hi>) on stone in the 9th year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Vijaya Kampavarman</hi>, was thus organised.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 38.) Three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> and six <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for sacred offerings (<hi rend="italic">to be given</hi>) at the three junctures (<hi rend="italic">sandhi) (of the day</hi>); four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for two vegetable offerings (<hi rend="italic">to be given</hi>) at the three junctures (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>); five <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) uḻakku</hi> of the daily ghee offering; three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) nāḻi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of curd which was (<hi rend="italic">to be offered</hi>) at the three junctures (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>) at the rate of one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of curd each time; three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for areca-nut offering at the three junctures; two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for firewood; one <hi rend="italic">padakku</hi> of paddy for one Brāhmaṇa who knows the Vēdas and performs worship; five <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold (<hi rend="italic">given</hi>) to this man as cloth money (<hi rend="italic">puḍavai-mudal</hi>) for the period of one year; six <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for one <hi rend="italic">māṇi</hi> who does service (<hi rend="italic">in the temple</hi>); one <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold (<hi rend="italic">given</hi>) to this man as cloth money (<hi rend="italic">puḍavai-mudal</hi>) for the period of one year; one <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy daily for one man who watches the sacred images (<hi rend="italic">of the temple</hi>); two <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold (<hi rend="italic">given</hi>) to this man as cloth money (<hi rend="italic">puḍavai-mudal</hi>) for the period of one year; one <hi rend="italic">kuṛuṇi</hi> and four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy per day for two persons who work in the flower garden; (<hi rend="italic">one) kaḻañju</hi> of gold (<hi rend="italic">given</hi>) to these for cloth<note>The words ‘for the period of one year’ are omitted here by mistake.</note> ; fifteen <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold for the twelve <hi rend="italic">Saṁkrāntis</hi> at the rate of (<hi rend="italic">one) kaḻañju</hi> and a quarter of gold for each <hi rend="italic">Saṁkrānti</hi>, including the priests’ honorarium (<hi rend="italic">āchārya-pūjaṉai</hi>); (one) <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and a half of gold for a period of one year for (<hi rend="italic">sandal-paste</hi>) rubbed over the sacred body (<hi rend="italic">of the god</hi>) and sacred smoke (<hi rend="italic">incense</hi>), at the rate of one-eighth <hi rend="italic">poṉ</hi> per month; three-quarters of a <hi rend="italic">poṉ</hi> for the period of one year for three sacred baths (<hi rend="italic">namanigai); (one) kaḻañju</hi> of gold for the period of one year for three sacred cloths. One hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāḍi</hi> of paddy (<hi rend="italic">which is the income</hi>) by interest (<hi rend="italic">measured out</hi>) by <hi rend="bold">Uḻai-ūr</hi> (<hi rend="italic">were assigned</hi>) inclusive of cloth money to nine persons of musicians (<hi rend="italic">ugachchagal), viz</hi>., one (<hi rend="italic">who beats</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">talaipparai</hi>, two drummers (<hi rend="italic">mattaḷi</hi>), one (<hi rend="italic">who beats</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">karaḍigai</hi>, one (<hi rend="italic">who strikes</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">tāḷam</hi>, one (<hi rend="italic">who beats</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">śegaṇḍigai</hi>, two (<hi rend="italic">who blow</hi>) the trumpets and one (<hi rend="italic">who sounds</hi>) the hand-bell (<hi rend="italic">kai-maṇi</hi>). One <hi rend="italic">paṭṭi (of land</hi>) called <hi rend="italic">Śittiravallipperuñjeru (included</hi>) in the lands purchased from the merchants (<hi rend="italic">nagarattār</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) paṭṭi</hi> of land of five <hi rend="italic">taḍis</hi>, consisting of three <hi rend="italic">taḍis (included</hi>) in the land purchased at <hi rend="bold">Tuṇḍuṇukkachchēri</hi> which lies to the north of the land of <hi rend="bold">Śendaraippottaṉ</hi> and is irrigated by the channel which flows from the high level sluice, of one <hi rend="italic">śeruvu</hi> to the north of the (<hi rend="italic">field) Kāḍāḍi-kuṇḍil</hi> and of (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṇḍil</hi> to the north of (<hi rend="italic">the land which is in the</hi>) enjoyment of <hi rend="bold">Kōṉēriyār</hi> and is (<hi rend="italic">included</hi>) in the lands irrigated by the channel which flows from the low-level sluice,—in all, these two <hi rend="italic">paṭṭis</hi> of land and the above-mentioned one hundred and fifty <hi rend="italic">kāḍis</hi> of interest-paddy shall provide the expenses (<hi rend="italic">nibanda</hi>) on account of the nine persons who form the musical troupe. Three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy (<hi rend="italic">were provided</hi>) daily to those who smear (<hi rend="italic">the temple</hi>) with cow dung. Also (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) are to be the expenses (<hi rend="italic">nibanda</hi>) of the two gods mentioned below:— three <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> and six <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy on account of the two gods in the sculptured hall of <hi rend="bold">Karikāla (Karikāla-teṟṟi)</hi>, at <hi rend="italic">six nāḻi</hi> of rice (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) one (<hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi>) and four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice (<hi rend="italic">to be offered respectively</hi>) at the three junctures daily (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>) to (<hi rend="italic">each of</hi>) these two gods; four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for vegetable offerings (<hi rend="italic">to be given</hi>) at the three junctures (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>); three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for firewood; five <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) uḻakku</hi> of ghee-offering (<hi rend="italic">required</hi>) at the three junctures (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>); one <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> and four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for (<hi rend="italic">one) uri</hi> of ghee (<hi rend="italic">required</hi>) for two sacred perpetual lamps to the two gods; twelve <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of gold for (<hi rend="italic">sandal paste</hi>) rubbed over the sacred body (<hi rend="italic">of the images</hi>) and for the sacred smoke (<hi rend="italic">incense</hi>) for the period of one year at the rate of (<hi rend="italic">one) mañjāḍi</hi> of gold per month.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 72.) In the 16th year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, from the god who was pleased to stand (<hi rend="italic">in the temple</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Ūragam</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi>, the residents of <hi rend="bold">Kambuḻāṉpāḍi</hi> (<hi rend="italic">a quarter</hi>) of this village, received 73 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and a half of gold; the residents of (<hi rend="italic">the quarter</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kañjagappāḍi</hi> received 35 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold and the residents of (<hi rend="italic">the quarter</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Eṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> received 18 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold. (<hi rend="italic">Thus</hi>) for the total gold of 200 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi>, the interest which accrues for the period of one year at the rate of one <hi rend="italic">piḷavu</hi><note>The word generally means a split or fraction. Dr. Winslow gives it as being equal to one half of a <hi rend="italic">kundumaṇi</hi> (weight) of gold.</note> on each <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju (for a month</hi>), was thirty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold. These thirty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold were used in providing for the expenses (<hi rend="italic">nibanda</hi>) of the <hi rend="italic">Śittirai-tiruviḻā (festival</hi>) of this god in the following manner:—7 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold for oil (<hi rend="italic">required</hi>) for the seven days of the festival, 2 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold for sweet-smelling flowers and scented sandalpaste on (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) seven days; 5 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold for food and presents to the devotees who form the <hi rend="italic">koṭṭi (gōshṭhī)</hi><note>The words <foreign>tevaraṭiyār</foreign> and <foreign>koṭṭi</foreign> may also be taken in the sense of dancing girls and some particular form of their dance; but this is not likely, for then the word <foreign>pūcaṉai</foreign> ‘worship’ would not have been used in connexion with the temple dancing girls.</note> during (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) seven days; 10 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold for the food of the Brāhmaṇas during (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) seven days by purchasing paddy . . . . . <note><foreign>aṉṟāṭakattāl </foreign> of the original is not intelligible.</note> and feeding (<hi rend="italic">them); (one) kaḻañju</hi> of gold for the palanquin-bearers who carry the palanquin of the bedchamber of the god and for the musicians invited for the seven days of the festival; and 5 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold for miscellaneous expenses. Thus the gold being equal (<hi rend="italic">to the expenses specified</hi>), the lamp-bearers and flag-hoisters for the festival (<hi rend="italic">shall be</hi>) the residents of <hi rend="bold">Kambuḻāṉpāḍi, Atimāṉappāḍi, Ēṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kañjagappāḍi</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 89.) Whereas <hi rend="bold">Toḷāchcheviyar</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Ēlākkaiyar</hi>, the former residents of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">chēri (quarter</hi>) of this god, have decreased in numbers and these <hi rend="bold">Ēlākkaiyar</hi> are unable to pay taxes as per old custom, the inhabitants who come from outside this <hi rend="italic">chēri</hi> and settle (<hi rend="italic">in it) (shall</hi>) give (<hi rend="italic">one) nāḻi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) uḻakku</hi> of oil and two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice per house per month as tax (<hi rend="italic">payable</hi>) only to this god, and shall not pay any other taxes fixed by the town magnates. Those who show (<hi rend="italic">in the books</hi>) against them any taxes other than the said (<hi rend="italic">taxes</hi>) shall incur the sin committed by the people who commit (<hi rend="italic">sin</hi>) between Gaṅgā (the Ganges) and Kumari (Cape Comorin).</p>
                
                <p>(L. 96.) Thus this god shall receive these taxes from these inhabitants in the manner described above, according to the very settlement (<hi rend="italic">vyavasthai</hi>) made by the merchants of this <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu</hi> in the eighteenth year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) the glorious <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> who took <hi rend="bold">Madirai</hi> (Madura) and <hi rend="bold">Īḻam</hi> (Ceylon). The accounts of this god shall be maintained by (<hi rend="italic">one of</hi>) the inhabitants of this <hi rend="italic">chēri</hi> and he shall be paid from the treasury of this god (<hi rend="italic">one) kuṟuṇi</hi> of paddy per day and two <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold per year.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 100.) The <hi rend="bold">Śaṅkarappāḍiyāṟ</hi><note>The term Śaṅkarappāḍi appears to be a general name applied to the quarter in which the <hi rend="italic">śaivas</hi> of a town lived.</note> of the three quarters, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Raṇajayappāḍi, Ēkavīrappāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Vāmana-Śaṅkarappāḍi</hi> of this village having received twenty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold shall burn one perpetual lamp which these inhabitants of the above-mentioned quarters have agreed (<hi rend="italic">to do</hi>) and an evening lamp from the oil supplied by the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻāniyamam</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 103.) For bathing the gods in the two sacred temples (<hi rend="italic">śrīkōyil) (on the occasion of) Uttaramayana</hi> (Uttarāyaṇa)-Saṁkrānti and <hi rend="italic">Śittirai</hi>-Vishu, for the lamp bearers and the man who hoists the flag during (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) festivals and for the chiefs of the assembly (<hi rend="italic">parushai</hi>) who enter the sacred court (<hi rend="italic">of the temple, to supervise</hi>), one <hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi> of rice (<hi rend="italic">has been provided</hi>); for one who organises the <hi rend="italic">gōshṭhi<note>A term applied to the congregation of devotees who sing the glory of the god, either Śiva or Vishṇu.</note> , (one) tūṇi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) padakku</hi> of rice; and half a <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold as honorarium (<hi rend="italic">for the same</hi>). Other items (<hi rend="italic">of expense</hi>) in the sacred temple which are omitted (<hi rend="italic">to be mentioned</hi>) shall be met from miscellaneous expenditure, without taking note of the provision (<hi rend="italic">nibanda) (made above</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(L. 108.) The (<hi rend="italic">Śrīvaishṇava</hi>) devotees of the 18 <hi rend="italic">nāḍu</hi> shall alone supervise and set right all obstructions to the management of the (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) business of these gods. The Chief Merchant (<hi rend="italic">nagaram-āḻvāṉ</hi>) of this guild (<hi rend="italic">nagara), (the members of the</hi>) Annual Supervision Committee (<hi rend="italic">āṭṭai-vāriyar</hi>), the residents of <hi rend="bold">Ēṟṟuvaḻichchēri</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kañjagappāḍi</hi>, shall, every year, look into the accounts of the expenses (<hi rend="italic">incurred</hi>) on (<hi rend="italic">viśam</hi><note>The word <foreign>vicam</foreign> is not found in Dr. Winslow's <hi rend="italic">Tamil Dictionary</hi>. It may stand for <foreign>vīcam</foreign> in which case <foreign>vīcam aḻintatu</foreign> would mean the smallest amount spent.</note> ) these gods, soon after the festivals are celebrated. The residents of the above-mentioned two <hi rend="italic">chēris</hi> alone shall provide for the watch of the sacred images as per the settlement (<hi rend="italic">nibandam</hi>) deposited in the treasury of the gods.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 113.) The mercantile guild shall itself choose the superintendent of the sacred business (<hi rend="italic">in the temple</hi>) of these gods, the watchman of the sacred images and the accountant and shall not receive (<hi rend="italic">any</hi>) taxes (<hi rend="italic">from them</hi>). If persons fully knowing the (<hi rend="italic">duties of</hi>) worship in sacred temples are not obtainable for (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) sacred temple, a Brāhmaṇa versed in the Vēdas shall alone be appointed to perform the worship.</p>
                
                <p>(L. 117.) Thus at the command of the officers, I, <hi rend="bold">Nāṟpatteṇṇāyira Maṅgalādittaṉ</hi>, an arbitrator (<hi rend="italic">madhyastha</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Vīrappāḍi</hi> of this city, executed (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, wrote) this document (<hi rend="italic">aṟai-ōlai</hi>) by order. (<hi rend="italic">This is</hi>) my writing. We (<hi rend="italic">the members</hi>) of the great guild of merchants sold with excess and deficiency (<hi rend="italic">in measurement</hi>), the land (<hi rend="italic">lying</hi>) east to west<note><hi rend="italic">Kiḻakkilmēṟ</hi> may perhaps be a mistake for <foreign>kiḻakkil mēṭu</foreign>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the high ground on the eastern side.</note> in the (<hi rend="italic">field</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Lōkamārāyapperuñjeru</hi> (<hi rend="italic">which we had</hi>) purchased from the citizens of this <hi rend="bold">Kachchippēḍu. Arantāṅgi Pōrmugavīraṉ</hi>. . . . who engraved the letters of this charter (<hi rend="italic">śāsanam</hi>). . . . . . . . .</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 3.128 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">264-276</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">128</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="plate">IX-X</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
