<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.96: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 96.—ON THE SOUTH WALL OF THE MANDAPA IN FRONT OF THE CENTRAL SHRINE IN THE CHANDRASEKHARA TEMPLE AT TIRUCHCHENDURAI. No. 316 of 1903.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0096</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>In this inscription which is dated in the 3rd year of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, we have a reference to the construction of the Śiva temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruchchenduṟai</hi> which was a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> suburb of <hi rend="bold">Īśānamaṅgala</hi>, by <hi rend="bold">Pūḍi Ādichchapiḍāriyār (Ādityapiḍāri)</hi>. This lady is here distinctly called the daughter of <hi rend="bold">Teṉṉavaṉ Iḷaṅgōvēḷār</hi> (another name of <hi rend="bold">Maṟavaṉ Pūdiyār)</hi><note n="228-3"><hi rend="italic">Madras Epigraphical Report</hi> for 1908, page 88, paragraph 90.</note> and the queen of <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsariyār</hi>, the son of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I.). Consequently, <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> to whose reign the record belongs is <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I. It may be noted that the 60 <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold granted by <hi rend="bold">Pūdi Ādichchapiḍāri</hi> for sacred offerings to the god, was weighed by a stone called after <hi rend="bold">Veḍēlviḍugu</hi> which was the surname of the Pallava king <hi rend="bold">TeḷḷāṟṟeṟindaNandippōttaraiyar</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">sasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi>ko<note n="228-4">ā symbol resembling the ṭamil letter <hi rend="italic">ō</hi> is inserted between <hi rend="italic">kō</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pa</hi>.</note> parakecaripaṉmmakku<note n="228-5">Read paṉmarkku.</note> yāṇṭu 3 Āva
<lb n="2" break="no"/>tu Ivvāṇṭu coḻaperumāṉaṭikaḷ makaṉār Arikulakeca
<lb n="3" break="no"/>riyār <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>viyār teṉṉavaṉiḷaṅkoveḷār makaḷār pūtiāticca
<lb n="4" break="no"/>piṭāriyār piramateyam piramateyam<note n="228-6">piramateyam is repeated twice by mistake.</note> Īcāṉamaṅkalattu tiru
<lb n="5" break="no"/>ccentuṟai tām Eṭuppicca kaṟṟaḷi perumāṉaṭikaḷukku ceṉṉaṭai
<lb n="6" break="no"/>tiruvamutukku mutalāka kuṭutta veṭelviṭukukallāl tuḷaippoṉ A
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ṟupatiṉ kaḻañcu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Ivvaṟupatiṉ kaḻañcu poṉṉum Īcāṉamaṅkalat
<lb n="8" break="no"/>tu paruṭaiyom koṇṭu Ippoṉṉāl palicai kaḻañciṉvāy pūvi
<lb n="9" break="no"/>l tūṇi patakku nellāka Āṭṭu Aṟupati<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> kala nel cūlakāllāl<note n="229-1">Read cūlakkālāl.</note> kārttikaiy
<lb n="10"/>Akappaṭa muppatiṉ kalamum picāṉam paṅkūṉi<note n="229-2">Read paṅkuṉi.</note> Aka<supplied reason="omitted">p</supplied>paṭa mu<supplied reason="omitted">p</supplied>patiṉ kala
<lb n="11" break="no"/>mum Āka nel Aṟupatin kalamum <hi rend="grantha">cantrāditya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">t</hi> Aṭṭuvomāṉo<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied>
<lb n="12"/>pariṭaiyyom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> pa<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>teṭṭu kuttal paḻavarici kuṟuṇi nāḷ tiruvamu<supplied reason="omitted">tu</supplied>kkum Uccam
<lb n="13" break="no"/>potaikkummāka<note n="229-3">Read kumāka.</note> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Itu paṉmā<hi rend="grantha">heśvarara</hi>k<hi rend="grantha">kṣai</hi><note n="229-4">Cancel the syllable ka.</note> <hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! In the 3rd year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman, Pūdi Ādichchapiḍāriyār</hi>, daughter of <hi rend="bold">Teṉṉavaṉ Iḷaṅgōvēḷār</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) queen of <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsariyār</hi> (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the son of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I.), gave, in this year, sixty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of (<hi rend="italic">pure gold called) tuḷaippoṉ<note n="229-5"><hi rend="italic">Tuḷaippoṉ</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tuḷainiraippoṉ</hi>, sometimes also preceded by the name of the stone on which it was tested or by which it was weighed, was apparently a term for pure gold. This is explained by the passage <ta>cuṭṭu veṭṭic cūṭukku tantu kāccāṟṟik kaicelvatu kaḻañciṟpertta tuḷaippoṉ uraiyum tuḷaiyum vaḻuvātatu. • • nakarakkallāl. • • poṉ</ta>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the gold <ta>tuḷaipoṉ</ta> which was heated, cut, melted (?), cooled after melting and made current, cut off from the <hi rend="italic">kalañju</hi>, which was neither wanting in fineness nor in <hi rend="italic">tuḷai</hi> (impression ?) and which was tested or weighed by the city stone.” It occurs in a record of Rājarāja I. (No. 218 of 1911). It was evidently a practice to allow the currency of gold in any transaction only after putting it to test by special officers appointed for the purpose. It may therefore be presumed that <hi rend="italic">tuḷaippoṉ</hi> represented gold that had passed through this test. It is not unlikely also that an impression was always left on such gold as a hall-mark.</note> (weighed</hi>) by the (<hi rend="italic">standard</hi>) stone <hi rend="bold">Veḍēlviḍugu</hi>,<note n="229-6">The correct form of this word is Viḍēlviḍugu which is the surname of Teḷḷāṟṟeṟinda Nandippōttaraiyar.</note> as capital (<hi rend="italic">from which</hi>) sacred offerings at the holy shrine (<hi rend="italic">śeṉṉaḍai) (have to be provided</hi>) to the lord of the stone temple constructed by her at <hi rend="bold">Tiruchchenduṟai</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a hamlet</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Īśāṉamaṉgala</hi> which was a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 7.) And we, (<hi rend="italic">the members of</hi>) the assembly (<hi rend="italic">paruḍai</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Īśāṉamaṅgala</hi>, having received this sixty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold, we (<hi rend="italic">the members of</hi>) the assembly agreed to measure out as long as the moon and the sun (<hi rend="italic">endure</hi>), sixty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy per year (<hi rend="italic">measured</hi>) by the <hi rend="italic">śūlakkāl, viz</hi>., thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> at the end of <hi rend="italic">Kārttigai</hi> and thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> in the harvest (<hi rend="italic">piśāṉam</hi>) at the end of Paṅguṉi—in all sixty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy—as interest on this gold (<hi rend="italic">calculated</hi>) at (<hi rend="italic">the rate of) (one) tūṇi</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one) padakku</hi> of paddy on (<hi rend="italic">one) kaḻañju</hi> for (<hi rend="italic">each) pū (crop</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 12.) One <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of old rice pounded ten or eight times shall be (<hi rend="italic">used each day</hi>) for (<hi rend="italic">providing</hi>) sacred offerings at the dawn (<hi rend="italic">nāḷ</hi>) and in the mid-day (<hi rend="italic">uchcham). (The assembly of</hi>) all <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvaras</hi> shall protect this (<hi rend="italic">charity</hi>).</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.96 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">228-229</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">96</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
