<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.156: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 156.—ON THE NORTH WALL OF THE CENTRAL SHRINE IN THE KHARAPURISVARA TEMPLE AT TIRUPPARKADAL. No. 692 of 1904.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0156</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This record refers to a number of committees which comprised the great assembly of <hi rend="bold">Kāviripākkam</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Amaninārāyaṇa-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>. These were <hi rend="italic">saṁvatsara-vāriyam, tōṭṭa-vāriyam, ēri-vāriyam, kaḻaṉi-vāriyam, pañchavāra-vāriyam, kaṇakku-vāriyam, kaliṅgu-vāriyam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">taḍivaḻi-vāriyam</hi>. Besides these, the assembly included a general body of <hi rend="italic">bhaṭṭas</hi> (learned Brāhmaṇas) of the village, the <hi rend="italic">‘ruler’ (i.e., the headman</hi>) of the village and the overseer. Perhaps the two last-mentioned personages were the representatives of Government in the village assembly. An elaborate description of the formation of the village assemblies during the time of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I. is given in the two <hi rend="bold">Uttaramallūr</hi> inscriptions published by Rai Bahadur V. Venkayya in the <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey Report</hi> for 1904-05.</p>						

						<p>In the 3rd year of king <hi rend="bold">Pārthivēndrādivarman</hi>, the village assembly received a petition from one of the trustees of the temple stating that a garden and a field which were the <hi rend="italic">archanābhōga</hi> of the god of <hi rend="bold">Tirukkarapuram</hi> had been lying waste, being silted up by sand by the breaches in the river. The assembly directed the <hi rend="italic">kaḻaṉi-vāriyam</hi> committee to grant 1,400 <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> of land from the village <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi> which was lying untaxed. The term <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi> perhaps corresponds to the present <hi rend="italic">poramboke</hi> and the right vested in the village assemblies to dispose of such land deserves to be specially noted.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> k<unclear>o</unclear> pā<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>ttive<hi rend="grantha">ndr<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice></hi><unclear>tipa</unclear>nma<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>kku <unclear>y</unclear>āṇṭu muṉṟā<unclear>va</unclear>tu nā<unclear>ḷ</unclear> muppa<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>toṉpatāvatu paṭuvū<unclear>r</unclear>koṭṭattu kāvi<unclear>ri</unclear>pākkamākiya Amaninārāya<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>ṇaca</unclear></hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvve</hi>timaṅkala<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tuḷ Ivvāṭ<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ai <hi rend="grantha">sam<supplied reason="omitted">va</supplied>ssa</hi>ravāriya<note n="328-1">Read va<hi rend="grantha">tsa</hi>ra.</note> 
<lb n="2" break="no"/>perumakkaḷum toṭṭavāriyaperumakkaḷum <unclear>E</unclear>rivāriyaperumakkaḷum kaḻanivāriyaperumakkaḷum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vaṭaviranāraṇaperu<unclear>ma</unclear>kkaḷum <unclear>pa</unclear><hi rend="grantha">ñca</hi>vāravāriyaperumakkaḷum kaṇakkuvāriyaperumakkaḷum kaliṅkuvāriyaperuma
<lb n="3" break="no"/>kkaḷum taṭivaḻivāriyaperumakkaḷum <hi rend="grantha">bhaṭṭa</hi>rkaḷum vi<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>śi</unclear>ṭṭa</hi>rkaḷum U<unclear>ḷ</unclear>ḷiṭṭa<note n="328-2">Read <hi rend="grantha">mahā</hi>.</note> mā<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>hāsabhai</unclear></hi>yum <unclear>Ū</unclear>rāḷkinṟa pallavaṉ <hi rend="grantha">bra<unclear>hmā</unclear></hi>tarayaṉum kaṇkāṇi Arumpākiḻāṉum Ivūr <unclear>pe</unclear>ri<unclear>yata</unclear>ḷi Api<hi rend="grantha">ṣe</hi>kamaṇṭapatte (kūṭirukka)
<lb n="4"/>kūṭi Irukka <unclear>Ittāṉa</unclear>(m)muṭaiya civa<hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇaṉ <hi rend="grantha">māgaṇḍa</hi>naṉ perumāḷ tiruk<unclear>karapura</unclear>ttu perumāṉ Aṭi<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku A<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>ccaṉāpoka<unclear>mā</unclear>ṉa toṭṭamum pulamum Āṟu Uṭ<unclear>aintu</unclear> <unclear>ma</unclear>ṇal Iṭṭu kiṭanti<unclear>t</unclear>eṉṟu viṇṇappam ceya
<lb n="5"/><hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi><unclear>yārum</unclear> Ivvā<unclear>ṭṭ</unclear>ai kaḻa<unclear>ni</unclear>vāriyaperumakka(ḷ)ḷe I<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tirukarapura<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tu perumā(ṉ)ṉaṭikaḷ<note n="328-3">Read arccaṉā.</note> Accinā<hi rend="grantha">bhoga(m)</hi>māṉa <hi rend="grantha">bhū</hi>mi maṇal Iṭṭu <unclear>ke</unclear>ṭṭu kiṭanta <hi rend="grantha">bhūmi</hi><unclear>yo</unclear>ṭu In<unclear>nila</unclear>m ka<unclear>ḻa</unclear>niko(l)lā<unclear>l</unclear> Āyirattu nānū<unclear>ṟu</unclear> kuḻi
<lb n="6"/>Ūrma<supplied reason="omitted">ñ</supplied>ci<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kamāna <hi rend="grantha">bhū</hi>mi nokki kal naṭṭu cilāle<unclear>k</unclear>aiy ce<unclear>ytukoḷ</unclear>ka Eṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi> tirumukamaruḷi<unclear>ce</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied><unclear>ta</unclear> tirumu<supplied reason="omitted">kat</supplied>tiṉpaṭi kaḻanivāriyaperumakkaḷom tirukarapura<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tu <unclear>peru</unclear>māṉ Aṭikaḷukku<note n="328-4">Read <hi rend="grantha">arcca</hi>.</note> <hi rend="grantha">Acci</hi>nā<hi rend="grantha"/>
<lb n="7" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">bhogam</hi> ceyvatāna <hi rend="grantha">bhūmi</hi> I<supplied reason="omitted">v</supplied>vūr piṭākai Occe<unclear>ri</unclear> vaṭakaḻaṉi ma<hi rend="grantha">hā</hi>tavāy<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kāl teṟku Ūrma<hi rend="grantha">ñci</hi>kka<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> Āy varici<unclear>la</unclear>ttu kiṭanta <hi rend="grantha">bhū</hi>mikku kiḻpāṟkellai mā<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kāṭṭuccomā<unclear>ci pū</unclear>mikku
<lb n="8"/>merkum teṉpār<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kellai Ūr ma<hi rend="grantha">ñci</hi>kkamāy kiṭan<supplied reason="omitted">ta</supplied> meṭṭu<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku vaṭakkum melpār<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kellai tirupaṉṟi<hi rend="grantha">śva</hi>ra<unclear>ttu</unclear> tirumulaṭṭāṉa<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tu perumā(ṉ)ṉaṭikaḷ Utamātampaṭṭikku kiḻakku<unclear>m</unclear> vaṭapāṟkellai _<note n="328-5">māta may be a contraction of ma<hi rend="grantha">hā</hi>ta which occurs in line 7.</note> mā
<lb n="9" break="no"/>tavāy<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kālu<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku teṟkum I<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>nālpālkellaiyum Uḷḷakappaṭṭa nilam kaḻaṉikolāl nāṉūṟu kuḻiyum I<unclear>ta</unclear>ṉ teṟkil Ūrma<hi rend="grantha">ñci</hi>kamāṉa meṭṭuciṟukaruke<unclear>cu</unclear>vakaḻani tirunā<supplied reason="omitted">ra</supplied>ṇavāykkāl va
<lb n="10" break="no"/>ṭaciṟaku Ūrmañcikkamāy varicilattu kiṭanta pūmi kiḻpā(la)ṟke<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied>lai Aṅkārai mātevapaṭṭar pūmi melaruke poṉa naṭaikālukku meṟku teṉpālkel<unclear>lai</unclear> tirunāraṇavāy<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kāliṉ vaṭakkum melpālke<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied>lai Aiyaṉ perumān pūmi<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku kiḻakku vaṭapārke<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied>lai muṭumpaippoṟkūḷi pūmikku vaṭa<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kum<note n="328-6">Read nāṟpālellai.</note> nālpālle yuḷḷakappa<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭa nilam ka
<lb n="11" break="no"/>ḻaṉikolāl nānūṟu kuḻiyum I<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kāl teṉ<unclear>ci</unclear>ṟaku <unclear>Ū</unclear>r ma<hi rend="grantha">ñci</hi>kamāy varicilattu kiṭanta pūmikku kiḻpārkellai variciraiyāy kiṭanta pūmi<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku merkum tenpārkellai Avaṭṭai kiḻavan nilamā<unclear>na</unclear> comāci pūmi<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku Itaṉ kiḻa<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kil kuṇṭilu<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kum va<unclear>ṭa</unclear>kkum melpārkellai Eṭukkuppaṭṭikaḷum Ikuṭi kāḷaya<unclear>comāci</unclear>pūmi<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku kiḻa<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kum kālu<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku teṟkum nāl pāl Ellai <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> 
<lb n="12"/>yum Āka mānilam kaḻanikolāl Aṟunūṟu kuḻiyum Āka Āyirattu nānūṟu kuḻiyum I<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tirukarapurattu perumāṉ Aṭikaḷukku nicatam Irunāḻi Ariciyāl Oru poḻu<supplied reason="omitted">tu</supplied> tiru Amutukkum <unclear>mun</unclear>ṟu <hi rend="grantha">sandhi</hi>yum Oru viḷa<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku koḷittikoṇṭu tiruā<supplied reason="omitted">rā</supplied>tiṉai cey<unclear>va</unclear>tarkumāka <unclear>ca</unclear><hi rend="grantha">ntrā</hi>ti<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>takālamum Iṟaiili A<hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>cca</hi>nā<hi rend="grantha">bhoga</hi>māka vaiccu cilālekai ceytu kal naṭṭu kuṭu<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tom ca <hi rend="grantha">bhai</hi>yār <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> ku <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> 
<lb n="13"/>Ivvāṭ<supplied reason="omitted">ṭ</supplied><hi rend="grantha">ai</hi> kaḻanivāriyaperumakkaḷom Itu kuṟiyuḷḷiruntu paṇi keṭṭu cilālekai Eḻutineṉ I<supplied reason="omitted">v</supplied>vāṭṭai kaḻanivāriya kaṇa<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kaṉ maṇimaṅkalamuṭaiyāṉ kaṅkātaramā
<lb n="14" break="no"/>yilaṭṭiyeṉ Ivai Eṉṉeḻuttu Itu kuṟiyuḷḷiruntu paṇi keṭ<unclear>ṭeḻuti</unclear>neṉ <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> kaṇa<supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>kan<note n="329-1">Read <hi rend="grantha">madhyastha</hi>ṉ.</note> <hi rend="grantha">madhya</hi>ttataṉ vāmaṉa <unclear>Ē</unclear>ḻāyirava(ṉ)neṉ Itu kuṟiyiliruntu pa<unclear>ṇikka Eḻu</unclear>
<lb n="15"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> ṭṭi kuṟi <gap reason="lost" quantity="4" unit="character"/> kal <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> Āti<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>ta Eḻāyiravaṉṉe<note n="329-2">Read yiravaṉēṉ.</note> Itu kuṟiyiliruntu paṇi keṭṭu Eḻutineṉ
<lb n="16"/>kaṇavatiyen Itu kuṟiyuḷḷiruntivv<unclear>ā</unclear>rikapperumakkaḷ paṇippa Eḻutiṉeṉ <hi rend="grantha">madhyastha</hi>ṉ maṅkala<hi rend="grantha">se</hi>ṉāpati <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> vaṉ Eḻāyiranilaiyalaṅkaṉ kaṟpakātittaṉeṉ [<g type="ddanda">.</g>] Itu kuṟiyuḷḷiruntivvārikapperumakkaḷ paṇippa <hi rend="grantha"> <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/> madhya<unclear>stha</unclear></hi> n <gap reason="lost" quantity="8" unit="character"/> kuṟi yuḷḷiruntivvārikapperumakkaḷ paṇikka Eḻutineṉ <hi rend="grantha">madhyasta</hi>ṉeṭṭi <gap reason="lost" quantity="8" unit="character"/> 
<lb n="17"/>kkuṟi <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāve<supplied reason="omitted">ri</supplied>maṅkala teraṉeṉ [<g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dash">.</g>]
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! In the 3rd year and the 39th day (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of king <hi rend="bold">Pārthivēndrādivarman</hi>, the great assembly of <hi rend="bold">Kāviripākkam</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Amaninārāyaṇa-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a village</hi>) in <hi rend="bold">Paḍuvūr-kōṭṭam</hi>, consisting of the great men of the annual-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">samvatsaravāriyam</hi>) for this year, the great men of the garden-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">tōṭṭa-vāriyam</hi>), the great men of the tank-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">ēri-vāriyam</hi>), the great men of the wet fields-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">kaḻani-vāriyam</hi>), the great men of (<hi rend="italic">the suburb ?</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Vaḍa-Vīranāraṇa</hi>; the great men of the <hi rend="italic">pañcha-vāra</hi> committee (<hi rend="italic">pañchavāra-vāriyam</hi>), the great men of the accountssupervision committee (<hi rend="italic">kaṇakku-vāriyam</hi>), the great men of the sluice-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">kaliṅgu-vāriyam</hi>), the great men of the fields-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">taḍivaḻi-vāriyam</hi>), the <hi rend="italic">bhaṭṭas, viśishṭas</hi> and others of the big assembly together with <hi rend="bold">Pallavaṉ Brahmādarāyaṉ</hi>, the ruler of the village and the overseer <hi rend="bold">Arumbākiḻāṉ</hi>, having met together in the <hi rend="italic">abhishēka-maṇḍapa</hi> of the big temple of this village.</p>

<p>(L. 4.) <hi rend="bold">Māgaṇḍanaṉ</hi>, a Śiva-Brāhmaṇa of this temple (<hi rend="italic">sthāna</hi>), petitioned that the garden and the field which were the <hi rend="italic">archchanābhōga</hi> of the god, the lord of <hi rend="bold">Tirukkarapura</hi>, were lying waste, being silted up with sand by breaches in the river. The members of the assembly directed that the great men of the wet field-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">holding office</hi>) this year shall themselves (<hi rend="italic">grant</hi>) this one thousand four hundred <hi rend="italic">kuḻi (of land) (measured</hi>) by the wet field-measure (<hi rend="italic">kaḻaṉi-kōl</hi>) out of the <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi> land of the village, (<hi rend="italic">in lieu of</hi>) the land which is the <hi rend="italic">archchanābhōga</hi> of the lord of this <hi rend="bold">Tirukarapura</hi> and is lying waste being silted up, shall set up stones (<hi rend="italic">for boundaries</hi>) and have (<hi rend="italic">the order</hi>) engraved on stone. In pursuance of the order (<hi rend="italic">tirumugam</hi>) which the assembly was (<hi rend="italic">thus</hi>) pleased to make, we the great men of the wet field-supervision committee gave the (<hi rend="italic">following</hi>) land as <hi rend="italic">archchanābhōga</hi> to the lord of <hi rend="bold">Tirukkarapura:—</hi></p>

<p>(L. 7.) Four hundred <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> of land, (<hi rend="italic">measured</hi>) by the wet field-measuring rod, comprised within the (<hi rend="italic">following</hi>) four boundaries:—the eastern boundary of (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) land, which not being taxed, lies as the <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi> of the village to the south of the (<hi rend="italic">channel</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahādavāykāl</hi> in the northern fields of <hi rend="bold">Ōchchēri</hi>, a hamlet of this village, (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the west of the land of <hi rend="bold">Sōmāśi</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Māṅgāḍu</hi>; the southern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the north of the high ground which has been lying as village <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi>; the western boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the east of (<hi rend="italic">the land called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Udamādampaṭṭi</hi> of the lord of <hi rend="bold">Tirumūlaṭṭāṉam</hi> in (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tirupaṉṟīśvaram</hi> and the northern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the south of the (<hi rend="italic">channel called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Māhāda-vāykāl</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 9.) Four hundred <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> south of this, (<hi rend="italic">measured</hi>) by the wet field-measuring rod,—a village <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi> land not taxed and (<hi rend="italic">situated</hi>) on the north side of (<hi rend="italic">the channel called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tirunāraṇa-vāykāl</hi> in the wet-field of the high ground (<hi rend="italic">called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śirukarugēśuva</hi> which was also a village <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi>—and comprised within the (<hi rend="italic">following</hi>) four boundaries:— (<hi rend="italic">viz.,</hi>) the eastern boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the west of (<hi rend="italic">the channel</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Naḍaikāl</hi> which runs closely to the west of the land belonging to <hi rend="bold">Aṅgārai Mādēva-bhaṭṭa</hi>; the southern boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the north of the <hi rend="bold">Tirunāraṇa-vāykāl</hi>; the western boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the east of the land of <hi rend="bold">Aiyaṉ Perumāṉ</hi> and the northern boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the south (?)<note n="330-1">The original uses the word <ta>vaṭakkum</ta> where we should have expected the word <ta>teṟkum</ta>.</note> of the land of <hi rend="bold">Muḍumbai-Porkūḷi</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 11.) Again, six hundred <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> on the south side of this <hi rend="bold">(Tirunāraṇavāykāl)</hi> channel (<hi rend="italic">measured</hi>) by the wet field-measuring rod, of (<hi rend="italic">one) mā</hi> of land which was also lying as village <hi rend="italic">mañjikkam</hi> not paying any tax, (<hi rend="italic">included within</hi>) the (<hi rend="italic">following</hi>) four boundaries (<hi rend="italic">viz.,):</hi>—the eastern boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the west of the land which paid no taxes; the southern boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the north of (<hi rend="italic">the field called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Sōmāśibhūmi</hi> which belonged to <hi rend="bold">Avaṭṭaikiḻavaṉ</hi> and of the <hi rend="italic">kunḍil</hi> to the east of it; the western boundary (<hi rend="italic">which is</hi>) to the east of • • • (<hi rend="italic">the field called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kāḷaya Sōmāśi-bhūmi</hi> and to the south of the channel (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Tirunāraṇa-vāykāl</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 12.) Altogether these one thousand four hundred <hi rend="italic">kuli</hi> (of land) we, the great men of the wet-field-supervision committee (<hi rend="italic">doing duty</hi>) for this year • • • members of the assembly, gave as tax-free <hi rend="italic">archchanābhōga</hi> as long as the moon and the sun (<hi rend="italic">last</hi>) engraving it on stone and fixing (<hi rend="italic">boundary</hi>) stones, to the god (<hi rend="italic">perumānaḍigaḷ</hi>) of this <hi rend="bold">Tirukarapura</hi> for (<hi rend="italic">providing</hi>) daily one sacred meal of two <hi rend="italic">nāḷi</hi> of rice, for performing worship at the three periods (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">for</hi>) lighting a lamp.</p>

<p>(L. 13.) This is the signature of me <hi rend="bold">Maṇimaṅgalam-uḍaiyāṉ Gaṅgādhara Māyilaṭṭi</hi>, the accountant of the wet field-supervision committee for this year, who wrote this stone inscription under orders, being (<hi rend="italic">myself</hi>) one of the assembly (<hi rend="italic">kuṟi</hi>). I, the accountant • • and <hi rend="italic">madhyasthaṉ</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vāmana • • Ēḻāyiravaṉ</hi> wrote this under orders being (<hi rend="italic">myself</hi>) one of the assembly (<hi rend="italic">kuṟi)</hi>.<note n="330-2">The last three lines, contain the names of six other signatories, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, Āditta Ēḻāyiravaṉ, Kaṇavadi, <hi rend="italic">madhyasthan</hi> Mangalasēnāpati • • • Ēḻāyiranilaiyalaṅgaṉ Kaṟpa�ādittaṉ, <hi rend="italic">madhyasthan • • </hi> Tēraṉ of Kāvērimaṅgala and two others. The lines are too fragmentary to translate.</note> </p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.156 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">327-330</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">156</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
