<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 3.106: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
                <title type="alt">XI.—INSCRIPTIONS OF PARAKESARIVARMAN PARANTAKA I. No. 106.—ON THE ROCK AT THE ENTRANCE INTO THE CENTRAL SHRINE OF THE NARASINGAPPERUMAL TEMPLE AT ANAIMALAI. No. 63 of 1905.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0106</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>This record which is written in the Vaṭṭeḻuttu character is the only inscription of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka's</hi> reign hitherto found in the vicinity of <hi rend="bold">Madura</hi>. It is dated in his 33rd year and records a gift by <hi rend="bold">Marudūruḍaiyāṉ Aruṇidi Kaliyaṉ</hi>, an officer of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> (Parāntaka I.) to the temple of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅgapperumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> of the sacred <hi rend="bold">Āṉaimalai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">hill</hi>). The temple had to pay 18 <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> every year to the assembly and it had only arranged for the payment of six <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi>. <hi rend="bold">Aruṇidi Kaliyaṉ</hi> apparently agreed to pay the rest himself taking possession of the tank <hi rend="bold">Kaliyaṉēri</hi> which must have belonged to the temple. He also provided for offerings to the god and the feeding of five Brāhmaṇas, by purchasing two <hi rend="italic">vēlis</hi> of wet land under the tank <hi rend="bold">Kaliyaṉēri</hi>. It was stipulated that the feeding of the Brāhmaṇas was to commence from Friday in the month of <hi rend="bold">Karkaṭaka</hi> (<hi rend="italic">of this year</hi>) when there was an eclipse of the sun and the <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi> was <hi rend="bold">Āślēsha</hi>. This incidental mention of the astronomical details helps us to confirm the initial date of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I. (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, 907 A.D.) already arrived at by Professor Kielhorn from other inscriptions. According to Mr. L.D. Swamikkannu Pillai's <hi rend="italic">Ephemeris</hi>, A. D. 939, July 19, was a Friday on which the <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi> Āślēsha ended at 80 after mean sunrise. There was also on this day an eclipse of the sun a 7 hours, 57 minutes after sunrise according to Dr. Robert Schram's <hi rend="italic">“Eclipses of the Sun in India.”</hi> It was a total eclipse of great importance. We learn again from the record that (1/4) <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi> was the interest charged on 1 <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> for one month and that each <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> was equal to 7(1/2) <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi>.<note n="239-3"><hi rend="italic">Puttakkam</hi> may be a compound of <hi rend="italic">pudu</hi> and <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi>. The latter term occurs in Tanjore inscriptions as the equivalent of 1/12 <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi>. If the value of <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">akkam</hi> did not change in the interval between the reigns of Parāntaka I. and Rājarāja I., the comparative value of <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> with reference to the <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> current in the Chōḷa country, could easily be obtained. The former would in this case be 5/8ths of the latter.</note> </p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> matiraikoṇṭa kopparakecaripaṉmaṟku yāṇṭu muppattumuṉṟāvatu Ivvāṇṭu <unclear>te</unclear>va<unclear>tā</unclear>ṉaṅ kiḻiraṇiyamuṭ<unclear>ṭat</unclear>tuppaṭum <unclear>pi</unclear>
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>rammateya<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> <unclear>na</unclear>raciṅkamaṅkalattuc cavaiyomñ<note n="240-1">Read cavaiyoñ.</note> coḻapperumāṉaṭikaḷatikārikaḷ coḻanāṭṭup puṟaṅkarampaiṉāṭ
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>ṭu marutūr marutūruṭaiyāṉaruṇitikaliyaṉukku Oṭṭikkuṭa<unclear>t</unclear>ta<note n="240-2">Read kuṭutta.</note> paricāvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Eṅkaḷūrt tiruvā<unclear>ṉai</unclear>malai naraciṅkapperumāṉaṭikaḷ <unclear>ta</unclear>
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>muṭaiya nilattālc cavaiyomukku <unclear>Ā</unclear>ṇṭeṭuttu Iṭakkaṭava Īḻakkācu patiṉeṭṭu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>kkācu<note n="240-3">Read patiṉeṭṭilum.</note> pataṉeṭṭilum muṉṟatt<supplied reason="omitted">o</supplied>ṉ<unclear>ṟu</unclear> Ī
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>ḻakkācu Āṟu<supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivvāṟu Īḻakkācukkum palicaiyākac cavaiyār kaiyvaḻi kuṭutta Īḻakkācu patiṉaiṉtu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <supplied reason="omitted">pa</supplied>tiṉaiñciṉālum vanta pali
                    <lb n="6" break="no"/>caiyāvatu Īḻakkāciṉvā<supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied>t tiṅkaḷ kāṟ putta<supplied reason="omitted">kka</supplied>māka Oro tiṅkaḷā<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied> vanta puttakkamuṉṟemukkāl muṉṟemukkālu Orāṇṭu panniraṇṭu ti
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/><note n="240-4">Read ṅkaḷāl.</note> ñkaḷāl vanta puttakkam nāṟpa<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>taiñcu nāṟpattaiñciṉāloru Īḻakkācukkup puttakkam Eḻarai Āka <unclear>Ī</unclear>ḻakkācu <unclear>Ā</unclear>ṟu Ivvāṟu <unclear>Ī</unclear>ḻa
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>kkācum Iṟai nīkkit tevar cavaiyārkku Iṭakkaṭava kācu <num value="12"><g type="numeral">10</g> 2</num> paṉṉiraṇṭum nīkki Atikā<unclear>ri</unclear>kaḷ marutūruṭaiyāṉ Aruṇitikaliyaṉ Iṟaikāvalā<supplied reason="omitted">ka</supplied> kātta
                    <lb n="9"/>kāci<unclear>ṉā</unclear>l vanta nilaṉ Ūruṭaiyāṉ<unclear>ku</unclear>ḷamāṉa kaliyaṉe<unclear>ri</unclear>yum Ikkuḷantā<note n="240-5">Read tāṉvēṇṭu.</note> <unclear>me</unclear>ṇṭumāṟu kallik karai nīḷam Aṭṭappeṟuvatākavum <unclear>I</unclear>
                    <lb n="10" break="no"/>kkuḷaṅkarai Ucara Aṭṭappeṟuvatākavum Ikkuḷatti ṉīr <unclear>tā</unclear>ṉ veṇṭu Aḷavuṅ kokkappeṟuvatākavumikkuḷam Itiṉkiḻ nīrnilaṉiruvē
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>liyu marutūruṭaiyāṉaruṇitikaliyaṉ vilaikkukkoṇṭu Ikkuḷattiṉ kiḻ nīrnilaṉiruvēliyi<unclear>ṉā</unclear>l vanta pokam Aññāḻikkālāl nel<unclear>lu</unclear> <num value="300">3 <g type="numeral">100</g></num> kalam
                    <lb n="12"/>Ivaiyiṟṟiṉ pāti <num value="150"><g type="numeral">100</g> 5 <g type="numeral">10</g></num> nelluṅkoṇ<unclear>ṭu I</unclear>varkku muṉṟu cantiyuntiruvamirtu cevatākavum niṉṟa <hi rend="grantha">1[<num value="50">5 <g type="numeral">10</g></num>]</hi> nelluṅkoṇṭu tiruvamirtu U
                    <lb n="13" break="no"/>ttama Akkiramākat tevar Amituceyyumpoḻutu vetappirāmaṇar nicatam Ayvar Amitu ceyvatākavum vacca<unclear>pa</unclear>ṭi patteṭṭukkuttal Oruvaṉu
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>kku Arici <unclear>Iru</unclear>nāḻiyuṅ kaṟi mu<unclear>ṉṟu</unclear>m tayir nā<supplied reason="omitted">ḻi</supplied>yum neyiruceviṭum kāyyilai Iraṇṭum tālamañcum vaṭṭilaiñcum Oṭṭuṭṭi Oṉṟu
                    <lb n="15" break="no"/><unclear>m</unclear> caṭṭuvam Oṉṟu Aṭuvā(ṉ)ṉoruva<unclear>ṉu</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">k</supplied>ku nicati ne<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied>lu Aññāḻi Aṟutiṅka<unclear>ḷo</unclear>ru puṭavai vaiccu Ipparicu Ikkalamuṭṭuvatāka Iv
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>vāṭṭai kaṟkaṭakanāyiṟṟu veḷḷikkiḻamai peṟṟa Āyile<unclear>ya</unclear>ttiṉāṉṟu cū(ṟ)ṟiyakkiraṇavelaik<unclear>kurai</unclear>kirāṇam paṟṟiṉa Aṉṟumutalāka Ikkala<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied>
                    <lb n="17"/>I<supplied reason="omitted">p</supplied>paricey Ūṭṭuvatāka ni<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟu ciṟikāṟiyamārāykaṉṟa<note n="240-6">Read mārāykiṉṟa.</note> tiruvāyppāṭi nārāyaṇaṉum Ivvūrc cavaiyārum Ipparicey Akkiramuṭṭāmey ca<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>tirā
                    <lb n="18" break="no"/>tittallam<note n="240-7">Perhaps read tittavalum.</note> Ūṭṭuvippomāṉom tiruvāṉaimalai naraciṅkapperumāṉaṭikaḷukku <note n="240-8">Read cirikāriyamārāyvāṉum.</note> cirikācciya Ārāyvārum cavayomum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>itiṟṟirampi<unclear>ṉō</unclear>maic cavaiy
                    <lb n="19" break="no"/>yālum<note n="240-9">Read yārum.</note> <unclear>ci</unclear>rikā(ṟ)ṟiyamārāyvāṉuntiṟamiṉāṉ nicati Iṟukācu Aṉṟāḻ koviṉukkuttaṇṭampaṭṭu Akkācu koṇṭu tevarkkut tiruviḷakku Erivatākavum cavaiyār
                    <lb n="20"/><unclear>t</unclear> tiṟampil <unclear>Ā</unclear>ṟukācu taṇṭappaṭuvatākavu<unclear>m</unclear> Oṭṭikkuṭuttom cavaiyomum <note type="repeated" n="240-8"/>cirikācciyamārāyvāṉum marutūruṭaiyāṉaruṇitikaliyaṉukku <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ittaṇṭamiṟu
                    <lb n="21" break="no"/>ttumittaṉ<supplied reason="omitted">mam</supplied> muṭṭāme Ayvarai<unclear>yum</unclear> cantirāticcar Uḷḷaḷavum Ūṭṭuvippomāṉoñ cavaiyyum<note n="240-10">Read cirikāriyam.</note> cirikārcciyam Ārāyum vayi<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi>varum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Itaṉ
                    <lb n="22" break="no"/><unclear>ma</unclear> <supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> <hi rend="grantha">rakṣi</hi>ttāṉ<note n="240-11">The few words that have to follow have been omitted.</note> 
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01">
                
                <p>Hail ! Prosperity ! In this, the 33rd year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, who took <hi rend="bold">Madirai</hi> (Madura), (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) is the deed agreed upon and given by us, the members of the assembly of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅgamaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">dēvadāna</hi> included in <hi rend="bold">Kīḻ-Iraṇiyamuṭṭam</hi>, to <hi rend="bold">Marudūruḍaiyāṉ Aruṇidi Kaliyaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Marudūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Puraṅgarambai-nāḍu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-nāḍu</hi> who was an officer of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻapperumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I.). (<hi rend="italic">The temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅga-Perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> of the sacred <hi rend="bold">Āṉaimalai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">hill</hi>) in our village has to pay to (<hi rend="italic">us</hi>) the members of the assembly, eighteen <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> annually on account of the lands belonging to it. One third of this eighteen <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> is six <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi>. For (<hi rend="italic">realising</hi>) this six <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi>, fifteen <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> had been deposited on interest in the hands of the members of the assembly. The interest accruing on the fifteen (<hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi>) is as follows:—At (<hi rend="italic">the rate of</hi>) one-fourth <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi> per month on each <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi>, there accrues in each month (<hi rend="italic">on the fifteen īḻakkāśu</hi>) three and three-fourths <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi>. For the twelve months of a year, (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) three and threefourths (<hi rend="italic">each month</hi>) would accumulate forty-five <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi>. At the rate of seven and a half <hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi> for one <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu (these</hi>) forty-five (<hi rend="italic">puttakkam</hi>) would give six <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi>. Deducting these six <hi rend="italic">īḻakkāśu</hi> from the taxes (<hi rend="italic">due</hi>), the god has (<hi rend="italic">still</hi>) to pay 12 <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> to the members of the assembly. The officer <hi rend="bold">Marudūruḍaiyāṉ AruṇidiKaliyaṉ</hi>, having caused to be deducted these 12 <hi rend="italic">kāśu (due to the assembly by the god), (by virtue of</hi>) the tax money (<hi rend="italic">iṟaikkāval</hi>) deposited (<hi rend="italic">by him</hi>), obtained (<hi rend="italic">possession of</hi>) the (<hi rend="italic">tank</hi>) land <hi rend="bold">Ūruḍaiyāṉkuḷam</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kaliyaṉēri</hi>. This tank he shall dig (<hi rend="italic">to any depth</hi>) he likes and throw up the embankment to its (<hi rend="italic">full</hi>) length; shall raise the tank bund and collect water in this tank to the extent required by him.<note n="241-1">See below, page 392, note 2.</note> <hi rend="bold">Marudūruḍaiyāṉ Aruṇidi Kaliyaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">also</hi>) purchased below this tank two <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> of wet land<note n="241-2">The phrase <ta>ikkuḷam itiṉkiḻ</ta> admits of the interpretation <ta>ikkuḷattiṉ kiḻ</ta>.</note> . And 300 <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy (<hi rend="italic">measured</hi>) by the <hi rend="italic">aññāḻikkāl</hi> was got as produce from (<hi rend="italic">these</hi>) two <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> of wet land under this tank. Receiving the moiety of this (<hi rend="italic">viz.,</hi>) 150 (<hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>) of paddy, (<hi rend="italic">he arṛanged that</hi>) sacred food shall be offered to this (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>) at the three junctures (<hi rend="italic">of the day</hi>). With the remaining 150 (<hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>) of paddy (<hi rend="italic">he also arranged that</hi>) five Brāhmaṇas (<hi rend="italic">versed in the</hi>) Vēdas shall be fed with superior food daily, when the god is fed, on the (<hi rend="italic">following</hi>) scale laid down:—for one man two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice pounded ten or eight times, three vegetables, (<hi rend="italic">one) nāḻi</hi> of curd, two <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> of ghee, two areca-nuts and (<hi rend="italic">two</hi>) betel leaves, five plates (<hi rend="italic">tālam</hi>), five cups (<hi rend="italic">vaṭṭil</hi>), one <hi rend="italic">oṭṭūṭṭi</hi>, one ladle (<hi rend="italic">śaṭṭuvam</hi>). Five <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy daily (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) one cloth for (<hi rend="italic">every</hi>) six months, were (<hi rend="italic">also</hi>) provided for one cook. Thus this feeding should be done. Commencing from the day when an eclipse of the sun at its least<note n="241-3">The phrase <ta>kurai kirāṇam</ta> must indicate “total eclipse” as appears from the remarks made in the ntroduction.</note> occurred on the (<hi rend="italic">asterism</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āślēshā</hi> corresponding to a Friday in the month of <hi rend="bold">Kaṟkaṭaka</hi> of this year, the supervisor of the temple business (<hi rend="italic">śrīkāryam), viz</hi>., <hi rend="bold">Tiruvāyppāḍi-Nārāyaṇaṉ</hi> and the members of this village personally arranged thus to conduct this feeding. We, who look after the business of the (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Naraśiṅga-Perumāṉ</hi> of the sacred Āṉaimalai (<hi rend="italic">hill</hi>), and the members of the assembly shall conduct the sumptuous feeding in this wise without failure as long as the sun and the moon (<hi rend="italic">last</hi>). Any of us that fails to do this, whether (<hi rend="italic">he be</hi>) a member of the assembly or a supervisor of temple business, when he fails, (<hi rend="italic">shall</hi>) pay a daily fine of two <hi rend="italic">kāśu</hi> to the then reigning king, and with that <hi rend="italic">kāśu (collected as fine</hi>) a sacred lamp shall be burnt in (<hi rend="italic">the temple</hi>) of the god. If the members of the assembly (<hi rend="italic">as a whole body</hi>) fail to do (<hi rend="italic">this), (they</hi>) shall pay a fine of six <hi rend="italic">kāśu. (Thus</hi>) we, the members of the assembly and the supervisor of temple business, gave an agreement to <hi rend="bold">Marudūruḍaiyāṉ Aruṇidi Kaliyaṉ</hi>. Even after paying this fine (<hi rend="italic">we</hi>), the assembly and the Vaishṇavas who supervise the temple business, shall feed the five persons as long as the moon and the sun last without stopping this charity. He who protects this charity. • • </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 3.106 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">239-242</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">106</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="plate">VIII</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
