<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.20: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 20.—ON THE SOUTH WALL OF THE PASUPATISVARA SHRINE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0020</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription refers itself to the time of <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vīrarājēndradēva</hi> (I.) (line 11), and records a royal grant which was to take effect “from the year which followed after the third year,”<note n="31-6">See below, p. 38, note 3.</note> <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> from the fourth year, of the king's reign. It opens with a panegyrical account of the donor, which resembles the introductions of four other inscriptions of his, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>—</p>						

						<p>1. Tv. = an inscription of the second year in the Śvētāraṇyēśvara temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruveṇkāḍu</hi> in the Tanjore district (No. 113 of 1896).</p>						

						<p>2. Tk. = an incomplete and undated inscription in the Jalanāthēśvara temple at <hi rend="bold">Takkōlam</hi> in the North Arcot district (No. 19 of 1897).<note n="31-7">This inscription winds round a pillar from top to bottom in a single spiral line and thus reminds of the Mahākūṭa inscription of Maṅgalēśa (<hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIX. p. 8), which, however, starts from the bottom of the pillar.</note> </p>						

						<p>3. M. = an inscription of the fifth year in the Rājagōpāla-Perumāḷ temple at <hi rend="bold">Maṇimaṅgalam</hi> in the Chingleput district (No. 2 of 1892).</p>						

						<p>4. G. = a much damaged inscription of the fifth year in the Bṛihadīśvara temple at <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Śōḻapuram</hi> in the Trichinopoly district (No. 82 of 1892).</p>						

						<p>The historical introductions of these four inscriptions have been compared with the text of the subjoined inscription, and a selection of their various readings is given in the footnotes.</p>						

						<p>The period of the reign of Rājakēsarivarman, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Vīrarājēndradēva I., can be approximately fixed in the following manner. According to his inscriptions, he defeated <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla</hi> and his two sons, <hi rend="bold">Vikkalaṉ</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Śiṅgaṇaṉ</hi>, at <hi rend="bold">Kūḍalśaṅgamam</hi>.<note n="32-1">See l. 5 ff. of the present inscription.</note> This battle is mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Kaliṅgattu-Paraṇi</hi> (viii. 29) and in the <hi rend="italic">Vikkirama-Śōḻaṉ-Ulā</hi>.<note n="32-2"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XXII. p. 142, No. IX.</note> In these two poems the victor at Kūḍalśaṅgamam is placed after the <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa</hi> kings <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I. (<hi rend="italic">Kaliṅgattu-Paraṇi</hi>, viii. 24, and <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XXII. page 142, note 3), <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Chōḷa</hi> I. (viii. 25, and <hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. note 4), <hi rend="bold">Rājādhirāja</hi> (viii. 26, and <hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. note 5), <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājēndradēva</hi> (viii. 27, and <hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. No. VII.),<note n="32-3">Compare above, Vol. II. p. 303.</note> and a king who has not yet been identified (viii. 28, and <hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. No. VIII.). After the victor of Kūḍalśaṅgamam, the <hi rend="italic">Vikkirama-Śōḻaṉ-Ulā</hi> places another king, of whom no particulars are given (<hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. No. X.), <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa</hi> I. (<hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. note 7), and <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. note 8).<note n="32-4">See also above, Vol. II. p. 309, note 1.</note> Now, Professor Kielhorn's astronomical calculations have definitely established the two facts that <hi rend="bold">Rājādhirāja</hi> reigned from A.D. 1018 to about 1050, and that <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa</hi> I. was crowned in A.D. 1070.<note n="32-5"><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 266.</note> Consequently, the victor at <hi rend="bold">Koppam</hi> (Parakēsarivarman, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Rājēndradēva) and the victor over the <hi rend="bold">Kuntaḷas</hi><note n="32-6"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> the Chālukyas; <hi rend="italic">Kaliṅgattu-Paraṇi</hi>, viii. 29.</note> at <hi rend="bold">Kūḍalśaṅgamam</hi> (Rājakēsarivarman, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Vīrarājēndradēva I.) must have reigned between A.D. 1050 and 1070. Further, as I have stated before,<note n="32-7">Above, Vol. II. pp. 231 and 303.</note> Āhavamalla and his two sons, Vikkalaṉ and Śiṅgaṇaṉ, who were the opponents of the three Chōḷa kings Rājēndra, Vīrarājēndra I. and Kulōttuṅga I., have to be identified with the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla-Sōmēśvara</hi> I. (A.D. 1044 and 1068) and two of his sons, <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi> VI. (A.D. 1055-56 and 1076 to 1126) and <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. (A.D. 1064 and 1081-82).<note n="32-8">The figures of these reigns are taken from Dr. Fleet's <hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, second edition, Table facing p. 428.</note> </p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">Kūḍalśaṅgamam</hi>, the site of Vīrarājēndra's victory over the Chālukyas, has been located by Mr. V.Kanakasabhai Pillai at the junction of the Tuṅgabhadrā and Kṛishṇā.<note n="32-9"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIX. p. 340.</note> But both <hi rend="italic">kūḍal</hi> and <hi rend="italic">saṁgama</hi> mean ‘junction’ and might refer to the confluence of any two rivers, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Kūḍali</hi> at the junction of the Tuṅgā and Bhadrā.<note n="32-10">Mr. Rice's <hi rend="italic">Mysore and Coorg</hi>, Vol. II. p. 380.</note> The battle of Kūḍalśaṅgamam was the third occasion<note n="32-11"><ta>mūṉṟām vicaiyiṉum</ta>, l. 5.</note> on which Vīrarājēndra I. professes to have defeated the Chālukyas. He had already before driven <hi rend="bold">Vikkalaṉ</hi> from <hi rend="bold">Gaṅga-pāḍi</hi> over the <hi rend="bold">Tuṅgabhadrā</hi> (l. 3 f.), and on a second occasion he had defeated an army which his enemy had sent into <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgai-nāḍu</hi> under the <hi rend="italic">Mahādaṇḍanāyaka</hi> <hi rend="bold">Chāmuṇḍarāja</hi>. The latter was killed and his daughter <hi rend="bold">Nāgalai</hi>, who was the queen of <hi rend="bold">Irugayaṉ</hi>, mutilated (l. 4 f.). Chāmuṇḍarāja is probably identical with the <hi rend="italic">Mahāmaṇḍalēśvara</hi> <hi rend="bold">Chāvuṇḍarāya</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Banavāsi</hi>, who is mentioned by Dr. Fleet<note n="32-12"><hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, second edition, p. 439.</note> as a feudatory of <hi rend="bold">Sōmēśvara</hi> I. with the dates A.D. 1045-46 and 1062-63. Two other chiefs whose names occur in the account of the battle of Kūḍalśaṅgamam,—though the context does not show on which side they were fighting,—<hi rend="bold">Kēśava-Daṇḍanāyaka</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Mārayaṉ</hi> (l. 6), are perhaps identical with two other feudatories of the Chālukyas, the <hi rend="italic">Daṇḍanāyaka</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kēśavādityadēva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>. p. 443) and <hi rend="bold">Mārasiṁha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> p. 439).</p>						

						<p>The whole Chālukya camp fell into the hands of Vīrarājēndra I., including the wives of the enemy, the boar-banner, and the female elephant <hi rend="italic">Pushpaka</hi> (l. 8 f.). In the concluding portion of the introduction (l. 9 f.), the king claims to have killed the king of <hi rend="bold">Pottappi</hi>,<note n="33-1">An inscription of Śaka-Saṁvat 1129 at Tiruvoṟṟiyūr near Madras (No. 104 of 1892) speaks of the town of Pottappi, which Madhurāntaka, an ancestor of Tammusiddhi, founded in the Andhra (Telugu) country. An inscription of Tammusiddhi's overlord, Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa III., in the Raṅganāyaka temple at Nellūr (No. 197 of 1894, dated A.D. 1197; see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 219) and the <hi rend="italic">Periyapurāṇam</hi> (p. 65 of the Madras edition of 1888) mention Pottappi-nāḍu, which, according to the <hi rend="italic">Madras Manual of Administration</hi> (Vol. III. p. 115), is the Telugu designation of the Kāḷahasti country.</note> the <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷa</hi> king, the younger brother of <hi rend="bold">Jananātha</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Dhārā</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king, and others.</p>						

						<p>Towards the beginning of the introduction (ll. 1-3) we learn the names of a few of the king's near relatives. On his elder brother <hi rend="bold">Āḷavandāṉ</hi> he conferred the title <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>; on his son <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntaka</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Pallava country) and the title <hi rend="bold">Chōḷēndra</hi>;<note n="33-2">This statement is taken from the Tiruveṇkāḍu inscription; see below, p. 36, note 11.</note> on his son <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Chōḷa</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍi-maṇḍalam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> country) and the title <hi rend="bold">Chōḷa-Pāṇḍya</hi>; and on <hi rend="bold">Muḍikoṇḍa-Chōḷa</hi> the title <hi rend="bold">Sundara-Chōḷa</hi>.<note n="33-3">In quoting the present inscription (<hi rend="italic">South-Indian Palaeography</hi>, p. 45, note 1), Dr. Burnell says that “Koppākēsari (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>) the Chōḷa established his younger brother on the [Pāṇḍya] throne. This prince's name was Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Chōḷa, but he took the name Sundara-Pāṇḍya-Chōḷa.” This series of mistakes has, on the strength of Dr. Burnell's authority, been accepted as history by Dr. Caldwell (<hi rend="italic">History of Tinnevelly</hi>, p. 31 f.) and Mr. Sewell (<hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. I. p. 221).</note> According to the Tañjāvūr inscription of Kulōttuṅga I.<note n="33-4">Above, Vol. II. p. 232.</note> the name of Vīrarājēndra's wife was <hi rend="bold">Arumoḻi-Naṅgai</hi>.</p>						

						<p>The immediate purpose of the subjoined inscription is to record that the king, residing in his palace at <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Śōḻapuram</hi><note n="33-5">The same place had been the residence of Rājēndra-Chōḷa I. See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> p. 105, and compare <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XXI. p. 323.</note> (l. 11 f.), granted to the Karuvūr temple the village of <hi rend="bold">Pākkūr</hi>, which, like Karuvūr itself (l. 14), belonged to <hi rend="bold">Veṅgāla-nāḍu</hi>, a district of <hi rend="bold">Adhirājarāja-maṇḍalam</hi> (l. 12).</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>ti</unclear>ru vaḷara tira<unclear>ḷ pu</unclear>yattiru<unclear>ni</unclear>lavalaiyantaṉ <unclear>ma</unclear>ṇippūṇeṉattaṅki<unclear>p</unclear>paṉmaṇikkoṟṟaveṇkuṭai niḻaṟkuvalaiyattuyirkaḷai<unclear>ppe</unclear>ṟṟa tāyilum pera<note n="33-6">ṭv. reads peṇa, and Tk. and M. peṇi.</note> maṟṟuḷḷavaṟaikaḻalaracar taṉṉaṭiyiṉilotuṅkavuṟaipilattuṭaiy kaliyatuvotuṅ<unclear>ka mu</unclear>ṟaimai<unclear>yi</unclear>larumpeṟal tamaiyaṇai<note n="33-7">Tv. reads [ta]maiyaṉai āḷava<hi rend="grantha">[ntā]</hi>ṉai.</note> <unclear>mu</unclear>
<lb n="2" break="no"/><unclear>ṉva</unclear>n<unclear>t</unclear>āṉaiyirum puvi pu<unclear>ka</unclear>ḻ <unclear>I</unclear>rā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>rā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉeṉṟoḷir<note n="33-8">ṭv. reads maṇi.</note> <unclear>mu</unclear>ṇimuṭi cūṭṭi taṉṟirumai<unclear>n</unclear>taṉākiya kaṅkaikoṇṭacoḻaṉaiye<unclear>ḻuy</unclear>āriyāṉai<note n="33-9">Tv. reads e[ḻu]ya[riy]ā[ṉai].</note> <unclear>c</unclear>ceṉaiccoḻapāṇ<unclear>ṭi</unclear>yaṉeṉṟuṇṭu<unclear>ya</unclear>r<note n="33-10">Tv. reads ṟiṇṭuyar, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> ṟīṇṭuyar.</note> maṇimuṭi<unclear>pp</unclear>āṇ<unclear>ṭi</unclear>maṇṭalaṅkuṭuttaru<unclear>ḷiy</unclear> vāṭkai vaṭikoṇṭakatirvel muṭikoṇ
<lb n="3" break="no"/>ṭac<unclear>o</unclear><unclear>ḻaṉaic</unclear>cuntaracoḻaṉeṉaccuṭar muṭi cūṭṭi<unclear>ya</unclear>nta<unclear>mi</unclear>l peruñ<unclear>ci</unclear>ṟapparuḷittaṉ kiḷaivarulaka<unclear>t</unclear>tavaṟkuri<unclear>ya</unclear>vakaliṭam ve<unclear>ṟu ve</unclear>ṟaruḷi I<unclear>ka</unclear>l vi<unclear>ḷai</unclear> virukoṭu<note n="34-1">ṭv. reads virutoṭu.</note> malaikkum vikkalaṉṟaṉṉoṭum veñcilaittaṭakkai māc<unclear>ā</unclear>mantaraikkaṅka(ṅka)pāṭik
<lb n="4" break="no"/><unclear>ka</unclear>ḷa<unclear>tti</unclear>ṭaiṉiṉṟu tuṅkapattirikkarai<note n="34-2">ṭv. and ṅ. read tuṅkapattirai.</note> pukatturantu Aṅkavar veṅ<unclear>k</unclear>ai<unclear>ṉā</unclear>ṭṭiṭai miṇṭavar<note n="34-3">Read mīṇṭavar.</note> viṭṭa tā<unclear>ṅ</unclear>karum peruvalit<unclear>ta</unclear>ṇṭu k<unclear>e</unclear>ṭat<unclear>t</unclear>ā<unclear>k</unclear>ki mā<unclear>ta</unclear>ṇṭanāyakkaṉ <unclear>c</unclear>āmuṇṭarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉaicceṉṟavaṉ<note n="34-4">Tk., M. and G. read ceṟṟavaṉ.</note> cirattiṉaiyaṟuttu ma<unclear>ṟ</unclear>ṟava<unclear>ṉ</unclear>orumakaḷākiyavirukaya
<lb n="5" break="no"/>ttevi<note n="34-5">ṭv. and ṭk. read irukayaṉ tevi nākalai.</note> <supplied reason="omitted">nā</supplied>kalaiyeṉṉunto<unclear>k</unclear>aiya<unclear>m</unclear>cāyalai mukattoṭu mukku<note n="34-6">Read mūkku.</note> veṟikki<note n="34-7">Tv., Tk. and M. read veṟākki.</note> pakaittetir muṉṟām<note n="34-8">Read mūṉṟām.</note> vicaiyiṉummeṉṟetir <unclear>p</unclear>orutu<note n="34-9">M. reads paripavan.</note> pariyavantivaṉeṉa-<note n="34-10">Tv. reads tirvateṉa , <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> tīrvateṉa.</note> k<unclear>ka</unclear>ruti<unclear>y</unclear> poruta<note n="34-11">Tv. and M. read porupuṉal.</note> pu<unclear>ṉa</unclear>l kū<unclear>ṭa</unclear>lcaṅkama<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>t<unclear>ā</unclear>kava<unclear>ma</unclear>l<unclear>laṉ</unclear> makaṉākiya<note n="34-12">Tv., Tk. and M. read makkaḷākiya.</note> vikkalaṉ<note n="34-13">Tv. and M. read ciṅkaṇa.</note> ciṅkaḷaṉeṉṟivartammoṭummeṇ<unclear>ṇi</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">l cā</supplied>mantarai
<lb n="6"/>veṉṟaṭu tūkki<note n="34-14">ṭv., ṭk. and M. read tūci.</note> muṉ viṭṭuttaṉṟuṇai maṉṉaṉ<note n="34-15">Tv., M. and G. read maṉṉarun=tāṉum.</note> tāṉum piṉṉaṭuttiruntu <unclear>va</unclear>ṭakaṭaleṉṉa vakuttu<note n="34-16">Tv. and M. read vakuttavattāṉaiyai.</note> vant<unclear>ā</unclear>ṉaiy<unclear>ai</unclear> kaṭakaḷiṟoṉṟāl kalakkiyuṭal<note n="34-17">Tv., Tk. and M. read aṭal.</note> purikkocalacciṅkaḷa<note n="34-18">Tv. and M. read kocalai ciṅkaṉai .</note> kko<unclear>ṭi</unclear>ppaṭai maṉṉaraittūci<note n="34-19">Tv. reads muṉnar tūci .</note> veṇkaḷiṟṟoṉtu<unclear>ṇit</unclear>tu<note n="34-20">Tv. and M. read veṅkaḷiṟṟoṭu <hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tuṇittu.</note> <unclear>k</unclear>ecavata<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭanā<unclear>ya</unclear>kkaṉ kettaracaṉ ta<unclear>ṉiṭaṟa</unclear>l<note n="34-21">Tv., Tk. and M. read tiṇṭiṟal.</note> <unclear>m</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">āraya</supplied>ṉ (t)tiṟaṟ
<lb n="7" break="no"/><note n="34-22">Tv. reads pottaracannereccayan, Tk. pottaraiyaṉireccayaṉ , and M. pottarayaṉireccayaṉ.</note> pottayaṉi<unclear>ka</unclear>l ce<unclear>y</unclear>ya poṟko<unclear>t</unclear>ai<note n="34-23">Read mū; Tv. and G. read muvetti .</note> muventiyeṉṟārtaṭuttuppila<unclear>ṉeka</unclear>-<note n="34-24">Tv., M. and G. read yeṉṟārttaṭutu.</note> c<unclear>āma</unclear>nta<unclear>rai</unclear>cciṉṉa<unclear>pi</unclear>ṉṉañce<unclear>y</unclear>tu <unclear>pi</unclear>ṉṉai muta<unclear>li</unclear>yākiya matuvaṇa<unclear>n</unclear>o<unclear>ṭa</unclear> viritta talai<unclear>y</unclear>oṭu vik<unclear>ka</unclear>laṉoṭa<unclear>c</unclear>ce<unclear>ru</unclear>kkeḻilaḻintu<note n="34-25">Tv., Tk. and M. read ciṅkaṇa .</note> ciṅkaḷa<unclear>ṉ</unclear>oṭa Aṇṇalamutalikaḷa<unclear>ṉai</unclear>varummar<note n="34-26">Tv. reads aṇṇalan mutalinaranaivarum amar porppa[ṇ]ṇi[ṉa].</note> poṟ<unclear>pa</unclear>ṇṇiṉa <unclear>pa</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">kaṭi</supplied>ḻint<unclear>o</unclear>
<lb n="8" break="no"/>ṭa ṉaṇṇiya Ākava<supplied reason="omitted">ma</supplied>llaṉumavaṟku<note n="34-27">ṭv. reads mavarkku.</note> muṉṉoṭa taṉ vekaveṅkaḷiṟṟiṉai vilakki vāka<note n="34-28">Tv., M. and G. read vākai koṇṭaṅkavar.</note> koṇaṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>va<unclear>r</unclear> t<unclear>ā</unclear>ramummavar kulata<unclear>ṉamu</unclear>m caṅ<unclear>ku</unclear>muṉ<note n="34-29">Tv., Tk. and M. read caṅkun .</note> <unclear>t</unclear>oṅkaluntāraiyum periyum me<unclear>ka</unclear>ṭama<unclear>ya</unclear>mum<note n="34-30">Tv., Tk. and M. read ṭampamum.</note> veṇcāmaraiyum <unclear>k</unclear>ākkaikko<supplied reason="omitted">ṭi</supplied>yum<note n="34-31">Tv. and M. read cūkarakkoṭiyum.</note> ma
<lb n="9" break="no"/>karatoraṇamum<note n="34-32">ṭv. and ṭk. read pu<hi rend="grantha">ṣpa</hi>ka.</note> pu<unclear>ṭpa</unclear>kap<unclear>pi</unclear>ṭi<note n="34-33">Tv., Tk. and M. read piṭiyum.</note> por<unclear>k</unclear>ka<unclear>ḷi</unclear>ṟṟiṭamum<note n="34-34">Tv. and M. read ṟīṭṭamum.</note> pāypa<unclear>ri</unclear>ttoraiyoṭum<note n="34-35">M. reads [t]okaiyoṭu[m].</note> <unclear>paṟi</unclear>t<unclear>tu</unclear> ceyy<unclear>oḷi</unclear>r vicaiyama<unclear>ṇi</unclear>ma<unclear>kuṭa</unclear>m<unclear>mi</unclear>c<unclear>ai</unclear>y<unclear>o</unclear>ṭun-<note n="34-36">Tv. adds cūṭṭi after icaiyoṭuñ; read cūṭi.</note> <unclear>tic</unclear>ai<unclear>t</unclear>oṟum ciṉappu<unclear>li</unclear> celut<unclear>ti</unclear>kkucai koḷuttum puravippot<unclear>tap</unclear>piventaṉai vāraṉai vaṉaikaḻal<note n="34-37">M. reads va[ṉ]kaḻaṟ.</note> toṉṟaṉai<note n="34-38">Tk. and M. read keraḷaṉṟaṉṉai.</note> 
<lb n="10" break="no"/><note n="35-1">M. reads <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉanātaṉ.</note> ttārācāṉātaṉṟam<unclear>piy</unclear>aipporkaḷattalaṅkalcūḻppacuntalaiyarintu polaṅkaḻa<unclear>lt</unclear>teṉṉaṉai civallavaṉ<note n="35-2">ṅ. reads <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vallapaṉ.</note> makaṉ ciṟuvaṉai miṉ<unclear>ṉa</unclear>vilmaṇimu<unclear>ṭi</unclear><note n="35-3">Read vīra.</note> virake<unclear>ca</unclear>riyai katakaṭakaḷiṟṟālut<unclear>ai</unclear>t<unclear>ti</unclear>ṭṭu matakoṭu ceyittu varappākācceṅkol celu<unclear>tti</unclear> vetanitiyai<note n="35-4">G. reads nīti[yai] .</note> 
<lb n="11"/>viḷa<unclear>k</unclear>ki<note n="35-5">Read mītu.</note> mituyar<note n="35-6">Read vīra.</note> virattaṉikko<unclear>ṭi</unclear>ttiyākakkoṭiyoṭum Eṟpavar varukeṉṟu niṟṟampa<note n="35-7">Tv. and M. read niṟpa.</note> <unclear>p</unclear>orttoḻivāymai<unclear>yil</unclear><note n="35-8">M. reads [to]ḻilu[rim]ai[yi]ley[ti] aracu vīṟṟirun=tu.</note> ne<hi rend="grantha">yta viṟṟiru</hi>n=ta<hi rend="grantha"> me</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rumaṉuṉeṟi viḷaṅki</hi>ṭa<hi rend="grantha">(<g type="ddanda">.</g>)kko</hi><note n="35-9">Tv. and M. read viḷakkiya ko.</note> <unclear>I</unclear>rācakecari[ pa<hi rend="grantha"><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>mma</hi>] rāṉa Uṭaiyār<note n="35-10">Read <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vīra.</note> <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>virarāj<unclear>e</unclear><hi rend="grantha">ntrade</hi>vaṟku <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> keṅkaiko
<lb n="12" break="no"/>ṇṭacoḻapurattukkoyiluḷḷāl tirumañcaṉacālaiyil Eḻuntaruḷiyiruntu Utakam paṇṇiyaruḷiṉa Ati<hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>maṇṭalattu veṅkālaṉāṭṭuppākkūr veḷḷāṉ vakaiyiliṟaimutal tavirttu yāṇṭu 3 vatukketirāvatu mutal
<lb n="13"/>Ivvūr Iṟaiyili t<unclear>e</unclear>vatāṉam tiruṉāmattukkāṇiyāka <unclear>I</unclear>ṟai pura<unclear>vu</unclear> ciṟṟāyam Elavaiyuka<unclear>v</unclear>ai maṉṟupāṭuteṇṭakuṟṟam Uṭumpoṭi Āmai tavaḻi<note n="35-11">ṇo. 21, l. 9, and No. 22, l. 6, read tavaḻ.</note> puṟṟum Eḻuvaṉa muḷaippaṉa kaṟṟup<unclear>pu</unclear>ṟpekkaramuṟcū<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭum<note n="35-12">No. 21, l. 10, No. 22, l. 7, and No. 23, l. 4, read perakaramuṟṟūṭṭum.</note> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivvūr Iṟai kaṭ<unclear>ṭi</unclear>ṉa kāṇikka<unclear>ṭa</unclear>ṉ
<lb n="14"/>poṉ muṉṉūṟṟu <unclear>mu</unclear>kkaḻañcaraiye mañcāṭi Araimāvum nellu muv<unclear>vā</unclear>yirattu <unclear>A</unclear>ñūṟṟu muppatto<unclear>ru</unclear>kala<unclear>ṉ</unclear>e tū<unclear>ṇi</unclear>yum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Iṉṉā<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭukkaruvūrttiruvānilai <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>vaṟku Iṟuppa<unclear>t</unclear>āka yāṇṭu mutal Iṟaiyili tevatāṉam tiruṉāmattukkāṇiyāka variyi
<lb n="15" break="no"/>viṭat<unclear>ti</unclear>ru<unclear>vā</unclear>y mo<unclear>ḻinta</unclear>ru<unclear>ḷi</unclear>ṉa paṭikku <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>ti</unclear>ruvāy mo<unclear>ḻintaruḷiṉāre</unclear>ṉ<unclear>ṟu tiru</unclear>ma[ <hi rend="grantha">ntra</hi>o] lai <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>kṣatri</unclear>ya<unclear>śikhā</unclear>ma</hi><unclear>ṇi</unclear>va<unclear>ḷa</unclear>ṉāṭṭu paṉai<unclear>yūrṉā</unclear>ṭṭu nerv<unclear>āyi</unclear>luṭaiyāṉ t<unclear>āḻi</unclear>tiruppaṉaṅk<unclear>ā</unclear>ṭuṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>yā<unclear>ṉ</unclear> vāṉava<unclear>ṉp</unclear>pa<unclear>lla</unclear>varaiyaṉe<unclear>ḻu</unclear>tiṉā<unclear>ṉu</unclear>m tiruma<hi rend="grantha">ntra</hi>olaiṉāyakam
<lb n="16"/>Accutaṉ I<hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>ṉāṉa toṇṭaimāṉum Ūraṉ Uttamacoḻaṉāṉa I<hi rend="grantha">rājarā<unclear>ja</unclear>brahmā<unclear>dhi</unclear>rā</hi>yaṉum Araiyaṉ I<hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>ṉāṉa vī<hi rend="grantha">rarāj<unclear>e</unclear>ntraja</hi><unclear>ya</unclear>muriṉāṭāḻvā<unclear>ṉum</unclear> vī<hi rend="grantha">rarājentra</hi>ma<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kalappe<unclear>ra</unclear>rai<unclear>ya</unclear>ṉum Ivarkaḷuṭa<unclear>ṉ</unclear> Oppiṭṭuppu
<lb n="17" break="no"/>kunta k<unclear>e</unclear>ḻvippaṭiye nam variyiliṭṭu<unclear>k</unclear>koḷkaveṉ<unclear>ṉa</unclear><note n="35-13">Read vīra.</note> virapattiraṉ tillaiviṭaṅkaṉāṉa villava<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>r</unclear>ājarāja</hi>ṉ <unclear>E</unclear>ṟa<note n="35-14">Read eva.</note> Ivaṉ Eviṉa paṭiye Uṭa<unclear>ṉ</unclear>kūṭ<unclear>ṭa</unclear>ttu Atikāri<unclear>ka</unclear>ḷ<note n="35-15">Read <hi rend="grantha">kṣatri</hi>ya.</note> <hi rend="grantha">kṣi[tri</hi>ya<hi rend="grantha">]śikhā</hi>maṇivaḷa<unclear>ṉā</unclear>ṭ<unclear>ṭu</unclear> paṉaiyūr<unclear>n</unclear>ā<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭu <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻana
<lb n="18" break="no"/>llūruṭaiyāṉ Utaiyativā<unclear>ka</unclear>raṉ kūttāṭuvāṉāṉa<note n="35-16">Read vīra.</note> virarā<hi rend="grantha">jentra</hi>maḻavarāyarum vī<hi rend="grantha">rarāje<supplied reason="omitted">ndra</supplied>brahmā<unclear>dhi</unclear></hi>rāyarum Arumo<unclear>ḻi</unclear>tevavaḷaṉāṭṭu ṉeṉmali<unclear>ṉā</unclear>ṭṭu p<unclear>e</unclear>riya<unclear>ku</unclear>ṭaiyū<unclear>r A</unclear>raṅkaṉ tirucciṟṟampalamuṭaiyāṉṉāṉa vāṉava<unclear>ṉ</unclear>muventira<note n="35-17">Read mūventaveḷāṉum .</note> 
<lb n="19" break="no"/>ve<unclear>ḷ</unclear>āṉum<note n="35-18">Read atirācarāca.</note> A<unclear>tirā</unclear>tarā<unclear>cava</unclear>ḷaṉāṭ<unclear>ṭu t</unclear>e<unclear>vūrṉā</unclear>ṭ<unclear>ṭu pa</unclear>ṉai<unclear>kku</unclear>ṭiyuṭai<unclear>y</unclear>ā<unclear>ṉ kāṭa</unclear>ṉ<note n="35-19">Read vīti.</note> vi<unclear>ti</unclear>viṭaṅ<unclear>kaṉā</unclear>ṉa [<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>]yaṅkoṇṭac<unclear>oḻa</unclear>viḻupparaiyarum vi<unclear>c</unclear>ai<unclear>ya</unclear>rā[<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>]n<unclear>taru</unclear>vaḷarnāṭ[ṭu<note n="36-1">Read <hi rend="grantha">rājendra</hi>vaḷanāṭṭu.</note> pu]li<unclear>yū</unclear>r<unclear>nāṭ</unclear>ṭup<unclear>pūṇ</unclear>ṭiyuṭaiyāṉ <unclear>Attā</unclear>ṇic<unclear>ciyarura</unclear>ṉ<note n="36-2">Read cīyārūraṉ.</note> <unclear>mu</unclear>ṭivi<unclear>ḻu</unclear>ppar<unclear>ai</unclear>ya<unclear>ṉu</unclear>m pa
<lb n="20" break="no"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> [irā<hi rend="grantha">jentra] bha</hi>ṭṭarum Irā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi><unclear>r</unclear>ā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi><unclear>p</unclear>pāṇṭikulavaḷa<unclear>ṉā</unclear>ṭṭu Uttamacoḻavaḷanāṭ<unclear>ṭu</unclear> mu<unclear>ḷ</unclear>ḷiṉā<unclear>ṭṭu ni</unclear>karilico<unclear>ḻa</unclear>ṉāṭṭu matimaṅka<unclear>lattu</unclear> kocc<unclear>ā</unclear>kk<unclear>ā</unclear>ṟpu<unclear>ṟat</unclear>tu viṇ<unclear>ṇava</unclear>n<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>rāyaṇa<hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṭṭaṉum viṭaiyil <unclear>A</unclear>tikā<unclear>ri</unclear>ka<unclear>ḷ U</unclear>yyak<unclear>ko</unclear>ṇ<unclear>ṭā</unclear>ṉum <unclear>I</unclear>ppaṭi
<lb n="21" break="no"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="6" unit="character"/> kat<unclear>tiruvāy</unclear> m<unclear>oḻi</unclear>ntaru<unclear>ḷi</unclear>ṉa paṭik<unclear>ku</unclear> nam <unclear>vari</unclear>yilār va<unclear>riyi</unclear>l<unclear>e Iṭ</unclear>ṭu I<unclear>ṟ</unclear>aiyi<unclear>li</unclear> t<unclear>e</unclear>vatāṉam tiruṉāmattukk<unclear>āṇiyā</unclear>kattiruvānilai <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>ma</unclear>hā<unclear>d</unclear>e</hi>vaṟku Avi<unclear>pe</unclear>liaṟcaṉāpoka<unclear>ttu</unclear>kkucce<unclear>m</unclear>pi<unclear>lum kallilum ve</unclear>ṭṭi ko
<lb n="22" break="no"/>ḷka <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>Ip</unclear>paṭi<unclear>k</unclear>ku A<unclear>ṟ</unclear>cutaṉ Irā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>nārāyaṇaṉ to<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭaimāṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ūra<unclear>ṉ</unclear> Uttamaco<unclear>ḻaṉāṉa</unclear> Irā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>rā<hi rend="grantha">jabrahmā(ma)</hi><unclear>ti</unclear>rāyaṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>ppaṭikku Arai[yaṉ<note n="36-3">Read vī<hi rend="grantha">rarājendraja</hi>ya.</note> vīra]rā<supplied reason="omitted">j</supplied><unclear>e</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> <unclear>ṉ</unclear><hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ya<unclear>mu</unclear>rināṭāḻ<unclear>vāṉ</unclear>
<lb n="23"/>Eḻut<unclear>tu</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>p<unclear>pa</unclear>ṭi<unclear>k</unclear>ku<note n="36-4">Read vīra.</note> virarā<hi rend="grantha">jentra</hi><unclear>ma</unclear>ṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>lapperarai<unclear>ya</unclear>ṉ Eḻu<unclear>t</unclear>tu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippa<unclear>ṭi</unclear>kku Atikāri <hi rend="grantha">kṣatri<unclear>ya</unclear>śikhā</hi>maṇivaḷaṉāṭṭu <unclear>paṉai</unclear>yūr<unclear>n</unclear>ā<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭu [<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅko]ṇ<unclear>ṭa</unclear>coḻanallūruṭai<unclear>y</unclear>āṉ Utaiyativākaraṉ kū<unclear>ttāṭuv</unclear>ā<unclear>ṉ vī</unclear>rarā<hi rend="grantha">jentra</hi>maḻavar<unclear>ā</unclear>yaṉ Eḻu
<lb n="24" break="no"/><unclear>t</unclear>tu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> I<unclear>p</unclear>pa<unclear>ṭikku v</unclear>āṉavaṉmuve<unclear>nti</unclear>raveḷāṉ<note n="36-5">Read mūventaveḷāṉ.</note> Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippaṭikku <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻaviḻu<unclear>p</unclear>paraiyaṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippaṭik<unclear>ku Attāṇi</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> <unclear>viḻu</unclear>p<unclear>par</unclear>aiya[ṉ<note n="36-6">Read attāṇiccīyārūraṉ muṭiviḻupparaiyaṉ in accordance with line 19.</note> Eḻu]ttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippa<unclear>ṭik</unclear>ku <unclear>ti</unclear>ru- <hi rend="grantha">mantra</hi><unclear>o</unclear>lai E<unclear>ḻu</unclear>tum vāṉa<unclear>va</unclear>ṉ<unclear>p</unclear>pallavaraiyaṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippaṭi<unclear>kku vi</unclear>
<lb n="25" break="no"/><unclear>ṭ</unclear>aiya<unclear>ti</unclear>kā<unclear>ri U</unclear>yyakkoṇṭāṉ Eḻut<unclear>tu</unclear> <g type="ddanda">.</g> Itu<note n="36-7">Read paṉ<hi rend="grantha">māheśvara</hi>.</note> <hi rend="grantha">panmāheśvarara<unclear>kṣ</unclear><unclear>ai</unclear></hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ittaṉmam nokku<unclear>v</unclear>āṉ [<hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>p]ātam Eṉ talai mele <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1899_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! While the goddess of fortune was prospering; while the circle of the great earth rested on (<hi rend="italic">the king's</hi>) round arm (<hi rend="italic">as lightly</hi>) as his bracelet of jewels, and while the shadow of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) royal white parasol (<hi rend="italic">set with</hi>) numerous jewels protected the living beings of the circle of the earth (<hi rend="italic">more tenderly</hi>) than the mother that bore (<hi rend="italic">them</hi>); while (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) other kings (<hi rend="italic">wearing</hi>) sounding ankle-rings took shelter at his feet; (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) while the Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>), in despair, retreated to (<hi rend="italic">its</hi>) natural abode: the abyss,—(<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) duly<note n="36-8">Or, ‘on account of relationship.’</note> bestowed a splendid crown of jewels on (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) incomparable<note n="36-9">Literally, ‘(whose like was) hard to be found.’</note> elder brother, <hi rend="bold">[Āḷa]vandāṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">along with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi><note n="36-10">The Tiruveṇkāḍu inscription reads ‘Rājādhirāja.’</note> who is praised on the great earth.’<note n="36-11">Here the Tiruveṇkāḍu inscription inserts a passage to the effect that the king gave to his son Madhurāntaka the Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam and the title Chōḷēndra.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 2.) (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) was pleased to grant the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍi-maṇḍalam</hi>, whose crown of jewels is exalted in this world, to his royal son <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">along with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Pāṇḍiyaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the leader</hi>) of an army of very tall elephants.’ (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) bestowed a brilliant crown on <hi rend="bold">Muḍikoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, whose hand (<hi rend="italic">held</hi>) the sword (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) whose spear had a sharp point, (<hi rend="italic">along with the title</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Sundara-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, and conferred endless great distinctions (<hi rend="italic">on him). (Thus he</hi>) granted to each of his numerous relations<note n="37-1">Literally, ‘to the world of his relations.’</note> suitable great riches.</p>

<p>(L. 3.) (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) drove from the battle-field in <hi rend="bold">Gaṅga-pāḍi</hi> into the <hi rend="bold">Tuṅgabhadrā</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Mahāsāmantas</hi>, whose strong hands (<hi rend="italic">wielded</hi>) cruel bows, along with <hi rend="bold">Vikkalaṉ</hi>, who fought under a banner that inspired strength.</p>

<p>(L. 4.) (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) attacked and destroyed the irresistible, great and powerful army which he (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Vikkalaṉ) had again despatched into <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgai-nāḍu</hi>; cut off the head of the corpse<note n="37-2">Literally, ‘he who had died.’</note> of the <hi rend="italic">Mahādaṇḍanāyaka</hi> <hi rend="bold">Chāmuṇḍarāja</hi>; and severed the nose from the face of his (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Chāmuṇḍarāja's) only daughter, called <hi rend="bold">[Nā]galai</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the queen of <hi rend="bold">Irugayaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) who resembled a peacock in beauty.</p>

<p>(L. 5.) The enemy, full of hatred, met and fought against (<hi rend="italic">him</hi>) yet a third time, hoping that (<hi rend="italic">his former</hi>) defeats would be revenged. (<hi rend="italic">The king</hi>) defeated countless <hi rend="italic">Sāmantas</hi>, together with these (<hi rend="italic">two</hi>) sons of <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla</hi>, who were called <hi rend="bold">Vikkalaṉ</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Śiṅgaṇaṉ</hi>, at <hi rend="bold">Kūḍalśaṅgamam</hi> on the turbid river. Having sent the brave van-guard in advance, and having himself remained close behind with the kings allied to him, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) agitated by means of a single <hi rend="italic">mast</hi> elephant that army (<hi rend="italic">of the enemy</hi>), which was arrayed (<hi rend="italic">for battle), (and which</hi>) resembled the northern ocean. In front of the banner-troop,<note n="37-3"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> the van-guard (of the Chōḷa king).</note> (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) cut to pieces <hi rend="bold">Śiṅgaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) of warlike <hi rend="bold">Kōśal[ai]</hi>, along with the furious elephants of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) van-guard. While <hi rend="bold">Kēśava-Daṇḍanāyaka, Kēttaraśaṉ, [Māraya]ṉ</hi> of great strength, the strong <hi rend="bold">Pōtta[ra]yaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) <hi rend="bold">[Irēchchayaṉ]</hi> were fighting, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) shouted:—“(<hi rend="italic">Follow</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mūvēndi</hi>,<note n="37-4">This name seems to be derived from <hi rend="italic">mūṉṟu</hi>, ‘three,’ and <hi rend="italic">vēndu</hi> or <hi rend="italic">vēndaṉ</hi>, ‘a king,’ and to be a surname of the Chōḷa king himself; compare above, p. 29, note 2.</note> (<hi rend="italic">who wears</hi>) a garland of gold !” and cut to pieces many <hi rend="italic">Sāmantas</hi>, who were deprived of weapons of war. Then <hi rend="bold">Maduvaṇaṉ</hi>, who was in command, fled; <hi rend="bold">Vikkalaṉ</hi> fled with dishevelled hair; <hi rend="bold">Śiṅgaṇaṉ</hi> fled, (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) pride (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) courage forsaking (<hi rend="italic">him</hi>); <hi rend="bold">Aṇṇalaṉ</hi> and all others descended from the male elephants on which they were fighting in battle, and fled; <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla</hi> too, to whom (<hi rend="italic">they were</hi>) allied, fled before them. (<hi rend="italic">The king</hi>) stopped his fast furious elephant, put on the garland of victory, seized his (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Āhavamalla's) wives, his family treasures, conches, parasols, trumpets, drums, canopies,<note n="37-5">See Platts' <hi rend="italic">Hindūstānī Dictionary</hi>, s.v. <hi rend="italic">mēghāḍambar</hi> or <hi rend="italic">mēgh-ḍambar</hi>. In the times of the Mughals the word had the meaning ‘a covered <hi rend="italic">hauda</hi>;’ see a quotation from Bernier's <hi rend="italic">Travels</hi> in Mr. Stanley Lane-Poole's <hi rend="italic">Aurangzīb</hi>, p. 132, where the word is misspelt <hi rend="italic">mēgh-dambhār</hi>.</note> white <hi rend="italic">chāmaras</hi>, the boar-banner, the ornamental arch (<hi rend="italic">makara-tōraṇa</hi>), the female elephant (called) <hi rend="italic">Pushpaka</hi>, and a herd of war elephants, along with a troop of prancing horses, and, amidst (<hi rend="italic">general</hi>) applause, put on the crown of victory, (<hi rend="italic">set with</hi>) jewels of red splendour.</p>

<p>(L. 9.) (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) despatched (<hi rend="italic">the banner of</hi>) the ferocious tiger into all directions and cut off the beautiful heads, surrounded by garlands (<hi rend="italic">won</hi>) on battle-fields, of the king of <hi rend="bold">Pottappi</hi>, whose horses chafed under the bridle, of <hi rend="bold">Vāraṉ</hi>, of the <hi rend="bold">[Kēraḷa]</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who wore</hi>) large ankle-rings, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) of the younger brother of <hi rend="bold">Ja[na]nātha</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Dhārā</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">He caused to be</hi>) trampled down by a furious <hi rend="italic">mast</hi> elephant the king of the South (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">who wore</hi>) golden ankle-rings, the young son of <hi rend="bold">Śrīvallabha</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Vīrakēsarin</hi>,<note n="37-6">According to the Takkōlam inscription the translation would run:—“(He) caused to be trampled down by a <hi rend="italic">mast</hi> elephant Vīrakēsarin, the son of the Pāṇḍya Śrīvallabha.”</note> whose crown of jewels glittered as the lightning, and captured <hi rend="bold">Madakōḍu (?)</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 10.) (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) wielded the sceptre beyond (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) limits and illustrated the laws of the Vēdas (<hi rend="italic">by his conduct</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 11.) (<hi rend="italic">During the reign</hi>) of (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Vīrarājēndradēva</hi>, who illustrated (<hi rend="italic">by his conduct</hi>) the laws of Manu, which are hard to follow, and was seated on the royal (<hi rend="italic">throne), (which he</hi>) had acquired by right of warlike deeds, while the matchless banner of heroism, along with the banner of liberality, was raised on high (<hi rend="italic">as if</hi>) to say:—“Let (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) supplicants come !”</p>

<p>Being graciously seated in the royal bathing-hall within the palace at <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Śōḻapuram</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) granted, with a libation of water, (<hi rend="italic">the village of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pākkūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Veṅgāla-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Adhirājarāja-maṇḍalam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) was pleased to order that this village,—excluding the tax-paying land in the portion of the ryots,<note n="38-1">With the words <ta>veḷḷāṉ vakaiyiliṟaimutal tavirttu</ta> compare <ta>veḷḷāṉ vakaiyil mutal tavirntu</ta> in Vol. II. No. 5, paragraph 3.</note> —should become tax-free temple land<note n="38-2">The two terms <ta>tevatāṉam</ta> and <ta>tirunāmattukkāṇi</ta> have both the same meaning.</note> from (<hi rend="italic">the year</hi>) which was opposite to the 3rd year<note n="38-3"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> ‘from the year which followed after the 3rd year;’ see Vol. II. p. 109 f., <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XX. p. 288 f., and <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. III. p. 67.</note> (<hi rend="italic">of his reign</hi>),— (<hi rend="italic">including</hi>) revenue, taxes,<note n="38-4">On the term <ta>puravu </ta> see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 225, note 8. The corresponding word in No. 22 below, l. 7, is <ta>vari</ta>, ‘a tax.’</note> small tolls, <hi rend="italic">ēlavai, ugavai</hi>, (the three fines called) <hi rend="italic">maṉṟupāḍu,<note n="38-5">An inscription at Tiruvallam (No. 44 below) proves that <hi rend="italic">maṉṟupāḍu</hi> or <hi rend="italic">maṉṟupāḍal</hi> (No. 22, l. 7) means a ‘fine,’ just <hi rend="italic">daṇḍa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kuṟṟam</hi>. Accordingly the translation of No. 12, l. 9 (p. 20 above) should run thus:— “The god himself shall levy penalties (and) fines for offences from the inhabitants of this village.”</note> ; daṇḍa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kuṟṟam</hi>, (every place) where the iguana runs, the tortoise crawls, an ant-hill rises (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) sprouts grow, the grass for the calves, and (<hi rend="italic">the land</hi>) enjoyed in full by the great village;<note n="38-6">See below, p. 41, note 1.</note> that (<hi rend="italic">this village</hi>) should pay to (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahādēva</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Tiruvānilai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) at <hi rend="bold">Karuvūr</hi> in the same <hi rend="italic">nāḍu</hi><note n="38-7">This refers to Veṅgāla-nāḍu in line 12.</note> the revenue (<hi rend="italic">hitherto</hi>) paid by this village,—(<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) three hundred and three and a half <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">one</hi>) and one twentieth<note n="38-8">See Vol. II. p. 36, note 1.</note> <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi>) of gold, and three thousand five hundred and thirty-one <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> and (one) <hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi> of paddy;—(<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) that (<hi rend="italic">this village</hi>) should be entered in the revenue register (<hi rend="italic">? vari</hi>) as tax-free temple land from (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) year forward.</p>

<p>(L. 15.) Accordingly, the royal secretary, <hi rend="bold">Vāṉavaṉ-Pallavaraiyaṉ</hi>, the lord of <hi rend="bold">Tāḻi-Tiruppaṉaṅgāḍu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the lord of <hi rend="bold">Nērvāyil</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Paṉaiyūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kshatriyaśikhāmaṇi-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, having written that (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) had been pleased to order (<hi rend="italic">thus), (and</hi>) the chief secretary, <hi rend="bold">Achchudaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Achyuta) <hi rend="bold">Rājarājaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi>, the citizen <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Brahmādhirāyaṉ, Araiyaṉ Rājarājaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vīrarājēndra-Jayamurināḍāḻvāṉ</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Vīrarājēndra-Maṅgalappēraraiyaṉ</hi> having unanimously approved (<hi rend="italic">of this document</hi>), <hi rend="bold">Vīrapattiraṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Vīrabhadra) <hi rend="bold">Tillai-Viḍaṅgaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Villava-Rājarājaṉ</hi>, ordered: “Let it be entered in our revenue register in accordance with intimation received.”</p>

<p>(L. 17.) In accordance with his order, <hi rend="bold">Udayadivākaraṉ Kūttāḍuvāṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vīrarājēndra-Maḻavarāyar</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">one of</hi>) the heads of the assembly (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the lord of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻanallūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Paṉaiyūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kshatriyaśikhāmaṇi-vaḷanāḍu, Vīrarājē[ndra]-Brahmādhirāyar, [A]raṅgaṉ Tiruchchiṟṟambalam-uḍaiyāṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vāṉavaṉ-Mūvēndavēḷāṉ</hi>, of <hi rend="bold">[P]eriya[ku]ḍaiyū[r]</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Neṉmali-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Arumoḻidēva-vaḷanāḍu, [Kāḍa]ṉ Vīdi-Viḍaṅgaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻa-Viḻupparaiyar</hi>, the lord of <hi rend="bold">[Pa]ṉai[kku]ḍi</hi> in <hi rend="bold">T[ēvūr-nā]ḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">A[dhirāja]rā[ja-va]ḷanāḍu, [Attā]ṇi-[Śīyārūra]ṉ<note n="38-9">See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> p. 252, and p. 257, note 6.</note> [Mu]ḍi-Viḻupparaiyaṉ</hi>, the lord of <hi rend="bold">[Pūṇ]ḍi</hi> in <hi rend="bold">[Pu]liyūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Vijayarā[jēndra]-vaḷanāḍu, • • • • • • • [Rājēndra]-bhaṭṭar, Viṇ[ṇava]nārāyaṇa-bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kōchch[ā]kk[ā]ṟpu[ṟa]m</hi> (<hi rend="italic">near</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Madimaṅgalam</hi> in <hi rend="bold">[Ni]garili-Śōḻa-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Mu[ḷ]ḷināḍu</hi><note n="39-1">See <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. V. p. 46 f.</note> in <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Śōḻa-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Pāṇḍikula-vaḷanāḍu</hi>,<note n="39-2">See above, p. 15, note 4.</note> and <hi rend="bold">Uyyakkoṇḍāṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">one of</hi>) the dispatching clerks, • • • • •<note n="39-3">The verb which is governed by the preceding names seems to be lost at the beginning of line 21.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 21.) “Our revenue officers having entered (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) in the revenue register in accordance with the royal order, let it be engraved on copper and on stone (<hi rend="italic">that this village was given</hi>) as tax-free temple land to (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahādēva</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Tiruvānilai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) for the expenses of burnt offerings, oblations and worship.”</p>

<p>(L. 22.) This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Aṟchudaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Achyuta) <hi rend="bold">Rājanārāyaṇaṉ Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi>. The writing of the citizen <hi rend="bold">Uttama-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Brahmādhirāyaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Araiyaṉ Vīrarājēndra-Jayamurināḍāḻvāṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Vīrarājēndra-Maṅgalappēraraiyaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of the superintendent <hi rend="bold">Udayadivākaraṉ Kūttāḍuvāṉ Vīrarājēndra-Maḻavarāyaṉ</hi>, the lord of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻanallūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Paṉaiyūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kshatriyaśikhāmaṇivaḷanāḍu</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Vāṉavaṉ-Mūvēndavēḷāṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻa-Viḻupparaiyaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">[Attāṇi-Śīyārūraṉ Muḍi]-Viḻupparaiyaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of the royal secretary, <hi rend="bold">Vāṉavaṉ-Pallavaraiyaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Uyyakkoṇḍāṉ</hi>, the dispatching clerk.</p>

<p>(L. 25.) “This (<hi rend="italic">charity is placed under</hi>) the protection of all <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvaras</hi>. The blessed feet of him who will protect this charity (<hi rend="italic">shall be</hi>) on my head.”<note n="39-4">Compare <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 178, note 7.</note> </p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.20 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">31-39</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">20</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
