<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.68: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 68.—INSCRIPTION IN THE PANDAVA-PERUMAL TEMPLE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0068</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription (No. 17 of 1893) is engraved on the north wall of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍava-Perumāḷ</hi> temple at <hi rend="bold">Conjeeveram</hi>. The ancient name of the temple was <hi rend="bold">Tiruppāḍagam</hi> (l. 3), and it is mentioned under the name of <hi rend="bold">Pāḍagam</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandham</hi>.</p>						

						<p>The date is the 5th year of the king, who is now styled <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva</hi> (I.), while in the inscriptions of his 2nd, 3rd and 4th years (Nos. 64 to 67 and 77) he still bears the name Rājēndra-Chōḷadēva (II.).</p>						

						<p>The new inscription refers to his early victories at <hi rend="bold">Śakkarakōṭṭam</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Vayirāgaram</hi>.<note n="140-14">See page 132 above.</note> It then states that he vanquished the king of <hi rend="bold">Kuntala</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Western Chālukya king Vikramāditya VI., that he crowned himself as king of the country on the banks of the <hi rend="bold">Kāvērī</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> of the Chōḷa country, and that he decapitated an unnamed <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king. An inscription of the 6th year of his reign<note n="140-15">On the south wall of the Śmaśānēśvara shrine in the Ēkāmranātha temple at Conjeeveram (No. 1 of 1893). This inscription is much obliterated and is therefore left unpublished.</note> adds nothing new to these</p>						

						<p>The subjoined inscription records that a merchant of <hi rend="bold">Kāñchipuram</hi> provided the temple with a flower-garden and purchased from the villagers of <hi rend="bold">Ōrirukkai</hi> some land for the benefit of the gardeners. I cannot find Ōrirukkai on the map; but it must be looked for near <hi rend="bold">Uttiramēlūr</hi><note n="141-1">This is another form of Uttaraṉmērūr on page 3 above, note 6.</note> (l. 4) in the Madurāntakam tāluka of the Chingleput district. As boundaries of the land granted, the inscription mentions also the river <hi rend="bold">Aḻichchiyāṟu</hi> and apparently the village of <hi rend="bold">Śāttamaṅgalam</hi>. A village of this name<note n="141-2">No. 491 on the <hi rend="italic">Madras Survey Map</hi> of the Madurāntakam tāluka.</note> I find 8 miles east of Madurāntakam.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>pu</unclear>kaḻ cūḻn=ta puṇari Akaḻ cūḻn=ta puviyil p<unclear>o</unclear>ṉnemiyaḷavun=taṉ nemi naṭātti viḷaṅku <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yamakaḷai Iḷaṅkop<unclear>pa</unclear>ruvattu cakkarakoṭṭattu vikkiramattoḻi<supplied reason="omitted">lā</supplied>l putumaṇam puṇar n=ta<note n="141-3">Read puṇarntu.</note> vaṉkaḷiṟṟiṭṭa<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied><note n="141-4">Read ṟīṭṭam .</note> vayirākarattu vāri Ayilmuṉaikkon=taḷavaraicar tan=tanamiri<unclear>ya</unclear> vāḷuṟai kaḻittu toḷ vali kāṭṭi porppari na<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ātti<note n="141-5">Read kīrtti.</note> kirttiyai niṟutti vaṭaticai vākai cūṭitteṉṟicai<unclear>t</unclear>temarukamalap<unclear>pū</unclear>makaḷ<note n="141-6">Read potumai.</note> putumaiyum poṉniyāṭai(yum) naṉnilappāvaiyu n=ta ṉimaiyun=tavirttu<note n="141-7">Read pāvaiyiṉ taṉimai.</note> <note n="141-8">Read puṉitattiru .</note> punitaru<unclear>tiru</unclear>maṇimaku
<lb n="2" break="no"/>-muṟaim<unclear>ai</unclear>yil cūṭi taṉ<unclear>na</unclear>ṭiyira<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭum taṭamuṭi<unclear>yā</unclear>ka <unclear>t</unclear>onnilav<unclear>e</unclear>n=tar <unclear>cūṭa</unclear>ppo<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ni matuvāṟu <unclear>p</unclear>e<unclear>ru</unclear>ka kaliy<unclear>ā</unclear>ṟu vaṟappa ce<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kol ticaitoṟuñcel<unclear>la</unclear> veṇkuṭai Irunilavaḷ<unclear>ā</unclear>kam<unclear>e</unclear>ṅkaṇun=tanātu tiruni<unclear>la</unclear>veṇṇilāttikaḻa Orutani meruvil puli viḷaiyāṭa <unclear>Āḻ</unclear>kaṭaṟ<unclear>ṟī</unclear>vān=tarattu pūvar tiṟai vi<unclear>ṭu</unclear>tta kala<unclear>ṉ</unclear> co<supplied reason="omitted">ri</supplied> kaḷiṟu muṟai ni<unclear>ṟ</unclear>pa viḷaṅkiya tennavanarun=talai parun=talaittukkiṭappa <unclear>na</unclear>ṉmaṇiyāramun=tirup<unclear>pu</unclear>yattalaṅkalum<note n="141-9">ōther inscriptions add pol.</note> tana<unclear>tu</unclear> <note n="141-10">Read vīra.</note> viramu<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>nti</unclear></hi>yākamu<unclear>m</unclear> viḷaṅka pārmicai meva<unclear>la</unclear>r vaṇaṅka<note type="repeated" n="141-10"/>vira<hi rend="grantha">siṁhāsa</hi>nattu puvanamuḻutuṭaiyāḷoṭum <unclear>vī</unclear>ṟṟi
<lb n="3" break="no"/>run=taruḷiya k<unclear>o</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">rājak<unclear>e</unclear>sari<unclear>vatma</unclear></hi>rāna Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kulottuṅkacoḻa<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">-</hi> <unclear>ṟ</unclear>ku yāṇṭu Añcāvatu [<g type="ddanda">.</g> U <g type="ddanda">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻamaṇṭalattukkāliyūrkkoṭṭattukkāliyūrnāṭṭu Ori<unclear>ru</unclear>kkai Ūrom <hi rend="grantha">śi</hi>lālekai ceytu kuṭutta paricāvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Eyiṟkoṭṭatteyilnāṭṭu nakaraṅkurañcipurattu<note n="141-11">Read kāñci.</note> Arumoḻitevapperun=teruvil viyāpāri kumāra<unclear>p</unclear>peruvāṇiyaṉ teva<unclear>ṉ</unclear> Eṟiñcoṭiyāka Aruḷāḷa<hi rend="grantha">dāsa</hi>ṉ tiruppāṭakatteḻun=taruḷiyirun=ta Āḻvā<unclear>nu</unclear>kkucceyta tirunan=ta<hi rend="grantha">-</hi> ṉavanam koyilil tiruppuṟakkuṭaiyil<note n="141-12">Read kaṭaiyil.</note> 
<lb n="4"/>Aru<unclear>ḷ</unclear>āḷa<hi rend="grantha">dāsa</hi>neṉnum tiruṉan=taṉava<unclear>ṉa</unclear>muḻapp<unclear>ār</unclear>kkukkoṟṟukku[m<note n="141-13">Read kkuṅkottukkum.</note> pu]ṭavai <unclear>mu</unclear>talukku<unclear>m</unclear> ni<hi rend="grantha">bandha</hi>ñ<unclear>c</unclear>e<unclear>yya</unclear> nāṅkaḷ Iṟaiyiḻicci Eṅkaḷuril<note n="141-14">Read ḷūril.</note> viṟṟukkuṭutta <unclear>ni</unclear>lamāvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied><note n="141-15">Read kīḻ .</note> kiḻpāṟkellai U<unclear>tti</unclear>ramelūrār vatikku meṟku- n=tenpāṟkellai Aḻicciyāṟṟukku vaṭakkum mel<unclear>p</unclear>āṟ<unclear>k</unclear>ellai <unclear>ti</unclear>ru<unclear>v</unclear>e<supplied reason="omitted">aH</supplied>kāvāḻv<unclear>ā</unclear>nukku nāṅka<unclear>ḷ</unclear> viṟṟa nila<unclear>t</unclear>tukkum cāttamaṅkalamuṭai<unclear>y</unclear>āṉ kaṭakaṉ ceṟuvukkum kiḻakkum vaṭapāṟkellai cāttamaṅkalamuṭaiyāṉ kaṭiccāñceṟukkuṇṭilukkutteṟkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Innāṉkellaiyu
<lb n="5" break="no"/><unclear>ḷ</unclear>ḷumakappaṭṭa Uṇṇilamoḻiviṉṟippa<unclear>ti</unclear>naṟucāṇ k<unclear>o</unclear>lāl kuḻiyiraṇṭāyaramu[m<note n="141-16">Read yiramum.</note> vi]ṟṟu Inṉilattukku vilaip<unclear>p</unclear>oruḷivaṉ pakkal koṇṭa p<unclear>o</unclear>ṉ <unclear>ma</unclear>turān=takaṉ māṭaiy<unclear>o</unclear>ṭo<unclear>k</unclear>ka kuṭi naṟkallāl niṟai pa<unclear>ti</unclear>noru<unclear>kaḻa</unclear>ñcu<unclear>m</unclear> Aṟakkoṇṭu Iṟaiyi<unclear>li</unclear> tevatānamākki Innilat<unclear>tu</unclear>kku v<unclear>e</unclear>likkācuma<note n="142-1">Read nīr.</note> ni<unclear>rvi</unclear>lai<unclear>yu</unclear>m cilliṟai co<unclear>ṟu</unclear>māṭṭuḷ<unclear>ḷi</unclear>ṭṭu Epp<unclear>e</unclear>rppaṭṭatum kāṭṭa<unclear>p</unclear>p<unclear>eṟā</unclear>tomākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> In<unclear>ni</unclear>la<unclear>m</unclear>āṉaikkaṟukkil Aṟutta<note n="142-2">Read nila.</note> kalattāl <hi rend="grantha">[va</hi>n=ta<hi rend="grantha">]</hi> nel<unclear>lu</unclear> Āḻvān <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>pa<unclear>ṇṭ</unclear>āratte Aḷappomākavu[m <g type="danda">.</g>*] <unclear>I</unclear>nnilattakappa
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ṭṭa kālvāy ki<unclear>ḻak</unclear>kuḷ<unclear>ḷa</unclear> nilattukku <unclear>nī</unclear>r pā<unclear>ya</unclear>ppeṟu<unclear>va</unclear>tākavu<unclear>m</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ipparicu Icai<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu <hi rend="grantha">candrā</hi>tittavaṟcella <unclear>ci</unclear>lālekai ceytu kuṭuttom Ori<unclear>ru</unclear>kkai Ūrom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivarkaḷ colla Eḻutinen Iv<unclear>vū</unclear>r veḷḷāḷan cāttamaṅkalamuṭai<unclear>y</unclear>ān veḷān kayi<unclear>lā</unclear>yatten<note n="142-3">īn modern ṭamil this would be kayilāyattāṉeṉ.</note> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai Enneḻuttu [<g type="ddanda">.</g> U <g type="ddanda">.</g>] <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vai<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rakṣai</hi> <g type="ddanda">.</g> U <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1903_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! Having made the wheel of his (<hi rend="italic">authority</hi>) to go as far as the golden circle (<hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>). Mount <hi rend="bold">Mēru</hi>) on the earth, which was surrounded by the moat of the sea, that was (<hi rend="italic">again</hi>) surrounded by (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) fame, (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) newly wedded, in the time (<hi rend="italic">when he was still</hi>) heir-apparent (<hi rend="italic">iḷaṅgō</hi>), the brilliant goddess of victory at <hi rend="bold">Śakkarakōṭṭam</hi> by deeds of valour and scized a herd of strong elephants at <hi rend="bold">Vayirāgaram</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) unsheathed (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) sword, showed the strength of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) arm, and spurred (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) war-steed, so that the king of <hi rend="bold">Kondaḷa</hi> (Kuntala), (<hi rend="italic">whose spear had</hi>) a sharp point, lost his wealth. Having established (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) fame, having put on the garland of (<hi rend="italic">the victory over</hi>) the Northern region, and having stopped the prostitution of the goddess with the sweet and excellent lotus-flower (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Lakshmī) of the Southern region, and the loneliness of the goddess of the good country whose garment is the <hi rend="bold">Poṉṉi</hi> (Kāvērī), (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) put on by right (<hi rend="italic">of inheritance</hi>) the pure royal crown of jewels, while the kings of the old earth bore his two feet (<hi rend="italic">on their heads</hi>) as a large crown.</p>

<p>(L. 2.) The sweet river <hi rend="bold">Poṉṉi</hi> swelled, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the river (<hi rend="italic">of the sins</hi>) of the Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>) dried up. (<hi rend="italic">His</hi>) sceptre swayed over every region; the heavenly<note n="142-4"><ta>tirunilam</ta> is perhaps used in the sense of ‘heaven,’ as <ta>tirunāṭu</ta> and the corresponḍing Telugu form <hi rend="italic">tirunāṇḍu</hi>; see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. V. p. 73.</note> white light of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) white parasol shone everywhere on the circle of the great earth; (<hi rend="italic">and his</hi>) tiger(<hi rend="italic">-banner</hi>) fluttered unrivalled on the <hi rend="bold">Mēru</hi> (<hi rend="italic">mountain). (Before him</hi>) stood a row of elephants showering jewels, which were presented (<hi rend="italic">as</hi>) tribute by the kings of remote islands of the deep sea. The excellent head of the brilliant king of the South (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi>) lay being pecked by kites. While his valour and liberality shone like (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) necklace of precious stones and (<hi rend="italic">like</hi>) the flower-garland on (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) royal shoulders, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) while (<hi rend="italic">all his</hi>) enemies prostrated themselves on the ground, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) was pleased to take his seat on the throne of heroes together with (<hi rend="italic">his queen</hi>), the mistress of the whole world.</p>

<p>(L. 3.) In the fifth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of this king <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi>) the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Kulōttuṅga-Śōḻadēva</hi>,—we, the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Ōrirukkai</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Kāliyūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kāliyūr-kōṭṭam</hi>,<note n="142-5">See above, p. 138, note 8.</note> (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅgoṇḍa-Śōḻa-maṇḍalam</hi>, made and gave the following writing on stone:—<hi rend="bold">Kumāra-Peruvāṇiyaṉ<note n="142-6">This title means ‘the great merchant of the heir-apparent.’ Compare <hi rend="italic">Śēramāṉ-lōka-pperuñ-jeṭṭi, Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 292 and note 6.</note> Dēvaṉ Eṟiñjōḍi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Aruḷāḷadāsaṉ</hi>,<note n="143-1">This name is derived from Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ, the name of the great Visḥnu temple in Little Kāñchī. Compare <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. III. pp. 71 and 118, Vol. IV. p. 145, and Vol. V. p. 72.</note> a merchant (<hi rend="italic">residing</hi>) in the great street of <hi rend="bold">Arumolidēva</hi><note n="143-2">See above, p. 8, note 3.</note> at <hi rend="bold">Kāñchipuram</hi>, a city in <hi rend="bold">Eyil-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Eyiṟkōṭṭam</hi>,<note n="143-3">See above, Vol. II. p. 390.</note> had made for the god who is pleased to reside in the <hi rend="bold">Tiruppāḍagam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) a flower-garden, called the flower-garden of <hi rend="bold">Aruḷāḷadāsaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and situated</hi>) on the outside of the temple. In order to provide for the cost (<hi rend="italic">mudal</hi>) of the clothing of those who work (<hi rend="italic">in this garden</hi>) and of (<hi rend="italic">their</hi>) families, we sold the following land in our village free from taxes.</p>

<p>(L. 4.) The eastern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the west of the road of the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Uttiramēlūr</hi>; the southern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the north of the <hi rend="bold">Aḻichchiyāṟu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">river</hi>); the western boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the cast of the land which we have sold to (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Tiruve[ḥ]kāvāḻvāṉ</hi><note n="143-4">According to the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandhan</hi>, Veḥkā was one of the Vishṇu temples in Kāñchī. Besides, Veḥkā or Vēgavatī is the name of a river which pa ses Conjeeveram and joins the Pālāṟu near Villivalam; see above Vol. II. p 345 and note 9.</note> and of the field of <hi rend="bold">Śāttamaṅgalam-Uḍaiyāṉ Kaḍagaṉ</hi>; and the northern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the south of the small field of <hi rend="bold">Śāttamaṅgalam-Uḍaiyāṉ Kaḍichchāṉ</hi>. Having sold the two thousand <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi>, (measured) by the rod of sixteen spans,<note n="143-5">See above, p. 106 and note 3, and p. 109.</note> enclosed in these four boundaries, not excluding the cultivated land, (<hi rend="italic">we</hi>) received from him<note n="143-6"><hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi> from Aruḷāḷadāsaṉ (l. 3).</note> as purchasemoney for this land eleven <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold, weighed by the true standard of the city (<hi rend="italic">kuḍinaṟ-kal</hi>) (and) equal (<hi rend="italic">in fineness</hi>) to the <hi rend="italic">Madurāntakaṉ-māḍai</hi>.<note n="143-7">On <hi rend="italic">kuḍi-naṟ-kal</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Madurāntakaṉ-māḍai</hi> see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. V. p. 106, notes 1 and 3.</note> Having received (<hi rend="italic">this amount</hi>) in full and having made (<hi rend="italic">the land</hi>) a tax-free <hi rend="italic">dēvadāna</hi>), we shall not be able to claim on this land <hi rend="italic">vēlikkāśu,</hi><note n="143-8">The same term occurs in No. 57 above, text line 9.</note> water-cess (<hi rend="italic">nīr-vilai</hi>), petty taxes,<note n="143-9"><hi rend="italic">Śill iṟai</hi> is the same as <hi rend="italic">śil-vari</hi>, on which see above, p. 122, note 6.</note> <hi rend="italic">śōṟumāṭṭu</hi><note n="143-10">With this obscure term compare <hi rend="italic">ēṟachchōṟu</hi>, above, No. 24, text line 7, and No. 27, text line 8.</note> and any other (<hi rend="italic">tax</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 5.) We have to measure into the treasury of the temple the paddy which comes from the land harvested in <hi rend="italic">Āṉaikkaṟukku</hi>, (a portion of ?) this land. It shall be lawful to irrigate the land lying to the east (<hi rend="italic">of the land sold</hi>), from the channels included in this land.</p>

<p>(L. 6.) Having thus agreed, we, the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Ōrirukkai</hi>, made and gave (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) writing on stone to continue as long as the moon and the sun. At the bidding of these, I, <hi rend="bold">Śāttamaṅgalam-Uḍaiyāṉ Vēḷāṉ Kayilāyatt[āṉ]</hi>, a cultivator of this village, wrote (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>). This is my writing. (<hi rend="italic">This is placed under</hi>) the protection of the <hi rend="italic">Śrī-Vaishnavas</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.68 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1903_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1903_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">140-143</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">68</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
