<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.99: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
			    <title type="alt">XI.—INSCRIPTIONS OF PARAKESARIVARMAN PARANTAKA I. No. 99.—ON THE NORTH WALL OF THE CENTRAL SHRINE IN THE KHARAPURISVARA TEMPLE AT TIRUPPARKKADAL. No. 693 of 1904.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0099</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This interesting record registers a gift of gold made by a military officer for strengthening the bund of a tank, by depositing on it the silt-removed from that tank. The gift, however, appears to have been utilized subsequently for feeding four Brāhmaṇas in the local temple, for the merit of the four heroes who fell in a battle on the occasion when the donor <hi rend="bold">Tīraṉ Śeṉṉippēraraiyaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Araiśūr</hi> made a frontal attack with his colleagues on the enemy, in a fierce battle (<hi rend="italic">astikkaḍai</hi>) fought at <hi rend="bold">Vēḷūr</hi> between <hi rend="bold">Perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Parāntaka I.) and the allied <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ceylon</hi> kings. The result of the battle is not stated; but from the <hi rend="bold">Udayēndiram</hi> plates published above, in Volume II, pages 375 ff., Parāntaka I. is known to have conquered Madura after defeating its ruler the Pāṇḍya king <hi rend="bold">Rājasiṁha</hi> and to have repulsed an army of the king of Laṅkā (Ceylon), thereby earning for himself the surname <hi rend="bold">Saṅgrāmarāghava</hi>. The Ceylon king who at this time must have sent his army in support of the Pāṇḍya could have been no other than <hi rend="bold">Kassapa</hi> V. who, according to the traditional account given in the <hi rend="italic">Mahāwamsa</hi>, would have reigned from A. D. 906 to 916 (<hi rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society for July</hi> 1913, page 525 f.). The commencement of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I. has been fixed by Professor Kielhorn to lie between 15th January and 25th July A.D. 907.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> matiraikoṇṭa kopparake<hi rend="grantha">saripatma</hi>ṟkku yāṇṭu paṉṉiraṇṭāvatu koṭṭanāḷ nūṟṟirupattoṉpatu paṭuvūrkkoṭṭattu kkāvatippākkamākiya Amaṉinārāyaṇa<unclear>c</unclear>catu<hi rend="grantha">rvve</hi>timaṅkalattu <gap reason="lost" quantity="4" unit="character"/> Ivvāṭṭaik kuṭumpuvārikapperu<supplied reason="omitted">ma</supplied>kkaḷun toṭṭa<unclear>v</unclear>ārikapperu<supplied reason="omitted">ma</supplied>kkaḷuṅ kaḻaṉivārikapperumakkaḷum vaṭakaḻaṉi
<lb n="2" break="no"/>vārikapperumakkaḷum <hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṭṭarkaḷum vi<hi rend="grantha">śiṣṭa</hi>rkaḷum Uḷḷiṭṭa <hi rend="grantha">mahāsabhai</hi>yār paṇiyāl <unclear>Iv</unclear>vāṇṭu Erivārikañ ceykiṉṟa Erivārikapperumakkaḷom coḻa<unclear>nā</unclear>ṭṭup pāmpuṇikkūṟṟa<unclear>t</unclear>tu <unclear>Ar</unclear>aicūr Araicūruṭaiy <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/> ṉ tīraṉ ceṉṉipperaraiyar pakkal Oṉpa<unclear>tarai</unclear>māṟi niṟai nūṟṟirupatiṉ kaḻañcu poṉ koṇṭu Innūṟṟirupati
<lb n="3" break="no"/>ṉ kaḻañcuppoṉṉum Emmur periya Eri karai maṇṇaṭṭukiṉṟa Oṭanāyaṉmārk kiṭuvataṟku mutalāka koṇṭu Innūṟṟirupatiṉ kaḻañcu poṉṉālum van=ta <hi rend="grantha">vṛtthi</hi><note n="232-1">Read <hi rend="grantha">vṛddhi</hi>.</note> yāley pāṇṭiyaṉum Īḻattaraiyaṉum vantu perumāṉaṭikaḷoṭu veḷūr <hi rend="grantha">Asti</hi>kaṭaiceyta nāṉṟu Icceṉṉipperaraiyar tām n<unclear>e</unclear>ṟṟi ceṉṟa Iṭattup paṭṭa cevakar kārimaṅkalamuṭaiyāṉukkum valikku<unclear>ṭṭi</unclear>kkum perunāyakaṉukkum Aḻiyānilai māṭampikkum Āka Innālvaraiyum cārtti Emmur
<lb n="4"/><unclear>pār</unclear>yāṟṟaṅkarait tirukkarapurattup perumāṉaṭika<unclear>ḷ</unclear> Amutuceyyumpoḻtu tāmeṭuppitta cālaimaṇṭakattey ve<hi rend="grantha">da</hi>m valla <hi rend="grantha">A</hi>pū<hi rend="grantha">rvvi</hi>kaḷ<unclear>e</unclear>y nicati nālvar <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇiṟku<note n="232-2">Read <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇarkku.</note> nālu kaṟiyum meyveṟu Āḻākku neyyum meyveṟu nāḻitta<hi rend="grantha">-</hi> yirum Aṭṭi <hi rend="grantha">Ācantra</hi>kālamum muṭṭ<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>mey Ipparicu A<hi rend="grantha">gra</hi>m<note n="232-3">Read ūṭṭuvi.</note> Uṭṭuvippomākavum Ivarkaḷ A<hi rend="grantha">gra</hi>m Uṇṭapoḻtu Ivar<supplied reason="omitted">ka</supplied>ḷukku meyveṟu Iraṇṭu k<unclear>āyu</unclear>m Ilaiyum Iṭuvatākavum Ipparicu A<hi rend="grantha">gra</hi>m Ūṭṭuvippatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <hi rend="grantha">I</hi> nālvar <hi rend="grantha">brahma</hi>ṇaraiyu
<lb n="5" break="no"/>m A<supplied reason="omitted">v</supplied>vavvāṇṭu Ērivārikañ ceyyum Erivārikapperumakkaḷey Ā<hi rend="grantha">candra</hi>kālamum kaṭaikkaṇṭu Ūṭṭuvippā<supplied reason="omitted">rā</supplied>kavum <g type="danda">.</g> I <hi rend="grantha">dhanma</hi>m <hi rend="grantha">rakṣitt<unclear>ār</unclear> Aśvamedha</hi>ñ ceyta <note n="232-4">Cancel the letter m of <hi rend="grantha">phala</hi>m.</note> <hi rend="grantha">phala</hi>mmey<supplied reason="omitted">tu</supplied>vārākavum <g type="danda">.</g> I <hi rend="grantha">dhanma</hi>ttukku viro<hi rend="grantha">dha</hi>ñ ceytār <hi rend="grantha">geṅ</hi>kaiyiṭaikkumariyiṭaic ceyta pāvattu<unclear>p pa</unclear>ṭuvārākavum <g type="danda">.</g> paṇittom Ivvāṭṭai Erivārikapperumakkaḷ U<unclear>ḷḷi</unclear>ṭṭa ma<hi rend="grantha">hāsabhai</hi>yom <g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g> Itukuṟiyuḷḷiruntu I<hi rend="grantha">vvā</hi>ṭṭai Erivārikapperumakkaḷ paṇikka Eḻutiṉeṉ <hi rend="grantha">madhyasta</hi>ṉ civakkuṟi nūṟṟeṇmaṉeṉ <g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! In the 12th year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi> who took <hi rend="bold">Madirai</hi> (Madura)—the day of the gift (<hi rend="italic">koṭṭa-nāḷ<note n="232-5">The word <ta>koṭṭanāḷ</ta> occurs for the first time. Other inscriptions use only <ta>nāḷ</ta>. The exact significance of the word is doubtful.</note> ) (being</hi>) one hundred and twenty nine—at the command of the members of the great assembly which included (<hi rend="italic">in it</hi>) the great men of the <hi rend="italic">wards-committee</hi>, the great men of the <hi rend="italic">garden-committee</hi>, the great men of the <hi rend="italic">fields-committee</hi>, the great men of the <hi rend="italic">north-fields (vaḍa-kaḻaṉi)-committee</hi><note n="232-6"><ta>vaṭakaḻaṉi vārikapperumakkaḷ</ta>. The function of this body as distingnished from <ta>kaḻaṉivārikapperumakkaḷ</ta> is not clear.</note> , the <hi rend="italic">Bhaṭṭas</hi> and other distinguished men (<hi rend="italic">viśishṭas</hi>) of this year. • • • • <hi rend="bold">Kāvadippākkam</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Amaṉinārāyaṇa-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Paḍuvūrkōṭṭam</hi>, the great men of the <hi rend="italic">tanks-committee</hi>, who do the <hi rend="italic">ēri-vāriyam</hi> for this year, received from <hi rend="bold">Araiśūruḍaiy[āṉ]. • • • • Tīraṉ Śeṉṉi-Pēraraiyar</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Araiśūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Pāmbuṇi-kūṟṟam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-nāḍu</hi>, one hundred and twenty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> weight of gold of nine and a half degrees of fineness<note n="232-7"><ta>māṟi</ta> is the word actually used. It has been taken to correspond to the modern <ta>māṟṟu</ta>.</note> .</p>

<p>(L. 3.) Receiving this one hundred and twenty <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of gold as a fund for paying the ferry-men depositing mud on the bund of the big tank of our village, we shall, from the interest accruing on this one hundred and twenty <hi rend="italic">kalañju</hi> of gold, for (<hi rend="italic">the merit of</hi>) these four servants (<hi rend="italic">viz.,</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kārimaṅgalam-Uḍaiyāṉ, Valikkuṭṭi, Perunāyagaṉ</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Aḻiyānilai-Māḍambi</hi> who died when this (<hi rend="italic">i.e., the above-mentioned</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śeṉṉi-Pēraraiyar</hi> himself made a frontal attack on the occasion when the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">king</hi>) and the king of <hi rend="bold">Ceylon</hi> marched (<hi rend="italic">against</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi> and fought with him a deadly battle<note n="232-8"><ta>a</ta><hi rend="grantha">sti</hi><ta>kkaṭai ceytanāṉṟu</ta>. The translation of this phrase by “a deadly battle” is purely conjectural. It is not found in the dictionaries. The word may also mean “a fight on elephants.”</note> at <hi rend="bold">Vēḷūr</hi>. in the manner described below, feed regularly at the time when offerings are made to the lord (<hi rend="italic">perumāṉaḍigaḷ</hi>) of our village of <hi rend="bold">Tirukkarapuram</hi>, on the bank of the <hi rend="bold">Pāryāṟu</hi><note n="233-1">Pāryāṟu must evidently be the Pālāṟu on which the present village of Tiruppāṟkkaḍal is situated.</note> , in the feeding hall (<hi rend="italic">śālai-maṇḍagam</hi>) constructed by him (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Śeṉṉi Pēraraiyar), without any break as long as the moon (<hi rend="italic">lasts</hi>), four <hi rend="italic">apūrvi</hi><note n="233-2">The technical term <hi rend="italic">apūrvi</hi> as applied to Vēdie Brāhmaṇas is also found in an inscription from the Vishṇu temple at Eṇṇāyiram (No. 333 of 1917). In describing a school for the students of the Vēdas, it mentions three students and teachers of the Ṛig, Yajus, etc., Vēdas who either studied <hi rend="italic">apūrva</hi> or taught it. It is not improbable that the term was intended to convey a special method of studying the Vēdas and was an accepted synonym for Vēdic literature which included Rig, Yajus, Chhāndōgya-Sāma, Talavakāra-Sāma, Vājasanēya, Atharva, Bandhāyanīya-Gṛihya, Kalpa, Gaṇa and Kāṭhaka.</note> Brāhmaṇas versed in the <hi rend="bold">Vēdas</hi>, with rich meals (<hi rend="italic">agram)</hi><note n="233-3"><hi rend="italic">Agram</hi> is still used in Malabar in connexion with the term <hi rend="italic">agra-śālā</hi>, ‘cooking houses in temples’ and with <hi rend="italic">agraśāla-para</hi> a special measure used in these cooking houses. <hi rend="italic">Agram</hi> also means excellent or chief. When applied to a meal it means perhaps the chief meal provided for in a temple.</note> supplying four vegetables (<hi rend="italic">kaṟi</hi>), one <hi rend="italic">āḻākku</hi> of ghee for each individual and one <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of curd for each individual.</p>

<p>(L. 4.) After these are richly fed, two areca-nuts (<hi rend="italic">kāy</hi>) and leaves shall be given to each of them. Thus shall the rich repast be given. The great men of the <hi rend="italic">tank-committee</hi> who perform (<hi rend="italic">the duties of) ēri-vāriyam</hi> year after year shall themselves supervise and feed the four Brāhmaṇas as long as the moon (<hi rend="italic">lasts</hi>). Those who protect this charity shall obtain the merit of the performance of Aśvamēdha (<hi rend="italic">sacrifice</hi>). Those who obstruct this, charity shall incur the sins committed (<hi rend="italic">by sinners</hi>) between the Ganges and Cape Comorin. We, the members of the great assembly including the great men of the <hi rend="italic">tankcommittee</hi> of this year, have ordered (<hi rend="italic">in the aforesaid manner</hi>). I, the arbitrator (<hi rend="italic">madhyastha</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śivakkuṟi Nūṟṟeṇmaṉ</hi>, wrote (<hi rend="italic">this document</hi>) under the orders of the great men of the <hi rend="italic">tank-committee</hi> of this year, being (<hi rend="italic">myself</hi>) present in the assembly.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.99 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">231-233</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">99</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
