<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.29: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 29.—ON THE OUTSIDE OF THE EAST WALL OF THE INNER PRAKARA OF THE RAJAGOPALA-PERUMAL TEMPLE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0029</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>Above, Vol. II. p. 303, I noticed two inscriptions of the 4th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājēndradēva</hi>. One of these is the subjoined inscription. It is dated on a week-day (l. 14 f.) which will probably admit of astronomical calculation as soon as a second, similarly dated record of the same reign may be discovered.<note n="58-4">As the day of the year of the reign is mentioned besides the week-day, the calculation of the latter would also settle the very date of Rājēndra's accession to the throne.</note> The text of the historical introduction has been settled with the help of two other inscriptions, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>—</p>						

						<p>1. Tv. = an inscription of the 4th year in the Bilvanāthēśvara temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruvallam</hi> in the North Arcot district (No. 190 of 1894).</p>						

						<p>2. Tm. = an inscription of the 8th year in the Vaidyanātha temple at <hi rend="bold">Tirumalavāḍi</hi> in the Trichinopoly district (No. 84 of 1895).</p>						

						<p>Like the inscriptions of his predecessor Rājādhirāja (p. 55 f. above) and those of his successor Vīrarājēndra I. (p. 33 above), this inscription of Rājēndra opens with a list of relatives on whom the king conferred certain titles (ll. 1 to 6). The recipients of these honours were a paternal uncle of the king, four younger brothers of his, six sons (?)<note n="58-5">See below, page 62, note 9.</note> and two grandsons (?).<note n="58-6">See below, p. 62, note 17.</note> The fifth of the sons—<hi rend="bold">Muḍikoṇḍa-Chōḷa</hi> with the title <hi rend="bold">Sundara-Chōḷa</hi><note n="58-7">The second son of the king also had the name Muḍikoṇḍa-Chōḷa, but bore the title Vijayālaya.</note> —is perhaps identical with a prince of the same name and title, who is mentioned in the inscriptions of Rājēndra's successor, Vīrarājēndra I.<note n="58-8">See p. 33 above.</note> </p>						

						<p>Lines 6 to 12 give a detailed account of the battle of <hi rend="bold">Koppam</hi>, which is only briefly noticed in the hitherto published inscriptions of Rājēndra.<note n="58-9">See above, p. 39, and Vol. II. p. 303.</note> His enemy <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla (-Sōmēśvara I.)</hi> is here expressly called <hi rend="bold">Śaḷukki</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Chalukya king (ll. 7, 9 and 10). The Chōḷa king invaded <hi rend="bold">Raṭṭa-maṇḍalam</hi> and was met by Āhavamalla at Koppam. At first the advantage seems to have been on the side of the Chalukya king. Rājēndra himself and his elephant were wounded by arrows, and the men who had mounted the elephant along with him were killed. But fresh troops were advanced and turned the fortune of the battle. Āhavamalla fled, and several of his officers fell. Among these the inscription mentions a younger brother of the <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king—<hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha,<note n="58-10">This prince is not mentioned in the Western Chālukya inscriptions.</note> Pulikēśin,<note n="58-11">This chief was named after the two Chalukya kings of the same name.</note> Daśapaṉmaṉ,</hi><note n="58-12">This chief was named after Daśavarman or Yaśōvarman, the younger son of Taila II. Daśavarman is a vulgar form of Yaśōvarman; compare <hi rend="italic">tuvarāya</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tuvarāśa</hi> for <hi rend="italic">yuvarāja, Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 180 and note 5.</note> <hi rend="bold">Aśōkaiyaṉ, Āraiyaṉ, Moṭṭaiyaṉ</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Naṉṉi-Nuḷambaṉ</hi>,<note n="59-1">This may have been a Pallava chief of Nuḷambapāḍi; see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 180 and note 3.</note> and among those who took part in the flight, <hi rend="bold">Vaṉṉiya-Rēvaṉ, Tuttaṉ</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Kuṇḍamayaṉ</hi>. The first of these three chiefs is perhaps identical with the <hi rend="bold">Haihaya</hi> <hi rend="italic">Mahāmaṇḍalēśvara</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rēvarasa</hi>, who is mentioned as a vassal of Sōmēśvara I. in an inscription of A.D. 1054-55.<note n="59-2">Dr. Fleet's <hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, second edition, p. 439.</note> Among the spoil of the battle were many elephants, three of which are mentioned by name (l. 11), the banner of the boar, and two queens by name <hi rend="bold">Śattiyavvai</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Śāṅgappai</hi> (l. 12).</p>						

						<p>Finally, Rājēndra despatched an army to <hi rend="bold">Ceylon</hi>, where the <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Śalāmēgaṉ</hi> was decapitated and the two sons of the Ceylon king <hi rend="bold">Mānābharaṇaṉ</hi> were taken prisoners. Another Vīra-Śalāmēgaṉ, who is stated to have migrated to Ceylon from Kanyakubja, had been killed by Rājēndra's predecessor Rājādhirāja.<note n="59-3">See page 56 above.</note> The same Chōḷa king had decapitated another Mānābharaṇa, who was, however, a Pāṇḍya king and not a king of Ceylon.<note n="59-4">See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi></note> The <hi rend="italic">Mahāvaṁsa</hi> mentions two princes of the name Māṇābharaṇa, and two others of the name Kittisirimēgha. Māṇābharaṇa I.<note n="59-5">He became the father of king Parakkamabāhu I.; see chapter lxii. verse 52.</note> and Kittisirimēgha I. were nephews and sons-in-law of the Ceylon king Vijayabāhu I. (chapter lix. verses 42 and 44). His queen Tilōkasundari was a princess of Kaliṅga (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> verse 29 f.).<note n="59-6">Verse 46 mentions three of her relations, Madhukaṇṇava, Bhīmarāja and Balakkāra.</note> Mānābharaṇaṉ and Vīra-Śalāmēgaṉ in the subjoined inscription might correspond to Māṇābharaṇa and Kittisirimēgha in the <hi rend="italic">Mahāvaṁsa</hi>, and the reason why Vīra-Śalāmēgaṉ is styled a Kaliṅga king in the inscription might be the fact that his mother-in-law was a Kaliṅga princess according to the <hi rend="italic">Mahāvaṁsa</hi>. On the other hand king Vijayabāhu I. is supposed to have reigned from A.D. 1065 to 1120, and Vikkamabāhu I., in whose time Māṇābharaṇa I. and Kittisirimēgha I. usurped the government of Ceylon, from A.D. 1121 to 1142, while Rājēndra and Vīrarājēndra I. have to be accommodated between A.D. 1050 and 1070.<note n="59-7">See page 32 above.</note> Consequently, Mānābharaṇaṉ and Vīra-Śalāmēgaṉ in the inscription must be distinct from, and prior to, Māṇābharaṇa I. and Kittisirimēgha I. in the <hi rend="italic">Mahāvaṁsa</hi>. But, as I have previously stated (p. 39 above), the conquest of Ceylon by Rājēndra is established by the existence of an inscription of his in that island.</p>						

						<p>The subjoined inscription records that the villagers received an unspecified sum from <hi rend="bold">Kāmakkavvaiyaḷ</hi>, the mother of the <hi rend="italic">Sēnāpati</hi> <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Chōḷa-Brahmādhirāja</hi>, and granted in return a piece of land at <hi rend="bold">Amaṇpākkam</hi>—the modern Ammaṇambākkam—on the south of <hi rend="bold">Maṇimaṅgalam</hi><note n="59-8">See above, p. 50 and note 3.</note> to the temple. This land was situated “to the south of the land that has been formerly granted to this god by a stone inscription.” The reference is to an inscription of <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman</hi> (No. 27 above), which registers a grant of land on the south of Maṇimaṅgalam and east of Amaṇpākkam.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī<unclear>ḥ</unclear></hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tirumātu puviyeṉu<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> peru<unclear>m</unclear>āta<unclear>r Iva</unclear>r <unclear>tan mā</unclear>t<unclear>e</unclear>viyaḷāka<note n="59-9">ṭm. reads teviyarkaḷāka.</note> <note n="59-10">Read mītoḷi.</note> mit<unclear>o</unclear><unclear>ḷi</unclear>v<unclear>e</unclear>ṇkuṭai<unclear>yuya</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied><unclear>t</unclear>tu <unclear>ti</unclear>ṇkali peyarttu <unclear>ta</unclear>ṉ ciṟiya<unclear>t</unclear>ā<unclear>t</unclear>aiyātiya<note n="59-11">Tv. and Tm. read yākiya.</note> Eṟivali ka<unclear>ṅ</unclear>k<unclear>ai</unclear>koṇṭacoḻa<unclear>ṉai p</unclear>oṅ<unclear>ki</unclear>tal<note n="59-12">Tv. and Tm. read poṅkikal .</note> Irumaṭicoḻaneṉ<unclear>ṟu</unclear>m porumuraṭṭaṉṟiru
<lb n="2" break="no"/>t<unclear>ta</unclear>mpiyarta<unclear>mmu</unclear>ḷ v<unclear>e</unclear>ṉṟiko<unclear>ḷ</unclear> mummaṭi<unclear>c</unclear>oḻa<unclear>ṉai</unclear>tte<unclear>m</unclear>muṉai<unclear>ya</unclear>ṭu<unclear>ti</unclear>ṟa<unclear>ṟ</unclear>coḻapāṇṭi<unclear>ya</unclear>n<unclear>e</unclear>ṉṟuṅkoḻimaṉṟoṭuka<unclear>ḻa</unclear>l <unclear>vī</unclear>racoḻaṉaippaṭipu<unclear>ka</unclear>ḻkkarikālacoḻaneṉṟum porutoḻilvāḻvalittaṭakkai<note n="60-1">ṭv. and ṭm. read vāḷvali.</note> maturān=takaṉai
<lb n="3"/>coḻakaṅkaneṉṟun=toḷvalimevikal parā<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>nta</unclear></hi>katevaṉai coḷa<unclear>va</unclear>y<unclear>o</unclear>ttiyarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>n<unclear>e</unclear>ṉṟu<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied><note n="60-2">Read perhaps tuyara.</note> tayarattaṉpoṭu karutu kātala<unclear>ru</unclear>ḷ It<unclear>ta</unclear>la<unclear>m</unclear> pu<unclear>ka</unclear>ḻ <hi rend="grantha">rāj<unclear>e</unclear>ntra</hi>co<unclear>ḻa</unclear>ṉai U<unclear>tta</unclear>macoḻaneṉṟu<hi rend="grantha">n<unclear>to</unclear></hi><unclear>t</unclear>taṇimu<unclear>k</unclear>ai<unclear>yaviḻa</unclear>laṅkal muṭiko
<lb n="4" break="no"/><unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭacoḻaṉai I<unclear>ka</unclear>l vicaiyālai<unclear>ya</unclear>neṉṟum pukarmukatteḻuyarkaḷiṟṟu c<unclear>o</unclear>ḻak<unclear>e</unclear>ra<unclear>ḷa</unclear>ṉai vārcilai coḻa<unclear>k</unclear>eraḷa<unclear>n</unclear>eṉṟu(m)n=tiṇṭiṟaṟkaṭāra<unclear>ṅ</unclear>koṇṭacoḻaṉai tiṉakara<unclear>ṉ</unclear> ku<unclear>la</unclear>t<unclear>tu ci</unclear>ṟappamar coḷa<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉakarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>neṉṟuṅkaṉaikaṭal paṭi
<lb n="5"/>koṇṭa palapu<unclear>ka</unclear>ḻ muṭikoṇṭacoḻaṉai cun=taracoḻaneṉṟu<supplied reason="omitted">ñ</supplied>cen=tamiḻ<unclear>p</unclear>piṭika<unclear>li</unclear>raṭṭapāṭikoṇṭacoḻa<unclear>ṉai</unclear> tolpuviyāḷu<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aiccoḻakaṉṉakucciyarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ne<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟumaṉṉutaṉ<note n="60-3">ṭv. reads [ṉ]e[ṉ*]ṟum piṉṉuntaṉ.</note> kātalar kātalartammuḷ meta<unclear>ku</unclear>katirāṅka<unclear>ṉai</unclear>kaḻa
<lb n="6" break="no"/>l maturān=takaṉai velpaṭaiccoḻavallapane<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟumāṉacilai<unclear>kkai</unclear>y<unclear>o</unclear>rāṉaiccevakaṉai<note n="60-4">Read nirupentira.</note> nirupe<hi rend="grantha">ntri</hi>raco<unclear>ḻa</unclear>neṉ<unclear>ṟu</unclear>m paruma<unclear>ṇi</unclear>ccuṭar<note n="60-5">ṭv. and ṭm. read neṭumakuṭañ.</note> maṇima<unclear>ku</unclear>ṭañ<unclear>cū</unclear>ṭṭippaṭi<note n="60-6">Tv. reads micai nikaḻu.</note> mi<unclear>c</unclear>ai<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>nti</unclear></hi>kaḻunāḷiṉu<unclear>ḷi</unclear>ka<unclear>l</unclear> veṭṭeḻu[ <hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu] ce<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟo<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭiṟa<unclear>li</unclear>raṭṭamaṇ
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ṭalameyti natikaḷunāṭum patikaḷumanekamaḻi<unclear>t</unclear>ta<unclear>ṉa</unclear>ṉ vaḷavane<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṉumo<unclear>ḻi</unclear>ppa<note n="60-7">ṭv. and ṭm. read moḻi.</note> poruḷ keṭṭu vekaveñ<unclear>ca</unclear>ḷukki Ākavama<unclear>l</unclear>laṉ paripavamiṉakkiceṉṟeri<note n="60-8">Tm. has parivam e[na]kitenṟeri; read paripavameṉakkiteṉṟeri.</note> <unclear>viḻi</unclear>tteḻu<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu cepparun=tiratta koppattakavaiyil ceṉṟeti
<lb n="8" break="no"/>reṉṟamar tuṭaṅkiya poḻutava<unclear>ṉ</unclear> ceñcaramāri taṉ kuñcaramukatti<unclear>ṉu</unclear>n=ta<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟiruttuṭaiyiluṅkuṉṟuṟa<unclear>ḷ</unclear><note n="60-9">Read kuṉṟuṟaḻ.</note> puyat<unclear>tilu</unclear><hi rend="grantha">nt</hi>aiyk<unclear>ka</unclear>vun=ta<unclear>ṉṉu</unclear>ṭa<unclear>ṉ kaḷiṟeṟiya to</unclear>ṭukaḻal<note n="60-10">Read vīrar.</note> <unclear>vi</unclear>rarkaḷ maṭiyavum vakaiyātota<unclear>ṉiya</unclear>n<unclear>e</unclear>kam<note n="60-11">Tv. and Tm. read torutani.</note> porupaṭai
<lb n="9"/><note n="60-12">Tv. and Tm. read vaḻaṅki.</note> vamaṅkiyammoymmar<note n="60-13">Tm. reads moym[pa]mar.</note> <unclear>ca</unclear>ḷukki tampi <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaciṅkaṉum<note n="60-14">Tm. reads pulikeci.</note> porppulakkeciyun=tārt<unclear>ta</unclear>caṉma<unclear>ṉu</unclear>māṉamaṉṉavaril<note n="60-15">ṭv. and ṭm. read tacapaṉma.</note> <note n="60-16">Tm. reads maṇṭali acokaiyanum āna vaṇpukaḻ āḷum āraiyanum.</note> maṇṭali<unclear>ka</unclear>cokaṉumā<unclear>ṉa va</unclear>ṇpukaḻāḷum<unclear>ār</unclear>aiyaṉun=teṉivarmaṭṭaviḻa<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kal<note n="60-17">ṭv. and ṭm. read viḻalaṅkal.</note> moṭ<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aiyaṉun=ti<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭiṟal naṉṉinuḷampaṉumeṉu
<lb n="10" break="no"/>miva<unclear>r</unclear> mutaliyar Eṇṇiliyaraica<unclear>r</unclear>ai vi<unclear>ṇṇa</unclear>katteṟṟi vaṉ<unclear>ṉi</unclear>yarevaṉum va<unclear>ya</unclear>ppaṭaittutta<unclear>ṉu</unclear>ṅko<unclear>ṉṉa</unclear>vilpaṭaikkuṇṭamaya<unclear>ṉu</unclear>m Eṉṟi<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṉaveñciṉavaraicaroṭañci<note n="60-18">ṭv. and ṭm. read ṭañciya.</note> caḷu<unclear>k</unclear>ki kula<unclear>ku</unclear>lakulai<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu talaimayir viri<unclear>t</unclear>tu v<unclear>eṉu</unclear>ṟa <unclear>n</unclear>eḷit<unclear>tu</unclear>ppiṉṉuṟa
<lb n="11"/>nok<unclear>ki</unclear> kāl paṟin=toṭi melkaṭal pāyattuttiya<note n="60-19">ṭv. reads turattiya.</note> poḻutaccerukkaḷattavaṉ viṭu catturupayaṅkaraṉ<note n="60-20">Tv. has mulapattara; read mūlapattira .</note> karapattiramutapattira<hi rend="grantha">jā</hi>tipakaṭṭa<unclear>r</unclear>aicaneka<unclear>mu</unclear>meṭṭu<unclear>ni</unclear>rai<note n="60-21">Tv. and Tm. read meṭṭunaṭai.</note> <unclear>pa</unclear>rikaḷumoṭṭakaniraika<unclear>ḷu</unclear>m <unclear>va</unclear>rākavelkoṭi mutal rā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>pariccan=tamum
<lb n="12"/>Op<unclear>pi</unclear>l cappiyavvaiy<note n="60-22">ṭv. reads cattiyavvai cāṅkappai.</note> cakappaiyeṉṟivar mutal teviyar kuḻāmum pāv<unclear>ai</unclear>yariṭṭamumeṉaiyaṉa<note n="60-23">Read rīṭṭa.</note> piṟavumuṉaivayaṟkoṭṭu<note n="60-24">Tv. and Tm. read muṉaivaiyiṟkoṇṭu.</note> vi<hi rend="grantha">jai</hi>yaa<hi rend="grantha">bhiṣe</hi>kam ceytu <note n="61-1">ṭv.reads ten[ṟi]caivayiṟporu.</note> t<unclear>o</unclear><unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟicaivayirpporppaṭai naṭātti<unclear>k</unclear>kārkkaṭalilaṅkaiyil viṟa<unclear>ṟ</unclear>paṭaikkaliṅkar <unclear>ma</unclear>
<lb n="13" break="no"/>ṉ<note n="61-2">Read vīra.</note> viracalāmekaṉaikkaṭaṟkaḷiṟṟoṭumakappaṭakkatirmuṭi <unclear>ka</unclear>ṭivittilaṅkaiyaṟkiṟaivaṉ<note n="61-3">Read yarkkiṟaivaṉ.</note> mā<unclear>p</unclear>paraṇaṉ<note n="61-4">Tv. reads mānāparaṇan .</note> <note n="61-5">Tv. and Tm. read kātalariru .</note> kātalararuvaraikkaḷattiṭaip<unclear>pi</unclear>ttu<note n="61-6">Tv. and Tm. read [pi]ṭittu .</note> māpperum pukaḻ <unclear>mi</unclear>ka vaḷartta kopparak<unclear>e</unclear><hi rend="grantha">śa</hi>ri[ pa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>r] Āna <unclear>U</unclear>ṭai<unclear>y</unclear>ār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendra</hi>tevaṟ<unclear>ku</unclear> yāṇṭu nālāva
<lb n="14" break="no"/>tu <supplied reason="omitted">nā</supplied>ḷ <hi rend="grantha">8<unclear>2</unclear></hi> <g type="ddanda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅko<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭacoḻamaṇṭalattu ceṅkāṭṭukkoṭṭattu mākaṇūrnā<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭu <hi rend="grantha">rāja</hi>cūḷāmaṇicca<supplied reason="omitted">tu</supplied>ruppetima<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kalattu <hi rend="grantha">mahāsabh<unclear>ai</unclear>-</hi> y<unclear>o</unclear>m Ivvāṭṭai <hi rend="grantha">si<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied>ha</hi>nāyaṟṟu <hi rend="grantha">Aparapakṣa</hi><unclear>t</unclear>tu <hi rend="grantha">Aṣṭa</hi>miyum viyāḻakkiḻamaiyum
<lb n="15"/>peṟṟa<note n="61-7">Read <hi rend="grantha">rohi</hi>ṇi.</note> <hi rend="grantha">roja</hi>ṇināḷ Emmur<note n="61-8">Read emmūr.</note> <hi rend="grantha">brahmasthā</hi>namaṇṭapa<unclear>t</unclear>te <unclear>kū</unclear>ṭṭakkuṟaivaṟak<unclear>kū</unclear>ṭiyittu<note n="61-9">Read yiruntu.</note> Eṅkaḷur<note n="61-10">Read eṅkaḷūr.</note> <hi rend="grantha">śrīma<supplied reason="omitted">d</supplied>dvārāpa</hi>tiyāṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāmakk<unclear>o</unclear>ṭiviṇṇakar<unclear>ā</unclear>ḻvārkku kuṭutta nilam<unclear>āva</unclear>tu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Eṅka<unclear>ḷu</unclear>r<note type="repeated" n="61-10"/> teṉpiṭākai Amaṇpākkattu nila
<lb n="16" break="no"/><note n="61-11">Read kīḻ.</note> ṅkiḻp<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>ṟkellai maṇṇikkālukku meṟkum teṉpāṟkellai maṇṇikkālukku vaṭakkum melpāṟkellai
<lb n="17"/>Araicaṅkuṭṭattukkum naṅkāciyeṉṉum pulattukkuṅkiḻakkum vaṭa<unclear>p</unclear>āṟkellai paḻuvur<note n="61-12">Read paḻuvūr.</note> nakkapputteri karaikku te
<lb n="18" break="no"/><unclear>ṟ</unclear>kum Ittevarkku muṉpu <hi rend="grantha">śilālekhai</hi> paṇṇiṉa nilattukku teṟkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Āka Iṉnāṟp<unclear>ā</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">ṟ</supplied>kellaikkum naṭuvupaṭṭa ni
<lb n="19" break="no"/><unclear>lamu</unclear>m Oṭaiyumuṭaippum menokki<unclear>ṉa</unclear> maramum <unclear>kī</unclear>ṇokkiya <unclear>ki</unclear>ṇaṟu<unclear>m</unclear> Iṉnāṟpāṟkellaikkum naṭuvupaṭṭa
<lb n="20" break="no"/><unclear>te</unclear>llām <hi rend="grantha">se</hi><unclear>ṉā</unclear>pati<unclear>ka</unclear>ḷ <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻa<hi rend="grantha">brahmādhirā</hi>[<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>]r tāy<unclear>ār</unclear> kāmakkavvaiyaḷ pakkal <hi rend="grantha">svam</hi> k<unclear>o</unclear>ṇṭu <hi rend="grantha">śantrā</hi><note n="61-13">Read <hi rend="grantha">candrā</hi>.</note> 
<lb n="21" break="no"/>tittavaṟ Iṉnilattukku Iṟaiyi<unclear>ṟu</unclear>t<unclear>tu</unclear>kkuṭuppomānom <hi rend="grantha">mahāsabhai</hi>yom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>sa</unclear>bhai<unclear>yu</unclear></hi>
<lb n="22" break="no"/><unclear>ḷi</unclear>ru<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu karaiyiṭṭukkaraippo<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu pa<unclear>ṇi</unclear>tta kārāmpiceṭṭu n<unclear>ā</unclear>rāya<unclear>ṇa</unclear>kkiramavittaṉum Irāyūr ca<note n="61-14">Read cantira.</note> 
<lb n="23" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">ntri</hi>rateva<unclear>a</unclear>ttāḻikkiramavitta<unclear>ṉu</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> <hi rend="grantha">saha</hi>ṇai <unclear>m</unclear>ātavakkira<unclear>ma</unclear>vittaṉum paṇippaṇiyāl
<lb n="24"/>pa<unclear>ṇi</unclear> keṭṭu <unclear>E</unclear>ḻutin<unclear>e</unclear>ṉ Ivvur<note n="61-15">Read ivvūr.</note> Ūrkkaraṇattāṉ Alaṅkāraṉ<note n="61-16">Read cīrāma.</note> ci<unclear>rā</unclear>maneṉ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai Eṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1899_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! While the goddess of fortune and the great goddess of the earth became his great queens, (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) raised on high (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) brilliant white parasol and uprooted the powerful Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>).</p>

<p>(<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) bestowed high crowns, resplendent with large jewels, on <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgaikoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-1">The same was a surname of Rājēndra-Chōḷa I. and the name of a son of Vīrarājēndra I.; see p. 33 above, and <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XXI. p. 323.</note> who was the younger brother of his father (<hi rend="italic">and who was</hi>) powerful in defeating (<hi rend="italic">his enemies), (with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Irumaḍi-Śōḻaṉ</hi> of exuberant valour;’ among his royal younger brothers of warlike strength, on the victorious <hi rend="bold">Mummaḍi-Śōḻaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-2">The same had been a surname of Rājarāja I.; see above, p. 22 and note 11.</note> (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Pāṇḍiyaṉ</hi> whose valour conquers (<hi rend="italic">enemies</hi>) on the battle-field;’ on <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, the lord of <hi rend="bold">Kōḻi</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Uṟaiyūr),<note n="62-3">See above, Vol. II. p. 380 and notes 3 and 4.</note> who wore ankle-rings, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Karikāla-Śōḻaṉ</hi><note n="62-4">Karikāla had been the name of an ancient Chōḷa king; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> p. 377 f.</note> (<hi rend="italic">who is</hi>) praised on earth;’ on <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntakaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-5">The same was the name or surname of three Chōḷa kings (<hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>). Vol. IV. p. 331) and the name of a son of Vīrarājēndra I. (p. 33 above).</note> whose strong and broad hand (<hi rend="italic">wielded</hi>) the sword in warfare, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) <hi rend="bold">‘Śōḻa-Gaṅgaṉ;’</hi><note n="62-6">Chōḍagaṅga was also a surname of the Eastern Gaṅga king Anantavarman; <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XVIII. p. 161.</note> on <hi rend="bold">Parāntakadēvaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-7">Parāṇtaka had been the name of two Chōḷa kings; see the Table on p. 112 of Vol. I. above.</note> whose valour was combined with strength of shoulders, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śōḷa-Ayōttiyarājaṉ;’</hi><note n="62-8"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> ‘the Ayōdhyā king (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Rāma) among the Chōḷas.’</note> among (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) sons,<note n="62-9">The word <hi rend="italic">kādalar</hi> may also mean ‘friends.’</note> who regarded with kindness (<hi rend="italic">their enemies ?</hi>) in distress, on <hi rend="bold">Rājēndra-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) praised on this earth, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) <hi rend="bold">‘Uttama-Śōḻaṉ;’</hi><note n="62-10">The same appears to have been a surname of Rājēndra-Chōḷa I. This may be concluded from the surname of one of his officers; see p. 14 above.</note> on <hi rend="bold">Muḍikoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who wore</hi>) a garland of opening buds (<hi rend="italic">as</hi>) an ancient (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> hereditary) ornament, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘the brave <hi rend="bold">Vijayālayaṉ;’</hi><note n="62-11">This had been the name of the ancestor of the ruling Chōḷa dynasty; see above, Vol. II. p. 379.</note> on <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Kēraḷaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-12">Compare the territorial designation Śōḻa-Kēraḷa-maṇḍalam, p. 31 above.</note> (<hi rend="italic">who possessed</hi>) very tall elephants with spotted foreheads, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Kēraḷaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">who holds</hi>) a long bow;’ on <hi rend="bold">Kaḍāraṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi><note n="62-13"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> ‘the Chōḷa who conquered Kaḍāram,’ which figures among the conquests of Rājēndra-Chōḷa I.; see above, Vol. II. p. 105 f.</note> of great valour, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Śōḷa-Janakarājaṉ</hi><note n="62-14">Janaka is the name of Rāma's father-in-law; compare note 8 above.</note> in whom the eminence of the race of the Sun rests;’ on <hi rend="bold">Muḍikoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi>, who conquered the earth (<hi rend="italic">surrounded by</hi>) the roaring ocean (<hi rend="italic">and who was</hi>) praised by many, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) <hi rend="bold">‘Sundara-Śōḻaṉ;’</hi> on <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭapāḍikoṇḍa-Śōḻaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-15"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> ‘the Chōḷa who conquered Raṭṭapāḍi,’ which figures among the conquests of Rājarāja I. and his successors.</note> (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the rock of support to pure Tamiḻ, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Kaṉṉakuchchiyarājaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-16">A similar title had been conferred by Rājādhirāja on one of his relatives; see p. 56 above.</note> the lord of the ancient earth;’ then, among the sons of his sons,<note n="62-17">Or, ‘the friends of his friends;’ see note 9 above.</note> on <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntakaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-18">Another Madhurāntaka was mentioned before as one of the king's younger brothers.</note> who was (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> resembled) the great sun (<hi rend="italic">and who wore</hi>) sounding ankle-rings, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) ‘<hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Vallabhaṉ</hi><note n="62-19">Vallabha was a title of the Chalukya kings; compare above, p. 55, note 20.</note> (<hi rend="italic">who leads</hi>) a victorious army;’ and on the matchless <hi rend="bold">Āṉaichchēvagaṉ</hi>,<note n="62-20">This name means ‘a mahout.’</note> whose hand (<hi rend="italic">held</hi>) a strong bow, (<hi rend="italic">with the title</hi>) <hi rend="bold">‘Nṛipēndra-Śōḻaṉ.’</hi></p>

<p>(L. 6.) While (<hi rend="italic">the</hi> Chōḷa <hi rend="italic">king</hi>) was resplendent on earth, the proud and furious <hi rend="bold">Śaḷukki</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Chalukya king) <hi rend="bold">Āhavamallaṉ</hi>,—having heard the substance of the report that the <hi rend="bold">Vaḷavaṉ</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Chōḷa king), desirous of war, had started (<hi rend="italic">from his country</hi>), had reached <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-maṇḍalam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">whose inhabitants are</hi>) very brave, and had destroyed many rivers (!), districts and towns,—exclaimed: “This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) a disgrace to me !,” sprang up, (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) eyes burning (<hi rend="italic">with rage</hi>), went into <hi rend="bold">Koppam</hi>, the strength (<hi rend="italic">of whose position is</hi>) hard to describe, (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) commenced to attack the enemy.</p>

<p>(L. 8.) At that time, when the shower of his (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Āhavamalla's) straight arrows pierced the forehead of his (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Chōḷa king's) elephant, his royal thigh, and (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) shoulders which resembled hillocks, and when the warriors wearing ankle-rings, who had mounted the elephant along with him, fell, (<hi rend="italic">the</hi> Chōḷa <hi rend="italic">king</hi>) distributed (<hi rend="italic">on the battle-field</hi>) many matchless warlike regiments (<hi rend="italic">which had</hi>) not (<hi rend="italic">yet been</hi>) detached, and transported to heaven <hi rend="bold">Jayaśiṅgaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who was</hi>) the younger brother of that strong <hi rend="bold">Śaḷukki</hi>, the warlike <hi rend="bold">Pulikēśi</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Daśapaṉmaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who wore</hi>) a garland; among proud princes: the chief (<hi rend="italic">Maṇḍalin</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Aśōkaiyaṉ, Āraiyaṉ</hi>, who ruled (<hi rend="italic">with</hi>) great fame which was well deserved, <hi rend="bold">Moṭṭaiyaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who wore</hi>) a garland of half-open (<hi rend="italic">buds</hi>) full of honey, <hi rend="bold">Naṉṉi-Nuḷambaṉ</hi> of great valour, and other princes without number.</p>

<p>(L. 10.) The <hi rend="bold">Śaḷukki</hi> was defeated,—with <hi rend="bold">Vaṉṉiya-Rēvaṉ, Tuttaṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who had</hi>) a powerful army, <hi rend="bold">Kuṇḍamayaṉ</hi>, whose army spoke (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> threatened) death, and other princes, —fled, trembling vehemently, with dishevelled hair, turning (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) back, looking round, and tiring (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) legs, and was forced to plunge into the western ocean.</p>

<p>(L. 11.) At that time (<hi rend="italic">the</hi> Chōḷa <hi rend="italic">king</hi>) captured in battle <hi rend="italic">Śatrubhayaṁkara, Karabhadra, Mūlabhadra</hi> and many (<hi rend="italic">other</hi>) excellent elephants of noble breed, horses of lofty gait, herds of camels, the victorious banner of the boar and the other insignia of royalty, the peerless <hi rend="bold">Śattiyavvai, Śāṅgappai</hi> and all the other queens, a crowd of women, and other (<hi rend="italic">booty</hi>) which he (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> Āhavamalla) had abandoned on that battle-field, and performed the anointment of victory.</p>

<p>(L. 12.) (<hi rend="italic">The king</hi>) despatched a warlike army into the southern region, captured in <hi rend="bold">Laṅkā</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">surrounded by</hi>) the black ocean, <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Śalāmēgaṉ</hi>, the king of the <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅgas</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">who had</hi>) a powerful army, with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) elephants (<hi rend="italic">which resembled</hi>) the ocean, caused to be cut off (<hi rend="italic">his head which wore</hi>) a brilliant crown, and seized on the battle-field the two sons of <hi rend="bold">Mānābharaṇaṉ</hi>, the king of the people of <hi rend="bold">Laṅkā</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 13.) On the 8[2]nd day of the fourth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the lord <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājēndradēva</hi>, who (<hi rend="italic">continually</hi>) increased very much (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) very great fame,—we, the great assembly of <hi rend="bold">Rājaśūḷāmaṇi-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Māgaṇūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Śēṅgāṭṭu-kōṭṭam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻa-maṇḍalam</hi>, being assembled, without a vacancy in the assembly, in the <hi rend="italic">Brahmasthāna-maṇḍapa</hi><note n="63-1">See above, p. 57 and note 9.</note> in our village on the day of <hi rend="italic">Rōhiṇī</hi>, which corresponded to a Thursday and to the eighth <hi rend="italic">tithi</hi> of the second fortnight of the month of <hi rend="italic">Siṁha</hi> in this year, gave the following land to (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śrīmad-Dvārāpati</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Kāmakkōḍi-Viṇṇagar-Āḻvār</hi>, in our village.</p>

<p>(L. 15.) Land at <hi rend="bold">Amaṇpākkam</hi>, a southern hamlet of our village. The eastern boundary (<hi rend="italic">of this land is</hi>) to the west of the <hi rend="italic">Maṇṇikkāl</hi> (channel);<note n="63-2">The same channel is mentioned in line 5 of No. 27 above.</note> the southern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the north of the <hi rend="italic">Maṇṇikkāl</hi> (channel); the western boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the east of the <hi rend="italic">Araiśaṅguṭṭam</hi> (pond) and of the field named <hi rend="italic">Naṅgāśi</hi>; and the northern boundary (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) to the south of the bank of the <hi rend="italic">Nakkapputtēri</hi> (tank) at <hi rend="bold">Paḻuvūr</hi> and to the south of the land that has been formerly granted to this god by a stone inscription.</p>

<p>(L. 18.) Having received funds (<hi rend="italic">svam</hi>) from <hi rend="bold">Kāmakkavvaiyaḷ</hi>, the mother of the <hi rend="italic">Sēnāpati</hi> <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻa-Brahmādhirājar</hi>, we, the great assembly, are bound to pay the taxes on this land for as long as the moon and the sun exist, and to give the whole land enclosed within these four boundaries, the water-courses, the breaches (<hi rend="italic">in the</hi>) bands <hi rend="italic">of tanks</hi>),<note n="64-1">Compare above, Vol. II. p. 393.</note> the trees overground and the wells underground.</p>

<p>(L. 21.) Having been present in the assembly and having heard the order of <hi rend="bold">Kārāmbiśeṭṭu Nārāyaṇa-Kramavittaṉ,<note n="64-2">See above, p. 4, note 10.</note> Chandradēva-[A]ttāḻi-Kramavittaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Irāyūr</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Sahaṇai Mādhava-Kramavittaṉ</hi>, who had distributed the blocks (<hi rend="italic">karai)</hi><note n="64-3">Compare above, Vol. II. p. 116.</note> and inspected the blocks, I, <hi rend="bold">Alaṅkāraṉ Śrīrāmaṉ</hi>, the village-accountant of this village, wrote (<hi rend="italic">the above</hi>). This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) my writing.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.29 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">58-64</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">29</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
