<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.80: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 80.—INSCRIPTION IN THE ARULALA-PERUMAL TEMPLE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0080</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription (No. 33 of 1893) is engraved on the west wall of the stone platform called ‘the mountain’ (<hi rend="italic">malai</hi>) in the <hi rend="bold">Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ</hi> temple at Little Conjeeveram.<note n="186-2">For a few other inscriptions in the same temple see <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XXI. p. 122, Nos. I. and III.; <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. III. pp. 71 and 118, and Vol. IV. p. 145.</note> As in the inscription of Ravivarman,<note n="186-3"><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 145 and note 3.</note> the temple is here stated to be situated in <hi rend="bold">Tiruvattiyūr</hi>, which belonged to <hi rend="bold">Eyil-nāḍu</hi>, a subdivision of <hi rend="bold">Eyiṟkōṭṭam</hi><note n="186-4">See above, p. 143 and note 3.</note> (l. 2).</p>						

						<p>The inscription is dated in the 9th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Chōḷadēva</hi>. The short poetical introduction mentions nothing of historical importance besides the conquest of <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi> and the name of Vikrama-Chōḷa's queen, <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiḻānaḍigaḷ</hi>. These two points are, however, sufficient to enable us to identify the king with the Vikrama-Chōḷa of the inscriptions opening with the words <ta>pūmālai miṭaintu</ta>, who claims to have burnt the country of <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi>,<note n="186-5">Above, Vol. II. p. 311, and Vol. III. p. 184.</note> and one of whose queens was named <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiḻānaḍi</hi>.<note n="186-6">Above, Vol. II. p. 311, and Vol. III. p. 75, No. 33, text line 14.</note> </p>						

						<p>The inscription records that a private person made over to the temple 780 <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy, with the stipulation that the interest, which amounts here to 50 <hi rend="italic">per cent</hi>., should be applied for the requirements of the worship on 13 days of every year, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> on the days of the <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi> Jyēshṭhā. In this <hi rend="italic">nakshatra</hi>, we are told, were born the two Vaishṇava saints <hi rend="bold">Pūdattāḻvār</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Poygaiyāḻvār</hi>,<note n="186-7">According to the <hi rend="italic">Guruparamparāprabhāva</hi> the former was born at Tirukkaḍaṉmallai (Māmallapuram) in Aviṭṭam (Śravishṭhā), and the latter at Kachchi (Conjeeveram) in Tiruvōṇam (Śravaṇa), during the Dvāpara-yuga (!).</note> “who were pleased to compose hymns in praise of the god (<hi rend="italic">Āḻvār</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Tiruvattiyūr</hi>” (l. 2). That portion of the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandham</hi>, which is entitled <hi rend="italic">Iyaṟpā</hi>, opens with two hymns of 100 stanzas each, the first of which is ascribed to <hi rend="bold">Poygaiyāḻvār</hi> and the second to <hi rend="bold">Pūdattāḻvār</hi>. In the first (verse 77) reference is made to <hi rend="bold">Veḥkā</hi>, and in the second (verse 95 f.) to <hi rend="bold">Attiyūr</hi>. The second name has to be referred to the temple at Tiruvattiyūr, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ temple, and the first may be connected with the same temple, because Veḥkā is the Tamil name of the river Vēgavatī,<note n="186-8">Compare above, p. 143, note 4.</note> which flows past the temple of Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ. At any rate the mention of the two <hi rend="italic">Āḻvārs</hi> as recognized saints in the subjoined inscription proves that they must have lived a long time before the 12th century of the Christian era. As stated before (p. 148), two other <hi rend="italic">Āḻvārs</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kulaśēkhara</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Śaṭhagōpa</hi>, are presupposed by an inscription of Kulōttuṅga I. at Śrīraṅgam. In the <hi rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> for 1899-1900 (p. 10) Mr. Venkayya states that an inscription of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Kēraḷadēva</hi>, whom he places in the 11th century of the Christian era, quotes the hymn <hi rend="italic">Tiruneḍundāṇḍagam</hi>. This is the name of the last hymn of the <hi rend="italic">Periyatirumoḻi</hi>, that portion of the <hi rend="italic">Nālāyiraprabandham</hi> which was composed by <hi rend="bold">Tirumaṅgaiyāḻvār</hi>. The upper limit of this <hi rend="italic">Āḻvār</hi> is the beginning of the 8th century A.D.; for he celebrates in one of his hymns the temple of <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara-Viṇṇagaram</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Kachchi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Vaikuṇṭha-Perumāḷ temple at Conjeeveram, which seems to have been founded by the Pallava king Paramēśvaravarman II.<note n="187-1">See above, Vol. II. p. 344.</note> </p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> pūmātu puṇara<unclear>p</unclear>puvimātu va<unclear>ḷara</unclear> nā<unclear>m</unclear>ātu vi<unclear>ḷa</unclear>ṅka <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yamātu virumpattaṉnirupa<unclear>ta</unclear>ma<unclear>la</unclear>r ma<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṉavar cūṭa maṉni<unclear>ya</unclear> Urimaiyāl maṇimuṭi cūṭicceṅkol ceṉṟu ticaitoṟu<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied> vaḷar<unclear>ppa</unclear> veṅkali <unclear>nī</unclear>ṅki meyyaṟa <hi rend="grantha">[nta</hi>ḻ] Aippakkaliṅkamiriyakkaṭamalai naṭātti vaḷa<unclear>ṅkoḷ</unclear>āḻivaraiyāḻi tiriya<note n="187-2">Read iru .</note> iricuṭara<unclear>ḷa</unclear>vumorukuṭai niḻaṟṟa<note n="187-3">Read vi<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yā<hi rend="grantha">bhi</hi>.</note> vij<unclear>ai</unclear><hi rend="grantha">abhiṣe</hi>kam pa<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṇi <unclear>vī</unclear>ra<hi rend="grantha">siṁhāsa</hi>nattu mukkokkiḻānaṭikaḷoṭum <unclear>vī</unclear>ṟ
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ṟi[ run=ta] ruḷiya kopparakecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>rāna t<hi rend="grantha">ribhu</hi>vana<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>k<hi rend="grantha">ra</hi>vattikaḷ<note n="187-4">Read <hi rend="grantha">cakra</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">r</hi>ti.</note> <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vikkiramacoḻatevarkku yāṇṭu Oṉpatāvatu <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻa<unclear>ma</unclear>ṇṭalattu Eyiṟkoṭṭattu Eyilnāṭṭuttiru<unclear>va</unclear>ttiyūrāḻvāraippāṭiyaruḷina <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi><unclear>pū</unclear>ta<unclear>t</unclear>tāḻ<unclear>v</unclear>ārum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>poy<unclear>k</unclear>aiyāḻvārum <unclear>pi</unclear>ṟan=ta tirukke<unclear>ṭṭ</unclear>ai nāḷ Aruḷāḷa<unclear>p</unclear>perumāḷ puṟa<unclear>p</unclear>paṭṭa<unclear>ru</unclear>ḷi <hi rend="grantha">Ekāśī</hi>ti tiru<unclear>ma</unclear>ñca<unclear>na</unclear>mu<unclear>m</unclear> perun=tiruvamutuñceytaru<unclear>ḷa</unclear>ttiru<unclear>ma</unclear>ñcanattukkuttirumuḷaiccār<unclear>t</unclear>ta tirumu
<lb n="3" break="no"/>ṉaippālikai muppattāṟukkuppālikai Oṉṟukkaṭikkiḻaṭṭa<note n="187-5">Read kīḻaṭṭa.</note> nellu Uriyāka nelluppatakkirunāḻiyum tirumu<unclear>ḷai</unclear>ppītaṅkoḷḷa<note n="187-6">Read pīcaṅ.</note> arici ṉānāḻiyum<note n="187-7">Read <hi rend="grantha">puṇyāhadakṣi</hi>ṇai.</note> pu<hi rend="grantha">ṇyāgada- kṣa</hi>ṇ<unclear>ai</unclear>kku <unclear>A</unclear>rici Aṟunā<unclear>ḻi</unclear> U<unclear>ḻa</unclear>kkum <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>balidra</unclear>vya<unclear>ttu</unclear></hi>kku Arici Irunāḻi Uriyum tirumu<unclear>ḷai</unclear>kkutti<unclear>ru</unclear>nan=tāviḷakkukku nāḷ<unclear>o</unclear><unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟukku Eṇṇai Uḻakkāka nāḷañcuk<unclear>ku</unclear> Eṇ<unclear>ṇai</unclear> nāḻi Uḻa<unclear>k</unclear>kuṅ<hi rend="grantha">kṛ</hi>ta<hi rend="grantha">hāroha</hi>ṇattukku ney <unclear>mu</unclear>vuḻakkāḻākkum tirumañ
<lb n="4" break="no"/>canattukkuk<unclear>ka</unclear>lacam Eṇpattoṉṟukku Aṭik<unclear>kī</unclear>ḻ nellu <unclear>Ai</unclear>ṅkuṟuṇi Uriyum kum<unclear>pa</unclear>nālukku nellu nānāḻiyum tiruccuṇṇakkalacamo<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟukkaṭikkiḻari<unclear>ci</unclear><note n="187-8">Read kīḻarici.</note> Irunā<unclear>ḻi</unclear>yuṅkalacañcūḻakkāṇavilai<unclear>yiṉ pu</unclear>ṭav<unclear>ai</unclear> pa<unclear>ti</unclear>nmuṉṟuṅkalacañcuṟṟa<note n="187-9">Read mūṉṟu.</note> nūla<unclear>r</unclear>aippalamum tirumañcanattukku ney muṉṉāḻiyum tenāḻiyum pāl muṉ
<lb n="5" break="no"/>ṉāḻiyu<unclear>m</unclear> tayir <unclear>muṉ</unclear>ṉā<unclear>ḻi</unclear>yum<note n="187-10">Read <hi rend="grantha">snapa</hi>na.</note> <hi rend="grantha">snama</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">dravya</hi>ṅkaḷ veṇṭuva<unclear>na</unclear>vum pañcaloka<unclear>mu</unclear>m pañcaran=tamum<note n="187-11">Read <hi rend="grantha">ratna</hi>mum.</note> tiruccuṇṇattukku nāṭa<unclear>ṉ</unclear>mañcaḷ nāṟpatin palamu<unclear>m</unclear> tiruviḷakkeṇṇai Uriyum <hi rend="grantha">homa</hi>ttukku ne<unclear>y</unclear>yuriyum cātti<note n="187-12">Read cārtti.</note> Aru<unclear>ḷa</unclear>cca<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>nta</unclear></hi>namukka<unclear>cum</unclear> kaṟpūramāṟu <unclear>m</unclear>āvum Aki<unclear>lar</unclear>aikka<unclear>ḻa</unclear>ñcuṅka<hi rend="grantha">stū</hi>ri ma<unclear>ñ</unclear>cāṭiyumiraṇṭu māvu<unclear>m</unclear> puḻuku<unclear>ne</unclear>yyiraṇṭu mañcāṭiyunālu mā<unclear>vum</unclear>āttiraikkarici nānāḻiyu<unclear>m</unclear> p<unclear>e</unclear>
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ruṉtiruvamutukku A<unclear>ri</unclear>ci mukkalaṉe kuṟuṇiyum paruppuppatakkirunāḻi Uriyum palavaṟkattukkaṟi niṟai Eṇṇūṟṟirupattaimpalamu<unclear>m</unclear> kaṟiyamutukku Uppu nānāḻiyumiḷaku Uriyum kaṭuku Āḻākke Iruceviṭaraiyum<note n="188-1">Read cīraka.</note> cirāmāḻakku<unclear>ñca</unclear>ṟka<unclear>r</unclear>ai I<unclear>ru</unclear>pa<unclear>tiṉ</unclear> palamum neyyuriyum Amutil paṭ<unclear>ai</unclear>kka caṟkarai <unclear>mu</unclear>ppattirupalavaraiyum ney patinorunāḻi Āḻakkum vā
<lb n="7" break="no"/><unclear>ḻ</unclear>ai<unclear>p</unclear>paḻamaimpattañcum tayir tūṇiyum kaṇṭacaṟka<unclear>r</unclear>ai mukkacum tirukkaṇ<unclear>ṇā</unclear>ma<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aikkarici Irunāḻiyuneyyuḻakkum caṟkarai Irupatiṉ pala<unclear>mu</unclear>m vāḻaippaḻam pattum A<unclear>ppa</unclear>amutukkarici patakkum ne<unclear>y</unclear>yirunāḻi Uriyum caṟkarai Eṇpatin palamumi<unclear>ḷak</unclear>āḻa<unclear>k</unclear>ku[m<note type="repeated" n="188-1"/>cira]ka<unclear>mi</unclear>ruc<unclear>e</unclear>viṭaraiyum viṟaku kaṭṭu mu<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṟum<note n="188-2">Read mūṉṟum.</note> kucak<unclear>ka</unclear>lauruvukku nellukkalamu[m<note n="188-3">Read taṇṇīra.</note> taṇṇiramu]tukkelam<unclear>o</unclear>ruceviṭaraiyum A
<lb n="8" break="no"/>ṭaikkā<supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied>amutukku pākku nānūṟ<unclear>ṟ</unclear>aim<unclear>pa</unclear>tu veḷḷilaippaṟṟonpatum tiru<unclear>vi</unclear>ḷakkeṇṇai nāḻi Uriyum tiruvi<unclear>ḷa</unclear>kkuṭaiyārkaḷ kuḻāy panniraṇṭukkeṇ<unclear>ṇai mu</unclear>nnāḻiyum pāvaiviḷakkukkeṇ<unclear>ṇai I</unclear>runāḻiyum Āka Ilaiyiṟṟukku niman=tamā<unclear>ka</unclear>cce<unclear>l</unclear>va<unclear>t</unclear>āka Iṭṭa <unclear>ca</unclear>mavilaippaṭiyālikkoyil <unclear>ci</unclear>la<unclear>va</unclear>ḷakkumarumoḻinaṅkai<unclear>ma</unclear>ra<unclear>k</unclear>kālāl tirukkeṭṭai nāḷonṟu
<lb n="9" break="no"/>kku nellu mu<unclear>p</unclear>patin kalamāka Orāṭṭai nāḷaikku veṇṭuvatāna nellu mu<unclear>ṉ</unclear>ṉūṟṟuttoṇṇūṟṟukkalattukkum coḻamaṇṭalat<unclear>tu</unclear> vi<hi rend="grantha">ru</hi>ta<hi rend="grantha">rājabha-</hi> yaṅkaravaḷanāṭṭu ma<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṇināṭṭu vaṅkamuḻaiyūr muḻ<unclear>ai</unclear>yūruṭaiyān veṇkāṭan Ātittatevanāna vaṅkat<unclear>tar</unclear>aiyan Ittevar paṇṭā<unclear>ra</unclear>ttuccilavaḷakku<unclear>ma</unclear>rum<unclear>o</unclear><unclear>ḻi</unclear>naṅkaimarakkālālaḷan=ta nellu
<lb n="10"/>Eḻunūṟṟ<unclear>e</unclear>ṇpatin kalaminnelleḻunūṟṟeṇpatin kala<unclear>t</unclear>tukku mā<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>ntoṟum nellu muppattirukalane tūṇippatakkāka yāṇṭu varai kaḷa<note n="188-4">ṭhis is the abbreviation for kalam; compare above, p. 7, note 10.</note> Ar <hi rend="grantha">Ai</hi>ppolicaiyāl palicai polivatāna nellu muṉ<unclear>ṉū</unclear>ṟṟuttoṇṇūṟṟukkalaminel<unclear>lu mu</unclear>nnūṟṟutto<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṇūṟṟuk<unclear>ka</unclear>lattukkum Aruḷāḷapperumā<unclear>ḷ</unclear> mā<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=toṟum tirukkeṭṭai nāḷ puṟappaṭṭaru<unclear>ḷi</unclear>
<lb n="11"/>tirumañcanamum peruntiruvamutum ceytaru<unclear>ḷa</unclear> v<unclear>eṇ</unclear>ṭu<unclear>va</unclear>navaiyiṟṟukku Inniman=tappaṭiye pa<unclear>ṇ</unclear>ṭārattile viṭṭu<hi rend="grantha">ccantrādi</hi>ttava<hi rend="grantha">t</hi> niman=tamākacceyyakkaṭavatākaccilālekai ceyvittukkuṭukatom Ikkoyilil <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>koyil vāriyam <unclear>pu</unclear>ṇṭa<unclear>va</unclear>- ttanattu <hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>k<hi rend="grantha">ra</hi><unclear>ma</unclear>vittanum tūta<hi rend="grantha">hari</hi> niṉṟanārāyaṇakkiramavittanum <hi rend="grantha">mṛhasthala</hi>ttu
<lb n="12"/>p<unclear>ā</unclear>ṇṭavatūtakkiramavittanum puṇṭavatta<unclear>nat</unclear>tu Iḷaiyakokkiramavittanum tūta<hi rend="grantha">hari</hi> <unclear>v</unclear>eṇṇaikkūttakkirama<unclear>vit</unclear>tanum tūta<hi rend="grantha">hari</hi> Iḷaiyaruḷā<unclear>ḷa</unclear>kakiramavittanum koyiṟkaṇakku Uttiramelūruṭaiyānāna Eṭṭi tirukkā<unclear>ḷa</unclear>tti Uṭaiyāṉum Ivvakaivom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Ippaṭik<unclear>ku</unclear> I<unclear>v</unclear>ai Ut<unclear>ti</unclear>rame<unclear>lū</unclear>ruṭai<unclear>y</unclear>āṉ Eṭṭi tirukkāḷattiyuṭaiyāṉ Eḻuttu <g type="ddanda">.</g> <unclear>U</unclear>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1903_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! While the goddess with the lotus (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Lakshmī) wedded (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>), while the goddess of the Earth prospered, while the goddess of Speech was resplendent, while the goddess of Victory loved (<hi rend="italic">him), (and</hi>) while (<hi rend="italic">all other</hi>) kings bore (<hi rend="italic">on their heads</hi>) his two lotus-feet, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) put on the jewelled crown by established right. While (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) seeptre went and made all regions prosper, the cruel Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>) was driven away, and true righteousness flourished. (<hi rend="italic">He</hi>) despatched mountains of rut (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> elephants) to subdue <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅga</hi>. (<hi rend="italic">His</hi>) discus wandered (<hi rend="italic">as far as</hi>) the circular mountain surrounding (<hi rend="italic">the earth</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">and his</hi>) single parasol cast its shade up to the two luminaries (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the sun and the moon). Having performed the anointment of victory, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) was pleased to take his seat on the throne of heroes together with (<hi rend="italic">his queen</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiḻānaḍigaḷ</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 2.) In the ninth year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of this king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi>) the emperor of the three worlds, <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Vikrama-Śōḻadēva</hi>.</p>

<p>When on the day of Tirukkēṭṭai (Jyēshṭhā), on which were born the saint <hi rend="bold">Pūdattāḻvār</hi> and the saint <hi rend="bold">Poygaiyāḻvār</hi>, who were pleased to compose hymns in praise of the god (<hi rend="italic">Āḻvār</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Tiruvattiyūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Eyil-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Eyiṟkōṭṭam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅgoṇḍa-Śōḻa-maṇḍalam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ</hi> is carried out, is bathed eighty-one times, and receives great offerings,—one <hi rend="italic">padakku</hi>) and two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi>) of paddy (<hi rend="italic">are required</hi>) for thirty-six pots of sprouts<note n="189-1"><hi rend="italic">Muḷaippāligai</hi> are pots with earth in which seeds are made to sprout at the <hi rend="italic">aṅkurārpaṇam</hi>, a ceremony preliminary to a religious or nuptial feast (Winslow).</note> to be offered at the bath, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of paddy to be spread underneath each pot; four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice to purchase seeds for sprouting; six <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">uḻakku</hi>) of rice as fee (<hi rend="italic">for wishing</hi>) an auspicious day (<hi rend="italic">puṇyāha</hi>); two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi>) and one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of rice for offerings (<hi rend="italic">balidravya</hi>); one <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">uḻakku</hi> of oil for a perpetual lamp (<hi rend="italic">burning</hi>) near the sprouts on five days, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> one <hi rend="italic">uḻakku</hi> of oil on each day; three <hi rend="italic">uḻakku</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">āḻākku</hi> of ghee for the <hi rend="italic">kṛitahārōhaṇam;</hi><note n="189-2">Mr. H.Krishna Sastri suggests that this corrupt term may be meant for <hi rend="italic">Kṛittikārōhaṇam</hi>, the name of a ceremony which is still observed in the temples of the Mysore State.</note> five <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of paddy (<hi rend="italic">to be spread</hi>) underneath eighty-one water-pots (<hi rend="italic">kalaśa</hi>) for the bath; four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of paddy for four large pots (<hi rend="italic">kumbha</hi>); two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice (<hi rend="italic">to be spread</hi>) underneath one water-pot (<hi rend="italic">coated with</hi>) chunnam; thirteen pieces of cloth costing one <hi rend="italic">kāṇam</hi> (of gold), to wrap round the water-pot; half a <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of thread, to tie round the water-pot; for the bath, three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of ghee, one <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of honey, three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of milk, three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of curds, the necessary ingredients for the bath, five metals and five gems; forty <hi rend="italic">palam</hi>) of saffron (<hi rend="italic">nāḍaṉ-mañjaḷ), (to be mixed</hi>) with the chunnam; one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi>) of lamp-oil; one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi>) of ghee for burnt oblations (<hi rend="italic">hōma</hi>); three <hi rend="italic">kaśu</hi><note n="189-3">On <hi rend="italic">kaśu</hi> or <hi rend="italic">kaiśu</hi> see above, Vol. II. p. 75, note 2, and p. 130, note 1.</note> of sandal, six twentieths of camphor, half a <hi rend="italic">kaḻañju</hi> of agallochum, one and two twentieths <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of musk, and two and four twentieths <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi> of civet-fat, to be rubbed on (<hi rend="italic">the image</hi>); four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice for <hi rend="italic">māttirai</hi> (?); for the great offerings, three <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">kuṟuṇi</hi> of rice, one <hi rend="italic">padakku</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of pulse, and eight hundred and twentyfive <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> in weight of vegetables of various kinds; for the vegetables, four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of salt, one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of pepper, one <hi rend="italic">āḻākku</hi> and two and a half <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> of mustard, one <hi rend="italic">āḻakku</hi> of cumin, twenty <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of sugar, and one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of ghee; to offer with the rice, thirty-two and a half <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of sugar, eleven <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">āḻakku</hi> of ghee, fifty-five plantains, one <hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi> of curds, and three <hi rend="italic">kaśu</hi> of sugar-candy; for <hi rend="italic">tirukkaṇṇāmaḍai (?</hi>), two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice, one <hi rend="italic">uḻakku</hi> of ghee, twenty <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of sugar, and ten platains; for cakes, one <hi rend="italic">padakku</hi> of rice, two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of ghee, eighty <hi rend="italic">palam</hi> of sugar, one <hi rend="italic">āḻakku</hi> of pepper, two <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> and a half of cumin, and three bundles of fire-wood; for pots, one <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy; one and a half <hi rend="italic">śeviḍu</hi> of cardamoms, (<hi rend="italic">to be mixed</hi>) with water; four hundred and fifty areca-nuts and nine bundles of betel-leaves; one <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">uri</hi> of lamp-oil; three <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of oil for twelve torches (?) of the lamp-lighters; and two <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi>) of oil for lamps (<hi rend="italic">held by</hi>) images.</p>

<p>(L. 8.) Altogether, for each day of Tirukkēṭṭai, thirty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy calculated by the average price (<hi rend="italic">and measured</hi>) by the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Arumoḻinaṅgai</hi>,<note n="189-4">This had been the name of the queen of the Chōḷa king Virarājēndradēva I. ; see above, Vol. II. p. 233.</note> with which the requirements of this temple are measured, were given in order to defray these (<hi rend="italic">requirements</hi>). Consequently, for (<hi rend="italic">thirteen</hi>) days in one year three hundred and ninety <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>) of paddy are required.</p>

<p>(L. 9.) For (<hi rend="italic">this purpose</hi>) seven hundred and eighty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy were measured into the treasury of this god with the <hi rend="italic">marakkāl</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Arumoḻinaṅgai</hi>, with which the requirements are measured, by <hi rend="bold">Muḻaiyūr-Uḍaiyāṉ Veṇgāḍaṉ<note n="190-1">Compare above, p. 159 and note 1.</note> Ādittadēvaṉ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vaṅgattaraiyaṉ</hi>, of <hi rend="bold">Vaṅga-Muḻaiyūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Maṇṇi-nāḍu</hi>,<note n="190-2">Muḻaiyūr in Maṇṇi-nāḍu is mentioned in an inscription of Kulōttuṅga I.; see above, p. 162 and note 3.</note> (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Virudarājabhayaṁkara-vaḷanāḍu</hi>,<note n="190-3">On this district see p. 152 above.</note> (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-maṇḍalam</hi>. The interest on these seven hundred and eighty <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy—at the rate of thirty-two <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>, one <hi rend="italic">tūṇi</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">padakku</hi> of paddy per month—amounts to three hundred and ninety <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy per year—the rate of interest being one half <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> (per <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 10.) We, all the members of the temple committee<note n="190-4">See above, p. 151, note 2.</note> of this temple:—<hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-Kramavittaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Puṇḍavattanam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Puṇḍravardhana); <hi rend="bold">Dūtahari-Niṉṟanārāyaṇa-Kramavittaṉ;<note n="190-5">On Dūtahari and Pāṇḍavadūta see above, p. 164, note 5.</note> Pāṇḍavadūta-Kramavittaṉ</hi><note type="repeated" n="190-5"/> of <hi rend="bold">Mṛihasthalam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> Bṛihatsthala ?); <hi rend="bold">Iḷaiyakō-Kramavittaṉ</hi><note n="190-6">The word Iḷaiyakō may refer either to the Chōḷa heir-apparent or to Lakshmaṇa; see <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. V. p. 72.</note> of <hi rend="bold">Puṇḍavattanam; Dūtahari-Veṇṇaikkūtta-Kramavittaṉ;<note n="190-7">Veṇṇeykkūttaṉ is one of the names of Kṛishṇa; see <hi rend="italic">loc. cit</hi>.</note> Dūtahari-Iḷaiyaruḷāḷa-Kramavittaṉ</hi>; and the accountant of the temple, <hi rend="bold">Uttiramēlūr-Uḍaiyāṉ</hi>,<note n="190-8">On Uttiramēlūr see above, p. 141 and note 1.</note> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Eṭṭi Tirukkāḷatti-Uḍaiyāṉ</hi>,<note n="190-9">Tirukkāḷatti is the Tamil form of Kālahasti in the North Arcot district.</note> caused to be engraved on stone that, as long as the moon and the sun shall last, provision shall be made out of these three hundred and ninety <hi rend="italic">kalam</hi> of paddy—(<hi rend="italic">the required principal</hi>) having been deposited in the treasury in accordance with this provision—for the requirements of (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Aruḷāḷa-Perumāḷ</hi> when, on the day of Tirukkēṭṭai in each month, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) is carried out, is bathed, and receives great offerings.</p>

<p>(L. 12.) This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Uttiramēlūr-Uḍaiyāṉ</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">alias</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Eṭṭi Tirukkāḷatti-Uḍaiyāṉ</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.80 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1903_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1903_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">186-190</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">80</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
