<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.111: original edition by H. Krishna Sastri</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 111.—ON THE NORTH WALL OF THE CENTRAL SHRINE IN THE ADIMULESVARA TEMPLE AT TIRUPPALATTURAI. No. 570 of 1908.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0111</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 8th year of <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman</hi> and registers a grant of land to the Śiva temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruppaṇambūdūr</hi> which was a hamlet of <hi rend="bold">Uttamaśīli-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, by <hi rend="bold">Tappildaram Pallavaraiyaṉ</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kīḻmāndūr Paruvūr</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">perundaram</hi> of prince (<hi rend="italic">piḷḷaiyāṟ</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsaridēva</hi>. The land granted was made tax-free by the village assembly.</p>						

						<p>The inscription is engraved on the walls of the stone temple at <hi rend="bold">Tiruppātturai</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the modern <hi rend="bold">Tiruppalātturai</hi> which is quite close to <hi rend="bold">Uttamaśīli</hi>,—the <hi rend="bold">Uttamaśīli-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi> of the inscription, evidently so called after prince <hi rend="bold">Uttamaśīli</hi>, a probable son of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I., not mentioned in the <hi rend="bold">Tiruvālaṅgāḍu</hi> plates. Of the two names <hi rend="bold">Vīraśrīkāmugavadi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ariñjigaivāykkāl</hi> mentioned among the boundaries of the land granted, the latter was probably named after prince <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsaridēva</hi>.</p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsaridēva</hi> is identical with the <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsarin</hi> of the Tirukkōyilūr record of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman Parāntaka</hi> I.<note n="246-2"><hi rend="italic">Epigraphia Indica</hi>, Vol. VII, p. 141.</note> Professor Kielhorn thinks that this <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsarin</hi> is the same as <hi rend="bold">Ariñjaya</hi>, one of the sons of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I., mentioned in the large Leyden grant.<note n="246-3">In the Tiruvoṟṟiyūr inscription (No. 104) above, the same prince is actually called Arindigai- Perumāṉār.</note> If this is correct, the king <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman</hi> of our inscription who was ruling at that time must evidently be <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman Gaṇḍarāditya</hi>.<note n="246-4">The Director-General's <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey Report</hi> for 1908-09, page 122.</note> </p>						

						<p><hi rend="italic">Perundaram</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Perundanam</hi> is already known as a title of high rank from the Tanjore inscriptions.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">sasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi> ko <hi rend="grantha">rājakesari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmma</hi><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>kku yāṇṭu 8 Āvatu piḷḷaiyār Arikula- <hi rend="grantha">kesaride</hi>var peruntarattu tappiltaram (p)pallavaraiya<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied> Āṉa kiḻmāntūr
<lb n="2"/>paruvūreṉ teṉkarai <hi rend="grantha">brahmade</hi>yam <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>uttamacili<hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedi</hi>maṅkalattu tiruppaṇampūtūr <hi rend="grantha">parameśvara</hi>rkku ca<hi rend="grantha">ndrā</hi>tittavaṟ tiruvamirtukkum
<lb n="3"/>tiruvuṇṇāḻikaippuṟamāka kuṭutta ṉilam<note n="246-5">Read ivvūr.</note> mi<unclear>yū</unclear>r Uṭkuṟai vira<hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāmukavatikkumeṟkku Aṟiñcikaivāykkālukku teṟkku veṅkaiy Iḷaya<hi rend="grantha">rudra</hi>kumā
<lb n="4" break="no"/>ra<hi rend="grantha">kra</hi>mavittaṉpakkal ṉāṉ vilaikoṇṭu Uṭaiya nilam maṇṇilai nikki Iraṇṭu māvum maṇṇilai Araimāvum Ivvūr kumāra<hi rend="grantha">kra</hi>mavittaṉ tirup<unclear>paṇa</unclear>mpūtūr <hi rend="grantha">para</hi>
<lb n="5" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">meśara</hi><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>kku tiruvamitukkum A<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied><hi rend="grantha">cca</hi>nā<hi rend="grantha">bhoga</hi>mumāka Itiṉoṭumaṭaiya Orumāvum Ivvatikkuk kiḻakku <hi rend="grantha">dve</hi>taikomapurattu caṉṉamaṇṭai<hi rend="grantha">kra</hi>mavittaṉ Uḷḷiṭṭa catukkattu Ai
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ñcām pāṭakam Iraṇṭumāviṟ kuṭṭur ṉārāyaṇaṉ <hi rend="grantha">daśa</hi>puriyaṉ <hi rend="grantha">brāhma</hi>ṇi pakkal vilai koṇṭu<note n="246-6">The syllable ṭu is written below the line.</note> ṭaiyeṉāy kuṭutta nilamaraiy māvumāka <unclear>Iṉ</unclear>ṉā<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied>māc ceyyum <hi rend="grantha">ca<unclear>ndr</unclear>āditya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">t</hi>
<lb n="7"/>tiruppaṇampūtūr pa<hi rend="grantha">rameśvara</hi><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>kku Innā<supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied>mācceyyum tiruppā<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tuṟai tirukka<supplied reason="omitted">ṟ</supplied>ṟaḷiyile <hi rend="grantha">ś</hi>l<note n="247-1">Read <hi rend="grantha">śilā</hi>.</note> Ā<hi rend="grantha">lekhai</hi> ceytukkuṭutt<unclear>o</unclear>m I<supplied reason="omitted">v</supplied>viruvom I<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>nilam <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>vat
<lb n="8"/>Iṟaiyiliyāka paṇ<unclear>ṇi</unclear>kkuṭuttom peruṅ(k)kuṟi<hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>y<supplied reason="omitted">o</supplied>m<supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> I<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>nilam Iṟaikoḷḷap paṇiccāraiyum Aṉṟu <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yil Irun=tāraiyum Iṟai kāṭṭi
<lb n="9" break="no"/>ṉāraiyum pa<hi rend="grantha">nmāheśvara</hi><supplied reason="omitted">re</supplied> tāṅkaḷ veṇṭu kovukku maṉṟappeṟuvatāka paṇiccukkuṭuttom peruṅkuṟi<hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> I<supplied reason="omitted">tu</supplied><note n="247-2">Cancel the first two syllables panā which are written twice.</note> <unclear>pa</unclear><hi rend="grantha">nmā</hi>pa<hi rend="grantha">nmāheśa</hi>ra Ira<hi rend="grantha">kṣai</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! In the 8th year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Rājakēsarivarman, I, Tappildaram Pallavaraiyaṉ</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kīḻmāndūr Paruvūr</hi> (<hi rend="italic">one</hi>) of the <hi rend="italic">Perundaram</hi> of prince (<hi rend="italic">piḷḷaiyār</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Arikulakēsaridēva</hi>, gave (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) land as a gift for the maintenance of the sacred central shrine (<hi rend="italic">tiruvuṇṇāḻigaipuram</hi>) for sacred offerings to the (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Tiruppaṇambūdūr</hi> (<hi rend="italic">hamlet</hi>) of the prosperous <hi rend="bold">Uttamaśīli-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brahmadēya</hi> on the southern bank<note n="247-3">Evidently of the river Kāvērī.</note> ; (<hi rend="italic">viz.)—</hi></p>

<p>(L. 3.) The land (<hi rend="italic">consisting</hi>) of 2 <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> excluding <hi rend="italic">maṇṇilai</hi><note n="247-4">The meaning of this word is not apparent. It must indicate a particular class of land.</note> and 1/2 <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> of <hi rend="italic">maṇṇilai, (both</hi>) purchased by me from <hi rend="bold">Vēṅgai Iḷaiya-Rudrakumāra-Kramavittaṉ</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">situated</hi>) to the west of the (<hi rend="italic">path called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Vīraśrīkāmugavadi</hi> and to the south of (<hi rend="italic">the channel called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ariñjigaivāykkāl</hi> and (<hi rend="italic">which is the) uṭkuṟai</hi><note n="247-5">The revenue term <hi rend="italic">uṭkuṟai</hi> is composed of <hi rend="italic">uḷ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kuṟai</hi> which signifies the deduction of the lands in question from within the village. Perhaps the <hi rend="italic">uṭkuṟai</hi>-lands were not subject to any assessment.</note> of this village; one <hi rend="italic">mā (of land given</hi>) by <hi rend="bold">Kumāra-Kramavittaṉ</hi> of this village to be enjoyed along with the above as (<hi rend="italic">a gift</hi>) for sacred offerings and for (<hi rend="italic">the maintenance of</hi>) worshippers (<hi rend="italic">archanābhōga</hi>) of the (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Tiruppaṇambūdūr</hi>; and (1/2) <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> which I purchased from the wife of <hi rend="bold">Nārāyaṇaṉ Daśapuriyaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kuṭṭūr</hi> and gave out of the 2 <hi rend="italic">mā (of land situated</hi>) to the east of this <hi rend="italic">vadi, (and formed</hi>) the fifth <hi rend="italic">pāḍagam</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">śadukkam</hi> owned by <hi rend="bold">Śannamaṇḍai-Kramavittaṉ</hi> and others of <hi rend="bold">Dvēdaigōmapuram</hi><note n="247-6">Same as Vēdagōmapuram.</note> . Thus (<hi rend="italic">were given</hi>) these 4 <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> of cultivable land (<hi rend="italic">śey</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 7.) (<hi rend="italic">The gift of</hi>) these 4 <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> of cultivable land was given by both of us as long as the moon and the sun (<hi rend="italic">endure</hi>) to the (<hi rend="italic">god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Paramēśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Tiruppaṇambūdūr</hi>, after having (<hi rend="italic">the gift</hi>) engraved on stone in the sacred stone temple of <hi rend="bold">Tiruppāttuṟai</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 8.) We, (<hi rend="italic">the members</hi>) of the big assembly, made this land tax-free as long as the moon and the sun (<hi rend="italic">endure</hi>). We, (<hi rend="italic">the members</hi>) of the big assembly, declared that (<hi rend="italic">the assembly of</hi>) all <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvaras</hi> could themselves decide upon and collect any (<hi rend="italic">fine</hi>) they choose for (<hi rend="italic">i.e., on behalf of</hi>) the king from (<hi rend="italic">such of us</hi>) as might order the levying of taxes on this land or those as were present in the assembly on the occasion or those as might enter the taxes (<hi rend="italic">in the books). (The assembly of</hi>) all <hi rend="italic">Māhēśvaras</hi> shall protect this (<hi rend="italic">charity</hi>).</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.111 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:KrishnaSastri1920_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">246-247</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">111</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
