<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.35: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 35.—ON THE OUTSIDE OF THE EAST WALL OF THE INNER PRAKARA OF THE RAJAGOPALA-PERUMAL TEMPLE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0035</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 8th year of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias Tribhuvanachakravartin</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi> (l. 5), and opens with a panegyrical passage, from which we learn nothing of any importance but that his queen bore the name or title <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiḻāṉaḍigaḷ</hi>.<note n="79-1">Mukkōkkiḻānaḍi had been the name of the chief queen of Vikrama-Chōḷa; see above, Vol. II. p. 309.</note> It records that some land near the village was purchased from <hi rend="bold">Sāhaṇai Mādhava-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> and assigned to the temple, with the condition that the produce of the land should be applied for providing offerings of boiled rice to the god.</p>						

						<p>At the time of the inscription the overseer of the <hi rend="italic">Śrī-Vaishṇavas</hi> was <hi rend="bold">Araṭṭamukkidāsaṉ</hi>. As the same officer is referred to in two inscriptions of the 12th and 28th years of the reign of <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa</hi> III. (Nos. 36 and 37 below), it may be assumed either that Parakēsarivarman, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Rājarājadēva, was identical with that Rājarājadēva who succeeded Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa III. or that he was the predecessor of the latter. I am inclined to adopt the second alternative, because the present inscription mentions as the person from whom the granted land was purchased a certain <hi rend="bold">Sāhaṇai Mādhava-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi>, whose name occurs in a similar connection in the inscription of <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa</hi> II. (No. 34 above). Hence the king to whose reign the subjoined inscription belongs has to be styled <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> II., and the successor of Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa III. will be Rājarāja III. The reign of Rājarāja II. would fall between A.D. 1132, the latest date of Kulōttuṅga II.,<note n="79-2"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XX. p. 285.</note> and A.D. 1178, the date of the accession of Kulōttuṅga III.<note n="79-3"><hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 266.</note> </p>						

						<p>I have impressions of two other inscriptions of Rājarāja II. which open with the same panegyrical introduction. The first of them, in the Śvētāraṇyēśvara temple at <hi rend="bold">Kaḍappēri</hi> near Madurāntakam in the Chingleput district (No. 132 of 1896), is dated in the 9th year; and the second, in the <hi rend="bold">Ēkāmranātha</hi> temple at Conjeeveram (No. 9 of 1893), is dated in the 15th year of the reign, “on the day of <hi rend="italic">Punarvasu</hi>, which was a Thursday and the fourteenth <hi rend="italic">tithi</hi> of the first fortnight of the month of <hi rend="italic">Tai</hi>.”<note n="79-4"><ta>yāṇṭu patiṉañcāvatu taimā</ta><hi rend="grantha">sa</hi><ta>ttu pū</ta><hi rend="grantha">rvva</hi><ta>pa<hi rend="grantha">kṣa</hi>ttu puṇarpūcamum</ta> <hi rend="grantha">ca</hi><ta>tu</ta><hi rend="grantha">[r]dda</hi><ta>ciyum viyāḻakkiḻamaiyumā[ṉa] nāḷ</ta>.</note> </p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> pū maruviya tirumātum puvimātum <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yamātum ṉā maruviya kalaimātum pukaḻmātum nayantu <unclear>pu</unclear>lka <unclear>Aru</unclear>maṟaivitine<unclear>ṟi</unclear>ya
<lb n="2" break="no"/><unclear>ṉai</unclear>ttumaruntamiḻun=ta<unclear>ṉi</unclear> taḻaippavarumuṟai <unclear>U</unclear>rimaiyiṉ ma<unclear>ṇi</unclear>muṭi cū<unclear>ṭi</unclear>ttiṅkaḷ veṇku<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aitticaikkaḷiṟeṭ[ ṭun=taṅ] ku tanitti<unclear>ṭa</unclear><note n="79-5">Two other inscriptions of the same king read taṉikkūṭa.</note> 
<lb n="3" break="no"/>n=tāṉeṉa viḷaṅkakkaruṅkalippaṭṭiyaicceṅkol turappapporuvaliyāḻi pu<unclear>vi</unclear> vaḷarttuṭaṉ vara villa<unclear>var</unclear> teluṅkar miṉavar<note n="79-6">Read mīṉavar.</note> 
<lb n="4"/>ciṅkaḷar pallavar mutaliya pārtti<unclear>va</unclear>r pa<unclear>ṇi</unclear>ya Eṇṇaruṅkaṟpamaṇṇakam puṇar<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu cempo<unclear>ṉ vī</unclear>ra<hi rend="grantha">siṁhāsa</hi>ṉa<unclear>t</unclear>tu Ulakuṭai muk
<lb n="5" break="no"/>kokkiḻāṉaṭikaḷoṭum <unclear>vī</unclear>ṟṟirun=taruḷiya kopparakecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>rāṉa <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vaṉaccakkaravarttikaḷ <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>vaṟku<note n="79-7">The va of vaṟku is entered below the line.</note> yāṇṭu 8
<lb n="6"/>Āvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻamaṇṭala<supplied reason="omitted">t</supplied>tu kulottuṅkacoḻavaḷaṉāṭṭu<note n="79-8">The ṭ of ṉāṭṭu is entered below the line.</note> kuṉṟattū<unclear>rṉā</unclear>ṭṭu maṇima<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kalamāṉa pāṇṭi
<lb n="7" break="no"/>ya<unclear>ṉai</unclear>irumaṭim<unclear>e</unclear>ṉ<unclear>koṇṭac</unclear>oḻacca<unclear>tu</unclear><supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>ppe<unclear>tima</unclear>ṅkalat<unclear>tu</unclear> <hi rend="grantha">ma</hi>h<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>āsa</unclear>bhai</hi>yom<note n="80-1">The m is entered below the line.</note> Eḻut<unclear>tu</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>nammū</unclear>r <unclear>vaṇṭuvar</unclear>ā<unclear>vati E</unclear>m<unclear>p</unclear>eru
<lb n="8" break="no"/>mān koyilil <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāriya<unclear>m</unclear> ceykiṟa<note n="80-2">The y of ceykiṟa is entered below the line.</note> Irāyūr vi<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇubha</hi>ṭṭaṉu<unclear>m</unclear><note n="80-3">The va of vāriya is entered below the line.</note> <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>v<unclear>ai</unclear>- <hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi>vavāriya(m)ñceykiṟa<note n="80-4">The y of ceykiṟa is entered below the line.</note> Araṭṭamukki<hi rend="grantha">dāsa</hi>ṉum kaṇṭu
<lb n="9"/>nammur<note n="80-5">Read mūr.</note> vaṇṭuvarā<unclear>va</unclear>ti Emp<unclear>e</unclear>rumāṉukku ciṟukālai<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>n=tikku <unclear>mu</unclear>ṉpākattiruma[ n=tira] poṉakam<note n="80-6">The word ma[ n=tira] is entered above the pe of poṉakam.</note> Orutiruppoṉakam ṉāṉāḻi
<lb n="10"/>Ariciyāl A<hi rend="grantha">mṛ</hi>tu ce<supplied reason="omitted">y</supplied>taru<unclear>ḷu</unclear>kaikku Immaṇṭalattu <unclear>Ū</unclear>ṟṟukkāṭṭukk<unclear>o</unclear>ṭṭattu Ūṟṟukkāṭṭuṉā<unclear>ṭ</unclear>ṭu<note n="80-7">The letters ṭṭu of kāṭṭu are entered below the line.</note> Ūṟṟukkāṭāṉa Aḻaki<unclear>ya</unclear>coḻanallūr ma<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kalaṅkiḻān <unclear>v</unclear>eḷā
<lb n="11" break="no"/>n malaikini<unclear>ya</unclear>ṉiṉṟā<unclear>ṉ</unclear> nammūr <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>s</unclear>ā</hi>kaṇai mā<unclear>ta</unclear>vapaṭṭaṉ pa<unclear>k</unclear>ka<unclear>l</unclear>kkācu Iṭṭu<unclear>k</unclear>koṇṭu viṭṭa ṉilam <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>vvūr kākka<unclear>m</unclear>pilāl karuṇākarapaṭṭaṉ pakkal I<supplied reason="omitted">m</supplied>māta<unclear>va</unclear>paṭṭa
<lb n="12" break="no"/>n koṇṭuṭai<unclear>ya</unclear> Ivvūrpperu<hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tūmpiniṉṟu va<unclear>ṭa</unclear>kku <unclear>ṉ</unclear>ok<unclear>ki</unclear>ppoṉa peruvāykkālukkukkiḻakkum Ālavatikku vaṭakku Iraṇṭāṅkaṇṇāṟṟu <unclear>k</unclear>ākkampirālccīrā
<lb n="13" break="no"/>ma<unclear>cī</unclear>riḷaṅkokkuḻi <unclear>Iru</unclear>ṉūṟṟañcaraiyum Ivvatikku vaṭakku ṉālāṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>ṇṇāṟṟukkāk<unclear>ka</unclear>mpirāl <unclear>cīr</unclear>āma<unclear>cīri</unclear>ḷaṅkokkuḻi I<unclear>ru</unclear>ṉūṟṟoru<unclear>pa</unclear>tteḻum Itiṉ(ṅ) kiḻakku Ipperuṭaiya
<lb n="14"/>taṭi Oṉṟiṉālkkuḻi<note n="80-8">The ṟ of ṉūṟ is entered below the line.</note> ṉūṟṟoṉpatum Itiṉ vaṭakku Immātavapaṭṭaṉ<note n="80-9">The second ṭa of paṭṭaṉ is entered below the line.</note> <unclear>Ikku</unclear>ṭi tiruveṅkaṭapaṭṭaṉ <unclear>pa</unclear>kkal <hi rend="grantha">supra</hi>ti<hi rend="grantha">graha</hi>mākakkoṇṭuṭaiya <hi rend="grantha">sā- ha</hi>ṇai paṭṭaraiya<unclear>ṉ</unclear> pulat<unclear>ti</unclear>laṟa<unclear>tta t</unclear>eṟ
<lb n="15" break="no"/>kkiṭaiyakkuḻi Eṇ<unclear>pa</unclear>tum Ākappottakappaṭi kuḻi Aṟuṉūṟṟorupattiraṇṭaraiyu<unclear>m</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Immaṅka<unclear>la</unclear>ṅkiḻān veḷān malaikiṉiyaṉiṉṟān <unclear>pa</unclear>kkal Iṉ<unclear>ṉi</unclear>lam Iṟaiviḻu<unclear>t</unclear>tukaik<unclear>ku</unclear>
<lb n="16"/>veṇ<unclear>ṭu</unclear>m poṉ koṇṭu ca<hi rend="grantha">ntrā</hi>tittavarai Iṟaivi<unclear>ḻu</unclear>ttikkuṭutt<unclear>o</unclear>m <hi rend="grantha">mahāsabhai</hi>yom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>I</unclear>ṉṉilan=tā<unclear>ṉ</unclear> veṇṭu per Iṭṭukkalli<unclear>lu</unclear>m cempilum veṭṭikkoḷvatā<note n="80-10">The ā of koḷ is entered above, and ḷ below the line.</note> 
<lb n="17" break="no"/>kavum I<supplied reason="omitted">v</supplied>va<hi rend="grantha">mṛ</hi>tu ceyta <hi rend="grantha">prasāda</hi>ttilccempāti<unclear>yum</unclear> Apūrvi <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vai<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa<unclear>va</unclear>-</hi> rāy van=tāṟ<unclear>kku</unclear> Iṭu<unclear>va</unclear>tā<unclear>ka</unclear>vum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivvūr naṭuviṟttirumuṟṟattukkūṭṭaṅkuṟaivaṟakkūṭi Iru[ <hi rend="grantha">n</hi>tu]<note n="80-11">Read irunta.</note> <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>
<lb n="18" break="no"/>yuḷ ṉinṟu Araṇaippuṟattuppuru<hi rend="grantha">ṣo</hi>ttama<hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>ṭṭaṉ paṇippappaṇi keṭṭeḻutinen ma<unclear>ṇima</unclear>ṅkalamu<unclear>ṭ</unclear>aiyān <unclear>Ā</unclear>ṉa<hi rend="grantha"><unclear>nta</unclear>bo<unclear>dha</unclear></hi>ṉ veḷān<note n="80-12">Read cīrāma.</note> cirāmatevanen <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai Eṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippaṭi 
<lb n="19" break="no"/>kku Ivvūrttaccakkā<unclear>ṇi</unclear><note n="80-13">The ā of kāṇi is entered below the line.</note> cempāti<unclear>yu</unclear>ṭaiya <unclear>ta</unclear>ccaṉ vaṭukaṉātaṉ tiruvāykkulamāṉ <unclear>t</unclear>oṇṭaiṉāṭṭācāriyaneṉ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai Eṉ Eḻut<unclear>tu</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> It<hi rend="grantha">dhanmam śrī</hi><unclear>v</unclear>ai<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rakṣai(ḥ) <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> ha</hi>ri <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1899_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! While the goddess of prosperity, who carries a (<hi rend="italic">lotus</hi>) flower, the goddess of the earth, the goddess of victory, the goddess of learning, who resided on (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) tongue, and the goddess of fame lovingly embraced (<hi rend="italic">him</hi>), and while all the rules prescribed in the sacred Vēdas and the elegant Tamiḻ flourished exceedingly, (<hi rend="italic">the king</hi>) put on the jewelled crown by right of royal descent.</p>

<p>(L. 2.) The moon of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) white parasol was glittering as if it were a matchless hall in which the eight elephants of the quarters abided;<note n="81-1"><hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi> he ruled over the whole earth.</note> (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) sceptre drove away, (<hi rend="italic">like</hi>) a prostitute, the dark Kali (<hi rend="italic">age</hi>); and (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) discus, powerful in battle, accompanied (<hi rend="italic">his sceptre</hi>), extending (<hi rend="italic">his conquests on</hi>) the earth.</p>

<p>(L. 3.) Having won the heart (<hi rend="italic">of the goddess</hi>) of the earth for countless ages, (<hi rend="italic">he</hi>) was pleased to be seated on the throne of heroes, (<hi rend="italic">made</hi>) of pure gold, with (<hi rend="italic">his queen</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mukkōkkiḻāṉaḍigaḷ</hi>, the mistress of the world, while the Villavar <hi rend="bold">(Chēras), Teluṅgar</hi>, Mīṉavar <hi rend="bold">(Pāṇḍyas), Śiṅgaḷar, Pallavar</hi> and other kings prostrated themselves (<hi rend="italic">before him</hi>).</p>

<p>(L. 5.) In the 8th year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of (<hi rend="italic">this</hi>) king <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the emperor of the three worlds, <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Rājarājadēva</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 6.) The writing of us, the great assembly of <hi rend="bold">Maṇimaṅgalam</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍiyaṉai-irumaḍi-mēṉ-koṇḍa-Śōḻa-chaturvēdimaṅgalam</hi>, in <hi rend="bold">Kuṉṟattūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Śōḻa-vaḷanāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śōḻa-maṇḍalam</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 7.) With the knowledge of <hi rend="bold">Vishṇu-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Irāyūr</hi>, the manager of the temple of <hi rend="bold">Vaṇḍuvarāpati-Emberumāṉ</hi> in our village, and of <hi rend="bold">Araṭṭamukkidāsaṉ</hi>, the overseer of the <hi rend="italic">Śrī-Vaishṇavas</hi>.<note n="81-2">The words <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vai<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi><ta>vavāriyañceykiṟa</ta> correspond to <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vai<hi rend="grantha">ṣṇa</hi><ta>vakkaṇkāṇi</ta> in other Maṇimaṅgalam inscriptions.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 9.) In order that (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Vaṇḍuvarāpati-Emberumāṉ</hi> in our village might receive (<hi rend="italic">every day</hi>) an offering of four <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of boiled rice before early dawn, the <hi rend="italic">Maṅgalaṅgiḻāṉ</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vēḷāṉ Malaigiṉiyaniṉṟāṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāḍu</hi>,<note n="81-3">This is a village in the Conjeeveram tāluka; see above, Vol. II. p. 345, note 4.</note> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Aḻagiya-Śōḻa-nallūr</hi>, in <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāḍu-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a subdivision</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Ūṟṟukkāṭṭu-kōṭṭam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of the same <hi rend="italic">maṇḍalam</hi>, purchased for money from <hi rend="bold">[S]āgaṇai<note n="81-4">This word is spelt Sāhaṇai in text line 14 below; see also above, p. 77, note 8.</note> Mādhava-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> of our village (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) land.</p>

<p>(L. 11.) Two hundred and five and a half <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kākkambirāl Śrīrāma-Śīriḷaṅgō</hi> in the second <hi rend="italic">Kaṇṇāṟu</hi><note n="81-5">See above, p. 73, note 6.</note> to the east of the large channel which flows to the north from the large sluice of this village,<note n="81-6">See No. 34, text line 6, and No. 30, text line 40.</note> and to the north of the <hi rend="italic">Ālavadi</hi> (road),<note n="81-7">See above, p. 78 and note 9.</note> which that <hi rend="bold">Mādhava-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> had purchased from <hi rend="bold">Kākkambilāl Karuṇākara-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> of this village; two hundred and seventeen <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Kākkambirāl Śrīrāma-Śīriḷaṅgō</hi> in the fourth <hi rend="italic">Kaṇṇāṟu</hi> to the north of this road; to the east of this, one hundred and nine <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi>, equal to one <hi rend="italic">taḍi</hi><note n="81-8">Compare above, p. 58, line 1.</note> (and) bearing the same name; and to the north of this, eighty <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi>, • • • in the field of <hi rend="bold">Sāhaṇai Bhaṭṭaraiyaṉ</hi>, which that <hi rend="bold">Mādhava-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> had received as a present from <hi rend="bold">Tiruvēṅgaḍa-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> of this village,—altogether,<note n="81-9">By adding up the preceding amounts, only 611(1/2) <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> are arrived at.</note> six hundred and twelve and a half <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> according to the land-register.<note n="81-10">The same term (<hi rend="italic">pottagam</hi>) occurs in Vol. II. No. 22, second tier, text line 4.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 15.) Having received the gold required for making this land free of taxes from that <hi rend="italic">Maṅgalaṅgiḻāṉ</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vēḷāṉ Malaigiṉiyaniṉṟāṉ</hi>, we, the great assembly, gave it free of taxes, for as long as the moon and the sun exist.</p>

<p>(L. 16.) The designation which he desires for this land shall be engraved on stone and on copper, and the better half of the leavings of these offerings shall be given to travellers who are <hi rend="italic">Śrī-Vaishṇavas</hi> (and) have not (<hi rend="italic">received it</hi>) before.<note n="82-1">The word <hi rend="italic">apūrvin</hi> is used similarly in Vol. II. No. 25, text line 36.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 17.) Having been present in the assembly, which met without a vacancy in the temple court in the middle of this village, and having heard the order of <hi rend="bold">Purushōttama-Bhaṭṭaṉ</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Araṇaippuṟam</hi>, I, <hi rend="bold">Maṇimaṅgalam-uḍaiyāṉ [Ā]na[nda]bō[dha]ṉ Vēḷāṉ Śrīrāmadēvaṉ</hi>, wrote (<hi rend="italic">the above</hi>). This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) my writing.</p>

<p>(L. 18.) To this (<hi rend="italic">witness</hi>) I, the carpenter <hi rend="bold">Vaḍuganādaṉ Tiruvāykkulamāṉ Toṇḍaināṭṭ-āchāryaṉ</hi>, who possesses the better half of the land of the carpenters (<hi rend="italic">tachcha-kāṇi</hi>) in the village. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) my writing.</p>

<p>(L. 19.) This charity (<hi rend="italic">is placed under</hi>) the protection of the <hi rend="italic">Śrī-Vaishṇavas</hi>. Hari !</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.35 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">79-82</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">35</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
