<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 3.23: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 23.—ON THE OUTSIDE OF THE SECOND PRAKARA, RIGHT OF ENTRANCE.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv03p0i0023</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 23rd year of the reign of <hi rend="italic">Tribhuvanachakravartin</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva</hi>, who claims to have conquered <hi rend="bold">Īḻam</hi> (Ceylon), <hi rend="bold">Madurai</hi> (Madhurā) and <hi rend="bold">Karuvūr</hi> and to have cut off the head of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king. The time of this <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷa</hi> is settled by an inscription in the Raṅganāyaka temple at <hi rend="bold">Nellūr</hi> (Nellore), which couples Śaka-Saṁvat 1119 with the 19th year of his reign.<note n="43-2">No. 197 of 1894; <hi rend="italic">Ep. Ind</hi>. Vol. IV. p. 219.</note> On the basis of this inscription and of some others which contain elements for astronomical calculation, Professor Kielhorn has shown that the king's reign commenced between the 5th June and 8th July, A.D. 1178.<note n="43-3"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> p. 266.</note> Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva I. ascended the throne in A.D. 1070,<note n="43-4">See Professor Kielhorn's calculations, <hi rend="italic">l.c</hi>.</note> and Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva II. issued the Chellūr plates in A.D. 1132.<note n="43-5"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XX. p. 285.</note> Consequently, the king, to whose reign the present inscription belongs, has to be designated <hi rend="bold">Kulōttuṅga-Chōḷadēva</hi> III. In other inscriptions he bears the names <hi rend="bold">Parakēsarivarman, Vīrarājēndradēva</hi> (II.) and <hi rend="bold">Tribhuvanavīradēva</hi>. His latest date is the 39th year in an unpublished inscription at Chidambaram. Accordingly, he must have been the immediate predecessor of <hi rend="italic">Tribhuvanachakravartin</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarājadēva</hi>, who ascended the throne about A.D. 1216.<note n="43-6">See Vol. I. p. 86. An inscription of the 2nd year of <hi rend="italic">Tribhuvanachakravartin</hi> Rājarājadēva at Tiruviḍaimarudūr (No. 143 of 1895) mentions an image which had been set up in the 37th year of “the great king (<hi rend="italic">periya-dēvar</hi>) Tribhuvanavīradēva.”</note> </p>						

						<p>The immediate purpose of the subjoined inscription is to record that the king granted to the Karuvūr temple the village of <hi rend="bold">Maṉṉaṟai</hi> and a portion of <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷapaḷḷi</hi><note n="43-7">The same village is mentioned in a short inscription (No. 68 of 1890) of the 34th year of Parāntaka I. at Sōmūr near Karavūr.</note> in <hi rend="bold">Taṭṭaiyūr-nāḍu</hi>.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2026-01-15" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-11-26" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi> tiripuvaṉaccakkaravarttikaḷ Īḻamum maturaiyum pāṇṭiyaṉ muṭittalaiyuṅkaruvūrum koṇṭaruḷiṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kulottuṅkaco<unclear>ḻa</unclear>tevarkku yāṇṭu Irupattumuṉṟāvatu<note n="43-8">Read mūṉṟāvatu.</note> tiripuvaṉaccakkaravartti koneri
<lb n="2" break="no"/><supplied reason="omitted">ṉ</supplied><unclear>mai</unclear>koṇṭāṉ koṅkāṉa co<unclear>ḻa</unclear>keraḷamaṇṭalat<unclear>tu</unclear> veṅkālanāṭṭu<unclear>k</unclear>karuvūrāṉa muṭivaḻa<unclear>ṅ</unclear>kucoḻapurattu tiruvānilai māte<unclear>va</unclear>r koyilil tevar kaṉmikkum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>mā<hi rend="grantha">heśvara</hi>kaṅkāṇi ceyva
<lb n="3" break="no"/><supplied reason="omitted">ār</supplied>kaḷukkum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kāri<unclear>ya</unclear>ñceyvāṉukkum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ittevarkku <unclear>v</unclear>eṇṭum nivantaṅkaḷukku veṇṭuvatāka Iṉṉāṭṭuttaṭṭaiyūrnāṭṭukkera<unclear>ḷa</unclear>paḷḷiyilum maṉṉaṟaiyilumāka Aimpatiṟṟu veli nila(m)
<lb n="4" break="no"/><unclear>mum centa</unclear> maṉṉaṟai<note n="44-1">Read nāmattu.</note> tirunāmaṟtu<unclear>kk</unclear>ā<unclear>ṇi</unclear>yā<unclear>ka ti</unclear>ruvā<unclear>nilai</unclear> ma[<hi rend="grantha">hā</hi>]te<unclear>va</unclear>ṟ<unclear>ku</unclear> kuṭuttom <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivvuṟku<note n="44-2">Read ivvūrkku.</note> <unclear>p</unclear>erunā<supplied reason="omitted">ṉkel</supplied><unclear>lai</unclear>kkuṭpaṭṭa nilamum kaṟṟup<unclear>pu</unclear>ṟperakaramuṟ<unclear>ṟū</unclear>ṭ<unclear>ṭu</unclear>m <unclear>Iṉāya</unclear>ṉār<unclear>ku</unclear><note n="44-3">Read innāyaṉārkku.</note> 
<lb n="5"/>Irupattumuṉṟāvatu<note n="44-4">Read mūṉṟāvatu.</note> mutal tevatāṉam Iṟai<unclear>yi</unclear>liyāka Iṭakkaṭavatākaccol<unclear>li</unclear> Ippaṭi kaṇakkilum Iṭṭukkoḷ<unclear>ḷa</unclear>kkaṭava<unclear>r</unclear>kaḷ<unclear>ā</unclear>ka varikkukūṟu ceyvārkaḷukkum coṉṉe<unclear>m</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
<lb n="6"/>Iṉṉilaṅkaikk<unclear>o</unclear>ḷ<unclear>ḷu</unclear>m Iṭattuṅkeraḷaṉ nicca<unclear>yi</unclear>tta <unclear>pa</unclear>ṭiye Ivvūrkaḷile <unclear>I</unclear>rupattumuṉṟāvatu<note n="44-5">Read mūṉṟāvatu.</note> <unclear>mu</unclear>ta<unclear>l</unclear> tevatā<unclear>ṉa</unclear>iṟaiyiliyākakkaikkoṇṭu nivantañcelut<unclear>ta</unclear>ppaṇṇuka <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
<lb n="7"/>Eḻutiṉāṉ tirumantiraolai mīṉavaṉmuventaveḷāṉ<note n="44-6">Read mūventa.</note> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai toṇṭaimāṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai viḻiñattarayaṉ Eḻut<unclear>tu</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai varakuṇarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉe<unclear>ḻu</unclear>ttu<note n="44-7">The syllable ḻu is entered below the line.</note> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai paṅkaḷattarayaṉ Eḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivai vāḷuva
<lb n="8" break="no"/>rā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉeḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1899_01">

<p>(Line 1.) Hail ! Prosperity ! In the twenty-third year (<hi rend="italic">of the reign</hi>) of the emperor of the three worlds, <hi rend="bold">Śrī-Kulōttuṅga-Śōḻadēva</hi>, who was pleased to take <hi rend="bold">Īḻam, Madurai</hi>, the crowned head of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Karuvūr</hi>,—the emperor of the three worlds, <hi rend="bold">Kōnēri[ṉmai] koṇḍāṉ</hi>,<note n="44-8">Regarding this title see Vol. II. pp. 110 and 246.</note> (<hi rend="italic">addresses the following order</hi>) to the Pūjāri (<hi rend="italic">dēvarkaṉmi</hi>), to the overseers of the <hi rend="italic">Śrī-Māhēśvaras</hi>, and to the manager of the temple of <hi rend="bold">Tiruvānilai-Mahādēva</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Karuvūr</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Muḍivaḻaṅgu-Śōḻapuram</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a city</hi>) in <hi rend="bold">Veṅgālanāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Koṅgu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Śōḻa-Kēraḷa-maṇḍalam</hi>.</p>

<p>(L. 3.) “We have given as temple land to (<hi rend="italic">the god</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Mahādēva</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Tiruvānilai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>) for the expenses required by this god (<hi rend="italic">the village of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Maṉṉaṟai</hi>, containing fifty <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> of land in <hi rend="bold">Kēra[ḷa]paḷḷi</hi> and in <hi rend="bold">Maṉṉaṟai</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Taṭṭaiyūr-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a district</hi>) of the same <hi rend="italic">nāḍu</hi>.<note n="44-9">This refers apparently to Veṅgāla-nāḍu in l. 2. But No. 24, l. 3, shows that both Veṅgāla-nāḍu and Taṭṭaiyūr-nāḍu were independent districts of Śōḻa-Kēraḷa-maṇḍalam.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 4.) “Having declared that the land enclosed within the four great boundaries of this village, (<hi rend="italic">including</hi>) the grass for the calves, and (<hi rend="italic">the land</hi>) enjoyed in full by the great village, should be given to this god as tax-free temple land from the twenty-third (<hi rend="italic">year of our reign</hi>), we have ordered (<hi rend="italic">our</hi>) revenue officers<note n="44-10"><ta>varikku kūṟu ceyvārkaḷ</ta> (which occurs also in Vol. II. No. 21, second section, l. 4) corresponds to <ta>variyilār</ta> in No. 20, l. 21.</note> to enter (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>) as such in the account (<hi rend="italic">book</hi>).”</p>

<p>(L. 6.) “If this land is (<hi rend="italic">actually</hi>) taken possession of, you shall permit (<hi rend="italic">the temple authorities</hi>) to take possession (<hi rend="italic">of it</hi>) as tax-free temple land and to defray the expenses (<hi rend="italic">of the temple</hi>) from (<hi rend="italic">the produce of</hi>) these villages from the twenty-third (<hi rend="italic">year of our reign</hi>), as determined by <hi rend="bold">Kēraḷaṉ.”</hi><note n="44-11">This is perhaps the name of the person at whose instance the king made the grant.</note> </p>

<p>(L. 7.) Written by the royal secretary, <hi rend="bold">Mīṉavaṉ-Mūvēndavēḷāṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Toṇḍaimāṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Viḻiñattarayaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Varaguṇarājaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Paṅgaḷattarayaṉ</hi>. This (<hi rend="italic">is</hi>) the writing of <hi rend="bold">Vāḷuvarājaṉ</hi>.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 3.23 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1899_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">43-45</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">23</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
