<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 28.257: original edition by J. Sundaram</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 257. (A.R. No. 411 of 1913.)</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName>
						<name>DHARMA team</name>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv28p0i0257</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>ĀṞAGAḶŪR, ATTUR TALUK, SALEM DISTRICT.</p>						

						<p>Kāmēśvara temple, central shrine, north wall.</p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">••• ••••• Śaka 1430, Vibhava, Kuṁbha śu. 10, Sunday, Āyilyam Irregular.</hi></p>						

						<p>Records that Eṟamāñchi Tulukkaṇa-nāyakkar, on finding that festival for the God Tirukkāmīśvaram-uḍaiya-ṉāyaṉār of Āṟagaḷ-ūr in Magadai-maṇḍalam was not being celebrated from the time of the Pāṇḍyas till that date, made a chariot (car) for that God and arranged for the celebration of the serial-festival in the month of Māśi (with the chariot festival on the day of <hi rend="italic">Āyilyam</hi>) and the bathing of the God (<hi rend="italic">tiru-mañjaṉam</hi>) on the day of <hi rend="italic">Magham.</hi> During that festival, for beating of the drum (<hi rend="italic">paṟai</hi>) one Paṟaiyan, son of Perumāḷ of Tāmaka •• nallūr was engaged. For him (the <hi rend="italic">kaikkōḷan</hi>) the God's secretary Ādichaṇḍēśvaranāyaṉār is stated to have been symbolically represented to, by Mudaliyār Chaṉṉakamala-ṉāyaṉār Ādichaṇḍēśvara-nāyanār, Tārum (?) and Māhēśvarar, who had assembled at Āṟai-ṉāyaka-maṇḍapam for the grant of wet and dry land and a house-site in Āṟagaḷūr and also cooked rice <hi rend="italic">(chōṟu)</hi> prepared out of 2 <hi rend="italic">nāḻi</hi> of rice to be doled out to him in the temple. This privilege <hi rend="italic">(chuvantiram)</hi> was to be enjoyed by the father of Perumāḷ and his lineage (<hi rend="italic">vargattār</hi>) till eternity.</p>						

						<p>This mention of the father of the beneficiary as the first one (or the associate one) to enjoy the benefit of the grant suggests that Perumāḷ might have died or in some way got (incapacitated). In line 7 the word starting with the letters <hi rend="italic">uti</hi> and ending with ṭi the intervening letters of which have been built in might have read <hi rend="italic">udirappaṭṭi</hi> and the benefaction might have been made to honour him in recognition of some service, he had rendered. It is possible that the surname of <hi rend="italic">kaikkōḷan</hi> indicated that Paṟaiyaṉs [family was hereditarily engaged as troopers in the regular army of the king and the beating of drum was an occupation taken up by <hi rend="italic">paṟaiyaṉ</hi> either in between military engagements or on becoming too old to be an effective soldier].</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2026-05-05" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g ref="sym:bar" type="punctuation">.</g></supplied> cakāttam <num value="1430"><g type="numeral">1000</g> 4 <g type="numeral">100</g> 3 <g type="numeral">10</g></num> Itan mel cellā ninṟa vipava caṅvaṟcarattu kumpa nāyaṟṟu <hi rend="grantha">pūrvvapakṣa</hi>ttu tecamiyum
<lb n="2"/>Ātittavāramum Āyiliyattu nāḷ makataima<unclear>ṇṭa</unclear>lam Āṟakaḻ Ūr nāyiṉā<unclear>r tirukkāmi</unclear>curamuṭaiya ṉāyaṉār pāṇṭiyar ṉāḷ mutal Innāḷ varai<hi rend="grantha">kk</hi>um
<lb n="3"/>tirunāḷum naṭavātirukkaiyil cuvāmi nāḷokaṇṭan vaṅki nārāyaṇan maṟaipukk<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>rkāvalan vallāḷa Irāya <hi rend="grantha">bha</hi>yaṅkaran cāṭikkāṟar kaṇṭa
<lb n="4" break="no"/>n <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>matu Eṟamāñci tulukkaṇanāyakkar nayaṉār tirukkāmicuramuṭaiya nāyaṉāṟkku terum camaittu tirunāḷum mācittirunāḷāka Āyiliyattile terum
<lb n="5"/>makattile tirumañcanamum Āka kaṭṭa<unclear>ḷai</unclear> paṇṇi tiru<unclear>nā</unclear>ḷ naṭakkayil tāmaka <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> nallūril kaikkoḷan perumāḷ makaṉ paṟaiyan paṟai Eṭuttu mutaliyār caṉṉakamala
<lb n="6" break="no"/>ṉāyaṉār Āticaṇṭecura nāyanārum tārumum mā<unclear>ke</unclear>curarum Āka Āṟai ṉāyaka maṇṭapattil niṟaivaṟa niṟaintu kuṟaivaṟa kūṭi Iruntu Āticaṇṭecuraṉāyaṉār
<lb n="7"/>tiruvāy malarntaruḷinapaṭi Inta paṟaiyaṉukku Uti<unclear>t</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="2" unit="character"/> ṭi Ā<unclear>ka</unclear> Āṟakaḻūr naṉcey nilattil kāḷi Ammai Uṭaippukku meṟku tiyākaṇa nallū<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied> vaya 
<lb n="8" break="no"/>lukku kiḻakku naṉcey rūpāy <num value="250">2 <g type="numeral">100</g> 5 <g type="numeral">10</g></num> Oraṇai Er naṭatta maṭṭu puṉcey mā nipamum Orumaṉaiyum Oru <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/> kkum māṉiyamum tirumañcaṉa vaḻikku teṟku Iraṇ
<lb n="9" break="no"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> ṭu Oru toṭṭamum koyilile niṟṟam Irunāḻi Aruciyil coṟum maṉaiyāvatu cannati teruvil vaṭaciṟakil Oru maṉaiyum kuṭuttaruḷi
<lb n="10"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> Āticaṇṭecuraṉāyaṉār tiruvāy malarntaruḷinapaṭiyāle Inta cuvantiram Uṇṭānatu Ivan takappaṉ perumāḷum Ivan vaṟkattārum cantiṟātit
<lb n="11" break="no"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="7" unit="character"/> Aṉupavittu koḷḷakaṭavarkaḷākavum Ivai tiruñāna campanta paṇṭitar Eḻuttu Ivai palamutal kaṅkāṇi periya nayiṉār Eḻuttu §
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 28.257 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Sundaram2010_01"/></bibl> automatically converted to DHARMA conventions.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Sundaram2010_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">420-422</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">257</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
