<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 28.297: original edition by J. Sundaram</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 297. (A.R. No. 451 of 1913.) ĀṞAGAḶŪR, ATTUR TALUK, SALEM DISTRICT.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName>
						<name>DHARMA team</name>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv28p0i0297</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>Karivaradarāja-perumāḷ temple, central shrine, south base of the <hi rend="italic">maṇḍapa</hi> in front.</p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">Kṛishṇadēva-mahārāyar Śaka 1446, Tāruṇa, Makara, Ēkādaśi, Rēvati, Friday, saṅkramaṇa. Irregular.</hi></p>						

						<p>The record gives the descent of the king from Tammarāya through Vīrapratāpa Narasā-nāyakkar and Vīra-bhōga-Vasantarāyar, though the relationship <hi rend="italic">inter se</hi> is not mentioned.</p>						

						<p>It registers the allotment of eight persons as Emberumāṉ-aḍiyār (servants of the God-priests ?) for doing service to God Kariya-perumāḷ of Āṟagaḻur in Āṟṟūr-kūṟṟam in Magadha-maṇḍalam in Malāḍu alias Jananātha-vaḷanāḍu by Mṟuttañjeya-nāyakkar, the agent of Tirumalai-nāyakkar for the merit of his master and grant of 1000 <hi rend="italic">kuḻi</hi> of wet land fed by Rāghavēśvaran-channel in Naraiyūr-kūṟṟam in the <hi rend="italic">chīrmai</hi> on the southern bank, out of the bloc <hi rend="italic">(chīrmai)</hi> given to him by Tirumalai-nāyakkar, free from all encumberances <hi rend="italic">(saṟvamānyam)</hi> and free from taxes (to those eight <hi rend="italic">aḍiyār</hi>) for their own maintenance and for providing food-offerings <hi rend="italic">(amudu-paḍi)</hi> to the God. While referring to the exemptions granted the following levies are mentioned-<hi rend="italic">aṛai-vari</hi> (tax for the maintenance of the dam), <hi rend="italic">ñīr-vaḷi-kāṇikkai, nāṭṭu-vechcham-vilaṭam, paḻa-vari,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pudu-vari.</hi> The grant was made at the auspicious time of <hi rend="italic">shaṅkiramam (saṅkramaṇam).</hi></p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2026-03-17" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> śrīman mahāmaṇḍaleśvaran rācādirācan rājaparameśva<supplied reason="omitted">ra</supplied>n śrīman pū<unclear>r</unclear>vva dakṣi</hi>ṇa<hi rend="grantha"> paścima</hi> Uttara <hi rend="grantha">ca</hi>tu<hi rend="grantha">śamutrādipadi tamma</hi>rāya <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>vi<hi rend="grantha">rapradāpa</hi> naracāṇāyakka vī<hi rend="grantha">rabhoga<unclear>va</unclear></hi> cantarāya <hi rend="grantha">śrīkikṣṇade</hi>va<hi rend="grantha"> mahā</hi>rāyar <hi rend="grantha">pradhi</hi>vi<hi rend="grantha"> rājyam pa</hi>ṇṇi Aruḷāyi niṉṟa cakā<hi rend="grantha">ptam <num value="1446"><g type="numeral">1000</g> 4 <g type="numeral">100</g> 4 <g type="numeral">10</g> 6</num></hi> Itaṉmel cellā niṉṟa tāruṇa <hi rend="grantha">samvatsara</hi>ttu makaranāyaṟṟu (i)<hi rend="grantha">ekādaśi</hi>yu<hi rend="grantha">m</hi> 
<lb n="2"/><hi rend="grantha">re</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">di</hi>yum peṟṟa cu<hi rend="grantha">gra</hi>vārattu nāḷ malāṭākiya cenanāta vaḷanāṭṭu makatai maṇṭalattu Āṟṟūr kūṟṟattu Āṟakaḻu perumāḷ kariya perumāḷukku tirumalai nāyakkar kāri<supplied reason="omitted">ya</supplied>ttukku kaṭavār miṟuttañceya nāyakkar cuvāmi tirumalai nāyakkar namakku pālittaruḷiṉa teṉkarai cirmaiyil naraiyūr kūṟṟattu rākave<hi rend="grantha">śvaran</hi> kālil melai veṭṭi nañcai nilattil ti<unclear>ru</unclear>malai nāyakkar
<lb n="3"/>taṉmamāka Ivvemperumāṉukku Eṭṭu per Emperumāṉaṭi yāraiyum viṭṭu Ivarkaḷukku <hi rend="grantha">prasā</hi><supplied reason="omitted">na</supplied>ttukku Amutupaṭik kaṭṭaḷaikkum Ivarkaḷukku Iṟai<supplied reason="omitted">yi</supplied>likkum Āka caṅkiṟama puṇya kālattil tārā <hi rend="grantha">pūrvva</hi>māka caṟuvamāṉiyamāka viṭṭa nilam kuḻi <num value="1000"><g type="numeral">1000</g></num> Inta nilam Āyiraṅ kuḻikkum Aṇaivari nirvaḻi kāṇikkai nāṭṭu veccam vilāṭam paḻavari putuvari maṟṟum Eṟpeṟpa
<lb n="4" break="no"/>ṭṭa cakala pirā<supplied reason="omitted">p</supplied>tiyum niṅkalāka caṟuva māṉiyamāka kaṭṭaḷaiyiṭṭu viṭṭapaṭiyāle Inta tiṟaiyattile Ā<hi rend="grantha">candrā</hi>kka kālamum Aṉupavittu varakkaṭavatākavum Inta tammam yātoruvar paripālaṉam paṇṇiṉavarkaḷukku Aṉanta pu<hi rend="grantha">ṇya</hi>m paṇṇiṉa <hi rend="grantha">bhalam</hi> Uṇṭākavum Itukku Akitam paṇṇiṉavarkaḷ <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>ga</unclear></hi>ṅkai karaiyile kārāmpacuvai koṉṟa pāvattile poka kaṭavatākavum § <hi rend="grantha">śubhamastu</hi> citampara<note n="485-1">Continuation lost.</note>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 28.297 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Sundaram2010_01"/></bibl> automatically converted to DHARMA conventions.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Sundaram2010_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">484-485</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">297</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
