<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 28.271: original edition by J. Sundaram</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 271. (A.R. No. 425 of 1913.) ĀṞAGAḶŪR, ATTUR TALUK, SALEM DISTRICT.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName>
						<name>DHARMA team</name>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv28p0i0271</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>Kāmēśvara temple, central shrine, on the north wall of the <hi rend="italic">maṇḍapa</hi> in front.</p>						

						<p><hi rend="bold">JaTAvarmaṉ Tribhuvanachakravartti Sundarapāṇḍya Year 10, MIṉa śu. 13, Thursday, Maghā.</hi><note n="441-1"><p>These details of date are capable of being equated to 1260 A.D., February 26 and 1287 A.D., February 27, the former falling in the regin of JaTAvarman Sundarapāṇḍya I who ascended the throne in 1250 A.D., and the latter in the reign of the king of that identical name who is stated to have ascended the throne in 1276 A.D.</p>

<p>Kaṇḍiyadēvar figuring in this record is stated to have been an officer of Jaṭāvarman Kulaśēkhara I (A.R.No. 1909, para 24). Kāḍuveṭṭī figuring in this record also figures in the record of <hi rend="italic">emmaṇḍalamum koṇḍaruḷiya</hi> Jaṭāvarman Sundara-pāṇḍya, identifiable with the first of that name. This has led to the identification of <hi rend="italic">aṇṇāḻvi</hi> Kulaśēkhara in whose name, the deities Āvuḍaiyār and his consort have been set up by Kaṇḍiyadēvar with a Jaṭāvarman Kulaśēkhara whose accession date had been given as 1237 A.D.</p>

<p>If the king of this record is identified with the one with the accession date 1276 A.D., then the <hi rend="italic">aṇṇāḻvi</hi> Kulaśēkhara will have to be identified with Māṟavarmaṉ Kulaśēkhara I (initial year 1268 A.D.). Then there will be the problem of identifying the Kaṇḍiyadēvar and Kāḍuveṭṭi. cf. <hi rend="italic">A.R.Ep.,</hi> 1914, Part II, para 19.)</p></note></p>						

						<p>The inscription records a royal order granting as tax-free land for the temple <hi rend="italic">(dēvadāna-iṟai-ili)</hi> including the right to (collect and appropriate) all cesses <hi rend="italic">(āyam),</hi> land 1/2 <hi rend="italic">(vēli ?)</hi> in extent, out of the first grade <hi rend="italic">vārappaṟṟu</hi> wet land in the village Poṉparappi <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Rājanārāyaṇanallūr to God Poṉparappi Kulaśēkhara-āvuḍaiyār and consort (Nāchchiyār) Vāḻvitta-maṅgai, set up in the name of <hi rend="italic">aṇṇāḻvi</hi> (elder brother of the king ?) by Kaṇḍiya-dēvar, in the temple of Tirukkāmīśvaramuḍaiyā-nāyaṉār in Āragaḷūr in Āṟṟūr-kūṟṟam in Malāḍu <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Jananātha-vaḷanāḍu. The order was addressed to the <hi rend="italic">tānattār</hi> of the temple. The record was attested by Ādichchaṉ Gaṇapati-aḻvāṉ <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Kāḍuveṭṭi of Kāppalūr <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Ulagaḷandachōḻanallūr in Muttūṟṟu-kūṟṟam in Pāṇḍi-maṇḍalam. (See No. 272 &amp; 275 below)</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2026-03-17" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">ḥ svastiśrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> tirumukappaṭi koccaṭapaṉmarāṉa <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vaṉacca<hi rend="grantha">kra</hi>vatti<hi rend="grantha"> śrīsundara</hi> pāṇṭi 
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ya<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vaṟku yāṇṭu <num value="10"><g type="numeral">10</g></num>vatu mīṉanāyaṟṟu <hi rend="grantha">pūrvvapakṣa</hi>ttu <hi rend="grantha">tra</hi>yo<hi rend="grantha"> daśi</hi>yum viyāḻakkiḻamaiyum peṟṟa
<lb n="3"/>makattu nāḷ malāṭākiya <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>ṉanā<hi rend="grantha">tha</hi>vaḷanāṭṭu Āṟṟūrk kūṟṟattu Āṟakaḷūr Uṭaiyār tiru
<lb n="4" break="no"/>kkāmī<hi rend="grantha">śvara</hi>muṭaiya nāyaṉār koyilt tāṉattārkku Ikkoyilil Aṇṇāḻvi tirunāmat
<lb n="5"/>tāl kaṇṭiyatevar Eḻuntaruḷuvitta kulecekara Āvuṭaiyārkku nācciyār
<lb n="6"/>vāḻvitta maṅkaiyarkku tevatāṉa Iṟaiyiliyāka poṉparappiyāṉa Irā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>n<unclear>ā</unclear>r<unclear>ā</unclear>yaṇanal<unclear>lū</unclear>
<lb n="7" break="no"/> <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> r vārappaṟṟu naṉcey nilattu mutal tarattile Arainilam Aṉaittāyaṅkaḷum Uṭpaṭa Iṟaiyili
<lb n="8"/>yāka tantom Ippaṭikku Iolai piṭipāṭāka koṇṭu Iṉilam cantiṟātittavaraiyum cellak kaṭavutāka kal
<lb n="9" break="no"/>lilum cempilum veṭṭi tevatāṉa Iṟaiyiliyāka Aṉupavittup potuvatu Ippaṭikku pāṇṭi maṇṭalattu mu
<lb n="10" break="no"/>ttūṟṟu kūṟṟattu kappalūrāṉa Ulakaḷantacoḻanallūr Āticcaṉ kaṇapati Āḻvāṉāṉa kāṭuveṭṭi Eḻuttu § tiru E
<lb n="11" break="no"/>ḻuttu tulliyam <hi rend="grantha">ḥ §</hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 28.271 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Sundaram2010_01"/></bibl> automatically converted to DHARMA conventions.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Sundaram2010_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">441-442</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">271</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
