<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 1.82: original edition by Eugen Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">PART II. TAMIL AND GRANTHA INSCRIPTIONS. VI. INSCRIPTIONS OF THE KAILĀSANĀTHA AT KĀÑCĪPURAM. No. 82. ON A PILLAR IN THE MAṆḌAPA IN FRONT OF THE RĀJASIṀHAVARMEŚVARA SHRINE.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0082</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>The following inscription is dated in the fifteenth year of <hi rend="bold">Madirai-koṇḍa Ko-Parakesarivarman</hi>. The same names are borne by the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I., <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vīranārāyaṇa</hi>, in a copper-plate grant published by Mr. Foulkes.<note><hi rend="italic">Salem Manual</hi>, Vol. II, pp. 369 ff.</note> As <hi rend="bold">Madirai</hi> seems to stand for <hi rend="bold">Madurai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Madura</hi>), the capital of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍyas,—Madirai-koṇḍa</hi>, “who took Madura,” might also be considered as the Tamil equivalent of <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntaka</hi>, “the destroyer of Madura.” This was the name of a grandson of <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I. according to the large Leyden grant.<note>Dr. Burgess' <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey of Southern India</hi>, Vol. IV, pp. 204 ff. <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntaka</hi>, and not Mathurāntaka, is the reading in lines 48, 62 and 87 of the original, an impression of which I owe to Dr. Burgess.</note> Another <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntaka</hi>, who was the son of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, issued the Sanskrit portion of the Leyden grant after his father's death.<note>See page 96, note 8.</note> He is probably identical with <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi>, who, according to Nos. 67 and 68, conquered the <hi rend="bold">Maduramaṇḍalam</hi>. The three kings just mentioned are Nos. 3, 9 and 11 of the subjoined table, which I insert for ready reference. It contains the pedigree of the <hi rend="bold">Choḷas</hi> according to the large Leyden grant. The first three kings of the table are also named in Mr. Foulkes' above-mentioned grant.<note><hi rend="italic">Salem Manual</hi>, Vol. II, pp. 369 ff., verses 4 to 11, 24 and 25.</note> On inscriptions of the two last kings and on other conquests of theirs, see the introductions of Nos. 40 and 67, above.</p>						
                            
                            <p>[[genealogical table]] [C1]1. Vijayālaya of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>. [C1]2. Āditya I. [C1]3. Parāntaka I., <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Vīranārāyaṇa or Madirai-koṇḍa Ko-Parakesarivarman. He covered the Śiva Temple at Vyāghrāgrahāra<note>As discovered by my assistant, V. Venkayya, M.A., <hi rend="bold">Vyāghrāgrahāra</hi> is the Sanskrit equivalent of <hi rend="bold">Puliyūr</hi>, “the tiger-village,” one of the names of <hi rend="bold">Chidambaram</hi>. The report of the Leyden grant is confirmed by the <hi rend="italic">Koṅgu Chronicle</hi>, which says twice, that <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> I. “built the <hi rend="bold">Kanaka-sabhā</hi> or Golden Hall” at <hi rend="bold">Chidambaram</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Salem Manual</hi>, Vol. I, p. 40.</note> with gold, married the daughter of the king of Keraḷa and conquered the Bāṇa king, Vaitumba,<note>Compare “the Vaidondai race” and “Vaidumba-raya” in the Rev. Taylor's translation of the <hi rend="italic">Koṅgu Chronicle, Madras Journal</hi>, Vol. XIV, Part I, pp. 15 and 16, and <hi rend="bold">V[ai]dumba</hi> in No. 144, below.</note> the king of Laṅkā (Ceylon) and Rājasiṁha Pāṇḍya.<note>See note 1.</note> [C1]4. Rājāditya, was killed in a battle with Kṛishṇarāja.<note>This seems to have been the <hi rend="bold">Rāshṭrakūṭa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Kṛishṇa</hi> IV., whose grants range between Śaka 868 and 879. The Amoghavarsha, who is mentioned in Mr. Foulkes' grant (verse 16) is probably identical with the <hi rend="bold">Rāshṭrakūṭa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Śarva Amoghavarsha I</hi>. (Śaka 737 to at least 800).</note> [C2]5. Gaṇḍarādityavarman, founded a village called by his name on the northern bank of the Kāverī.<note>In Sewell's <hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. I, p. 265, a village called <hi rend="bold">Kaṇḍarādityam</hi> in the Trichinopoly District is mentioned.</note> [C3]6. Ariṁjaya. [C1]7. Parāntaka II., <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Rājendra, fought a battle at Chevūr.<note>Mr. Sewell, <hi rend="italic">u.s</hi>., pp. 168 and 207, mentions two villages of this name in the North and South Arcot Districts.</note> [C1]8. Āditya II., <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Karikāla, fought in his youth with Vīra- Pāṇḍya. [C1]9. Madhurāntaka I. [C1]Kundavai, married to the Pallava king Vandyadeva.<note>See page 97, note 9.</note> [C3]10. Rājarāja, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Rājāśraya or Rājakesarivarman, made certain gifts in Śaka 926<note>See page 64, note 1.</note> and conquered the Western Chālukya king Satyāśraya II. (Śaka 919 to about 930). [C1]11. Rājendra-Choḷa, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Madhurāntaka II. or Parakesarivarman, fought with the Western Chālukya king Jayasiṁha III. (about Śaka 940 to about 964). [C1]Kūndavā, married to the Eastern Chalukya king Vimalāditya (Śaka 937 (?) to 944). [C1]Ammaṅga-devī, married to the Eastern Chalukya king Rājarāja I. (Śaka 944 to 985).</p>						
                            
                            <p>On <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi>, the probable successor of (II) <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>, see the remarks on No. 127, below. In the introduction of No. 67, I might have added that the Miraj grant of the Western Chālukya king Jayasiṁha III.<note><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. VIII, p. 18.</note> calls <hi rend="bold">(Rājendra-) Choḷa</hi> <hi rend="italic">Pañcha-Dramilādhipati</hi> (read thus instead of <hi rend="italic">yaṁ Chaṁdramilādhipati</hi><note>This correction was suggested by my assistant, V. Venkayya, M.A.</note>), “the lord of the five <hi rend="bold">Draviḍa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">nations)</hi>.<note>The “five Draviḍas,” as opposed to the “five Gauḍas,” are the chief tribes or languages on the south of the Vindhya:—Draviḍa proper (Tamil), Āndhra (Telugu), Karṇāṭa (Kanarese), Mahārāshṭra and Gurjara; see Böhtlingk and Roth's <hi rend="italic">Sanskrit Dictionary, s.v</hi>. <foreign>draviḍa,</foreign> and Winslow, <hi rend="italic">s.v</hi>. <foreign>tiraviṭam</foreign>.</note>” The village, which was the object of the Miraj grant, belonged to “the <hi rend="bold">Eḍadore</hi> (read thus instead of <hi rend="italic">Paḍadore</hi>) Two-thousand.” Accordingly, the country of <hi rend="bold">Eḍatore</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Maisūr</hi> must have been in the possession of <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. in Śaka 946 (expired). The same country of <hi rend="bold">Eḍatore</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Iḍaituṟai-nāḍu</hi>) occupies the first place in the list of the conquests of <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi>.<note>See pages 96 and 99, above.</note></p>						
                            
                            <p>The subjoined inscription records that a certain <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍaparākrama-vīra</hi> gave to the god of “the holy stone-temple” (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the Rājasiṁhavarmeśvara Temple<note>See page 118, below.</note>) at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippeḍu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Kāñchīpuram) 270 sheep, from the milk of which three lamps had to be supplied with ghee. A certain <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍaparākrama-maṉṟāḍi</hi>, who seems to be distinct from the donor, pledged himself, that he and his descendants would supply the ghee daily or otherwise incur certain fixed fines.</p>						
                            
                            <p>It is worthy of note, that in this very archaic inscription the <hi rend="italic">puḷḷi</hi> or the dot above consonants, which corresponds to the Nāgarī <hi rend="italic">virāma</hi>, occurs five times.<note>Line 2: <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">ṇ</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">koṇṭa; ṉ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">k</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">paṉmakku</foreign>. Line 3: <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">ṇ</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">yāṇṭu</foreign>. Line 12: <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">ṇ</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">koṇṭu</foreign>.</note> It is represented by a short vertical stroke. The same sign is found in the Tamil portion of the <hi rend="bold">Kūram</hi> plates of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Parameśvaravarman</hi> I. (No. 151, below.)</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-05-24" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-05-06" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/><g type="ddanda">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <g type="ddanda">.</g> matirai <unclear>ko</unclear><!--kompu is clear-->
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>ṇṭa kopparakecaripaṉmak<unclear>ku</unclear>
                    <lb n="3"/>yāṇṭu patinañcāvatu ka<unclear>cci</unclear>
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>ppeṭṭupperiya <unclear>tiru</unclear>
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>kkaṟṟaḷi <hi rend="grantha">mahāde</hi>var<unclear>ku</unclear>
                    <lb n="6"/>caṇ<supplied reason="omitted">ṭa</supplied>parākkirama<supplied reason="omitted">ma</supplied>nṟāṭiyen <unclear>E</unclear>
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>ḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tirukaṟtaḷi tevarku mū<unclear>n</unclear>
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>ṟu no<hi rend="grantha">nd<unclear>ā</unclear></hi>viḷakku <hi rend="grantha">candrāditya</hi>r Uḷa
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>ḷavum caṇṭaparākkiramavira v<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>tta
                    <lb n="10"/>cāvā mūvā perāṭu Irunūṟṟu
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>Eḻupatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ivvāṭṭā<supplied reason="omitted">l</supplied> nicati mū<unclear>ḻa</unclear>
                    <lb n="12" break="no"/>kku ney koṇṭu ceṉṟu U<unclear>ṇ</unclear>
                    <lb n="13" break="no"/>ṇāḻi<unclear>kai</unclear> Uṭaiyarkaḷ kai<unclear>yi</unclear>
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>l ṉāluḻakku vaḻuvā<unclear>ta</unclear> nāḻi
                    <lb n="15" break="no"/>yāl En makkaḷ makkaḷ <unclear>va</unclear>
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>ḻi vaḻi <unclear>Eṉṟum A</unclear>ṭṭuven <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Aṭ<unclear>ṭe</unclear>
                    <lb n="17" break="no"/>ṉāyil <hi rend="grantha">dharmmā<unclear>sa</unclear></hi><unclear>na</unclear>ttil nica<unclear>ti</unclear>
                    <lb n="18"/>nālekāl <unclear>taṇṭapaṭuve</unclear>ṉā<unclear>ṉ</unclear>e
                    <lb n="19" break="no"/>ṉ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ittaṇ<unclear>ṭapaṭṭum Iṉe</unclear>y mu<unclear>ṭ</unclear>
                    <lb n="20" break="no"/>ṭāme Aṭṭuve<unclear>ṉāneṉ</unclear> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> <unclear>mu</unclear>ṭṭil A
                    <lb n="21" break="no"/>ṉṟāḷ ko<unclear>vukku nicati ma</unclear>ñcāṭi
                    <lb n="22"/>poṉ manṟa <unclear>Oṭṭi kuṭutteṉ</unclear>
                    <lb n="23"/><gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> <unclear>vi</unclear>rama <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> 
                    <lb n="24"/><unclear>I</unclear><hi rend="grantha">ddharmma</hi>m <hi rend="grantha"><unclear>ca</unclear>ndrā<unclear>ditya</unclear></hi> <gap reason="lost" quantity="4" unit="character"/>
                    <lb n="25"/><gap reason="lost" quantity="10" unit="character"/> 
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1890_01">
                
                <p>Hail! Prosperity! In the fifteenth year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Madirai-koṇḍa Ko-Parakesarivarman</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the following</hi>) written agreement (<hi rend="italic">was made</hi>) with <hi rend="bold">Mahādeva</hi> of the large holy stone-temple at <hi rend="bold">Kachchippeḍu</hi> by me, <hi rend="bold">Chaṇḍaparākrama-maṉṟāḍi. Chaṇḍaparākrama-vīra</hi> gave two hundred and seventy undying and unending<note>This seems to mean, that the sheep, if dead, had to be replaced by fresh ones.</note> big sheep to the god of the holy stone-temple, (<hi rend="italic">in order to keep</hi>) three <hi rend="italic">nondā</hi> lamps<note>In other inscriptions, we find the spelling <foreign>nantāviḷakku</foreign> for <foreign>nontāviḷakku</foreign>, which occurs also in No. 83, line 8, and in No. 147, line 5.</note> (<hi rend="italic">burning</hi>) as long as the moon and the sun exist. From (<hi rend="italic">the milk of</hi>) these sheep,—myself, my sons and my further descendants shall take three <hi rend="italic">uṛakkus</hi> of ghee daily<note><foreign xml:lang="tam-Latn">nicati</foreign> seems to be connected with <foreign>niccam, nitam, nittam</foreign> or <foreign>nittiyam</foreign> (Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">nityam</hi>).</note> and shall, for ever, pour them out into the hands of those, who are in charge of the <hi rend="italic">nāṛigai (measure</hi>) within (<hi rend="italic">the temple</hi>), with a <hi rend="italic">nāṛi (measure</hi>) which is equal to four <hi rend="italic">uṛakkus</hi>.<note>According to the Tamil dictionaries, 1 <hi rend="italic">nāṛi</hi> or <hi rend="italic">paḍi</hi> consists of 4 <hi rend="italic">uṛakkus</hi>.</note> If I do not pour them out, I shall be liable to a fine of four and a quarter (<hi rend="italic">uṛakkus</hi>) daily in court. Although I am fined thus, I shall pour out this ghee without resistance. If I resist, I solemnly agree to pay one <hi rend="italic">mañjāḍi</hi><note>1 <hi rend="italic">manjāḍi</hi> weighs 4 grains.</note> of gold daily to the king who is then ruling.  . . . . . . . . . . This meritorious gift <hi rend="italic">[shall last as long as]</hi> the moon and the sun.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 1.82 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">111-114</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">82</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
