<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 1.40: original edition by Eugen Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">PART II. TAMIL AND GRANTHA INSCRIPTIONS. I. INSCRIPTIONS AT MĀMALLAPURAM. No. 40. ON THE SOUTH BASE OF THE SHORE TEMPLE.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0040</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>This inscription is dated in the twenty-fifth year of <hi rend="bold">Ko-Rājarāja-Rājakesarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>. It states, that the king “built a jewel-like hall at <hi rend="bold">Kāndaḷūr</hi>,” and then gives a list of the countries, which he is said to have conquered. Among them <hi rend="bold">Veṅgai-nāḍu</hi> is the well-known country of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī; Gaṅga-pāḍi</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Nuḷambapāḍi</hi> are found on Mr. Rice's Map of Mysore;<note><hi rend="italic">Mysore Inscriptions</hi>, p. lxxxiv.</note> <hi rend="bold">Kuḍamalai-nāḍu</hi>, “the western hillcountry,” is Coorg; <hi rend="bold">Kollam</hi> is Quilon; <hi rend="bold">Kaliṅgam</hi> is the country between the Godāvarī and Mahānadī rivers; <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi> is Ceylon; <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-pāḍi</hi> is the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukyan</hi> empire;<note>See the introduction of No. 67, below.</note> and the <hi rend="bold">Śeṛiyas</hi> are the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍyas</hi>. I have been unable to identify <hi rend="bold">Taḍigaipāḍi</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Sir Walter Elliot's and Dr. Burnell's tentative lists of <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> kings<note><hi rend="italic">Coins of Southern India</hi>, p. 131; <hi rend="italic">South-Indian Palaeography</hi>, 2nd edition, p. 40.</note> contain a king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, who reigned from 1023 to 1064 A.D. These figures rest on three Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> grants, of which two have since been published by Mr. Fleet and one has been edited and translated above (No. 39). From these three grants it appears, that the Rājarāja, who reigned from Śaka 944 to 985, was not a <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> king, but a king of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>, and that his insertion in the list of <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> kings was nothing but a mistake.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The historical portion of the subjoined inscription is almost identical with lines 166 to 173 of the large Leyden grant<note>Dr. Burgess' <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Survey of Southern India</hi>, Vol. IV, p. 204.</note> and must belong to the same king. The Leyden grant states that <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> conquered <hi rend="bold">Satyāśraya</hi> (line 65). This name was borne as a surname by no less than six of the carlier Western <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> kings and was also the name of one of the later Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukyas</hi>. From certain unpublished inscriptions of the Tanjore Temple it can be safely inferred, that <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> was the predecessor of <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷadeva</hi>, the enemy of the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III., who ruled from about Śaka 944 to about 964.<note>See the introduction of No. 67, below.</note> Hence the <hi rend="bold">Satyāśraya</hi> mentioned in the Leyden grant might be identified with the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Satyāśraya</hi> II., who ruled from Śaka 919 to about 930;<note>Mr. Fleet's <hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, p. 42.</note> and the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, who issued the large Leyden grant and the inscriptions Nos. 40, 41 and 66 of the present volume, with that <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, whose daughter <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi> was married to the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi>,<note><hi rend="italic">Indian Antiquary</hi>, Vol. XIV, p. 50.</note> who reigned from Śaka 937 (?) to 944. As <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> boasts in his inscriptions of having conquered <hi rend="bold">Veṅgai-nāḍu</hi>, the country of the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukyas</hi>, this marriage was probably a forced one and the result of his conquest of <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi>.<note>See the remarks of Dr. Burnell, <hi rend="italic">S. I. Palaeography</hi>, 2nd edition, p. 22, note.</note> The identification of the <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> of the Leyden grant and of Nos. 40, 41 and 66 with the father of <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi> is confirmed by the <hi rend="italic">Koṅgu Chronicle</hi>, where some of his charities are placed in Śaka 926.<note><hi rend="italic">Madras Journal</hi>, Vol. XIV, Part I, p. 17.</note> The <hi rend="bold">Koṅgu Chronicle</hi> further suggests the probability of identifying <hi rend="bold">Kāndaḷūr</hi>, where <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> built a hall (<hi rend="italic">śālā</hi>), with <hi rend="bold">Chidambaram</hi>, as it records that “he enlarged the temples at Chidambaram and erected all kinds of towers, walls, <hi rend="italic">maṇḍapas</hi>, flights of steps, etc., and other matters.”</p>						
                            
                            <p>From this and the next-following inscription we learn that <hi rend="bold">Māmallapuram</hi> belonged to <hi rend="bold">Āmūr-nāḍu</hi>,<note>Instead of <hi rend="bold">Āmūr-nāḍu</hi>, the present inscription uses the term “the fifty (<hi rend="italic">villages called after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pudukkuḍaiyāṉ Ekadhīra</hi>,” which occurs also in lines 32 f. of No. 41.</note> a division of <hi rend="bold">Āmūr-koṭṭam</hi>, and that the name of the Shore Temple was <hi rend="bold">Jalaśayana</hi>. The purport of the inscription is a new division of the land of the town of <hi rend="bold">Māmallapuram</hi>, which had been agreed upon by the citizens.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-05-24" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-05-06" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tirumakaḷ po
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>lapperu nilaccelvi<unclear>yu</unclear>n=taṉakke
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>yurim<unclear>ai</unclear> pūṇ<unclear>ṭa</unclear>mai maṉa<unclear>kk</unclear>oḷakkā
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>n=taḷuṟcālai kalamaṟut<unclear>taruḷi</unclear> veṅkai
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>nāṭuṅ<unclear>ka</unclear>ṅkapāṭiyu<unclear>nuḷa</unclear>mpapāṭiyu<unclear>n=ta</unclear>
                    <lb n="6" break="no"/>ṭikaipāṭiyuṅkuṭama<unclear>lai</unclear>ñāṭuṅkol
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>lamuṅkaliṅkamum Eṇṭicai pukaḻ tara
                    <lb n="8"/>Īḻamaṇṭalamum Iraṭṭapāṭi Eḻaraiyila
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>kkamun=tiṇṭiṟal veṉṟittaṇṭāṟko
                    <lb n="10" break="no"/>ṇṭa taṉneḻil vaḷa<unclear>ru</unclear>ḻiyuḷellāyā
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>ṇṭun=toḻutaka viḷaṅkum yāṇṭe ceḻi
                    <lb n="12" break="no"/>yarai tecu koḷ <hi rend="grantha">śrīkorājarājarāja</hi>
                    <lb n="13" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">kesari</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">rmmarā</hi>ṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājarājade</hi>vaṟku yā
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>ṇṭu Irupattaiñcāvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Āmu<unclear>rk</unclear>ko
                    <lb n="15" break="no"/>ṭṭam vakai ceykiṉṟa <unclear>pu</unclear>tukkuṭai
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>yāṉ Ekatiraṉ Aiyampatiṉ maṉnakara
                    <lb n="17" break="no"/>māmallapurattu <hi rend="grantha">jalaśa</hi>yaṉa<hi rend="grantha">de</hi>var te
                    <lb n="18" break="no"/>ṟkkil tirunan=tāvaṉatte Iruk<unclear>ka</unclear> Iṉna
                    <lb n="19" break="no"/>karattu nakarattomum periḷamaiyo
                    <lb n="20" break="no"/>mum Emmilicain=tu ceyta <hi rend="grantha">vya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">stai</hi>
                    <lb n="21" break="no"/>yāvatu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Emmur nirnilamum veṇṇi
                    <lb n="22" break="no"/>lamum toṭṭanilamum kollainilamu
                    <lb n="23" break="no"/>m Iṟainilamāmacceppeṟpaṭṭatu
                    <lb n="24" break="no"/>m nūṟu ma<unclear>ṉai</unclear>kkiḻ nā<unclear>l kūṟā</unclear>ka Aṭai
                    <lb n="25" break="no"/>ppatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ippa<unclear>ri</unclear>cu Aṭaiccu n<unclear>ā</unclear>
                    <lb n="26" break="no"/>lu kūṟiṭṭa Oru kūṟu Innakarattu ka<unclear>ṭu</unclear>
                    <lb n="27" break="no"/>mpiṭukucericcaṅkarappāṭiyā<unclear>rk</unclear>
                    <lb n="28" break="no"/>ku Irupattaiñcu maṉaikku kūṟāva
                    <lb n="29" break="no"/>tākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> niṉṟa muṉṟu kūṟum Eḻu
                    <lb n="30" break="no"/>pattaiñcu maṉaikkiḻ <unclear>kū</unclear>ṟāvatā
                    <lb n="31" break="no"/>kavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> kūṟiṭṭa parice maṉaiyum nilamu
                    <lb n="32" break="no"/>m viṟkkavum Oṟṟivaikkavum <hi rend="grantha">dharmma</hi>
                    <lb n="33" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha"><unclear>d</unclear>ā</hi>ṉañceyya peṟuvatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> ni
                    <lb n="34" break="no"/>lamum maṉaiyum kū<unclear>ṟaṭai</unclear>t<unclear>ta</unclear> paric<unclear>e</unclear>
                    <lb n="35"/><hi rend="grantha"><unclear>la</unclear>kṣa</hi>ṇañceytu kuṭuppatākavu
                    <lb n="36" break="no"/>m <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> muṉpuḷḷa <hi rend="grantha">lakṣa</hi>ṇañc<unclear>āṅkam ki</unclear>
                    <lb n="37" break="no"/>ḻivatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> kūṟaṭaitta nilaṅka
                    <lb n="38" break="no"/>ḷil niṉṟa palluruvil pa<unclear>ḻa</unclear>maraṅka
                    <lb n="39" break="no"/>ḷ Avvavakūṟuṭaiyāṉe peṟu
                    <lb n="40" break="no"/>vāṉākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mañcikkattil niṉṟa
                    <lb n="41" break="no"/>ṉa nūṟu maṉaikkuṅkū<unclear>ṟā</unclear>vatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    <lb n="42"/>nilamiṉṟiye patiṉāṟu vaya<hi rend="grantha">si</hi>ṉ
                    <lb n="43"/>mel viyāpārañceytiruppārai
                    <lb n="44"/>Araikkaḻañcu poṉṉum kūli
                    <lb n="45" break="no"/>kkucceytiruppārai Araikkā
                    <lb n="46" break="no"/>l poṉṉum E
                    <lb n="47" break="no"/>ruṭaiyarāy va
                    <lb n="48" break="no"/>ricaikku muvārai
                    <lb n="49" break="no"/>kkālppoṉṉu
                    <lb n="50" break="no"/>m Āṇṭu varai
                    <lb n="51" break="no"/>kkoḷvatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    <lb n="52"/>Ipparicu Aṉṟe
                    <lb n="53" break="no"/>ṉṟārai me<unclear>l</unclear> ve
                    <lb n="54" break="no"/>ṟu Irupattaiṅkaḻañcu poṉ <hi rend="grantha">da</hi>ṇ
                    <lb n="55" break="no"/>ṭaṅkoḷvatākavum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ipparicu Em
                    <lb n="56" break="no"/>millicain=tu<hi rend="grantha"> vya</hi>va<hi rend="grantha">stai</hi> ceyto
                    <lb n="57" break="no"/>m nakarattomum periḷamaiyo
                    <lb n="58" break="no"/>mum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Ipparicu nakarattārum periḷa
                    <lb n="59" break="no"/>maiyāruñcolla Eḻutiṉeṉ
                    <lb n="60"/>Iṉṉakarattu karaṇattāṉ tiruva
                    <lb n="61" break="no"/>ṭikaḷ maṇi kaṇṭa ṉāṉ tiruveḷaṟai
                    <lb n="62"/>muvāyirattuEḻunūṟṟuvaṉeṉ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> I
                    <lb n="63" break="no"/>vai Eṉṉeḻuttu <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1890_01">
                
                <p>Hail! Prosperity! In the twenty-fifth year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Ko-Rājarāja-Rājakesarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>, who,—while both the goddess of fortune and the great goddess of the earth, who had become his exclusive property, gave him pleasure,—was pleased to build a jewel (<hi rend="italic">-like</hi>) hall (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Kāndaḷūr</hi> and conquered by his army, which was victorious in great battles, <hi rend="bold">Veṅgai-nāḍu, Gaṅgapāḍi, Nuḷamba-pāḍi, Taḍigai-pāḍi, Kuḍamalai-nāḍu, Kollam, Kaliṅgam, Īṛamaṇḍalam</hi>, which is famed in the eight quarters, and <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-pāḍi</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">the revenue from which amounts to</hi>) seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi>; who,—while his beauty was increasing, and while he was resplendent (<hi rend="italic">to such an extent</hi>) that he was always worthy to be worshipped,—deprived the <hi rend="bold">Śeṛiyas</hi> of their splendour,—We, the middle-aged citizens of this town, unanimously made the following contract, while assembled in the <hi rend="italic">tirunandāvana</hi> to the south of (<hi rend="italic">the temple of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Jalaśayana-deva</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Māmallapuram</hi>, the chief town of the fifty (<hi rend="italic">villages called after</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pudukkuḍaiyāṉ Ekadhīra</hi>,<note><hi rend="italic">Pudukkuḍaiyāṉ</hi> (Tamil) means “the owner of a new parasol,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, one who has recently risen to royal power; <hi rend="italic">Ekadhīra</hi> (Sanskrit) means “the singly brave.”</note> which form part of <hi rend="bold">Āmūr-koṭṭam</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 21.) The wet land, white (?) land, garden land, dry land and all other<note><foreign>maccu</foreign> is perhaps a corrupted from of <foreign>maṟṟu</foreign>.</note> taxable (?) land of our town shall be divided into four lots of one hundred <hi rend="italic">maṉais</hi>.<note>1 <hi rend="italic">maṉai</hi> is equal to 2,400 square feet.</note> One lot of (<hi rend="italic">the land</hi>), which has been divided into four lots according to this contract,<note><foreign>paricu</foreign>, Sanskrit <foreign>sparśa,</foreign> originally means “the touching of water (<hi rend="italic">in a solemn declaration</hi>).”</note> shall be a lot of twenty-five <hi rend="italic">maṉais (which belongs</hi>) to the inhabitants of (<hi rend="italic">the quarter of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ka[ḍu]mbiḍugu-śeri</hi> (<hi rend="italic">alias</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Śaṁkara-pāḍi</hi> of this town. The remaining three lots shall be a lot of seventy-five <hi rend="italic">maṉais</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">maṉais (of</hi>) the land (<hi rend="italic">included in</hi>) the contract of division into lots may be sold, mortgaged, or used for meritorious gifts; (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">maṉais (of</hi>) the land shall be given away as defined by the contract of the division into lots. The previous definition shall be wholly cancelled. The fruit-trees, which stand in the various parts of the lands divided into lots, shall be enjoyed by the owner of the respective lot. Those (<hi rend="italic">trees</hi>) which stand on the causeways between the rice-fields,<note><foreign>mañcikkam</foreign> seems to mean the same as <foreign>mañcil</foreign>.</note> shall belong to (<hi rend="italic">the whole of</hi>) the hundred <hi rend="italic">maṉais</hi>. Among those who are without land and are over the age of sixteen,—from those who are engaged in trade half a <hi rend="italic">kaṛañju</hi> of gold (<hi rend="italic">poṉ</hi>), from those who work for hire one-eighth of a <hi rend="italic">poṉ</hi> and for (<hi rend="italic">each</hi>) turn as ploughmen (?) three-eighths of a <hi rend="italic">poṉ</hi> shall be taken at the end of the year. From those who do not submit to this contract, further twenty-five <hi rend="italic">kaṛañjus</hi> of gold shall be taken besides as a fine. We, the middle-aged citizens of the town, have unanimously established this contract.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 58.) I, <hi rend="bold">Tiruveḷaṟai Muvāyirattu-eṛunūṟṟuvaṉ</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">karaṇam</hi> of this town, who worships the holy feet (<hi rend="italic">of the god</hi>), wrote this contract according to the orders of the middle-aged citizens. This is my signature.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 1.40 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">63-66</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">40</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
