<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 1.67: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
			    <title type="alt">PART II. TAMIL AND GRANTHA INSCRIPTIONS. IV. INSCRIPTIONS AT TIRUMALAI NEAR POLÛR. No. 67. ON A PIECE OF ROCK ON THE TOP OF THE TIRUMALAI HILL.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:emfr">
						<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
						<surname>Francis</surname>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0067</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p>This inscription is dated in the 12th year of <hi rend="bold">Ko-Parakesarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Uḍaiyār Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi>. It opens with a long list of the countries which the king had conquered. Among these we find “the seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas (of revenue</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭapāḍi</hi>,” which <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi> took from <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi>. This conquest must have taken place between his 7th and 10th years, as another of Rājendra-Choḷa's inscriptions, which is dated in his 7th year,<note n="95-8"><hi rend="italic">Madras Christian College Magazine</hi>, Vol. V, p. 41.</note>does not mention it, while it occurs in some unpublished Tanjore inscriptions of the 10th year.<note n="96-1">The conquest of “the high mountains of <hi rend="bold">Navanedikkula (?)</hi>” took also place between the 7th and 10th years, but subsequently to the war against <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi>.</note>The <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> of the present inscription can be no other than the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. (about Śaka 940 to about 964), who, according to the Miraj grant, “warred against the Chola,”<note n="96-2"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. VIII, p. 18.</note>and who, in another inscription, is called “the lion to the elephant <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>.”<note n="96-3"><hi rend="italic">Rājendra-Choḷa-gaja-mṛigarāja; Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. V, p. 15, lines 13 f. Mr. Rice's <hi rend="italic">Mysore Inscriptions</hi>, p. 149.</note>Consequently, “the seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi>. of <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭapāḍi</hi>” have to be taken as a designation of the <hi rend="bold">Chalukyan</hi> empire,<note n="96-4">See the remarks of Sir W. Elliot in Carr's <hi rend="italic">Seven Pagodas</hi>, pp. 138 ff.</note>which, in two Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> grants, is called “the Dekhan which yields seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi>.”<note n="96-5">See No. 39, line 26, and <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 51, line 29.</note>As both <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. boast of having conquered the other, it must be assumed that either the success was on both sides alternately, or that neither of the two obtained a lasting advantage. If, in order to identify <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>, the enemy of <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III., we turn to the table of the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> Dynasty, which is found on page 32, above, we find that he cannot be that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi>, who reigned from Śaka 985 to 1034. Undoubtedly, the enemy of <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. was that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, whose daughter <hi rend="bold">Ammaṅga-devī</hi> was married to the Eastern Chalukya king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I.<note n="96-6">See p. 51, above.</note> (Śaka 944 to 985). He is further identical with that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi>, who was the son of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, and whose younger sister <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi> was married to the Eastern Chalukya king <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi><note n="96-7"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 50.</note> (Śaka 937 (?) to 944). From certain Tanjore inscriptions it can be safely concluded, that he was the successor of his father <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>, whose time I have tried to fix in the introduction of No. 40, above. <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa's</hi> name occurs also on the seal of the large Leyden grant, and he is in all probability identical with the <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntaka</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, “the destroyer of Madura,” who issued that grant after the death of his father <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>.<note n="96-8">See lines 86 to 88 of the large Leyden grant; Dr. Burgess' <hi rend="italic">Arch. Survey of S. India</hi>, Vol. IV, p. 208.</note></p>						

						<p>Among the other countries, which <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi> is said to have conquered, the two first in the list are <hi rend="bold">Iḍaituṟai-nāḍu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the country of Eḍatore, the head-quarters of a tālluqa in the Maisūr District, and <hi rend="bold">Vaṉavāśi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Banawāsi in the North Kanara District of the Bombay Presidency. With <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷippākkai</hi> compare <hi rend="bold">Kollipāke</hi>, which, according to Mr. Fleet,<note n="96-9"><hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, p. 44.</note>was one of the capitals of the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. <hi rend="bold">Īṛam</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi> is Ceylon. “The king of the South” (<hi rend="italic">Teṉṉavaṉ</hi>) is the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king. Of him the inscription says, that he had formerly given the crown of <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi> to the king of Ceylon, from whom <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi> took that crown of Sundara. The name <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi> occurs in the traditional lists of <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> kings.<note n="96-10">Sewell's <hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. II, pp. 218 ff. Dr. Caldwell's <hi rend="italic">Comparative Grammar</hi>, pp. 139 ff. of the Introduction and pp. 535 ff.</note>In the present inscription, the term “the crown of <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi>” seems to be used in the sense of “the crown of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king,” and the composer of the historical part of the inscription seems to have known <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi> as a former famous member of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> dynasty. But no conclusions as to the date of <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi> can be drawn from this mention of his name. The names of the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> king, who was conquered by the king of Ceylon, and of the king of Ceylon, who was conquered by <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>, are not mentioned. The inscription further records that Rājendra-Choḷa vanquished the <hi rend="bold">Keraḷa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the king of Malabar. With <hi rend="bold">Śakkara-koṭṭam</hi>, whose king <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Vīra</hi> was defeated by Rājendra-Choḷa, compare <hi rend="bold">Chakrakoṭa</hi>, whose lord was conquered by the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi> VI.,<note n="97-1">Dr. Bu7hler's <hi rend="italic">Vikramāṅkacharita</hi>, sarga iv, verse 30.</note>and <hi rend="bold">Chakragoṭṭa</hi>, which was taken by the <hi rend="bold">Hoysaḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana.<note n="97-2">Mr. Fleet's <hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, p. 66.</note> Madura-maṇḍalam</hi> is the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍya</hi> country, the capital of which was Madura. <hi rend="bold">Oḍḍavishaya</hi>, the country of the <hi rend="bold">Oḍḍas</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Oḍras</hi><note n="97-3">Sanskrit: <hi rend="bold">Oḍra</hi>; Telugu: <hi rend="bold">Ōḍhrulu</hi>, the inhabitants of <hi rend="bold">Ōḍhra-dēśa</hi>; Kanarese: <hi rend="bold">Oḍḍaru</hi>; Tamil: <foreign>oṭṭar</foreign> or <foreign>oṭṭiyar</foreign>, the inhabitants of <foreign>oṭṭam</foreign> or <foreign>oṭṭiyam</foreign>.</note>and the <hi rend="bold">U-cha</hi> of Hiuen-Tsiang,<note n="97-4">Beal's <hi rend="italic">Si-yu-ki</hi>, Vol. II, p. 204.</note>is the modern Orissa. <hi rend="bold">Kośalai-nāḍu</hi> is Southern <hi rend="bold">Kosala</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Kiao-sa-lo</hi> of Hiuen-Tsiang,<note n="97-5"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> p. 209.</note> which, according to General Cunningham, corresponds to the upper valley of the Mahānadī and its tributaries.<note n="97-6"><hi rend="italic">Arch. Survey of India</hi>, Vol. XVII, p. 68.</note> <hi rend="bold">Takkaṇalāḍam</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Uttiralāḍam</hi> are Northern and Southern <hi rend="bold">Lāṭa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Gujarāt</hi>). The former was taken from a certain <hi rend="bold">Raṇaśūra</hi>. Further, Rājendra-Choḷa asserts that he conquered <hi rend="bold">Vaṅgāḷa-deśa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Bengal, from a certain <hi rend="bold">Govindachandra</hi> and extended his operations as far as the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgā</hi>. The remaining names of countries and kings I have been unable to identify.</p>						

						<p>The inscription mentions <hi rend="bold">Tirumalai</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, “the holy mountain,” and records a gift to the temple on its top, which was called <hi rend="bold">Kundavai-Jinālaya</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Jina</hi> temple of <hi rend="bold">Kundavai</hi>. According to an Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> grant<note n="97-7"><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 53, lines 60 f.</note> (and an unpublished Chidambaram inscription<note n="97-8">See paragraph 5 of my <hi rend="italic">Progress Report for February, March and April</hi> 1888, Madras G.O., 27th July 1888, No. 745, Public.</note>), <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> Kundavai) was the name of the daughter of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, the younger sister of <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>, and the queen of the Eastern Chalukya king <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi>. The Tanjore inscriptions mention another, still earlier <hi rend="bold">Kundavai</hi>, who was the daughter of the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Parāntaka</hi> II., the elder sister of the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>, and the queen of the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vandyadeva</hi>.<note n="97-9">See paragraph 8 of my <hi rend="italic">Progress Report for July, August and September</hi> 1888, Madras G.O., 7th November 1888, No. 1050, Public.</note>It seems very probable that it was one of these two queens, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, either the younger sister or the aunt of the then reigning sovereign <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>, who founded the temple on the top of the <hi rend="bold">Tirumalai</hi> Rock and called it after herself. As <hi rend="bold">Tirumalai</hi> is much closer to the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> country, than to the country of the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukyas</hi>, we shall scarcely be wrong in attributing the foundation of the temple rather to the king's aunt, who was a <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> queen, than to his younger sister, who was married to an Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king.</p>						

						<p>According to this and the next inscription, the village at the foot of the <hi rend="bold">Tirumalai</hi> Hill bore the name of <hi rend="bold">Vaigavūr</hi> and belonged to <hi rend="bold">Mugai-nāḍu</hi>, a division of <hi rend="bold">Paṅgaḷanāḍu</hi>, which formed part of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Choḷa-maṇḍalam</hi>.</p>						

						<p>With the text of the subjoined inscription, I have compared four other inscriptions of <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, 1. the inscription No. 68, which is likewise dated in the 12th year; 2. an undated inscription of the <hi rend="bold">Kailāsanātha</hi> Temple at <hi rend="bold">Uttaramallūr</hi> in the Chingleput District, an impression of which I owe to the kindness of Mr. R.Sewell; 3. an inscription of the <hi rend="bold">Bṛihadīśvara</hi> Temple at <hi rend="bold">Tanjore</hi> (15th year); and 4. an inscription of the <hi rend="bold">Chidambaram</hi> Temple (24th year).</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="2025-05-24" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-05-06" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi> tirumaṉṉi vaḷaraviru nilamaṭa<hi rend="grantha">nt</hi>aiyum porccayappāvaiyuñcīrttaṉiccelviyuntaṉ perunteviyarāki Iṉpuṟu<note n="98-1">ōther inscriptions read iṉpuṟa.</note>neṭu tiyal<note n="98-2">An inscription at Uttaramallūr reads tūyar.</note>Ūḻiyuḷ Iṭaitu
<lb n="2" break="no"/>ṟaināṭuntuṭar vaṉavelippaṭar vaṉavāciyuñcuḷḷiccūḻ matiṭkoḷḷippākkaiyunaṇṇaṟkaru muraṇ<note n="98-3">The ra of muraṇ looks almost like ka.</note>maṇṇaikkaṭakkamum poru kaṭal Īḻattaracar tamuṭiyum Āṅka 
<lb n="3" break="no"/>var teviyaroṅkeḻiṉmuṭiyumuṉṉavar pa<unclear>k</unclear>kaltteṉṉavar vaitta cuntaramuṭiyum Intiranāramunteṇṭirai Īḻamaṇṭalamuḻuvatum Eṟi paṭaikkeraḷar
<lb n="4"/>muṟaimaiyiṟcūṭuṅkulataṉamākiya palar pukaḻ muṭiyuñceṅkatir mālaiyuñcaṅkatir velaittol peruṅkāvaṟpala paḻantivuñceruviṟceṉa
<lb n="5" break="no"/>vil<note n="98-4">ā ṭanjore inscription reads ciṉavi for ceṉavil.</note>Irupattoru kālaraicukaḷai kaṭṭa paracurāmaṉ mevaruñcāntimattivavaraṇ karuti Iruttiya cem poṟṟiruttaku muṭiyum payaṅkoṭu paḻi mika mucaṅkiyil mu
<lb n="6" break="no"/>tukiṭṭoḷitta cayaciṅkaṉ<note n="98-5">ci looks like cī.</note>Aḷapperum<note n="98-6">A Tanjore inscription reads aḷapparum.</note>pukaḻoṭum pīṭiyal<note n="98-7">An inscription at Uttaramallūr reads piṭi instead of pīṭiyal.</note>Iraṭṭapāṭi Eḻarai Ilakkamunavanetikkulapperumalaikaḷum vikkiramavīrar cakkarakoṭṭamu
<lb n="7" break="no"/>mutirapaṭavallai maturamaṇṭalamum kāmiṭaivaḷaiyanāmaṇaikkoṇamum veñcilaivīrar pañcappaḷḷiyum pācuṭai<note n="98-8">ōther inscriptions read pācaṭai.</note>ppaḻanaṉmācuṇitecamum Ayarvi
<lb n="8" break="no"/>l vaṇ kirttiyātinakaravaiyiṟcan=tiraṉṟol kulattirataraṉai viḷaiyamarkkaḷattukkiḷaiyoṭum pi<unclear>ṭit</unclear>tuppala taṉattoṭu niṟai kulataṉa<unclear>k</unclear>kuvai
<lb n="9" break="no"/>yuñciṭṭaruñ<note n="98-9">The Uttaramallūr and Tanjore inscriptions read kiṭṭaruñ.</note>ce<unclear>ṟi</unclear> miḷaiyoṭṭa<note n="98-10">A Chidambaram inscription reads puṉaloṭṭa instead of miḷaiyoṭṭa.</note>vi<hi rend="grantha">ṣai</hi>yamum pūcurar cer nalkkocalaināṭu- n=taṉmapālaṉai vem muṉaiyaḻittu vaṇṭuṟai colaittaṇṭayutti<note n="98-11">The Chidambaram and ṭanjore inscriptions read putti.</note>yumiraṇa
<lb n="10" break="no"/>cūraṉai muraṇuṟattākkittikkaṇai kirttittakkaṇalāṭamuṅkovin=tacan=taṉ māviḻi- n=toṭattaṅkāta cāral vaṅkāḷatecamun=toṭu kaṭaṟcaṅkukoṭṭaṉ <hi rend="grantha">mahī</hi>pālaṉai
<lb n="11"/>veñcama<note n="98-12">The inscription No. 68 reads camar for cama.</note>vaḷākattañcuvittaruḷi Oṇṭiṟal yāṉaiyum peṇṭir paṇṭāramunittilaneṭuṅkaṭalutti<unclear>ra</unclear>lāṭamum veṟi<note n="98-13">An Uttaramallūr inscription reads eṟi.</note>maṇaṟṟirttatteṟi puṉaṟkaṅkaiyumā<unclear>p</unclear>
<lb n="12" break="no"/>poru taṇṭāṟkoṇṭa kopparakecaripaṉmarāṉa Uṭaiyār <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājendracoḷade</hi>vaṟku yāṇṭu <num value="12"><g type="numeral">10</g> 2</num> Āvatu [<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>]yaṅkoṇṭacoḻamaṇṭalattu paṅkaḷanāṭṭu naṭuvil
<lb n="13"/>vak<unclear>ai</unclear> mukaināṭṭuppaḷḷiccan=tam vaikavūrttirumalai <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kun=tavai<hi rend="grantha">ji</hi>nālayattu <hi rend="grantha">de</hi>vaṟkupperumpāṇappāṭikkaraivaḻimalliyūr Irukkum <hi rend="grantha">vyā</hi>
<lb n="14" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">pāri</hi> na<hi rend="grantha">nna</hi>ppayaṉ maṇavāṭṭi cāmuṇṭappai vaitta tirunan=tāviḷakku <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> Oṉṟinukkukkācu Irupatum <unclear>tiru</unclear>vamutukku vaitta kācu pattum <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied><note n="98-14">The remainder of the inscription is written in faint and small characters, and seems to be a rough postscript, which was added after the bulk of the inscription had been carefully engraved by a skilled stonemason.</note> 
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1890_01">

<p>Hail! Prosperity! In the 12th year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ko-Parakesarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Uḍaiyār Śrī-Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi>, who,—during his long life (<hi rend="italic">which resembled that of</hi>) pure people, (<hi rend="italic">and in which</hi>) the great goddess of the earth, the goddess of victory in battle, and the beautiful and matchless goddess of fortune, who had become his great queens, gave him pleasure, while (<hi rend="italic">his own</hi>) illustrious queen was prospering,—conquered with (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) great and warlike army <hi rend="bold">Iḍaituṟai-nāḍu; Vaṉavāśi</hi>, the roads (<hi rend="italic">to which are bounded by</hi>) continuous walls of trees; <hi rend="bold">Koḷḷippākkai</hi>, whose walls are surrounded by <hi rend="italic">śuḷḷi (trees</hi>); <hi rend="bold">Maṇṇaikkaḍakkam</hi> of unapproachable strength; the crown of the king of <hi rend="bold">Īṛam</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">which is situated in the midst of</hi>) the rough sea; the exceedingly beautiful crown of the queen of the king of that (<hi rend="italic">country</hi>); the crown of <hi rend="bold">Sundara</hi>, which the king of the South (i.e., <hi rend="italic">the Pāṇḍya</hi>) had formerly given to that (<hi rend="italic">king of</hi> Īṛam); the pearl-necklace of <hi rend="bold">Indra</hi>; the whole <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi> on the transparent sea; the crown praised by many, a family-treasure, which the spearthrowing (<hi rend="italic">king of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Keraḷa</hi> usually wore; the garland of the sun (?); many ancient islands, which are the old and great guards of the shore, against which conches are dashed; the crown of pure gold, worthy of <hi rend="bold">Lakshmī</hi>, which <hi rend="bold">Paraśurāma</hi>, who, out of anger, bound the kings twenty-one times in battle, having thought the fort of the island of <hi rend="bold">Śāndima</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Śāntimat ?</hi>) unapproachable, had deposited (<hi rend="italic">there</hi>); the seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-pāḍi</hi>—through the conquest of which immeasurable fame arose—(<hi rend="italic">of</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi>, who, out of fear and full of revenge, turned his back at <hi rend="bold">Muśaṅgi (?)</hi> and hid himself; the high mountains of <hi rend="bold">Navanedikkula; Śakkara-koṭṭam</hi> (<hi rend="italic">belonging to</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Vīra; Madura-maṇḍalam</hi> with the fort of <hi rend="bold">Mudira-paḍa (?); Nāmaṇaikkoṇam</hi>, which is surrounded by dense groves; <hi rend="bold">Pañchappaḷḷi</hi> (<hi rend="italic">belonging to</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Veñjilai-Vīra</hi><note n="99-1">Literally, “the hero of the cruel bow.” Compare <foreign>veñcilaiccelvaṉ</foreign>, an epithet of <hi rend="bold">Vīrabhadra</hi> as bearing a cruel bow (<hi rend="italic">Winslow</hi>).</note>; the good <hi rend="bold">Māśuṇi-deśa</hi>, where leaves and fruits are green; the large heap of family-treasures, together with many (<hi rend="italic">other</hi>) treasures, (<hi rend="italic">which he carried away</hi>) after having seized <hi rend="bold">Dhīratara</hi> of the old race of the moon, together with his family, in a fight which took place in the hall (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Ādinagar</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">a city</hi>) which is famous for its unceasing abundance; <hi rend="bold">Oḍḍa-vishaya</hi>, whose copious waters are difficult to approach; the good <hi rend="bold">Kośalai-nāḍu</hi>, where <hi rend="italic">Brāhmaṇas</hi> assemble; <hi rend="bold">Daṇḍabutti</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Daṇḍa-bhukti</hi>), in whose gardens bees abound, (<hi rend="italic">and which he acquired</hi>) after having destroyed <hi rend="bold">Dharmapāla</hi> in a hot battle; <hi rend="bold">Takkaṇalāḍam</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Dakshiṇa-Lāṭa</hi>), whose fame reaches (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) directions, (<hi rend="italic">and which he occupied</hi>) after having forcibly attacked <hi rend="bold">Raṇaśūra; Vaṅgāḷa-deśa</hi>, where the rain does not last (<hi rend="italic">long</hi>), and from which <hi rend="bold">Govindachandra</hi>, having lost his fortune, fled; elephants of rare strength, (<hi rend="italic">which he took away</hi>) after having been pleased to frighten in a hot battle <hi rend="bold">Mahīpāla</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Śaṅgu-koṭṭam</hi> (?), which touches the sea; the treasures of women (?); <hi rend="bold">Uttiralāḍam</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Uttara-Lāṭa</hi>) on the great sea of pearls; and the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgā</hi>, whose waters sprinkle <hi rend="italic">tīrthas</hi> on the burning sand:—</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Chāmuṇḍappai</hi>, the wife of the merchant <hi rend="bold">Nannappayaṉ</hi>, who lives at <hi rend="bold">Perumbāṇappāḍi</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">alias</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Karaivaṛi-malliyūr</hi>, gave a <hi rend="italic">tirunandā</hi> lamp to the temple (<hi rend="italic">called</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Srī-Kundavai-Jinālaya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">on</hi>) the holy mountain (<hi rend="italic">Tirumalai) (at</hi>) the <hi rend="italic">paḷḷichchandam</hi><note n="99-2">This term probably means “a village belonging to a temple,” “a holy village;” see p. 91, note 5.</note>of <hi rend="bold">Vaigavūr</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Mugai-nāḍu</hi>, a division in the middle of <hi rend="bold">Paṅgaḷa-nāḍu</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">which forms part</hi>) of <hi rend="bold">Jayaṅkoṇḍa-Śoṛa-maṇḍalam</hi>.</p>

<h4><hi rend="italic">Postscript</hi>.</h4>

<p>Twenty <hi rend="italic">kāśus</hi> were given for one (<hi rend="italic">lamp</hi>) and ten <hi rend="italic">kāśus</hi> for the sacred food.</p>

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 1.67 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">95-99</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">67</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
