<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 1.78: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">PART II. TAMIL AND GRANTHA INSCRIPTIONS. V. INSCRIPTIONS AT PAḌAVEḌU. No. 78. ON THE EAST AND NORTH BASES OF THE AMMAIAPPEŚVARA TEMPLE.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0078</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>This inscription is dated in the year, which was current after the expiration of the Śaka year 1180, and records a grant, which <hi rend="bold">Rājagambhīra-Śambuvarāyaṉ</hi> made to the temple of <hi rend="bold">Ammaiappeśvara</hi>. The name of the object of the grant must be contained in the final portion of the first line, which is buried underground. The donor is evidently identical with that <hi rend="bold">Rājagambhīra-Śambuvarāyaṉ</hi>, who is mentioned in a <hi rend="bold">Tirumalai</hi> inscription (No. 74), which seems to be dated in Śaka 1157-58. It may be further conjectured, that the <hi rend="bold">Ammaiappeśvara</hi> Temple at <hi rend="bold">Paḍaveḍu</hi> had received its name from <hi rend="bold">Ammaiappaṉ</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Ammaiyappaṉ</hi>,<note n="108-2">See the introduction of the Poygai inscriptions, p. 87, above.</note>one of the <hi rend="italic">birudas</hi> of another <hi rend="bold">Śambuvarāyaṉ</hi>, who was a contemporary and probably a relation of <hi rend="bold">Rājagambhīra-Śambuvarāyaṉ</hi>.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-05-24" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-05-06" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> śakābdam</hi> Āyirattoruṉūṟṟueṇpatiṉ meṟcellāniṉṟa kaṟkaṭakanā<unclear>ya</unclear>ṟṟu <hi rend="grantha">pūrvvapakṣa</hi>ttu tiṅkaṭkiḻamaiyum <hi rend="grantha">saptami</hi>yum <hi rend="grantha">re</hi>vatiyumāṉa Iṉṟu Uṭaiyār Ammaiappī<hi rend="grantha">śvara</hi>muṭaiya nāyaṉāṟku Irā<hi rend="grantha">jagambhī</hi>racampuvarāya <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> 
                    <lb n="2"/><unclear>ta</unclear>rattu muḷḷaṭi Ūrkkaṇakkavari Uvaccaṉperkkaṭamai Ācuvikaṉperkkaṭamai taṟiiṟai <unclear>ta</unclear>ṭṭārppāṭṭamum Iṉavari <unclear>Ē</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> yattaṟi Iruntu parimāṟuvārum cekkukkaṭamai <unclear>v</unclear>ālamañcāṭi nilaiyāḷ veṭṭinellu Uṭpaṭ<unclear>ṭa</unclear> Eḷurppala taḷi tevatānam nīkki Innāyaṉārkkuttevatāṉam viṭṭeṉ Irā<hi rend="grantha">jagambhī</hi>raccampu<unclear>va</unclear> <gap reason="lost" quantity="5" unit="character"/> 
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1890_01">
                
                <p>Hail! Prosperity ! To-day, which is (<hi rend="italic">the day of the nakshatra) Revati</hi> and Monday, the seventh lunar day of the former half of the month of <hi rend="italic">Karkaṭaka</hi>, which was current after the Śaka year one thousand one hundred and eighty (<hi rend="italic">had passed</hi>),—I, <hi rend="bold">Rājagambhīra-Śambuvarāya[ṉ]</hi> gave to the god, who is the lord of the <hi rend="bold">Ammaiappeśvara</hi> (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>), as a divine gift • • • • • excluding the divine gifts to the various temples (<hi rend="italic">at</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Eḷūr</hi>, including • • •<note n="108-3">The meaning of <ta>muḷḷaṭi</ta>, which occurs also in line 15 of the Poygai inscription No. 64, is not apparent.</note>the tax for the village-accountant, the tax on <hi rend="bold">Uvachchas</hi>, the tax on <hi rend="bold">Ājīvakas,</hi><note n="108-4">On the <hi rend="bold">Uvachchas</hi>, see page 82, note 4; on the <hi rend="bold">Ājīvakas</hi>, page 88, note 5.</note> the tax on looms, the tax on goldsmiths,. • • • • •<note n="108-5">Of the terms left untranslated, <ta>iṉavari</ta> occurs also in the Poygai inscriptions Nos. 61 and 62.</note>the tax on oil-mills, • • • (<hi rend="italic">and</hi>) the paddy for the <hi rend="italic">Veṭṭi</hi>.<note n="108-6">See page 82, note 3. The <ta>talaiyāri</ta> or watchman and the <ta>veṭṭiyāṉ</ta> or scavenger are mentioned as members of the ancient village-establishment in the <hi rend="italic">Tanjore Manual</hi>, p. 415. They used to get their share of the produce, as well as the accountant, the washerman and the other village-officers; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> pp. 421 f. In the Kanarese country, the corresponding officers were the <hi rend="italic">talāri</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">tōṭi</hi>, who likewise received their share of the crops; see Dr. Buchanan's <hi rend="italic">Journey from Madras through the countries of Mysore, Canara, and Malabar</hi>, Vol. I. pp. 266 ff. Vol. II, p. 109. Vol. III, p. 449.</note></p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 1.78 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">108</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">78</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
