<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 1.66: original edition by Eugen Julius Theodor Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">PART II. TAMIL AND GRANTHA INSCRIPTIONS. IV. INSCRIPTIONS AT TIRUMALAI NEAR POLÛR. No. 66. ON A BURIED ROCK IN FRONT OF THE GOPURA AT THE BASE OF THE TIRUMALAI HILL.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0066</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>This inscription is dated in the 21st year of <hi rend="bold">Ko-Rāja-Rājakesarivarman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>, and again (<hi rend="italic">in words</hi>) in the twenty-first year of <hi rend="bold">Śoṛaṉ Arumoṛi</hi>, the lord of the river <hi rend="bold">Poṉṉi</hi>, i.e., of the <hi rend="bold">Kāverī</hi>. The greater part of the historical portion of this inscription is identical with that of the two <hi rend="bold">Māmallapuram</hi> inscriptions Nos. 40 and 41. <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭa-pāḍi</hi> is, however, omitted from the list of the countries conquered by the king.<note n="94-2">The same is the case in the large Leyden grant (Dr. Burgess' <hi rend="italic">Arch. Survey of S. India</hi>, Vol. IV, p. 210) and in an inscription published by S.M. Naṭeśa Śāstrī (<hi rend="italic">Madras Christian College Magazine</hi>, Vol. V, p. 36), both of which are likewise dated in the twenty-first year.</note> Consequently <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> must have taken possession of <hi rend="bold">Iraṭṭapāḍi</hi> between his twenty-first and his twenty-fifth years, the dates of Nos. 66 and 40 respectively.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The inscription records that a certain <hi rend="bold">Guṇavīramāmunivaṉ</hi> built a sluice, which he called after a <hi rend="bold">Jaina</hi> teacher, whose name was <hi rend="bold">Gaṇiśekhara-Maru-Poṟchūriyaṉ</hi>.<note n="94-3"><hi rend="bold">Gaṇiśekhara</hi> means “the chief of (<hi rend="italic">Jaina</hi>) teachers.” With <hi rend="bold">Maru</hi> compare <hi rend="bold">Marudeva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Nābhi</hi>) and <hi rend="bold">Marudevī</hi>, the names of the parents of the <hi rend="italic">Arhat</hi> <hi rend="bold">Ṛishabha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Śatruṁjaya-māhātmya</hi>, iii, 7; <hi rend="italic">Kalpasūtra</hi>, edited by Jacobi, p. 74, line 2). <hi rend="bold">Poṟchūriyaṉ</hi> means “the golden sun.”</note>The <hi rend="bold">Tirumalai</hi> Rock is mentioned under the name <hi rend="bold">Vaigai-malai</hi>, “the mountain of Vaigai.” In Nos. 69 and 70, it is called <hi rend="bold">Vaigai-Tirumalai</hi>, “the holy mountain of Vaigai.” The name <hi rend="bold">Vaigai</hi> seems to be connected with <hi rend="bold">Vaigavūr</hi>, the name of the village at the base of the rock, which occurs in Nos. 67 and 68.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-05-24" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-05-06" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <p>
                    <lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied></hi> tirumakaḷ polapperu nilaccel
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>viyuntaṉakkeyurimai pūṇṭamai maṉakkoḷakkāntaḷurccālai kalamaṟuttaruḷi veṅkaināṭuṅkaṅkapāṭiyu
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>nuḷampapāṭiyu<note n="95-1">ān ē seems to stand above yu.</note>ntaṭikaipāṭiyuṅkuṭamalaināṭuṅkollamuṅkaliṅkamum Eṇṭicai pukaḻ taraviḻamaṇṭalamum tiṇṭiṟal veṉṟitta
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>ṇṭāṟkoṇṭa<unclear>tte</unclear>ḻil<note n="95-2">The two inscriptions No. 40 and No. 41 read taṉneḻil.</note>vaḷaruḻi Ellāyāṇṭum toḻuteḻa viḷaṅku<note n="95-3">The inscriptions No. 40 and No. 41 read toḻutaka viḷaṅkum.</note> yāṇṭe ceḻiñaraittecu koḷ <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>kovi
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/><hi rend="grantha">rāja</hi>i<hi rend="grantha">rāja</hi>kecaripa<hi rend="grantha">nmarā</hi>[ ṉa <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>] I<hi rend="grantha">rāja</hi>i<hi rend="grantha">rājade</hi>varkku yāṇṭu <num value="21">2 <g type="numeral">10</g> 1</num> Āvatu Alai puriyum puṉaṟpoṉṉi Āṟuṭaiya coḻaṉ
                    <lb n="6"/>Arumoḻikku yāṇṭu Irupattoṉṟāvateṉṟuṅkalai puriyumatinipu<note n="95-4">pu looks like yu.</note>ṇaṉ veṇ kiḻāṉ
                    <lb n="7"/>kaṇic<unclear>c</unclear>ekkaramarupoṟcūriyaṉṟaṉ nāmattāl vāmanilai ni<unclear>ṟṟa</unclear>kuṅ
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>kaliñciṭṭu nīmir vaiykai malaikku nīṭuḻi Iru maruṅum nel viḷaiya
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>kkaṇṭoṉ kulai puriyum paṭai Araicar koṇṭāṭum pātaṉ kuṇaviramāmunivaṉ
                    <lb n="10"/>kuḷir vaiykaikkovey <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1890_01">
                
                <p>Hail! Prosperity! In the 21st year of (<hi rend="italic">the reign of</hi>) the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Ko-Rāja-Rājakesarivarman</hi>,<note n="95-5">Instead of <hi rend="italic">rāja</hi>, this inscription uses the Tamil form <hi rend="italic">irāja</hi>, and consequently, instead of <hi rend="italic">Ko-Rāja</hi>, which is found in the Māmallapuram inscriptions Nos. 40 and 41, the form <hi rend="italic">Ko-v-irāja</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>, who,—while both the goddess of fortune and the great goddess of the earth, who had become his exclusive property, gave him pleasure,—was pleased to build a jewel-like hall at <hi rend="bold">Kāndaḷūr</hi> and conquered by his army, which was victorious in great battles, <hi rend="bold">Veṅgai-nāḍu, Gaṅga-pāḍi, Nuḷamba-pāḍi, Taḍigai-pāḍi, Kuḍamalai-nāḍu, Kollam, Kaliṅgam</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Īṛa-maṇḍalam</hi>, which is famed in the eight directions; who,—while his beauty was increasing, and while he was resplendent (<hi rend="italic">to such an extent</hi>) that he was always worthy to be worshipped,—deprived the <hi rend="bold">Śeṛiyas</hi> of their splendour,—and (<hi rend="italic">in words</hi>) in the twenty-first year of <hi rend="bold">Śoṛaṉ Arumoṛi</hi>, who possesses the river <hi rend="bold">Poṉṉi</hi>, whose waters are full of waves,—<hi rend="bold">Guṇavīramāmunivaṉ</hi>, whose feet are worshipped by kings of destructive armies, the lord (<hi rend="italic">? ko</hi>) of the cool <hi rend="bold">Vaigai</hi>,—having given a sluice,<note n="95-6"><ta>kaliñcu</ta> must be a corruption of <ta>kaliṅku</ta> which occurs in two other Tirumalai inscriptions (Nos. 69 and 77).</note>which is worthy of being preserved in a good state (<hi rend="italic">and which is called</hi>) by the name of <hi rend="bold">Gaṇiśekhara-Maru-Poṟchūriyaṉ</hi>, the pure master, who is skilled in the elegant arts and very clever,—saw the paddy grow for a long time on both sides of the high mountain of <hi rend="bold">Vaigai</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Vaigai-malai)</hi>.<note n="95-7">This seems to mean nothing but that he lived to an old age.</note></p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 1.66 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">94-95</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">66</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
