<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 1.39: original edition by Eugen Hultzsch</title>
                <title type="alt">PART I. SANSKRIT INSCRIPTIONS. II. COPPER-PLATE GRANTS OF THE EASTERN CHALUKYA DYNASTY. No. 39. A GRANT OF VĪRA-CHOḌA.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0039</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>The original of the subjoined grant belongs to the Sir W. Elliot Collection in the British Museum and was lent to me for publication by Dr. Burgess. It had been previously in the possession of the <hi rend="italic">karaṇam</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Chellūr</hi>, a village in the Cocanada: Tālluqa of the Godāvarī District: The grant consists of five copper-plates with raised rims. Each plate measures 5 3/4 by 10 1/4 inches. The first plate bears writing only on its inner side, while the remaining ones are inscribed on both sides. The preservation of the plates is fairly good; the fifth only is somewhat damaged. The ring, which bears the seal, has been cut. It is 5/8 inch thick and 6 1/4 inches in diameter. The well-preserved seal measures 2 5/8 inches in diameter. It rests on an expanded lotus-flower and bears in relief on a counter-sunk surface the legend <foreign>śrītribhuvanāṁkuśa</foreign>. Over the latter, it contains a boar, which faces the right and is surrounded by two lamp stands, two <hi rend="italic">chāmaras</hi>, the sun and the moon, an elephant-goad and a conch. Below the legend, there is a drum (?), an expanded lotus-flower (<hi rend="italic">bird's-eye view</hi>), an emblem resembling what Mr. Fleet supposes to be a <hi rend="italic">makara-toraṇa,</hi><note><hi rend="italic">Indian Antiquary</hi>, Vol. XIV, p. 49. Compare line 24 of the present grant.</note> and a <hi rend="italic">svastika</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>Abstracts of the present inscription have already been published by Sir W. Elliot.<note><hi rend="italic">Coins of Southern India</hi>, pp. 88 and 150; <hi rend="italic">Indian Antiquary</hi>, Vol. XIV, p. 203.</note> It is the latest known document of the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> a dynasty and possesses considerable interest, as it contains valuable details about the connection between the Eastern Chalukyas and the <hi rend="bold">Choḷas</hi> and thus settles the dates of several kings of the last-mentioned dynasty.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The <hi rend="italic">vaṁśāvali</hi> of the inscription consists of four parts:—</p>						
                            
                            <p>I. (<hi rend="italic">Lines</hi> 1-16.) A genealogy of the lunar race down to <hi rend="bold">Udayana</hi>, commencing with whom fifty-nine emperors are supposed to have reigned at <hi rend="bold">Ayodhyā</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>II. (<hi rend="italic">Lines</hi> 16-28.) An account of five Early <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> kings, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>:—</p>						
                            
                            <p>[[genealogical table]] Vijayāditya I., killed in a battle with Trilochana-Pallava. Vishṇuvardhana, married to a Pallava princess. Vijayāditya II. Pulakeśi-Vallabha. Kīrtivarman.</p>						
                            
                            <p>III. (<hi rend="italic">Lines</hi> 28-46.) The usual succession of the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukyas</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> from <hi rend="bold">Kubja-Vishṇuvardhana</hi> to <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>IV. (<hi rend="italic">Lines</hi> 46-78.) An account of the later Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukyas</hi> during their connection with the <hi rend="bold">Choḷas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>:—</p>						
                            
                            <p>[[genealogical table]] [C1]Vimalāditya. [C1]Rājarāja I. [C2]Vijayāditya. [C1]Rājendra-Choḍa, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Kulottuṅga-deva or Rājanārāyaṇa. [C1]<hi rend="italic">Two sons</hi>, of whom one was Rājarāja II. [C2]Vīra-Choḍa, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Vishṇuvardhana. [C3]<hi rend="italic">Four other sons</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The first and second parts of the <hi rend="italic">vaṁśāvali</hi> need not be treated in detail, as the first is entirely mythical, and Mr. Fleet considers the second to be “a mere <hi rend="italic">farrago</hi> of vague tradition and Purāṇik myths, of no authority, based on the undoubted facts that the Chalukyas did come originally from the north, and did find the Pallavas in possession of some of the territories afterwards acquired by themselves, and on a tradition of the later Kādambas that the founder of their family was named Trilochana or Trinetra.”<note><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. VII, p. 246; <hi rend="italic">Kanarese Dynasties</hi>, p. 19; <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 49.</note></p>						
                            
                            <p>The third part of the <hi rend="italic">vaṁśāvali</hi> agrees with Mr. Fleet's grants of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I. and of <hi rend="bold">Kulottuṅga-Choḍa-deva</hi> II.<note><hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, pp. 48 and 55.</note> Just as in the grant of Rājarāja I. a reign of 3 years is allotted to <hi rend="bold">Dānārṇava</hi>, who is here also called <hi rend="bold">Dāna-nṛipa</hi>, and an interregnum of 27 years is stated to have taken place after him. There follow the reigns of his sons <hi rend="bold">Śaktivarman</hi> (12 <hi rend="italic">years</hi>) and <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi> (7 <hi rend="italic">years</hi>). No mention is made of the Choḷa princess <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi>, whom the latter married according to the grant of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I.</p>						
                            
                            <p>We now turn to the fourth part of the <hi rend="italic">vaṁśāvali</hi>. The son of Vimalāditya, <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, who ruled for 41 years (<hi rend="italic">line</hi> 47), married <hi rend="bold">Ammaṅga-devī</hi>, the daughter of a <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> of the solar race (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 7). Their son <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 8), <hi rend="bold">Kulottuṅga-deva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 11) or <hi rend="bold">Rājanārāyaṇa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 12) at first ascended the throne of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 9), conquered <hi rend="bold">Kerala, Pāṇḍya, Kuṇtala</hi> and other countries (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 10), and was anointed to the <hi rend="bold">Choḍa</hi> kingdom (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 11). He married <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntakī</hi>, the daughter of a <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi> of the solar race (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 12) and had by her seven sons (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 13). When he rose to the <hi rend="bold">Choḍa</hi> kingdom, he had given the kingdom of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> to his paternal uncle <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 14), who died after a reign of fifteen years (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 15). Then he gave <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> to his son <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verses</hi> 13 <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 16) and, when the latter had returned after one year's reign (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 17), to Rājarāja's younger brother <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 18), who was crowned at <hi rend="bold">Jaganātha-nagarī</hi><note>Jaganātha is a Prākṛit form of Jagannātha. Jaganātha-nagarī may be identified with Jagannāthapuram, which is, according to Mr. R. Sewell, “the portion of the town of Cocanada lying south of the river.” See <hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. I, p. 24.</note> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 20) in <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 1001 (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 21). As the difference between this date and <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 944, the date of the accession of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I. according to Mr. Fleet's grant, is equal to the sum of the intervening reigns of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I., <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya</hi> VI. and <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> II. (41+15+1=57), it follows that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> must have appointed <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya</hi> VI. viceroy of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> in the very year of his accession. The present grant of <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa</hi> is dated in the 21st year of his reign, i.e., <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 1022, or 12 years before the death of his father <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> and before the accession of his elder brother <hi rend="bold">Vikrama-Choḍa</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The chief importance of the <hi rend="bold">Chellūr</hi> plates consists in the light, which they throw on a portion of the history of the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> dynasty. The large Leyden grant and some of the Tamil inscriptions contained in the present volume mention three Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> kings, who were the antagonists of three <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> kings:—</p>						
                            
                            <p>1. According to the large Leyden grant, <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> (see Nos. 40, 41 and 66, below) conquered <hi rend="bold">Satyāśraya</hi>. This was probably the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Satyāśraya</hi> II. (<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 919 to about 930.) Consequently, <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi> may be identified with that <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, whose daughter <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi> was married to the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 937 (?) to 944). With this agrees the <hi rend="bold">Koṅgu</hi> Chronicle, which places <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja's</hi> reign about <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 926.</p>						
                            
                            <p>2. According to Nos. 67 and 68, below, <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi> conquered <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi>. This was the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> III. (about <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 940 to about 964), who, in one of his inscriptions, calls himself “the lion to the elephant <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi>” (see the introduction to No. <ref target="DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0067">37</ref>). Consequently, <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi> must be identified with that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, whose daughter <hi rend="bold">Ammaṅga-devī</hi> was married to the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I. (<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 944 to 985), and who may be the same as that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi>, whose younger sister <hi rend="bold">Kūndavā</hi> was married to <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 937 (?) to 944). If the last identification is correct, <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi> would have been the son of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-deva</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>3. According to the fragmentary inscription No. <ref target="DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0127">127</ref>, below, and according to an inscription at <hi rend="bold">Māmallapuram, Rājendra-deva</hi> conquered <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla</hi>. This was probably the Western <hi rend="bold">Chālukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Āhavamalla</hi> II. or <hi rend="bold">Someśvara</hi> I. (about <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 964 to about 990), who, according to inscriptions and according to the <hi rend="italic">Vikramāṅkacharita</hi>, fought with the <hi rend="bold">Choḷas</hi>. Consequently, <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi> may be identified with that <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>, whose daughter <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntakī</hi> was married to the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Kulottuṅga-Choḍa-deva</hi> I. (<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 985 to 1034.) The inscriptions do not inform us, in what manner <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi> was related to his predecessor <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa-deva</hi>.</p>						
                            
                            <p>The subjoined table will show at a glance all supposed synchronisms:—</p>						
                            
                            <p>[[genealogical table]] [C1]Western Chālukyas. [C2]Choḷas (<hi rend="italic">Sūryavaṁśa</hi>). [C3]Eastern Chalukyas (<hi rend="italic">Somavaṁśa</hi>). 1. Satyāśraya II. <hi rend="italic">fought with</hi> Rājarāja-deva, <hi rend="italic">who was the father-in-law of</hi> Vimalāditya [C1](<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 919 <hi rend="italic">to about</hi> 930.) [C2](<hi rend="italic">about Śaka</hi> 926.) [C3](<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 937 (?) <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 944). 2. Jayasiṁha III. <hi rend="italic">fought with</hi> Rājendra-Choḷa-deva, <hi rend="italic">who was the father-in-law of</hi> Rājarāja I. [C1](<hi rend="italic">about Śaka</hi> 940 <hi rend="italic">to about</hi> 964.) [C2](<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 944 <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 985.) 3. Āhavamalla II. <hi rend="italic">fought with</hi> Rājendra-deva, <hi rend="italic">who was the father-in-law of</hi> Rājendra-Choḍa <hi rend="italic">or</hi> (<hi rend="italic">about Śaka</hi> 964 <hi rend="italic">to about</hi> 990.) [C2]Kulottuṅga-Choḍa-deva I. (<hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 985 <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 1034.)</p>						
                            
                            <p>In order to prevent its re-occurrence, I conclude with alluding to the in all previous pedigrees of the <hi rend="bold">Choḷas</hi>. This was the confounding of the two <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> kings <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḷa</hi> with their Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> grandsons, who seem to have received their names from those of their maternal grandfathers. In reality the Eastern <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi> I. ruled only over <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>. His son <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Kulottuṅga-Choḍa-deva</hi> I., though at first king of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>, seems to have inherited the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> kingdom from his father-in-law, the <hi rend="bold">Choḷa</hi> king <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Śaka</hi> 985.</p>						
                            
                            <p>After the <hi rend="italic">vaṁśāvali</hi>, the subjoined inscription contains the grant itself. It is an order, which was addressed by the <hi rend="italic">paramamāheśvara</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa-deva</hi> (<hi rend="italic">line</hi> 79), <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi> (<hi rend="italic">line</hi> 78) to the inhabitants of the <hi rend="bold">Guddavāṭi-vishaya</hi><note>This is the same as Guddavādi-vishaya, <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 53. Perhaps both are identical with the Gudravāra-, Gudrāvāra- or Gudrahāra-vishaya (see page 47, note 1) and connected with the modern Guḍivāḍa, the head-quarters of a tālluqa of the Kistna District.</note> (<hi rend="italic">line</hi> 80). In the 21st year of his reign (<hi rend="italic">line</hi> 113) the king gave a village of the above-mentioned district, whose name is indistinct, but seems to have been <hi rend="bold">Kolāṟu</hi><note>Sir W. Elliot read it <hi rend="italic">Kaleru</hi>. The name of the village may have something to do with the Kolār or Kolleru Lake (<hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 204; Sewell's <hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. I, p. 52) in the Guḍivāḍa Tālluqa.</note> (<hi rend="italic">line</hi> 103), to a temple of <hi rend="bold">Vishṇu</hi> at the <hi rend="italic">agrahāra</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Chellūru</hi>.<note>This is the modern village of Chellūr, whence Sir W. Elliot obtained the plates.</note> This Vishṇu temple had been founded (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 36) by the king's <hi rend="italic">senāpati</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 30) <hi rend="bold">Meḍamārya</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 27), <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Guṇaratnabhūshaṇa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 29), who had also constructed a pond at the same village of Chellūru (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 34) and founded two <hi rend="italic">sattras</hi> at <hi rend="bold">Drākshārāma</hi><note>“This is one of the most sacred places in the (Godāvarī) District, with a large and important temple dedicated to Bhīmeśvara;” Sewell's <hi rend="italic">Lists of Antiquities</hi>, Vol. I, p. 25.</note> and <hi rend="bold">Pīṭhapurī</hi><note>This is probably the modern Piṭṭāpuram, the residence of the Rājā of this name in the Godāvarī District.</note> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 33). He was the son of <hi rend="bold">Potana</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Mudgalagotra</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 24), who had received from <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi><note>By this, Rājarāja I., the son of Vimalāditya, seems to be meant.</note> the somewhat lengthy title of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-brahma-mahārāja</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 25), by <hi rend="bold">Kannamāmbā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">verse</hi> 26). The edict ends with the statement, that its executors (<hi rend="italic">ājñapti</hi>) were the five ministers (<hi rend="italic">pañcha pradhānāḥ</hi>), and with the names of the composer and the writer.</p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-05-25" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-05-06" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:undetermined maturity:undetermined">
                
                <!--compare with new edition by daba, as some OCR might be wrong here-->
                <!--check seg rendition="class:telugu"-->
                
                <!-- C· checked-->
                <!--check initial vowels and wordsplit-->
                
                <pb n="1r"/>
                
                <p>
                    <pb n="1v"/>
                    <lb n="1"/>śrīdhāmnaḥ puruṣottamasya mahato nārāyaṇasya prabhornnābhīpaṁkaruhāt· babhūva
                    <lb n="2"/>jagata<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> sraṣṭā svaya<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied>bhūstata<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    jajñe mānasa<surplus><g type="danda">.</g></surplus>sūnuratririti yastasmānmuneratritassomo vaṁśaka
                    <lb n="3" break="no"/>rasmudhāṁśurudita<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrīkaṇṭhacūḍāmaṇiḥ <supplied reason="omitted"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">1</supplied> tasmādabhūtsudhāsūterbbudho budhanutastataḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> jātaḥ purū
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>ravā nāma cakravarttī savikramaḥ <g type="ddanda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">2</supplied> tasmādāyustato nahuṣaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> tato yayātiścakravarttī vaṁśakarttā <unclear><g type="danda">.</g></unclear> ta
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>taḥ puruḥ tato janamejayaḥ tataḥ prācīśaḥ tatass<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>nyayātiḥ tato hayapatiḥ tatassārvvabhauma<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> ta
                    <lb n="6" break="no"/>to jayasenaḥ tato mahābhaumaḥ tasmādaiśānakaḥ tataḥ krodhānanaḥ tato devakiḥ tasmādṛbhu
                    <lb n="7" break="no"/>kaḥ tasmādṛkṣakaḥ tato mativarassatrayāgayājī sarasvatīnadīnāthaḥ tataḥ kātyā
                    <lb n="8" break="no"/>yanaḥ tato nīlaḥ tato duṣyaṁtaḥ tatsutaḥ <surplus><g type="danda">.</g></surplus> gaṁgāyamun<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>tīray<choice><sic>ad</sic><corr>or</corr></choice>avicchinnānnidhāya yū
                    <lb n="9" break="no"/>pān· kramaśaḥ kṛtvā tathāśvamedhannāma mahākarmma bharata Iti yolabhata <g type="danda">.</g> tato bharatādbhvama
                    <lb n="10" break="no"/>nyuḥ <g type="danda">.</g> tato hastī tato virocanaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> tasmādajam<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice><choice><sic>l</sic><corr>ḷ</corr></choice>a<supplied reason="omitted">ha</supplied>ḥ tatassaṁvaraṇaḥ tatassudhanvā <unclear><g type="danda">.</g></unclear> tataḥ parikṣi
                    <lb n="11" break="no"/>t· tato bhīmas<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>nastataḥ pradīpanaḥ tataśśaṁtanuḥ tato vicitravīryya<unclear>ḥ</unclear> tataḥ pāṇḍurājaḥ ta
                    <lb n="12" break="no"/>taḥ pāṇḍavāḥ <g type="danda">.</g> yenādāhi vijitya <choice><sic>k</sic><corr>kh</corr></choice>āṇḍavamaṭho gāṇḍīvinā vajriṇaṁ yuddhe pāśupatāstrama
                    <lb n="13" break="no"/><unclear>ndha</unclear>karipoścālābhi daityān· bahūn· <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Iṁdrārddhāsanamadhyarohi jayinā yat· kālikeyādi
                    
                    <pb n="2r" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="14" break="no"/>kān· hatvā sv<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>ramakāri vaṁśavipina<choice><sic>ś</sic><corr>c</corr></choice>chedaḥ kurūṇāṁ vibhoḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">3</supplied> tatorjjunādabhimanyuḥ tataḥ parikṣit
                    <lb n="15"/>tato<surplus>ḥ</surplus> janamejayaḥ tataḥ kṣemukaḥ tato naravāhanaḥ tataśśatānīkaḥ tasmādudayanaḥ tataḥprabhṛ
                    <lb n="16" break="no"/>tiṣvavicchinnasaṁtān<choice><sic>ap</sic><corr>eṣ</corr></choice>vayodhyāsiṁhāsanāsīneṣvekānnaṣaṣṭicakravarttiṣu gateṣu tadvaṁśyo vija
                    <lb n="17" break="no"/>yādityo nāma rājā <unclear><g type="danda">.</g></unclear> vijigīṣayā dakṣiṇāpatha<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> gatvā trilocanapallavamadhikṣipya daivadurīhayā
                    <lb n="18"/>lokāṁtaramagamat· <g type="danda">.</g> tasmin· saṁkule purohitena vṛddhāmātyaiśca sārddhamaṁtarvvatī tasya mahādevī
                    <lb n="19"/>muḍivemunāmāgrahāramupagamya tadvāstavyena viṣṇubhaṭṭasomayājinā mahāmuni
                    <lb n="20" break="no"/>prabhāve<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>ṇ</corr></choice>a duhitṛnirvviśeṣamabhirakṣitā satī viṣṇuvarddhanannaṁdanamasūta <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> sā ta
                    <lb n="21" break="no"/>sya kumārakasya mānavyasagotrahār<choice><sic>ī</sic><corr>i</corr></choice>t<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>putradvi<surplus>ṁ</surplus>pakṣagotrakramocitāni karmmā
                    <lb n="22" break="no"/>ṇi kārayitvā tamavarddhayat· <g type="danda">.</g> sa ca mātrā viditavṛttāṁtassannirggatya calukyagirau na<choice><sic>ṁ</sic><corr>n</corr></choice>dā<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> bha
                    <lb n="23" break="no"/>gavatīṁ gaurīmārādhya kumāranārāyaṇamātṛgaṇāṁśca saṁtarppya śvetātapatraikaśaṁkhapaṁca
                    <lb n="24" break="no"/>mahāśabdapāliketanaprati<choice><sic>ḍ</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>akk<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>varāhalāṁcchanapi<surplus>ṁ</surplus>cchakuṁtasiṁhāsanamakaratoraṇakanakadaṇḍagaṁ
                    <lb n="25" break="no"/>gāyamunādīni sva<choice><sic>r</sic><corr>k</corr></choice>ulakramāgatāni nikṣiptānīva sāmrājyacihrāni samādāya kaḍaṁbagaṁgādibhū
                    <lb n="26" break="no"/>mipānnirjjitya s<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>tunarmmadāmadhyaṁ sārddhasaptalakṣaṁ dakṣiṇāpathaṁ pālayāmāsa <g type="danda">.</g> tasyāsīdvija
                    
                    <pb n="2v" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="27" break="no"/>yādityo viṣṇuvarddhanabhūpateḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> pallavānvayajātāyā mahādevyāśca naṁdana<unclear>ḥ</unclear> <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">4</supplied> tatsutaḥ
                    <lb n="28"/>pulakeśivallabha<choice><sic>m·</sic><corr>ḥ</corr></choice> tatputraḥ kīrttivarmmā tasya tanayeḥ svasti śrīmatāṁ sakalabhuvanasaṁ
                    <lb n="29" break="no"/>stūyamānamānavyasagotrāṇāṁ hārītiputrāṇāṁ kau<unclear>śikī</unclear>varaprasādalabdharājyānā<unclear>mmā</unclear>
                    <lb n="30" break="no"/>tṛgaṇaparipālitānāṁ svāmimahāsenapādānudhyātānāṁ bhagavannārāyaṇaprasādasamā
                    <lb n="31" break="no"/>sāditavaravarāhalā<choice><sic>c</sic><corr>ñ</corr></choice>chane kṣaṇakṣaṇavaś<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>kṛtārātimaṇḍalānāmaśvamedhāvabhṛthasnānapa
                    <lb n="32" break="no"/>vitrīkṛtavapuṣāṁ cālukyānāṁ kulamalaṁkariṣṇossatyāśrayavallabheṁdrasya bhrā
                    <lb n="33" break="no"/>tā kubjaviṣṇuvarddhanoṣṭādaśa varṣāṇi v<choice><sic>aṁ</sic><corr>eṅ</corr></choice>gīdeśamapālayat tadātmajo jayasi<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied>
                    <lb n="34" break="no"/>havallabhastrayastriṁśatam· <g type="danda">.</g> tadanuja I<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>drarājassapta dināni <g type="danda">.</g> tatsuto viṣṇuvarddhano nava va
                    <lb n="35" break="no"/>rṣāṇi <g type="danda">.</g> tatsūnurmmagiyuvarājaḥ paṁcaviṁśatim tatputro jayasiṁhastrayodaśa tadavarajaḥ
                    <lb n="36"/>kokkiliṣṣaṇmāsān· tasya jyeṣṭho bhrātā viṣṇuvarddhanastamuccāṭya saptatriṁśatam tatputro vija
                    <lb n="37" break="no"/>yādityabhaṭṭārakoṣṭādaśa <g type="danda">.</g> tattanujo viṣṇuvarddhana<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> ṣaṭ·triṁśatam· tatsuto nareṁdramṛgarājoṣṭā
                    <lb n="38" break="no"/>catvāriṁśataṁ tatsutaḥ kaliviṣṇuvarddhanoddhyarddhavarṣa tatsuto guṇagāṁkavijayādityaścatuśca
                    <lb n="39" break="no"/>tvāriṁśatam tadbhrāturvvikramādityasya tanayaścālukyabhīmastriṁśatam <g type="danda">.</g> tatsutaḥ kollabhigaṇḍa                
                    
                    <pb n="3r" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="40" break="no"/>vijayādityaṣṣaṇmāsān· <g type="danda">.</g> tatsutommarājassapta varṣāṇi <g type="danda">.</g> tatsutaṁ vijayādityaṁ bālamu
                    <lb n="41" break="no"/>ccāṭya tāḍap<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>o</corr></choice> māsamekam· <g type="danda">.</g> taṁ jitvā cālukyabhīmasuto vikramāditya Ekādaśa māsān·
                    <lb n="42"/>tattāḍaparājasuto yuddhamallassapta varṣāṇi <g type="danda">.</g> tamuccāṭya deśādammarājānujo rājabhī
                    <lb n="43" break="no"/>maḥ dvādaśa varṣāṇi tat·sūnurammarājaḥ paṁcaviṁśatiṁ <g type="danda">.</g> tasya dv<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>māturo dānanṛpastrīṇi va
                    <lb n="44" break="no"/>rṣāṇi taṁta<choice><sic>ss</sic><corr>ḥ s</corr></choice>aptaviṁśativarṣāṇi daivadurīhayā veṁgīmahiranāyikābhavat· <g type="danda">.</g> tato dān<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>rṇṇavasu
                    <lb n="45" break="no"/>t<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>śśaktivarmmabhūpatirdvādaśa varṣāṇi samarakṣadur<surplus>v</surplus>v<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>īm·</corr></choice> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> tatastadanujassapta vatsarān bhūtavatsalaḥ <g type="danda">.</g>
                    <lb n="46"/>vimalādityabhūpālaḥ pālayāmāsa med<choice><sic>ī</sic><corr>i</corr></choice>nīm· <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">5</supplied> tattanayo nayaśālī jayalakṣmīdhā
                    <lb n="47" break="no"/>ma rājarājanare<supplied reason="omitted">n</supplied>draścatvāriṁśatamabdānekaṁ ca punarmmahīmapālayadakhilāṁ <g type="danda">.</g> yo
                    <lb n="48"/>rūp<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>u</corr></choice>ṇa ma<surplus>bha</surplus>nobhavaṁ viśadayā kāṁtyā kalānānnidhiṁ bhogenāpi puraṁdaraṁ vipulayā lakṣmyā
                    <lb n="49"/>ca lakṣmīdharaṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> bhīmaṁ bhīmaparākrameṇa vihasan bhāti sma bhāsvadyaśā<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> śrīmat·somakul<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>ka
                    <lb n="50" break="no"/>bhūṣaṇamaṇirddīnaikaciṁtāmaṇiḥ <supplied reason="omitted"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">6</supplied> tasyāsīdapakalmaṣā sucaritairammaṁganāmrā bhuvi pra
                    <lb n="51" break="no"/>khyātā śubhalakṣaṇaikavasatirddevī jagatpāvanī <g type="danda">.</g> yā jahroriva jāhravī himavato gaurīva la
                    <lb n="52" break="no"/>kṣmīriva kṣīrodāddivaseśavaṁśatilakādrājeṁdracoḍādabhūt· <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">7</supplied> putrastayorabhavadapratighā
                    
                    <pb n="3v" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="53" break="no"/>taśaktiniśśeṣitārinivaho mahanīyakīrttiḥ <g type="danda">.</g> gaṁgādharādrisutayoriva kārttikeyo rājeṁdra
                    <lb n="54" break="no"/>coḍa Iti rājakulapradīpaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">8</supplied> bhāsāmunnatihetuṁ pra<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>th</corr></choice>amaṁ veṁgīśvaratvamadhyāsya <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yastejasā
                    <lb n="55"/>digaṁtānākramadudayaṁ sahasraraśmiriva <g type="ddanda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">9</supplied> Udyañcaṇḍatarapratāpadahanapluṣṭākhiladve
                    <lb n="56" break="no"/>ṣiṇā sarvvān· keralapāṇḍyakuṁtalamukhān· nirjjitya deśān· kramāt· <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ājñā mauliṣu bhūbhṛtāṁ
                    <lb n="57"/>bhayarujā citteṣu durmmedhasāṁ kīr<surplus>t</surplus>ti<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>dikṣu sudhāṁśudhāmadhavalā yenārppitojjṛṁbhate <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">10</supplied> bho
                    <lb n="58" break="no"/>gīśābhīlabh<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>o</corr></choice>gapratibhayabhujanir<surplus>b</surplus>bha<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>tsanātyaṁtabibhyannānābhūpālalokaprahi
                    <lb n="59" break="no"/>tabahuvidhānargdhyaratnābhirāmam· <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> dhatte mauliṁ parārddhyo mahati nṛpakule yaḥ kulo
                    <lb n="60" break="no"/>ttuṁgadevo deveṁdratvādanūne surapatimahimā coḍarājyebhiṣiktaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">11</supplied> hastabhrājitaśaṁ
                    <lb n="61" break="no"/>khacakrajalajaṁ yaṁ rājanārāyaṇaṁ loka stauti sa sūryyavaṁśatilakādrājeṁdradevārṇṇavā
                    <lb n="62" break="no"/>t· <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> saṁbhūtāmmadhurāṁtakīti viditānnāmrāpa<choice><sic>g</sic><corr>r</corr></choice>eṇa svayaṁ lakṣmīmudvahati sma lokamahītā<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied>
                    <lb n="63"/>devīṁ caritronnatām· <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">12</supplied> gāṁgaughā Iva nirmmalāḥ kṛtatamodhvaṁsā dineśā Iva kṣoṇīdhrā Iva
                    <lb n="64"/>bhūbharaśr<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>masahā jātāstayostūnavaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> tanmadhye nayavikramaikanilaya<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> śrīrājarājaṁ
                    <lb n="65"/>prati prem<choice><sic>n</sic><corr>ṇ</corr></choice>ā vācamimāmavocata pitā sarvvorvvarādhīśva<unclear>ra</unclear>ḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">13</supplied> mayā veṁgīmahīrā
                    
                    <pb n="4r" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="66" break="no"/>jyaṁ coḍarājyābhilāṣiṇā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> matpitṛvye purā nyastaṁ vijayādityabhūbhuji <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">14</supplied> sa ca paca
                    <lb n="67" break="no"/>daśābdāni paṁcānanaparākramaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mahīṁ rakṣanmahīnātho divaṁ devopamo gataḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">15</supplied> Ityuktvā tā
                    <lb n="68" break="no"/>ndhuraṁ dattāṁ guruṇā cakravarttinā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Aniṣṭatadviyogopi vin<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>to vahati sma saḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">16</supplied> śrīpādasevāsu
                    <lb n="69" break="no"/>khato gurūṇānna jātu rājyaṁ sukhamityavekṣya <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> saṁrakṣya veṁgībhuvamekamabdam bhūyassa pitro
                    <lb n="70" break="no"/>ragamatsamīpam· <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">17</supplied> tadanujama<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>th</corr></choice>adhīraṁ vīracoḍaṁ kumāraṁ guṇamiva tanubaddhaṁ vikramaṁ cakra
                    <lb n="71" break="no"/>varttī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Udayamiva ravistvaṁ prāpya ve<choice><sic>ṁ</sic><corr>ṅ</corr></choice>gīśva<choice><sic>t</sic><corr>r</corr></choice>atvaṁ vitanu śirasi pādaṁ bhūbhṛtāmityavo
                    <lb n="72" break="no"/>cat· <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">18</supplied> Ityāśiṣaṁ samadhigamya nṛpādava<choice><sic>va</sic><corr>n</corr></choice>dhyā<choice><sic>m·</sic><corr>ṁ</corr></choice> devyāsta<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>th</corr></choice>āgrajanṛpadvitayāt·
                    <lb n="73"/>krameṇa <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ānamya tānavanatovarajaiḥ kumāra<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> sṛṣṭa<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> svadeśagamanāya sa taiḥ kathaṁcit· <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">19</supplied> śatrudhvāṁ
                    <lb n="74" break="no"/>tamapāsya rājanikarānācchādya dhāmrāparān durvvṛttānvinivartya bhūka<choice><sic>ro</sic><corr>ma</corr></choice>linīṁ kṛtvā ta<choice><sic>d</sic><corr>t</corr></choice>hā naṁdinī<supplied reason="omitted">m·</supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Ā
                    <lb n="75" break="no"/>rūḍho ja<choice><sic><unclear>bha</unclear></sic><corr>ga</corr></choice>nāthanāmanagarīharmmyodayādriṁ vibhurvvegībhūtalabhūṣaṇaṁ nṛpasuto bālārkka
                    <lb n="76" break="no"/>biṁbadyutiḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">20</supplied> śākābde śaśikhadva<unclear>yeṁ</unclear>dugaṇite siṁhādhirū<choice><sic>ḍ</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>e ravau caṁdre vṛddhimati trayodaśati
                    <lb n="77" break="no"/><choice><sic>d</sic><corr>t</corr></choice>hau vāre gurorvvṛścike <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> lagretha śravaṇe samastajagatīrājyābhiṣi<unclear>kto mudā</unclear> lokasyodva
                    <lb n="78" break="no"/>hati sma paṭṭamanagha<unclear>ḥ</unclear> śrīvīracoḍo nṛpaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">21</supplied> sa sarvvalokā<unclear>śrayaśrī</unclear>viṣṇuvarddhanamahārā
                    
                    <pb n="4v" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="79" break="no"/>jādhirājo rājaparameśvaraḥ paramamāheśvaraparamabhaṭṭārakaḥ paramabra<unclear>hmaṇyaśrīvīra</unclear>coḍadevaḥ gudda
                    <lb n="80" break="no"/>vāṭiviṣayanivāsino rāṣṭrakūṭapramukhān· kuṭuṁbinassarvvān· samāhūya <unclear>maṁ</unclear>tripurohitasenāpa
                    <lb n="81" break="no"/>tiyuvarājadauvārikasamakṣamitthamājñāpayati <g type="danda">.</g> ya<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>ṁy</corr></choice>ā <g type="danda">.</g> pāvane brahmavaṁśebhūtparamā<seg rend="check">l</seg>ādada<supplied reason="omitted">rś</supplied>anaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    <lb n="82"/>munīṁdro mudgalo nāma kṣīroda Iva caṁdramāḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">22</supplied> yenāta<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>kyānubhāvena samāhūte divākare <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yasya ya
                    <lb n="83" break="no"/>ṣṭissamādiṣṭā raviceṣṭāmaceṣṭata <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">23</supplied> Āsītpavitracāritrastadnotre gotravarddhanaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> diśo nijayaśodhāmnā dyo
                    <lb n="84" break="no"/>tayan potanāhvayaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">24</supplied> guṇādhiko guṇajñena rājarājādhipena yaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> rājarājabrahmamahārājanāmrā
                    <lb n="85"/>stuto mudā <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">25</supplied> tasya puṇyanidheḥ patnī kannamāṁbā jagannutā <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> Atrerivānasūyāsīdanasūy<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>
                    <lb n="86" break="no"/>guṇonnatā <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">26</supplied> sutamiva vasudevāddevakī vāsudevaṁ guhamiva girikanyā naṁdanaṁ caṁdramauleḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    <lb n="87"/>Atha tanayamasūta śr<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>nidhiṁ sā ca tasmādakhilavibudhasaṁghairīḍitammeḍamāryyam <supplied reason="omitted"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">27</supplied> Uddāmadhā
                    <lb n="88" break="no"/>mavimalīkṛtadigvibhāge nityodayasthitimati pravikāsipadm<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>e</corr></choice> <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yatrodite nikhilabandhukulāni lakṣmīra
                    <lb n="89" break="no"/>dhyāsta vārijavanāni vivasvatīva <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">28</supplied> yasminnāśr<choice><sic>ī</sic><corr>i</corr></choice>tavatsale kṛtayugācāraikadhīre sthitiṁ bibhrāṇā guṇaratnabhū
                    <lb n="90" break="no"/>ṣaṇa Iti prakhyātanāmni svayaṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> satyatyāgaparākramaprabhṛtayassaṁbhūya sarvve guṇā varddhate
                    <lb n="91"/>guṇarāśilopanipuṇaṁ nirjjitya kālaṁ kalim <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">29</supplied> dh<choice><sic>i</sic><corr>ī</corr></choice>ro nityānurakto dṛ<choice><sic>ḍ</sic><corr>ḍh</corr></choice>aniśitamatirbrahmavaṁśapradīpo
                    <lb n="92"/>lakṣmībhūriddhatejā nayavinayanidhiśśāstraśastrapravīṇaḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mānya<choice><sic>śś</sic><corr>ḥ ś</corr></choice><choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>le<choice><sic>ṁ</sic><corr>n</corr></choice>drasārasthira Iti ca mayā sāda
                    <lb n="93" break="no"/>raṁ saprasādaṁ s<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>ai</corr></choice>nāpatyebhiṣikto vahati janamude paṭṭamāropitaṁ yaḥ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">30</supplied> śuśrūṣayā gurujanaṁ
                    
                    <pb n="5r" break="no"/>
                    <lb n="94" break="no"/><surplus>ṁ</surplus>ccaritena lokammā<unclear>nena ba</unclear>ndhujanamiṣṭadhanena śiṣṭān· <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yo māmma<unclear>dīya</unclear>ni<unclear>khi</unclear>la<unclear>kṣi</unclear>tirājyabhārakṣāṁtyābhinaṁda
                    <lb n="95" break="no"/>yati <add place="below">bhakti</add><!--<note n="56-12"><foreign>bhakti</foreign> is entered below the line</note>-->bhareṇa śau<unclear>riṁ</unclear> <supplied reason="omitted"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">31</supplied> <unclear>yasya</unclear> prāṁgaṇabhūmiṣu pratidinaṁ prakṣālyamānāmitakṣoṇīdevasamūhapā<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>d</corr></choice>avigaladvāripra
                    <lb n="96" break="no"/>vāhaiśśubhaiḥ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> śaśva<unclear>nmārggasa</unclear>hasrapūribhiraho gaṁgāpravāhā jitā deveṣvanyatamasya pādagalitā mārggatrayāyāsitā<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> <g type="ddanda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">32</supplied>
                    <lb n="97"/><g type="danda">.</g> d<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>ākṣārāme pāvane puṇyabhājā puṇyakṣetre pī<choice><sic>dh</sic><corr>ṭh</corr></choice>apur<surplus>y</surplus>y<choice><sic>āṁ</sic><corr>o</corr></choice> ca yena <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> bhoktuṁ prītyā <add place="below">pratya</add>haṁ<!--<note n="56-16">pratya is entered below the line.</note>--> brāhmaṇānāmākalpāṁttaṁ kalpi
                    <lb n="98" break="no"/>taṁ satrayugmaṁ <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">33</supplied> cellūrunāmaprathitābhirāmaśiṣṭāgrahārottaradigvibhāge <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> mahattaṭāka<surplus>ṁ</surplus>mmadhurāṁbupūrṇṇama
                    <lb n="99" break="no"/>cīkaradyaḥ karuṇārasātmā <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">34</supplied> viprairagastyapratimairasaṁkhyairnnityopabhogyena śaśiprabheṇa <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> yadvāriṇābdhiṁ hasatīva bhū
                    <lb n="100" break="no"/>yo niśśeṣapītaṁ kalaśodbhavena <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">35</supplied> mahaujasā tena mahāmahimnā grāmasya tasyāparadigvibhāge <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> nirmmāpitaṁ dharmma
                    <lb n="101" break="no"/>parāyaṇena viṣṇo<supplied reason="omitted">r</supplied>gṛhaṁ vaiṣṇavapuṁgav<choice><sic>ai</sic><corr>e</corr></choice>na <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">36</supplied> samunnate caṁdramarīcigaure lakṣmīnivāse nayanābhirāme <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                    <lb n="102"/>tatrāvirāsītsvayamev<choice><sic>e</sic><corr>a</corr></choice> devo lakṣmīpatirllakṣitaśaṁkhacakra<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> <g type="danda">.</g> <supplied reason="subaudible">37</supplied> tasmai śrīviṣṇubhaṭṭārakāya pratyahaṁ caruba
                    <lb n="103" break="no"/>lipūjārtthaṁ khaṇḍas<choice><sic>p</sic><corr>ph</corr></choice>u<choice><sic>d</sic><corr>ṭ</corr></choice>ītanavakarmmārtthaṁ ca bhavadviṣaye <unclear>kolā</unclear><seg rendition="class:telugu maturity:00000"><unclear>ṟu</unclear></seg><unclear>nāma grāmassarvvakaraparihāreṇa</unclear>
                    <lb n="104"/><unclear>devabhogīkṛtya Udakapūrvvakaṁ datta Iti viditamastu vaḥ Asya grāmasya sīmānaḥ pūrvvataḥ ku</unclear>
                    <lb n="105-108"/>Illegible <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> 
                    <lb n="109"/><gap reason="lost" quantity="10" unit="character"/> sīmā <g type="ddanda">.</g> Asyopari na kenacidb<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>dhā ka<unclear>rttavyā <g type="danda">.</g> yaḥ karo</unclear>ti sa
                    
                    <pb n="5v"/>
                    <lb n="110"/>paṁcamahāpātakayukto bhavati <g type="danda">.</g> tathā coktaṁ bhagavatā vyāsena <g type="danda">.</g> svadattāṁ paradattā<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> <unclear>vā yo hare</unclear>ta va
                    <lb n="111" break="no"/>sundharāṁ <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied> ṣaṣṭiṁ varṣasahasrāṇi viṣṭhāyāṁ jāyate krimiḥ <g type="danda">.</g> gāmekāṁ svarṇṇamekaṁ vā <unclear>bhūmerapyeka</unclear>maṁgu
                    <lb n="112" break="no"/>laṁ <g type="danda">.</g> harannarakamāpnoti yāvadābhūtasaṁplavaṁ <g type="danda">.</g> bahubhirvvasudhā dattā bahubhi<unclear>ścānupā</unclear>litā <g type="danda">.</g> yasya
                    <lb n="113"/>yasya yadā bhūmistasya tasya tadā phalaṁ <g type="danda">.</g> śrīvijayarājyasaṁvatsare Ekaviṁśe dattasyāsya
                    <lb n="114"/>śāsanasyājñaptiḥ paṁca pradhānāḥ kāvyakarttā viddayabhaṭṭaḥ lekhakaḥ pennācāriḥ <g type="ddanda">.</g>
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app loc="19">
                        <lem>muḍi</lem>
                        <note><foreign>ḍi</foreign> looks almost like <foreign>hi</foreign>.</note>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="19">
                        <lem>gurujanaṁ</lem>
                        <note >The <hi rend="italic">anusvāra</hi> is repeated at the beginning of the next plate.</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" source="bib:Hultzsch1890_01">
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 1.) From the lotus-flower, (<hi rend="italic">which rose</hi>) from the navel of the abode of Śrī, the supreme spirit, the great lord Nārāyaṇa (<hi rend="italic">Vishṇu</hi>), there was born Svayaṁbhū (<hi rend="italic">Brahman</hi>), the creator of the world. From him there sprang a spiritual son, called Atri. From this saint Atri there arose <hi rend="bold">Soma</hi>, the founder of a race, the nectar-rayed, the crest-jewel of Śrīkaṇṭha (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 2.) From this producer of nectar there sprang <hi rend="bold">Budha</hi>, who was praised by the wise. From him there was begot a valorous emperor called <hi rend="bold">Purūravas</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 4.) From him (<hi rend="italic">came</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Āyu</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Nahusha</hi>; from him the emperor <hi rend="bold">Yayāti</hi>, the founder of a race; from him <hi rend="bold">Puru</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Janamejaya</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Prāchīśa</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Sainyayāti</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Hayapati</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Sārvabhauma</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Jayasena</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Mahābhauma</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Aiśānaka</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Krodhānana</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Devaki</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Ṛibhuka</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Ṛikshaka</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Mativara</hi>, the performer of great sacrifices and lord of the <hi rend="bold">Sarasvatī</hi> river; from him <hi rend="bold">Kātyāyana</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Nīla</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Dushyanta</hi>. His son was he who, having placed sacrificial posts in an uninterrupted line on the banks of the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgā</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Yamunā</hi>, and having successively performed the great rite (<hi rend="italic">called</hi>) horse-sacrifice, obtained the name of <hi rend="bold">Bharata</hi>. From this Bharata (<hi rend="italic">came</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Bhūmanyu</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Hastin</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Virochana</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Ajamīḷha</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Saṁvaraṇa</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Sudhanvan</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Parikshit</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Bhīmasena</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Pradīpana</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Śaṁtanu</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Vichitravīrya</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍurāja</hi>; from him the <hi rend="bold">Pāṇḍavas</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 3.) (<hi rend="italic">From</hi>) that victorious bearer of (<hi rend="italic">the bow) gāṇḍīva</hi>, who, having conquered (<hi rend="italic">Indra</hi>) the bearer of the thunderbolt, burnt the hermitage in the Khāṇḍava (<hi rend="italic">forest</hi>), who acquired the weapon of Paśupati (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) in battle from (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) the enemy of Andhaka, who, having killed Kālikeya and many other Daityas, partook of one half of Indra's throne, and who wilfully destroyed the forest-like race of the lord of the Kurus;—</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 14.) From that <hi rend="bold">Arjuna</hi> (<hi rend="italic">came</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Abhimanyu</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Parikshit</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Janamejaya</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Kshemuka</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Naravāhana</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Śatānīka</hi>; from him <hi rend="bold">Udayana</hi>. When, commencing with him, fifty-nine emperors, whose succession was uninterrupted, and who sat on the throne of <hi rend="bold">Ayodhyā</hi>, had passed away, a king of this race, <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya</hi> by name, went to the Dekhan (<hi rend="italic">Dakshiṇāpatha</hi>), in order to conquer (<hi rend="italic">it</hi>) and attacked <hi rend="bold">Trilochana-Pallava</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) through ill-luck he went to another world. During this battle, his great queen, who was pregnant, reached together with the family-priest and the old ministers an <hi rend="italic">agrahāra</hi> called <hi rend="bold">Muḍivemu</hi>, and, being protected like a daughter by <hi rend="bold">Vishṇubhaṭṭa-somayājin</hi>, a great ascetic, who dwelt there, she gave birth to a son, <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi>. She brought him up, having caused to be performed for this prince the rites, which were suitable to (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) descent from the double <hi rend="italic">gotra</hi> of those, who belonged to the <hi rend="italic">gotra</hi> of the <hi rend="bold">Mānavyas</hi> and were the sons of <hi rend="bold">Hāritī</hi>.<note>The Chalukyas claim descent from both the Mānavya and the Hārita gotras.</note> And he, having been told the (<hi rend="italic">above-mentioned</hi>) events by his mother, went forth, worshipped <hi rend="bold">Nandā</hi>, the blessed <hi rend="bold">Gaurī</hi>, on the <hi rend="bold">Chalukya</hi> mountain, appeased Kumāra (<hi rend="italic">Skanda</hi>), Nārāyaṇa (<hi rend="italic">Vishṇu</hi>) and the assemblage of (<hi rend="italic">divine</hi>) mothers, assumed the insignia of sovereignty which had descended (<hi rend="italic">to him</hi>) by the succession of his race, (<hi rend="italic">but</hi>) which had been, as it were, laid aside, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) the white parasol, the single conch, the five <hi rend="italic">mahāśabdas</hi>, the flags in rows,<note>On <hi rend="italic">pāliketana</hi> see <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. XIV, p. 104.</note> the <hi rend="italic">pratiḍhakkā (drum</hi>), the sign of the boar, the peacock's tail, the spear, the throne, the arch (<hi rend="italic">in the shape</hi>) of a <hi rend="italic">makara,</hi><note><hi rend="italic">Makara-toraṇa</hi>, ‘an honorary wreath or string of flowers, etc., raised upon poles and carried in front of one, as an emblem of distinction’; Sanderson's <hi rend="italic">Canarese Dictionary</hi>.</note> the golden sceptre, (<hi rend="italic">the signs of</hi>) the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅgā</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Yamunā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">etc</hi>., conquered the <hi rend="bold">Kaḍamba</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Gaṅga</hi> and other princes, and ruled over the Dekhan (<hi rend="italic">Dakshiṇāpatha), (which is situated</hi>) between the bridge (<hi rend="italic">of Rāma</hi>) and the (<hi rend="italic">river</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Narmadā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">and the revenue from which amounts to</hi>) seven and a half <hi rend="italic">lakshas</hi>.<note>The above passage has been previously translated by Mr. Fleet. <hi rend="italic">Ind. Ant</hi>. Vol. VII, p. 245.</note></p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 4.) The son of this king <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi> and of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) great queen, who was born from the <hi rend="bold">Pallava</hi> race, was <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 27.) His son was <hi rend="bold">Pulakeśi-Vallabha</hi>. His son was <hi rend="bold">Kīrtivarman</hi>. His son,—Hail! <hi rend="bold">Kubja-Vishṇuvardhana</hi>, the brother of <hi rend="bold">Satyāśraya-Vallabhendra</hi>, who adorned the race of the glorious <hi rend="bold">Chālukyas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">etc.,</hi><note>The passage, which is omitted in the translation, is identical with the first 4 lines of No. <ref target="DHARMA_INSSIIv01p0i0035">35</ref>.</note> ruled for eighteen years over the country of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>; his son <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha-Vallabha</hi> for thirty-three (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his younger brother <hi rend="bold">Indra-rāja</hi> for seven days; his son <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi> for nine years; his son <hi rend="bold">Maṅgi-yuvarāja</hi> for twenty-five (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his son <hi rend="bold">Jayasiṁha</hi> for thirteen (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his younger brother <hi rend="bold">Kokkili</hi> for six months; his elder brother <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi>, having expelled him, for thirty-seven (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his son <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya-bhaṭṭāraka</hi> for eighteen (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his son <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi> for thirty-six (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his son <hi rend="bold">Narendra-mṛigarāja</hi> for forty-eight (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his son <hi rend="bold">Kali-Vishṇuvardhana</hi> for one and a half years; his son <hi rend="bold">Guṇagāṅka-Vijayāditya</hi> for forty-four (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); <hi rend="bold">Chālukya-Bhīma</hi>, the son of his brother <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi>, for thirty (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); his son <hi rend="bold">Kollabhigaṇḍa-Vijayāditya</hi> for six months; his son <hi rend="bold">Amma-rāja</hi> for seven years; having expelled his infant son <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya, Tāḍapa</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ruled</hi>) for one month; having conquered him, <hi rend="bold">Vikramāditya</hi>, the son of <hi rend="bold">Chālukya-Bhīma</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">ruled</hi>) for eleven months; then <hi rend="bold">Yuddhamalla</hi>, the son of <hi rend="bold">Tāḍaparāja</hi>, for seven years; having expelled him from the country, <hi rend="bold">Rāja-Bhīma</hi>, the younger brother of <hi rend="bold">Amma-rāja</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">ruled</hi>) for twelve years; his son <hi rend="bold">Amma-rāja</hi> for twenty-five (<hi rend="italic">years</hi>); <hi rend="bold">Dāna-nṛipa</hi>, his brother from a different mother, for three years. Then the country of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> was through ill-luck without a ruler for twenty-seven years. Then king <hi rend="bold">Śaktivarman</hi>, the son of <hi rend="bold">Dānārṇava</hi>, ruled over the earth for twelve years.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 5.) Then his younger brother, king <hi rend="bold">Vimalāditya</hi>, who was kind to (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) beings, ruled over the earth for seven years.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 46.) His son, king <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, who possessed political wisdom, and who was the abode of the goddess of victory, ruled over the whole earth for forty-one years.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 6.) He whose fame was brilliant, who was the only jewel which adorned the glorious race of the moon, and who was the only jewel which fulfilled the desires of the distressed, surpassed Cupid by his beauty, the moon by his pure splendour, Puraṁdara (<hi rend="italic">Indra</hi>) by his possessions, (<hi rend="italic">Vishṇu</hi>) the bearer of Lakshmī by his great prosperity, and Bhīma by his terrible power.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 7.) He had a spotless queen, <hi rend="bold">Ammaṅga</hi> by name, who was famed on earth by her good deeds, who was the only abode of lucky marks, who purified the world, and who sprang from <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi>, the ornament of the race of the sun, just as Gaṅgā from Jahnu, Gaurī from Himavat and Lakshmī from the milk-ocean.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 8.) Just as (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) the bearer of Gaṅgā and (<hi rend="italic">Pārvatī</hi>) the daughter of the mountain had a son called Kārttikeya, these two had a son called <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-Choḍa</hi>, who annihilated the multitude of his enemies by his irresistible power, whose fame was worthy of praise, and who was the light of the warrior-caste.<note>With <hi rend="italic">rājakulapradīpa</hi> compare <hi rend="italic">parārdhyo mahati nṛipakule</hi> in verse 11.</note></p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 9.) Having at first occupied the throne of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">which became</hi>) the cause of the rising of (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) splendour, just as the sun at morn occupies the eastern mountain, he conquered (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) quarters with his power.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 10.) Having burnt all foes with the rising and fierce fire of his valour, and having successively conquered <hi rend="bold">Kerala, Pāṇḍya, Kuntala</hi> and all other countries, he placed his commands on the heads of princes, the pain of fear in the hearts of fools and his fame, which was as white as the rays of the moon, in (<hi rend="italic">all</hi>) quarters.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 11.) <hi rend="bold">Kulottuṅga-deva</hi>, the most eminent of the great warrior-caste, whose might resembled that of the king of the gods (<hi rend="italic">Indra</hi>), was anointed to the <hi rend="bold">Choḍa</hi> kingdom, which was not inferior to the kingdom of the gods, and put on the tiara, embellished with invaluable gems of many kinds, which had been sent by various kings, who were exceedingly afraid of the threatening of his arms, which were as formidable as the terrible coils of the serpent-king.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 12.) He in whose hands the conch, the discus and the lotus were shining, and whom (<hi rend="italic">therefore</hi>) the world praised as <hi rend="bold">Rājanārāyaṇa</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">a Vishṇu among kings</hi>), married (<hi rend="italic">as it were</hi>) Lakshmī (<hi rend="italic">the wife of Vishṇu</hi>) herself, who was known by her other name, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Madhurāntakī</hi>, and who (<hi rend="italic">just as the goddess Lakshmī</hi>) from the ocean, arose from <hi rend="bold">Rājendra-deva</hi>, the ornament of the race of the sun, a queen who was praised in the world and exalted by her deeds.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 13.) To these two there were born (<hi rend="italic">seven</hi>) sons, who were as pure as the (<hi rend="italic">seven</hi>) streams of the Gaṅgā, who, like the (<hi rend="italic">seven</hi>) Ādityas, had destroyed the darkness (<hi rend="italic">of sin</hi>), and who, like the (<hi rend="italic">seven</hi>) mountains, were able (<hi rend="italic">to undergo</hi>) the fatigue of supporting the earth. To (<hi rend="italic">one</hi>) among these, the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, who was the joint abode of polity and valour, (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) father, the lord of the whole earth, affectionately addressed the following speech:—</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 14.) “Being desirous of the <hi rend="bold">Choḍa</hi> kingdom, I formerly conferred the kingdom of the country of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> on my paternal uncle, king <hi rend="bold">Vijayāditya</hi>.”</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 15.) “Having ruled over the country for fifteen years, this god-like prince, who resembled the five-faced (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) in power, has gone to heaven.”</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 16.) This obedient one (viz., <hi rend="italic">Rājarāja</hi>) took up that burden, (viz., <hi rend="italic">the kingdom of Veṅgī</hi>,) which the emperor, (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) father, gave him with these words, though he did not like the separation from him.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 17.) “The kingdom is not such a pleasure as the worship of the illustrious feet of the elders”; considering thus, he returned to his parents, after having ruled over the country of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi> for one year.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 18.) Then the emperor spoke to his (viz., <hi rend="italic">Rājarāja's</hi>) younger brother, the brave prince <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa</hi>, who seemed to be an incarnation of the quality (<hi rend="italic">of</hi>) valour: “Having ascended the throne of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>, place thy feet on the heads of (<hi rend="italic">other</hi>) kings, just as the sun, having ascended the eastern mountain, places his rays on the peaks of (<hi rend="italic">other</hi>) mountains.”</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 19.) Thus having successively obtained the powerful blessing of the king, of the queen and of his two elder brothers, having bowed to these and having been bowed to by his younger brothers,<note>The plural in the original shows that <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa</hi> had at least <hi rend="italic">three</hi> younger brothers; according to verse 13, their number was <hi rend="italic">four</hi>.</note> the prince was with difficulty prevailed upon by them to start for his country.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 20.) Having driven away his enemies, having eclipsed with his splendour the other crowds of kings, having stopped the wicked and having made the earth rejoice, the lord, the ornament of the country of <hi rend="bold">Veṅgī</hi>, the king's son ascended (<hi rend="italic">his</hi>) palace in the town called <hi rend="bold">Jaganātha</hi>, resembling the disk of the morning-sun, who, having driven away the darkness, having eclipsed with his splendour the other crowds of stars,<note>This seems to be the second meaning of <hi rend="italic">rājanikarān aparān</hi>.</note> having stopped the wicked, and having made the lotus-group blossom, ascends the eastern mountain.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 21.) In the <hi rend="italic">Śāka</hi> year, which is reckoned by the moon, the pair of ciphers and the moon, (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, 1001,) while the sun stood in the lion, while the moon was waxing, on the thirteenth lunar day, on a Thursday, while the scorpion was the <hi rend="italic">lagna</hi> and in (<hi rend="italic">the nakshatra) Śravaṇa</hi>, having been anointed to the kingdom of the whole earth, the sinless king, the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa</hi>, joyfully put on the tiara of the world.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 78.) This asylum of the whole world, the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Vishṇuvardhana</hi>, the king of great kings, the supreme master of kings, the devout worshipper of <hi rend="bold">Maheśvara</hi>, the supreme lord, the most pious one, the illustrious <hi rend="bold">Vīra-Choḍa-deva</hi>, having called together all householders, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) heads of provinces, <hi rend="italic">etc.</hi>, who inhabit the district of <hi rend="bold">Guddavāṭi</hi>, thus issues his commands in the presence of the ministers, the family priest, the commander of the army, the heir-apparent and the door-keeper:—</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 22.) Just as the moon in the milk-ocean, there was in the pure race of Brahman a chief of ascetics, called <hi rend="bold">Mudgala</hi>, whose appearance was extremely gladdening.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 23.) When he, whose power was incomprehensible, had invited the sun, his staff performed the action of the sun at his command.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 24.) In his <hi rend="italic">gotra</hi> there was a certain <hi rend="bold">Potana</hi>, whose deeds were pure, who made his <hi rend="italic">gotra</hi> prosper and who illuminated the quarters with the splendour of his fame.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 25.) This virtuous one was joyfully praised by the lord <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja</hi>, who knew (<hi rend="italic">how to appreciate</hi>) virtues, by the name of <hi rend="bold">Rājarāja-brahma-mahārāja</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">the great king of the brāhmaṇas of Rājarāja</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 26.) Just as the wife of Atri was Anasūryā, the wife of this treasure-house of merit was <hi rend="bold">Kannamāmbā</hi>, who was praised in the world, and who was exalted by the virtue of freedom from envy (<hi rend="italic">anasūyā</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 27.) Just as Devakī bore from Vasudeva a son called Vāsudeva (<hi rend="italic">Kṛishṇa</hi>), and just as the mountain-daughter (<hi rend="italic">Pārvatī</hi>) bore from the moon-crested (<hi rend="italic">Śiva</hi>) a son called Guha, thus she bore from him a son called <hi rend="bold">Meḍamārya</hi>, who was a treasure-house of prosperity, and who was praised by all the assemblies of wise men (<hi rend="italic">or gods</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 28.) After he was born, prosperity dwelt on all the crowds of his relatives, just as on the groups of lotus-flowers at the rising of the sun; for (<hi rend="italic">like the sun</hi>) he purified the quarters with his unrestrained splendour, was daily in the state of rising and was possessed of a blossoming lotus (<hi rend="italic">-face</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 29.) Having conquered the <hi rend="italic">kali</hi>-age which is skilled in plundering heaps of virtues,—all virtues, (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>) truthfulness, liberality, prowess, <hi rend="italic">etc.</hi>, prosper, abiding jointly in him, who is kind to refugees, who is alone constant in a conduct (<hi rend="italic">which is worthy</hi>) of the <hi rend="italic">kṛita</hi>-age, and who is famed by the name of <hi rend="bold">Guṇaratnabhūshaṇa</hi> (i.e., <hi rend="italic">he who is adorned with jewel-like virtues</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 30.) Because he was firm, always attached, of strong and sharp mind, a light of the race of Brahman, an abode of prosperity, possessed of blazing splendour, a treasurehouse of polity and modesty, skilled in sciences and in weapons, worthy of honour and as hard as the substance of the king of mountains, he was respectfully and graciously anointed by me to the dignity of a commander of the army (<hi rend="italic">senāpati</hi>) and wears the tiara which was placed (<hi rend="italic">on his head</hi>) to the delight of the people.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 31.) He delights his elders by obedience, the world by his conduct, his relations by respect, the good by the riches which they desire, myself by his patience in bearing my kingdom of the whole earth and Śauri (<hi rend="italic">Vishṇu</hi>) by great devotion.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 32.) Ah! the auspicious streams of water, which drop from the feet of innumerable crowds of earth-gods (i.e., <hi rend="italic">brāhmaṇas</hi>), who daily perform their ablutions in his courtyards, and which continually fill thousands of paths, surpass the streams of the Gaṅgā, which drop from the feet of <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of the gods (viz., <hi rend="italic">Vishṇu</hi>), and which are tired of their <hi rend="italic">three</hi> paths (viz., <hi rend="italic">heaven, earth and the lower world</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 33.) At holy <hi rend="bold">Drākshārāma</hi> and at the sacred place of <hi rend="bold">Pīṭhapurī</hi>, this charitable one joyfully founded two <hi rend="italic">sattras</hi> for brāhmaṇas, in order that they might daily enjoy their meals (<hi rend="italic">there</hi>) till the end of the <hi rend="italic">kalpa</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 34.) On the north side of a lovely <hi rend="italic">agrahāra</hi> of good people, which is famed by the name of <hi rend="bold">Chellūru</hi>, he whose mind is full of compassion caused to be constructed a large pond which is filled with sweet water.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 35.) By its water, which glitters like the moon, and which is daily enjoyed by numberless brāhmaṇas who resemble Agastya, this (<hi rend="italic">pond</hi>) repeatedly laughs, as it were, at the ocean, which was completely drunk up by the pitcher-born (<hi rend="italic">Agastya</hi>).</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 36.) On the west side of that village, this powerful, mighty and charitable chief of the <hi rend="bold">Vaishṇavas</hi> caused to be built a temple of <hi rend="bold">Vishṇu</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Verse</hi> 37.) In this lofty (<hi rend="italic">temple</hi>), which is as white as the rays of the moon, which is the abode of splendour (<hi rend="italic">or Lakshmī</hi>) and which pleases the eye, the god himself, who is the husband of Lakshmī, made his appearance, his conch and discus being distinctly visible.</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 102.) “Be it known to you, that to this blessed lord <hi rend="bold">Vishṇu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">I</hi>) gave for the daily (<hi rend="italic">performance of) charu, bali</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pūjā</hi> and for the repairs of gaps and cracks [<hi rend="italic">the village called</hi> <hi rend="bold">Kolāṟu</hi>] in your district <hi rend="italic">[with exemption from all taxes, making it the property of the temple, with a libation of water.]</hi>”</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 104.) [The boundaries of this village are:—on the east . . . . . . . . . .]</p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 109.) Nobody shall cause obstruction to this (<hi rend="italic">grant</hi>). He who does it, becomes possessed of the five great sins. And the holy <hi rend="bold">Vyāsa</hi> has said: <hi rend="italic">[Here follow three of the customary imprecatory verses.]</hi></p>
                
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Line</hi> 113.) The executors (<hi rend="italic">ājñapti</hi>) of this edict (<hi rend="italic">śāsana</hi>), which was given in the twentyfirst year of the glorious and victorious reign, (<hi rend="italic">were</hi>) the five ministers (<hi rend="italic">pañcha pradhānāḥ</hi>). The author of the poetry (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Viddaya-bhaṭṭa</hi>. The writer (<hi rend="italic">was</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Pennāchāri</hi>.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary"/>
                
            
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 1.39 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:Hultzsch1890_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">49-62</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">39</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
