<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>SII 38.201: original edition by S. Swaminathan</title>
				<title type="alt">No. 201. (A.R. No. 201 of 1912.) TIRUVOṞṞIYŪR, SAIDAPET TALUK, CHINGLEPUT DISTRICT. On the west wall, first prākāra, Ādhipurīśvara temple.</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName>
						<name>DHARMA team</name>
					</persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv38p0i0201</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary>

						<p><hi rend="bold">King: Kulōttuṅga III Year 38: 1216 A.D.</hi></p>						

						<p>States that this record is a copy of royal order (see following no.). It registers an exemption of taxes such as <hi rend="italic">antarāyam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pāṭṭam</hi> on eighty <hi rend="italic">vēli</hi> of land at Kuḷattūr <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Kulōttuṅgasōḻankāvaṉūr which was separated from Puṉṉaivāyil <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Rājanārāyaṇa-chchaturvēdimaṅgalam (a sub-division) of Puḻar-kōṭṭam <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Vikramachōḻavaḷanāḍu. The land was donated by Duṟgayāṇḍāṉ Nāyakkan, an agent of Chittaraisan. The royal order exempting the above taxes were conveyed to the pontiff, superintendent of devotees and executive officials of the Tiruvoṟṟiyūr temple. The donor made this land grant inorder to conduct worship at the <hi rend="italic">Vyākyāna maṇḍapa</hi>, when the deity was pleased to appear there and also for the maintenance of both the students and teachers of <hi rend="italic">Vyākarṇa</hi>, which was imparted at the above <hi rend="italic">maṇḍapa</hi>, of the (Tiruvoṟṟiyūr) temple, constructed by the donor himself. The king on the recommendation of Vāṇādarāyaṉ got the above taxes exempted from his 38th year onwards. This order was taken down by the official <hi rend="italic">(tirumandira ōlai)</hi> Neṟiuḍaichchōḻa Mūvēndavēḷāṉ, Villavarāyaṉ, Toṇḍaimāṉ and others figure as signatories.</p>						

						</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2026-03-17" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/>tirumukappaṭi <g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="danda">.</g><g type="dashLong">.</g> <hi rend="grantha">svastiśrī <supplied reason="undefined"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied> tribhu</hi>vaṉaccakkaravatti koṉeriṉmai koṇṭān <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻamaṇṭalattu Uṭaiyār tiruvoṟṟiyūruṭaiyārkoyil maṭapatikkum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi>mā<hi rend="grantha">heśva</hi>rak kaṇkāṇi ceyvārkaḷukkum <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> kāriyañceyvāṉukkum cittaraicaṉ kāriyattukku kaṭava tuṟkaiyāṇṭi nāyakkan Ikkoyilil ceyvikkiṟa <hi rend="grantha">vyā</hi>karaṇatāna <hi rend="grantha">vyākhyā</hi>nama<hi rend="grantha">ṇḍa</hi>pattu Ittevar Eḻun=taruḷum nāṭkaḷil pūcaikkum Immaṇṭapattu <hi rend="grantha">vyā</hi>karaṇamvācippārkkum vācippippārkkum veṇṭuvaṉa vai
<lb n="2" break="no"/>yiṟṟukku Iṟuppatākap puḻaṟkoṭṭamāna vikkiramacoḻavaḷanāṭṭu puṉṉaivāyilānairācanārāyaṇaccatu<hi rend="grantha">rvvedi</hi>maṅkalattu piṟinta kuḷattūrāṉa kulottuṅkacoḻaṉkāvaṉūr Ivaṉ kāṇiyāṉa nilam Eṇpatiṟṟu veliyum muppatteṭṭāvatu mutal Antarāyam pāṭṭam Uṭpaṭa Iṟaiyiliyāka Iṭakkaṭavatākap peṟaveṇumeṉṟu vāṇatarāyaṉ namakkuc coṉṉamaiyil Ippaṭi ceyyak kaṭavatākac collik kaṇakkilum Iṭṭuk koḷ<note n="233-1">Letters ḷ and k are engraved below their respective places.</note>ḷak<note n="233-1">Letters ḷ and k are engraved below their respective places.</note>kaṭavārkaḷāka vari
<lb n="3" break="no"/>k kūṟuceyvārkaḷukkum coṉṉom Iṉṉilam muppatteṭṭāvatu mutal Antarāyam pāṭṭam Uṭpaṭa Iṟaiyiliyāka kaikkoḷka Eḻutiṉāṉ tirumantiraolai neṟiyuṭaiccoḻamuventaveḷāne Eḻuttu villavarāyaṉ Eḻuttu toṇṭaimāṉ Eḻuttu viḻiñattaraiyan Eḻu<unclear>t</unclear>tu Aṅkarāyaṉ Eḻuttu ciṅkaḷarāyaṉ Eḻuttu Irācatarāca viḻupparain Eḻuttu cittarāyaṉ Eḻuttu vayanāṭṭaraiyaṉ Eḻuttu <hi rend="grantha"><num value="38">3 <g type="numeral">10</g> 8</num> <num value="100"><g type="numeral">100</g></num> <num value="239">2 <g type="numeral">100</g> 3 <g type="numeral">10</g> 9</num></hi>
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

	<p>Digital edition of SII 38.201 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2019_01"/></bibl> automatically converted to DHARMA conventions.</p>

	<listBibl type="primary">

		<bibl n="SII">
			<ptr target="bib:Swaminathan2019_01"/>
			<citedRange unit="page">233-234</citedRange>
			<citedRange unit="item">201</citedRange>
		</bibl>

	</listBibl>

	<listBibl type="secondary">

		<bibl/>

	</listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
