<volume n="2-5"> <h1>SOUTH-INDIAN INSCRIPTIONS [2-5]</h1>

<h2>VOLUME II.</h2>

<h2>PART V.—PALLAVA COPPER-PLATE GRANTS FROM <lb/> VELURPALAYAM AND TANDANTOTTAM <lb/> (WITH TWO PLATES)</h2>

<h2>INCLUDING TITLE PAGE, PREFACE, TABLE OF CONTENTS, LIST OF PLATES, ADDENDA AND</h2>

<h2>CORRIGENDA, INTRODUCTION AND INDEX OF VOLUME II <lb/> EDITED AND TRANSLATED <lb/> BY <lb/> RAO SAHIB H. KRISHNA SASTRI, B.A., <lb/> ASSISTANT ARCHAEOLOGICAL SUPERINTENDENT FOR EPIGRAPHY, SOUTHERN CIRCLE. <lb/> MADRAS. <lb/> PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY THE SUPERINTENDENT, GOVERNMENT PRESS. <lb/> CALCUTTA: THACKER, SPINK &amp; Co. BOMBAY: THACKER &amp; Co. (LD.). <lb/> LONDON: LUZAC &amp; Co. <lb/> 1916.<pb n="2:501"/></h2>

<h2>PART V.</h2>

<h2>SUPPLEMENT TO THE SECOND VOLUME.</h2>

<h2>V.—TWO PALLAVA COPPER-PLATE GRANTS.</h2>

<inscription n="2:501:98"><head>No. 98.—VELURPALAIYAM PLATES OF VIJAYA-NANDIVARMAN (III).</head>

<p>These plates were discovered in 1911 by the late Rai Bahadur V.Venkayya, M.A., in the <lb/> village <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em>, about 7 miles north-west of Arkonam in the North Arcot district. <lb/> They have since been purchased by the Government for deposit in the Madras Museum. <lb/> A detailed description of the plates and their contents has appeared in the Epigraphical <lb/> Report for 1911, Part II, paragraphs 5 to 12. Mr. Venkayya also, has published a valuable <lb/> note on them in the <i>Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society</i> for 1911, pp. 521 ff.</p>

<p>The plates are five in number and consist of eight written sides, the outer faces of the <lb/> first and last being completely blank. They vary in length from 9(5/8)" to 9(3/4)", and are slightly <lb/> convex on their right and left sides. The breadth of each plate is about 3(1/2)". The ring <lb/> which holds the plates together is oval-shaped, and measures 7"x6(1/4)", while the circular <lb/> seal in whose massive bottom the edges of the ring are firmly fixed, is 3(1/4)" in diameter. The <lb/> seal bears on a depressed surface an elongated figure of a <em>Pallava</em> bull in a recumbent posture <lb/> facing the proper right with an ornamental lamp-stand on either side of it. The bull and <lb/> the lamp-stands are placed on a straight line which is perhaps to be taken for the surface of <lb/> a pedestal. Below this latter, there appear the faint traces of an expanded lotus flower. <lb/> Above the bull are engraved in one row, eight symbols of which a goddess (perhaps Lakshmī), <lb/> flanked by two lamp-stands occupies the centre. Another symbol which is recognisable is <lb/> the <i>svastika</i>. The remaining four are indistinct. Above these again are the insignia of <lb/> royalty, <i>viz.</i>, two <i>chauris</i> mounted on handles and a parasol between them. Right round the <lb/> margin of the seal is a defaced legend in Pallava-Grantha characters of which the syllables <lb/> • • • • <i>va-nāthasya Nan[tipa]ṉmas[ya] bhū[pa*]tēḥ [|*] viśva-[vi]śva[ṁ]bharā-<lb break="no"/>pāla śrīḥ</i>, are visible. The plates including ring and seal weigh 394 <i>tolas</i>.</p>

<p>The inscription on the plates is engraved partly in <em>Grantha</em> and partly in <em>Tamil</em> char-<lb break="no"/>acters. The writing discloses two different scripts, the first of which (ll. 1 to 28) is somewhat less <lb/> deeply cut and slanting. The <i>virāma</i> or the <i>puḷḷi</i> in the Tamil portion of the inscription is <lb/> marked almost regularly throughout, by a zigzag line resembling the final <i>m</i> of Grantha or by <lb/> the usual dot. The grant consists of 31 <em>Sanskṛit</em> verses intercepted in the middle by a prose <lb/> passage in Tamil from lines 47 to 63, and including at the end a short Tamil sentence in lines <lb/> 68 and 69. Verses 1 and 2 are invocations addressed to the Supreme Being and to <em>Śrīkaṇṭha <lb/> (Śiva)</em>. The two next supply the legendary origin of the <em>Pallavas</em> from <em>Vishṇu</em>, down <lb/> to the eponymous king <em>Pallava</em>, through <em>Brahmā, Aṅgiras, Bṛihaspati, Śaṁyu, <lb/> Bharadvāja, Drōṇa</em>, and <em>Aśvatthāman</em>, and eulogise the family as being very powerful. <lb/> From verses 5 to 8, we learn the names of some probably historical kings. One of them was <lb/> <em>Aśōkavarman</em> in whose family was born <em>Kāḷabhartṛi</em>. His son was <em>Chūtapallava</em>; <lb/> his son, <em>Vīrakūrcha</em>; from him came <em>Skandaśishya</em>; from him, <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> and<pb n="2:502"/> <lb/> after him, <em>Buddhavarman</em>. It is evident, as Professor Hultzsch has remarked, (above, <lb/> p. 342), that <em>Aśōkavarman</em> “can scarcely be considered a historical person, but appears <lb/> to be a modification of the ancient <em>Maurya</em> king <em>Aśōka</em>.” <em>Kāḷabhartṛi</em> is a possible <lb/> synonym of <em>Kāṇagōpa</em>, who is mentioned in the <em>Kāśākuḍi</em> plates, in the group of kings <lb/> that ruled after <em>Aśōkavarman</em>. Vīrakūrcha, the grandson of <em>Kāḷabhartṛi (Kāṇa-<lb break="no"/>gōpa)</em>, must be the <em>Vīrakōrchavarman</em> whose name occurs as that of the great grand-<lb break="no"/>father (of the donor) in an odd <em>Pallava</em> plate published by Professor Hultzsch in the <i>Epi-<lb break="no"/>graphia Indica</i> (Vol. I, p. 397 f.) and the same as Vīravarman of the Pīkira, Māṅgaḷūr, Uruvu-<lb break="no"/>palli and the Chendalūr grants, all of which belong practically to the same period. Vīrakūrcha <lb/> is stated to have married the daughter of a Nāga chief <note n="2:502-1">The account of the Pallava connection with a Nāga princess, here attributed to Vīrakūrcha, is already <lb/> mentioned of the progenitor Aśvatthāman himself, in the Rāyakōṭa plates of Skandaśishya-Vikramavarman <lb/> (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. V, p. 52). A similar story of the early Chōḷa king Kiḷḷi having taken to wife a Nāga prin- <lb/> cess, is related in the <i>Perumbāṇāṟṟuppaḍai</i>. The mythical account given in the <i>Mahābhārata</i>, of the epic hero <lb/> Arjuna marrying a Nāga queen, combined with what is stated of the Nāga connections in inscriptions and <lb/> literature, confirms the accepted belief, that the Nāgas were the original indigenous rulers of Southern India <lb/> and that they were subdued in course of time by foreign invaders from the North, eventually losing their <lb/> individuality by intermarriages with them.</note> and through her, to have acquired the <lb/> insignia of royalty. Their son <em>Skandaśishya</em> seized from king <em>Satyasēna</em> the <i>ghaṭikā</i> <lb/> of the Brāhmaṇas. The reference to a <i>ghaṭikā</i> at this early period is very interesting. It <lb/> occurs also in the Tālagunda inscription of Kakusthavarman which is ascribed by Professor <lb/> Kielhorn to about the first half of the 6th century A.D. <note n="2:502-2"><i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. VIII, p. 26. According to the Kāñchī inscription of Vikramāditya II, Conjeeveram <lb/> continued to be the seat of a <i>ghaṭikā</i> in the beginning of the 8th century A.D. (<i>ibid.</i>, Vol. III, p. 360, note 4). <lb/> The hill at Sholinghur in the North Arcot district is known as Ghaṭikāchala, perhaps on account of its having <lb/> also been the seat of a <i>ghaṭikā</i>.</note> <em>Skandaśishya</em> is perhaps <lb/> identical with the Pallava king of the same name, who is referred to in one of the <em>Tiruk-<lb break="no"/>kaṛukkuṉṟam</em> inscriptions <note n="2:502-3"><i>Ibid.</i> Vol., III, p. 277 f.</note>, as having made a gift to the holy temple of <em>Mūlasthāna</em> at <lb/> that village. If <em>Skandaśishya</em> is synonymous with <em>Skandavarman</em> as suggested by <lb/> Mr. Venkayya in his article on the Tirukkaṛukkuṉṟam inscription, we shall have to identify <lb/> him with Skandavarman II, particularly because the two generations after him supplied by <lb/> the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates would, in this case, be the same as those found in the <em>Chenda-<lb break="no"/>lūr</em> plates of Kumāravishṇu II. <note n="2:502-4"><i>Ibid.</i>, Vol. VIII, p. 233 f.</note> Satyasēna, the king from whom <em>Skandaśishya</em> seized the <lb/> <i>ghaṭikā</i>, remains unidentified. Kumāravishṇu, the son of <em>Skandaśishya</em>, is next stated <lb/> to have captured <em>Kāñchī</em>, and his son <em>Buddhavarman</em> to have been the conqueror of <lb/> the <em>Chōḷas</em>.</p>

<p>Mr. Venkayya mentions two distinct periods in early <em>Pallava</em> history, viz. (1) the period <lb/> in which their grants are recorded in the <em>Prākṛit</em> language and (2) that in which the grants <lb/> are in <em>Sanskṛit</em>. <note n="2:502-5"><i>Archaeological Survey Report</i> for 1906-7, pp. 217—43.</note> The first has been tentatively assigned to the beginning of the 4th century <lb/> A.D. Evidently, the break suggested at the beginning of verse 5 in the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> <lb/> plates with the words “<em>Aśōkavarman</em> and others,” included this earlier period of the <lb/> <em>Prākṛit</em> charters, and counted within it such names as <em>Śivaskandavarman, Vijayaskan-<lb break="no"/>davarman, Vijayabuddhavarman, Buddhyaṅkura</em> and <em>Vishṇugōpa</em>. The <em>Sans-<lb break="no"/>kṛit</em> charters, which are to be referred probably to the 5th and the 6th centuries of the Chris-<lb break="no"/>tian era, supply the names of a number of <em>Pallava</em> kings who may now be arranged in order of<pb n="2:503"/> <lb/> succession, with the help of the information given in the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates. The capture, <lb/> or rather the re-capture of <em>Kāñchī</em> attributed to <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> in these plates confirms <lb/> Mr. Venkayya's suggestion that that town was not the <em>Pallava</em> capital for some time during <lb/> the interval between the <em>Prākṛit</em> period and the later <em>Sanskṛit</em> period. <em>Kāḷabhartṛi <lb/> (Kāṇagōpa)</em> may have been the first of the kings of the second period which lasted down to <lb/> <em>(Kāṇagōpa)</em> may have been the first of the kings of the second period which lasted down to <lb/> <em>Buddhavarman</em> according to our plates, or down to his son <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> II according <lb/> to the <em>Chendalūr</em> plates. The question however arises whether <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> (I) of the <lb/> <em>Chendalūr</em> and the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates has to be identified with <em><i>Yuvamahārāja</i> Vish-<lb break="no"/>ṇugōpavarman</em> or to be treated as still another son of <em>Skandaśishya</em> (<em>Skandavarman</em> <lb/> II). The former alternative was suggested by Mr. Venkayya together with the further suppo-<lb break="no"/>sition that <em>Buddhavarman</em> and <em>Siṁhavarman</em> II may have been brothers. <note n="2:503-1"><i>Ind. Ant</i>., Vol. XXXVII, p. 284, foot-note 48.</note> But as the <lb/> names <em>Vishṇugōpa</em> and <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> are mentioned simultaneously together among <lb/> <em>Pallava</em> ancestors, as for instance, in the <em>Vāyalūr</em> pillar inscription of the time of <em>Rāja-<lb break="no"/>siṁha</em>, <note n="2:503-2">Madras Epigraphical Report for 1909, Part II, paragraph 17.</note> we may presume, perhaps tentatively, <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> I to be a third son of <lb/> <em>Skandavarman</em> II. The following revised pedigree of the <em>Pallava</em> kings based on the <lb/> <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates and the <em>Sanskṛit</em> charters of Pīkira, Māṅgaḷūr, Uruvupalli and <lb/> Chendalūr, is given provisionally, subject to the identifications and suggestions made above:—</p>

<table>[C1]Kāḷabhartṛi (Kāṇagōpa) [C1]Chūtapallava <lb/> (perhaps, a surname of Skandavarman I <lb/> mentioned in the Uruvupalli <lb/> grant) [C1]Vīrakūrcha (Vīrakōrchavarman or Vīravarman) [C1]Skandaśishya (Skandavarman II) [C1]Siṁhavarman I [C2]<i>Yuvamahārāja-</i> <lb/> Vishṇugōpa or <lb/> Vishṇugōpavarman [C3]Kumāravishṇu I [C1]Skandavarman III [C2]Siṁhavarman II [C3]Buddhavarman [C1]Nanḍivarman <note n="2:503-3">The names Nandivarman, Skandavarman III, and Siṁhavarman I are taken from a grant published by <lb/> Professor Kielhorn (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. III, pp. 142 ff.) and suspected by him to be a spurious document.</note> [C2]Kumāravishṇu II</table>

<p>After v. 8 we are again introduced to another gap in the succession in which were included <lb/> a host of kings such as <em>Vishṇugōpa</em> <note n="2:503-4">A Pallava copper-plate grant from the Guntur district recently examined, belongs to the time of a <lb/> certain Vishṇugōpavarman II whose father was Siṁhavarman, a son of Vishṇugōpavarman I and grandson <lb/> of Kandavarman. I have assigned this to the period subsequent to Kumāravishṇu II of the Chendalūr plates <lb/> (Madras Epigraphical Report for 1914, p. 82).</note> and others. Then appeared a king named <em>Nandi-<lb break="no"/>varman</em> I who brought under his control a powerful snake apparently called <i>Dṛishṭivisha</i>. <note n="2:503-5">The influence of the Nāgas who, as already suggested, must have been the original rulers of Southern <lb/> India apparently continued down to the time of Nandivarman of about the 6th century A.D. In later times <lb/> the Sindas of Yelburga (Dr. Fleet's <i>Dynasties of the Kanarese districts</i>, p. 572) and the Chhindas of Bastar traced <lb/> their origin to the serpents (<i>nāga</i>).</note> <lb/> In verse 10, <em>Siṁhavarman</em>, the father of <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em>, is introduced,—no connection <lb/> being specified between himself and the <em>Nandivarman</em> just mentioned. <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> <lb/> was the conqueror of the <em>Chōḷa</em> country which was fertilized by the river Cauvery.<pb n="2:504"/></p>

<p>What follows of the <em>Pallava</em> genealogy is not new. It is a repetition of the account <lb/> already supplied by the <em>Kāśākuḍi, Kūram</em> and the <em>Udayēndiram</em> plates. Stone in-<lb break="no"/>scriptions written in the <em>Pallava-Grantha</em> characters commence from this period,—a fact <lb/> which suggests that, with the conquest of <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em>, the <em>Pallavas</em> must have ex-<lb break="no"/>tended their dominion further south of Kāñchī into the <em>Chōḷa</em> country and adopted the Dravi-<lb break="no"/>dian language generally found mixed up with Sanskṛit in the later stone inscriptions. From <lb/> <em>Siṁhavishṇu's</em> son <em>Mahēndravarman</em> I was born <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> I. This King <lb/> whose conquest of <em>Vātāpi (Bādāmi)</em> and the Western Chalukya <em>Pulakēśin</em> II has fre-<lb break="no"/>quently been described, is stated in verse 11 to have defeated his enemies and to have taken <lb/> from them the pillar of victory standing at <em>Vātāpi</em>. <note n="2:504-1">It is not unlikely that this pillar of victory had been set up there by one of the ancestors of <lb/> Narasiṁhavarman himself. The fragmentary rock inscription at Bādāmi published by Dr. Fleet (<i>Ind. <lb/> Ant</i>., Vol. IX, p. 99f.) refers to Vātāpi, [Narasiṁ]havishṇu and to a pillar of victory (<i>jayastambha</i>). <lb/> Dr. Fleet is of opinion that Bādāmi (Vātāpi) “was originally the Western India stronghold of the <lb/> Pallavas and that it was from them that the Chalukyas wrested it. It is probable that Vātāpi was <lb/> temporarily recovered by the Pallavas from the Western Chalukyas after the reign of Pulakēśin II”.</note> Then came <em>Paramēśvaravar-<lb break="no"/>man</em> I, an enemy of the <em>Western Chalukya</em> king <em>Vikramāditya</em> I, whom, <lb/> according to the <em>Kūram</em> and the <em>Udayēndiram</em> plates, he defeated at <em>Peruvaḷanal-<lb break="no"/>lūr. Paramēśvara's</em> “son's son” was <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> II, who re-organised <lb/> the <i>ghaṭikā</i> of the Brāhmaṇas, and built a temple for <em>Śiva</em> “comparable with the <lb/> mountain <em>Kailāsa</em>”. This is a clear reference to the building of the <em>Kailāsanātha</em> <lb/> temple at Conjeeveram by <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> II. <note n="2:504-2">Recorded in an inscription round the central shrine of the temple; above, Vol. I, No. 24.</note> The latter's son was <em>Paramēśvara</em> <lb/> II. The usurpation of the <em>Pallava</em> throne by <em>Nandivarman</em> II, subsequent to the death <lb/> of <em>Paramēśvara</em> II, is clearly stated in verse 15. The distant relation that existed <lb/> between the usurper <em>Nandivarman</em> II and <em>Paramēśvara</em> II is described in the <lb/> <em>Kāśākuḍi</em> plates.</p>

<p>Two points in the account given above are worthy of note: (1) the omission of the <lb/> name <em>Mahēndravarman</em> II after <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> I and (2) the statement that <lb/> <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> II was the “son's son” <note n="2:504-3">The actual word <i>putra-sūnu</i> though used, very peculiarly, in place of the more common <i>pautra</i>, <lb/> leaves no doubt that the composer could not have intended any other term of relationship.</note> of <em>Paramēśvara</em> I. The latter is proba-<lb break="no"/>bly an error, since all the three published <em>Pallava</em> accounts agree in saying that <em>Nara-<lb break="no"/>siṁhavarman</em> II was the <i>son</i>, not the <i>grandson</i>, of <em>Paramēśvara</em> I. The former, <lb/> however, may be different. For although the <em>Kūram</em> plates call <em>Paramēśvaravarman</em> <lb/> I, the grandson of <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> I, still the doubtful way in which this relation-<lb break="no"/>ship is expressed in the <em>Kāśākuḍi</em> and the <em>Udayēndiram</em> plates, taken together with <lb/> the statement of the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates, makes it appear as if <em>Mahēndravar-<lb break="no"/>man</em> II and <em>Paramēśvaravarman</em> I were both sons of <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> I, thus <lb/> reducing the seven generations between <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> and <em>Paramēśvaravarman</em> <lb/> II, to six. The usurper <em>Nandivarman</em> II who, according to the <em>Kāśākuḍi</em> plates, was <lb/> sixth in descent from a brother of <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> could not at the time of his usur-<lb break="no"/>pation be a generation older than <em>Paramēśvaravarman</em> II whose kingdom he <lb/> usurped. Indeed, as hinted in the <em>Udayēndiram</em> plates, he must have been much <lb/> younger to justify his being called there the <i>son</i> of <em>Paramēśvaravarman</em>. Conse-<lb break="no"/>quently it appears probable that <em>Mahēndravarman</em> II and <em>Paramēśvaravarman</em> I <lb/> were actually brothers and that the succession after <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> I passed<pb n="2:505"/> <lb/> on directly to the latter, the former having, perhaps, died before him. Two <lb/> successions after the usurper <em>Nandivarman (Pallavamalla)</em> are further supplied <lb/> for the first time by the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates. <em>Nandivarman</em> II's son by <lb/> <em>Rēvā</em> was the <em>Pallava-Mahārāja Dantivarman</em> (verse 18). His queen was <lb/> the <em>Kadamba</em> princess <em>Aggaḷanimmaṭī</em>; from these, was born king <em>Nandivarman</em> <lb/> III, or according to the Tamil portion of the inscription, <em>Vijaya-Nandivarman</em>, in the <lb/> sixth year of whose reign the subjoined grant was made. No specific historical facts are <lb/> mentioned in connection with these kings. <em>Nandivarman</em> III is stated to have <lb/> “acquired the prosperity of the <em>Pallava</em> kingdom by the prowess of his (own) arms” <lb/> (verse 20). From this we may infer that the sovereignty over the <em>Pallava</em> kingdom had <lb/> now been keenly contested either by outsiders or by some direct descendents of the <lb/> <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> line.</p>

<p>In the Chingleput, North Arcot, South Arcot and Trichinopoly districts, there have been <lb/> discovered a number of stone records (more or less of the same age as the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> <lb/> plates) which refer themselves to the reigns of <em>Dantivarman, Dantivarma-Mahārāja, <lb/> Dantippōttaraśar</em> or <em>Vijaya-Dantivikramavarman</em>, and also of <em>Nandivarman</em> <lb/> with similar variations in the name. Again, the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates <note n="2:505-1">See Postscript.</note> supply the names <em>Danti-<lb break="no"/>varman</em>, (his son) <em>Nandivarman</em> and (his son) <em>Nṛipatuṅgadēva</em> or <em>Vijaya-Nṛipa-<lb break="no"/>tuṅgavarman</em>, as members of the <em>Pallava</em> family, among whose ancestors were <em>Vimala, <lb/> Koṅkaṇika</em> and others. From this latter statement Professor Hultzsch concluded that the <lb/> kings mentioned in the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates were different from the <em>Pallavas</em> of <em>Kāñchī</em> and were <lb/> only “<em>Pallava</em> by name but <em>Western Gaṅga</em> by descent.” It is now, therefore, diffcult to <lb/> say if the <em>Dantivarmans</em> and the <em>Nandivarmans</em> of the stone records mentioned above, <lb/> are to be identified with those mentioned in the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates, or with those of the <em>Vēlūr-<lb break="no"/>pāḷaiyam</em> plates or with both. Mr. Venkayya is inclined to connect the names in the <lb/> <em>Bāhūr</em> plates with those of the <em>Vēlūrpaḷaiyam</em> plates, and suggests that <em>Vijaya-Nṛipa-<lb break="no"/>tuṅgavarman</em> of the former was apparently the son of <em>Nandivarman</em> III of the latter. <lb/> Against this the only objection is the ancestry which, in the one case includes the clear <lb/> <em>Western Gaṅga</em> name (or surname) <em>Koṅkaṇika</em>, while in the other it does not. If, <lb/> however, Mr. Venkayya's suggestion is accepted, we must presume two facts to arrive at a <lb/> concurrent genealogy, and to connect the kings of stone records with those mentioned in <lb/> the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> and the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates. The prefix <i>kō-vijaya</i> and the suffix <i>vikrama-<lb break="no"/>varman</i> which are invariably found appended to the names of the kings in this series <lb/> must have been introduced for the first time by the usurper <em>Nandivarman Pallava-<lb break="no"/>malla</em>, who, we know, literally won the kingdom by victory (<i>vijaya</i>) and by prowess <lb/> (<i>vikrama)</i> <note n="2:505-2"><i>Vijaya</i> and <i>vikrama</i> as prefixes and suffixes of Pallava names occur in much earlier records <i>e.g.</i> in <lb/> names like Vijaya-Buddhavarman, Vijaya-Īśvaravarman and Mahēndravikramavarman; but here they do <lb/> not signify any distinct branch of kings.</note>, and that <em>Nṛipatuṅgavarman</em> who was decidedly the most powerful <note n="2:505-3"><i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. VIII, p. 293 and foot-note 3.</note> of this <lb/> last branch of the <em>Pallavas</em>, and a son of the <em>Rāshṭrakūṭa</em> princess Śaṅkhā, must have <lb/> contracted new relations with the <em>Western Gaṅgas</em> to justify the insertion of one or more <lb/> of the names of that dynasty among his <em>Pallava</em> ancestors. Even with these suppositions <lb/> granted, the identification of kings mentioned in stone records with the <em>Nandivarmans</em> <lb/> and <em>Dantivarmans</em> of the copper-plate grants presents peculiar difficulties. The script of<pb n="2:506"/> <lb/> the copper-plates, though of the same age with that of the stone inscriptions often <lb/> differs from it, <note n="2:506-1">See the remarks of Professor Hultzsch on the alphabet of the Rāyakōṭa plates in <i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. V, p. 49.</note> and the information supplied by the latter is so meagre that hardly any points <lb/> of contemporaneous nature that could help us in such identification, are forthcoming. In <lb/> the present state of our knowledge therefore, it may be hypothetically presumed that kings <lb/> of names <em>Nandivarman</em> and <em>Dantivarman</em> with or without the prefix <i>kō-vijaya</i> and the <lb/> suffix <i>vikramavarman</i>, may be taken to be one or the other of the immediate ancestors of <lb/> <em>Nṛipatuṅga-Vikramavarman</em>; while kings described as <em>Dantivarma-Mahārāja</em> <lb/> of the Bhāradvāja-<i>gōtra,</i> <note n="2:506-2">See below, p. 513, footnote 1.</note> <em>Dantivarman</em> and <em>Nandivarman</em> of the <i>Pallava-tilaka-kula,</i> <note n="2:506-3"><i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. XI, p. 157.</note> <lb/> and <em>Nandivarman</em> “who conquered [his enemies] at <em>Teḷḷāṟu</em>,” <note n="2:506-4">This was the hero of the Tamil work <i>Nandikkalambagam; Ind. Ant</i>., Vol. XXXVII, p. 171.</note> have to be kept distinct.</p>

<p>In conclusion it may be stated, by way of a resumé, that the <em>Pallava</em> history covers <lb/> four separate periods extending from about the 4th to the 9th century A.D. with three gaps <lb/> which remain yet to be filled up satisfactorily by later researches. These are (1) the period <lb/> of the <em>Prākṛit</em> charters; (2) after a gap of a little more than a century, the period of the <lb/> <em>Sanskṛit</em> charters; (3) after another gap (or rather two gaps) of about the same length <lb/> the period of stone inscriptions when, the <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> line was predominant; and (4) <lb/> the last period when the <em>Nandivarman</em> line (developing later, into what has been called <lb/> the <em>Gaṅga-Pallava</em> line) was powerful until it was completely crushed by the Chōḷas. <lb/> A table of the kings of the <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> line and of the collateral branch of <em>Nandivar-<lb break="no"/>man Pallavamalla</em> down to <em>Nṛipatuṅgavarman</em> of the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates is appended <lb/> below:—</p>

<table>[C1]Nandivarman I [C1]Siṁhavarman [C1]Siṁhavishṇu [C2]Bhīmavarman [C1]Mahēndravarman I [C2]Buddhavarman [C1]Narasiṁhavarman I [C2]Ādityavarman [C1]Mahēndravarman II [C2]Paramēśvaravarman I [C3]Gōvindavarman [C1]Narasiṁhavarman II [C2]Hiraṇya (I) [C1]Paramēśvaravarman II [C2]Mahēndravarman III [C3]Nandivarman II Pallavamalla [C1]Dantivarman or <lb/> Vijaya-Dantivikramavarman <lb/> (Hiraṇyavarman II) <note n="2:506-5">See below, p. 518.</note> [C1]Nandivarman III, <lb/> Vijaya-Nandivarman or <lb/> Vijaya-Nandivikramavarman [C1]Nṛipatuṅgavarman or <lb/> Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</table>

<p>The object of the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> grant was the gift of the village <em>Śrīkaṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> <lb/> or <em>Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> to a temple of Śiva built at that village by a certain <em>Yajñabhaṭṭa</em> <lb/> or <em>Śaṉṉakkuṟi Yajñabhaṭṭa</em>, surnamed <em>Bappa-Bhaṭṭāraka</em>, <note n="2:506-6">This surname occurs in early Sanskṛit charters of the Pallavas and has been translated “lord- <lb/> father”. Perhaps the term was one of high respect applied to spiritual preceptors, and it is not unlikely that <lb/> Yajñabhaṭṭa stood in this relation to king Nandivarman III. The spiritual preceptor of Nandivarman <lb/> Pallavamalla is also called Bappa-Bhaṭṭāraka in the Kāśākuḍi plates (text, 1. 78).</note> in the sixth year of the<pb n="2:507"/> <lb/> reign of king <em>Nandivarman</em> III. The request (<i>vijñapti</i>) was made by the <em>Chōḷa-Mahā-<lb break="no"/>rāja <note n="2:507-1">The Chōḷas at this period must have been occupying a subordinate position. Neither literature nor <lb/> inscriptions afford any clue to the identification of this Chōḷa-Mahārāja Kumārāṅkuśa, who was evidently a <lb/> feudatory of king Nandivarman III. The name Kumārāṅkuśa-Gāvuṇḍa occurs among the signatories in a <lb/> record of Parāntaka I (No. 457 of the Madras Epigraphical collection for 1911).</note> Kumārāṅkuśa</em>, while the executor (<i>ājñapti</i> or <i>āṇatti</i>) was the minister <em>Namba</em> <lb/> (in Tamil, <em>Iraiyūr-uḍaiyāṉ-Nambaṉ</em>) of the <em>Agradatta</em> family. The donee was the <lb/> <em>Mahādēva (Śiva)</em> temple of <em>Yajñēśvara</em> at <em>Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em>. Verse 28 informs <lb/> us that the composer of the <i>praśasti</i> <note n="2:507-2">Strangely enough this series of the latest Pallava grants have all been registered as <i>praśasti</i>; see above, <lb/> p. 345.</note> was the <i>Māhēśvara</i> <em>Manōdhīra</em>. Verse 31 and the <lb/> <em>Tamil</em> sentence following it, supply the name of <em>Pēraya</em>, a clever carpenter of <lb/> <em>Maṉaichchēri</em> in <em>Kachchippēḍu</em> (Conjeeveram), who engraved the writing on these <lb/> plates.</p>

<p>One point of great interest in the Tamil portion of the grant is the long list of exemp-<lb break="no"/>tions (<i>parihāra</i>) and the written declaration (<i>vyavasthā</i>) with which <em>Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> <lb/> was made over to the temple assembly (<i>paraḍai</i>, Skt. <i>parishad</i>). The former included items <lb/> of collection whose significance is not quite clear, but which, as the inscription says, the king <lb/> “could receive and enjoy.” It appears as though most of the items here mentioned were <lb/> not necessarily sources of revenue to the State, as now understood, but only obligatory services <lb/> which the king could enforce on the people for the benefit of the community. By the written <lb/> declaration the donee was permitted to build (without any special license) mansions of burnt <lb/> brick; to grow <i>Artimissia, Andropogan Muricatum</i>, red lilies and <i>uḷḷi</i> in gardens; to plant <lb/> cocoanut trees in groves; to sink reservoirs and wells; to use large oil-presses; and to <lb/> prohibit toddy-drawers from tapping for toddy, the cocoanut and the palmyra trees planted <lb/> within the four boundaries of the village.</p>

<p>The village <em>Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> is identical with <em>Kāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> in the Poṉṉēri tāluk <lb/> of the Chingleput district; <em>Nāyaṟu-nāḍu</em> of <em>Puṛaṟ-kōṭṭam</em>, in which the village is <lb/> stated to have been situated, takes its name from the village Nāyar of the same tāluk, about <lb/> 8(1/2) miles south-west of <em>Kāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em>. In the British Museum plates of the <em>Vijayanagara</em> <lb/> king <em>Sadāśivarāya</em> of the 16th century A.D., <em>Nāyattu-nāḍu</em> (<i>i.e.</i>, <em>Nāyaṟu-nāḍu</em>) is <lb/> described as being a sub-division of <em>Puḷali-kōṭaka</em> (<i>i.e.</i>, <em>Puṛaṟ-kōṭṭam</em>). <note n="2:507-3"><i>Ep. Ind</i>, Vol. IV., p. 8f.</note></p>

<edition>

<h4 ignore="yes">TEXT. <note n="2:507-4">From the original plates and a set of ink-impressions.</note></h4>

<h4><i>Plate I</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:507:98:1"><de>svasti śrīḥ namaśśivāya ||—nityam vyāpi nirāmayam paramayā bhaktyādhigamyaṁ śivam vācāndūramaci-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:2"><de>ntyamakṣayamiti prodgīyamānam budhaiḥ [|*] saṁyamyendriyavāhinīṁ yativarairyyanmṛi[gya]te santa-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:3"><de>ta[m] tejastatparamārtthasaccirataranniśreyasāyāstu va[ḥ*] ||—[1*] śarvvāṇīkucakuṁkumāṁka[śu]bhaka</de><note n="2:507-5">The three letters <de>[śu]bhaka,</de> which were evidently written by mistake, are to be cancelled.</note><de>subha-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:4"><de>gāḥ proddāmadarppāmaradveṣivrātavadhūprasādhanaparāmṛiṣṭiprasaṁgocitāḥ [|*] yuṣmānpāntu yu-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:5"><de>gāntavahnivilasaddīprāstracakrāśriraṁ śrīkaṇṭhasya śikhaṇḍaratnaruciravyāḷāṁgadā bāha-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:6"><de>vaḥ [|| 2*] āsīdaṁbujanābhanābhikamalā[dbra]hmā tatopyaṁgirā[sta]smāddevagurustataśśubhamatiśśaṁyu-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:7"><de>stataśśāṁ[yava]ḥ [|*]</de><note n="2:507-6">Read <de>tasmāº</de>.</note><de>stasmātku[m]bhasamudbhava[ḥ*] smararipo[rdrau]ṇistatoṁśaḥ kramādasmādvismayanīyakīrttira-</de></l>

<l n="2:507:98:8"><de>khila[kṣmā]vallabhaḥ pallavaḥ [|| 3*] vaṁśastatovattata</de><note n="2:507-7">Read <de>ºvarttataº</de>.</note><de>pallavānāṁ rakṣāvidhidhvastavipalla[vā]nā[m] [|*] bhū-</de><pb n="2:508"/></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:508:98:9"><de>bhārakhedālasapannagendrasāhāyyaniṣṇātabhujārggaḷānām [|| 4*] aśokavarmmādiṣu devabhūyaṁ ga-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:10"><de>te[ṣu vaṁśye]ṣvatha pārtthiveṣu [|*] vaṁśasya</de><note n="2:508-1">Read <de>cūḍāº</de>.</note><de>cūḷāmaṇirāvirāsīdbharttendirāyā iva kāḷabharttā ||—[5*]</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:11"><de>tatsutādajani cūtapallavādvīrakūrcca iti viśrutāhvayaḥ [|*] yaḥ phaṇīndrasutayā sahāgrahīdrāja-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:12"><de>cihnamakhilaṁ yaśodhanaḥ [|| 6*] anvavāyanabhaśrandra[ḥ*] skandaśiṣyastatobhavatvijānāṁ</de><note n="2:508-2">Read <de>ºbhavat | dvijānāṁ</de>.</note><de>ghaṭikāṁ rājñassatya-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:13"><de>senātjahāra</de><note n="2:508-3">Read <de>ºsenajjahāra</de>.</note><de>yaḥ |[| 7*] gṛihītakāñcīnagarastatobhūtkumāraviṣṇussamareṣu ji[ṣṇu]ḥ [|*] bharttā bhuvo-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:14"><de>bhūdatha buddhavammā</de><note n="2:508-4">Read <de>ºvarmmā</de>.</note><de>yaścoḷasainyārṇṇavavāḍabāgniḥ <note n="2:508-5">Read <de>ºbāḍabāgniḥ</de>.</note> [|| 8*] saviṣṇugope ca narendrabṛinde gate</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:15"><de>tatojāyata nandivarmmā [|*] anugrahādyena pinākapāṇeḥ</de><note n="2:508-6">Read <de>praṇātato</de>.</note><de>pranarttito dṛiṣṭiviṣaḥ phaṇīndraḥ [|| 9*] atha <lb/> prathitavikra-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:16"><de>mo jagati siṁhavarmmāhvayānnṛipātparamadāpahādajani siṁhaviṣṇujayīḥ</de><note n="2:508-7">Read <de>ºviṣṇurjayī</de>.</note><de>[|*] lasatkramukamaṇḍalāḥ kaḷama <note n="2:508-8">Read <de>kalama</de>.</note>-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:17"><de>kānanālaṁkṛitāḥ kavīratanayāñcitāssapadi yena coḷā hṛitāḥ [|| 10*]</de><note n="2:508-9">Read <de>tadātmajāº</de>.</note><de>tadānmajādāvirabhūnmahendrādupe-</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:508:98:18"><de><note n="2:508-10">Read <de>ºkīrttirnnaraº</de>.</note>ndrakīrttinnarasiṁhavarmmā [|*] vātāpimaddhye vijitāriva[rgga][ḥ*] sthitañjayastambhamalambhayadyaḥ [|| 11*] tataḥ <lb/> paramadaddhvaṁ-</de><note n="2:508-11">The <i>anusvāra</i> stands at the beginning of the next line.</note></l>

<l n="2:508:98:19"><de>sī babhūva parameśvaraḥ [|*] cāḷukyakṣitibhṛitsainyadhvāntadhvaṁsadivākaraḥ [|| 12*] tatputrasūnurnnarasiṁhavarmmā pu-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:20"><de><note n="2:508-12">Read <de>ºnarvyadhāº</de>.</note><de>naryyadhādyo ghaṭikāṁ dvijānāṁ [|*] śilāmayaṁ veśma-śaśāṁkamauleḥ kailāsakatpañca</de><note n="2:508-13">Read <de>ºkalpañca mahendrakalpaḥ</de>.</note>mahendraka-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:21"><de>tpaḥ [|| 13*] tatsūnurbhūbhṛitāṁ [m]ānyo babhūva parameśvaraḥ [|*] mānavena krameṇorvvīmaśādyaḥ kaliśāsanaḥ <lb/> [|| 14*] tada-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:22"><de>nantaramanvayasya lakṣmīñcatura[mbho]nidhivāsasā sahorvvyā [|*] samavāpadaśeṣapūrvva[bhū]-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:23"><de><note n="2:508-14">Read <de>ºsemalanaº</de>.</note>bhṛidguṇasaṁmeḷanadhāma nandivarmmā [|| 15*] tasyāṁburāśeriva vāhinīnānnāthasya nānāguṇara[tna]-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:24"><de>dhāmnaḥ [|*] dhīrasya bhūbhṛidvaralabdhajanmā reveva revā mahiṣī babhūva [|| 16*]</de><note n="2:508-15">Read <de>ºbhūttriº</de>.</note><de>tasyāmāvirabhūtrilokaparira-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:25"><de><note n="2:508-16">Read <de>ºkṣārtthaḥ</de>.</note>[kṣā]tthaḥ kṣamānandanaḥ</de><note n="2:508-17">Read <de>ºnandanassākṣāº</de>.</note><de>sākṣādaṁburuhekṣaṇassvayamiha śrīdantivarmmā nṛipaḥ [|*] śauryyatyāgakṛitajña-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:26"><de>tādiramalo yasminguṇānāṁ gaṇaḥ pra[ā]pta[ā]nyonyasamāgamotsava iva prāpatpra[ti*]ṣṭhāñci-</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:508:98:27"><de>rāt [|| 17*] prakhyātasya kada[mba]vaṁ[śa*]tilakasyorvvīpaterātmajā vīrāṇāṁ prathamasyaṁ pallavamahārāja-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:28"><de>sya tejasvinaḥ [|*] ākhyāmaggaḷanimmaṭīti [da*]dhatī śuddhānvavāyocitā [bha]rttustasya bhuvo</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:29"><de>babhūva mahiṣī gaurīva jetuḥ pura[ā*]m |—[18*] śrīnandivarmmāṇamasūta seyaṁ sandhyeva te-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:30"><de>jasvinamambikeva [|*] kumāramatyadbhutaśaktiyuktaṁ yathā jayantaṁ jayinaṁ śacīva |—[19*] utkhāta-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:31"><de>khaḍganihatadvipakumbhamuktāmuktāphalaprapāsite</de><note n="2:508-18">Read <de>ºprahasite</de>.</note><de>samarāṁgaṇe yaḥ [|] śatrū-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:32"><de>nnihatya samavāpadananyalavyāṁ</de><note n="2:508-19">Read <de>ºlabhyāṁ rājyaśriyaṁ</de>.</note><de>rājyaśiśrayaṁ svabhujavikramadarppaśālī |—[20*] u[dya]ānaṁ ma-</de></l>

<l n="2:508:98:33"><de>dhunā guṇaiḥ kulabhuvaḥ</de><note n="2:508-20">Read <de>ºbhūvaśśīlena vāmekṣaṇā</de>.</note><de>śīlena vāmertṣaṇā tyāgenārtthapatiśśrutena vinaya-</de><pb n="2:509"/></l>

<l n="2:509:98:34"><de>ssūryyeṇa</de><note n="2:509-1">Read <de>padmākaraḥ</de>.</note><de>patmākaraḥ [|*] prāleyadyutinā payodasamayāpāye nabhaḥprāṁgaṇannai-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:35"><de>vaṁ [bhā]ti tathā yathā jagadidaṁ yena</de><note n="2:509-2">Read <de>kṣamāº</de>.</note><de>tṣamābandhunā [| 21*] pṛithvīpālasya tasya <note n="2:509-3">Read <de>prāthataº</de>.</note>pradhitagu-</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:509:98:36"><de>ṇaga[ṇo] bappabhaṭṭārakāgyaśśāstre</de><note n="2:509-4">Read <de>kākhyaº</de>.</note><de>vede ca sāṁkhye prakaṭitamahimā yajña-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:37"><de><note n="2:509-5">Read <de>ºbhidhānaḥ | śrīº</de>.</note>bhaṭṭābhidhānaśśrīkaṭṭuppa</de><ta>ḷḷi</ta><de>nāmni śrutavina[ya*]dharastuṁgakailāsakalpaṁ grā-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:38"><de>me</de><note n="2:509-6">Read <de>ºmaulerbhavanaº</de>.</note><de>bālendumaulerbhbhavanamakṛita yadbhaktiyogapra[tī]taḥ |—[22*] pitābhavadyasya</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:39"><de>viśuddhabuddhirggirāmiveśaśśivadāsanāmā [|*] mātābhavadyasya guṇaissamaśrai-</de><note n="2:509-7">Read <de>ºssamagraiº</de>.</note></l>

<l n="2:509:98:40"><de>rggarīyasī [dre]ṇamaṇirmmahīva |—[23*] pitāmaho yasya viśuddhavṛittirdvijāgragaṇya-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:41"><de>stamasānnipāntā</de><note n="2:509-8">Read <de>ºnnihantā</de>.</note><de>[|*] nidhiḥ kalānāmi[va] yajñanāmā babhūva vikhyātayaśaḥprakāśaḥ [|| 24*] tasmai</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:42"><de>devāya śarvvāya pūjāsatrādikarmaṇe [|*]</de><note n="2:509-9">Read <de>ºsodādgāº</de>.</note><de>sodāggrāmanti</de><ta>rukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</ta><de>nāmāna-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:43"><de>mīśvaraḥ [|*]—[25*] vijñaptimatrākṛita</de><note n="2:509-10">Read <de>ºcūḍāmaṇiº</de>.</note><de>coḷavaṁśacūḷāmaṇirvviśrutavikramaśrīḥ [|*] dhīraḥ kumā-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:44"><de>rāṁkuśanāmadheyastyāgena rādheyasamaḥ kṛitajñaḥ |—[26*] atrājñaptirabhūnmantrī na-</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate IVa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:509:98:45"><ta>m</ta><de>panāmā mahīpateḥ [|*] agradattānvayavyomaśarannīhāradīdhiti[ḥ*] |—[27*] vāgmanaḥ[ka]ā-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:46"><de>yakarmmāṇi parārtthānyeva yasya saḥ [|*]māheśvaro manodhīraḥ praśastiṁ kṛita-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:47"><de>vānima[ām] |—[28*]</de> <ta>puḻaṟkoṭṭattu nāyaṟunāṭṭuttirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷippañcavaram āi-<lb break="no"/>rakkā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:48"><ta>ṭi itu kovicaiya</ta> <gr>nantivarmma</gr><ta>ṟku yāṇṭu āṟāvatu coḻa</ta><gr>ma</gr><ta>hārājar viṇṇappattā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:49"><ta>l iraiyūr uṭaiyāṉ nampaṉāṇattiyākattirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷiccaṉṉa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:50"><ta>kkuṟi ya</ta><gr>jñabhaṭṭa</gr><ta>[r]eṭuppitta ya</ta><gr>jñeśva</gr><ta>rattu</ta> <gr>mahāde</gr><ta>varkku nāṭṭu nīṅkalā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:51"><ta>y uṭpuravāy tevar</ta><gr>dā</gr><ta>ṉamākap peṟṟataṟkup peṟṟa</ta> <gr>parihāra</gr><ta>m nāṭāṭciyum</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:52"><ta>ūrāṭciyum puravupoṉṉum tirumukkāṇamum vaṭṭināḻiyum putāḻiyum taṭṭu-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:53"><ta>kāyamum īḻampūṭciyum iṭaippūṭciyum maṉṟupāṭumt <note n="2:509-11">Cancel <ta>t</ta>.</note> tarakum taṟikkū[ṟ]ai-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IVb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:509:98:54"><ta>yum kūlamum nallāvum nallerutum nallāṭum nāṭukāvalum ūṭupokkum</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:55"><ta>kallāṇakkāṇamum kucakkāṇamum pāṟaikkāṇam paṭṭiṉaceriyum maṟṟumivvū-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:56"><note n="2:509-12">Read <ta>rellai</ta>.</note> <ta>raillai u[ḷ*]ḷakappaṭṭatu kottoṭṭuṇṇappālatellām ev[vak]aippaṭṭa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:57"><ta>tum kok[k]oḷḷappeṟāte ivya</ta><gr>jñeśva</gr><ta>rattu</ta> <gr>mahāde</gr><ta>vareyi <note n="2:509-13">Read <ta>ºrēy</ta>.</note> koḷḷappe-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:58"><ta>ṟṟataṟkuppeṟṟa</ta> <gr>vyavasthai[|*]</gr> <ta>cuṭṭoṭṭāl māṭamāḷikai eṭukkappeṟuvatā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:59"><ta>kavum tamaṉakamum iruveliyum ceṅkaḻunīrum uḷḷiyum naṭappeṟuvatākavum kāvute-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:60"><ta>ṅkiṭappeṟuvatākavum turavukiṇaṟiḻittappeṟuvatākavum peruñcekkiṭappeṟu-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:61"><ta>vatākavum ivvūrellai u[ḷ*]ḷiṭṭa teṅkum paṉaiyum ivarkaḷ maṉamiṉṟi īḻavareṟap-</ta></l>

<l n="2:509:98:62"><ta>peṟātārākavum ivvakaippaṭṭa</ta> <gr>vyavasthai</gr><ta>yiṉūṭu</ta><note n="2:509-14">Read <ta>ºṉōṭu</ta>.</note> <gr>yajñeśvara</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>mahāde</gr><ta>vark-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate V</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:509:98:63"><ta>kuttevatāṉamāy</ta> <gr>sarvvaparihāramāka paraṭatti</gr> <ta>ceṉṟatu</ta> |— <de>sukṛitamidamajasraṁ</de><note n="2:509-15">Read <de>rakṣaº</de>.</note><de>ratṣate-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:64"><de>ti</de><note n="2:509-16">Read <de>kṣitīśā</de>.</note><de>tṣitīśāssakalanṛipatiketussoyamāgāmino vaḥ [|*] haracaraṇasaro[jo]-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:65"><de>ttaṁsacihnena mūrddhnā mukuḷitakara[pa]tmo</de><note n="2:509-17">Read <de>ºpadmo</de>.</note><de>vandate nandivarmmā |—[29*] sarvvānetānbhāvinaḥ</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:66"><de>pā[rtthi]vendrānbhūyo bhūyaḥ prārtthayatyeṣa rāmaḥ [|*] sāmānyoyandharmmasetunnṛipāṇāṁ</de><note n="2:509-18">Read <de>ºrnnṛipāṇāṁ</de>.</note><de>kā-</de></l>

<l n="2:509:98:67"><de>lekāle pa[ā]lanīyo</de><note n="2:509-19">Read <de>bhavīdbhaḥ</de>.</note><de>bhavanbhiḥ [|]—[30*] karakauśalakṛitayaśasā</de> <ta>ciṟṟa</ta> <de>yaputre-</de><pb n="2:510"/></l>

<l n="2:510:98:68"><de>ṇa patrasaṁghoyam [|*] likhitaṁ</de><note n="2:510-1">Read <de>likhitaḥ</de>.</note><de>perayanāmnā sthapatikulavyomacandreṇa [|]—[31*]</de> <ta>kaccip-</ta></l>

<l n="2:510:98:69"><ta>peṭṭaimmaṉaiccerikkā</ta><gr>ṣṭha</gr><ta>kārimakaṉ perayaṉ eḻuttu</ta> |—</l>

<translation>

<h4 ignore="yes">TRANSLATION.</h4>

<p>Hail! Prosperty! Adoration to Śiva !</p>

<p>(<i>Verse</i> 1.) May that effulgence which is the existence absolute, which is sung by the wise <lb/> to be eternal, universal, infallible, accessible (<i>only</i>) to highest devotion, benevolent, beyond the <lb/> reach of words and thoughts, and endless and which, the best of sages ever strive to attain by <lb/> putting a restraint upon the currents of (<i>their</i>) sense-perceptions,—grant you permanent bliss !</p>

<p>(V. 2.) May (<i>they</i>) always protect you, the arms of <em>Śrīkaṇṭha</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Śiva</em>), which are <lb/> lovely by bearing on them the marks of saffron from the breasts of <em>Śarvāṇī</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Pārvatī</em>), <lb/> which delight themselves in the work of removing the ornaments (<i>from the body</i>) of the wives <lb/> of the highly conceited hoards of the enemies of gods, <note n="2:510-2">This is an elegant expression for saying that the enemies of gods (<i>i.e.</i>, the demons) were destroyed by <lb/> Śiva. It is usual with Hindu women to remove their ornaments and to give up their toilet after the death <lb/> of their husbands.</note> which (hold) a number of weapons <lb/> that shine with the brilliance of the fire at the end of the world and wear armlets of serpents <lb/> radiant with gems in (<i>their</i>) crests !</p>

<p>(V. 3.) From the lotus-(like) navel of the lotus-navelled <em>(Vishṇu)</em>, was (<i>produced</i>) <lb/> <em>Brahmā</em>; from him (<i>was born</i>) <em>Aṅgiras</em>; from him, the preceptor of the gods <em>(Bṛihas-<lb break="no"/>pati)</em>; from him, the good-natured <em>Śaṁyu</em>; from him <em>Śāṁyava</em> (<i>i.e.</i> Bharadvāja); from <lb/> him the pitcher-born (Drōṇa); from him <em>Drauṇi</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Aśvatthāman</em>), who is of the <lb/> essence of <em>(Śiva)</em>, the enemy of Cupid; and from him in (<i>the same</i>) order (<i>came</i>) <em>Pallava</em>, <lb/> the lord of the whole earth, whose fame was bewildering.</p>

<p>(V. 4.) Thence, came into existence the race of the <em>Pallavas</em>, who by the law of <lb/> protection (<i>which they adopted</i>) removed (<i>even</i>) the slightest distress (<i>of their subjects</i>); and <lb/> whose bar-like arms were skilled in rendering assistance to the lord of serpents who was <lb/> fatigued by the labour of (<i>carrying on his head</i>) the burden of the earth.</p>

<p>(V. 5.) After kings, such as <em>Aśōkavarman</em> (<i>and others</i>), born in that family, had <lb/> attained god-hood (<i>i.e. died</i>), was born <em>Kāḷabhartṛi</em>, the head-jewel of (<i>his</i>) family, like <lb/> <em>(Vishṇu)</em> the husband of <em>Indirā</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Lakshmī</em>).</p>

<p>(V. 6.) From his son <em>Chūtapallava</em>, was produced <em>Vīrakūrcha</em>, of celebrated name, <lb/> who simultaneously with (<i>the hand of</i>) the daughter of the chief of serpents grasped also <lb/> the complete insignia of royalty and became famous.</p>

<p>(V. 7.) From him came <em>Skandaśishya</em>, the moon in the sky of (<i>his</i>) family, who seized <lb/> from king <em>Satyasēna</em> the <i>ghaṭikā</i> of the twice-born (<i>i.e.</i> Brāhmaṇas).</p>

<p>(V. 8.) From him came <em>Kumāravishṇu</em> who captured the city of <em>Kāñchī</em> and was <lb/> victorious in battles. Then became king, <em>Buddhavarman</em>, the submarine fire to the <lb/> ocean-like army of the <em>Chōḷas</em>.</p>

<p>(V. 9.) And after a host of kings including <em>Vishṇugōpa</em> had passed away, was born <lb/> <em>Nandivarman</em>, who with the favour of (<i>the god</i>) <em>Pinākapāṇi (Śiva)</em> caused to dance a <lb/> powerful snake whose poison was in (<i>its</i>) eyes (<i>Dṛishṭivisha</i>).</p>

<p>(V. 10.) Then from the king named <em>Śiṁhavarman</em>, who wiped off the pride of (<i>his</i>) <lb/> enemies, was born the victorious <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> whose prowess was widely known on earth. <lb/> He quickly seized the country of the <em>Chōḷas</em>, embellished by the daughter of <em>Kavīra</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <lb/> the river Kāvērī), whose ornaments are the forests of paddy (<i>fields</i>) and where (<i>are found</i>) <lb/> brilliant groves of areca (<i>palms</i>). <pb n="2:511"/></p>

<p>(V. 11.) From his son <em>Mahēndra</em> was born <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> (I), famous (<i>like</i>) <lb/> <em>Upēndra</em> (<i>i.e.</i> Vishṇu), who, defeating the host of (<i>his</i>) enemies, took (<i>from them</i>) the pillar <lb/> of victory standing in the centre of (<i>the town of</i>) <em>Vātāpi</em>.</p>

<p>(V. 12.) From him came <em>Paramēśvara</em> (I) who crushed the conceit of (<i>his</i>) enemies, <lb/> (<i>and was</i>) a sun in destroying the darkness which was the army of the <em>Chāḷukya</em> king.</p>

<p>(V. 13.) His son's son (<i>was</i>) <em>Narasiṁhavarman</em> (II) who, equal to Mahēndra, once <lb/> again organised the <i>ghaṭikā</i> of the twice-born (<i>i.e.</i> Brāhmaṇas) and built of stone a house for <lb/> the moon-crested (Śiva) which was comparable with the (<i>mountain</i>) <em>Kailāsa</em>.</p>

<p>(V. 14.) His son who was respected by kings, was <em>Paramēśvara</em> (II). This chastiser <lb/> of the dark age (<i>Kali</i>) governed the earth according to the rules laid down by <em>Manu</em>.</p>

<p>(V. 15.) After him, <em>Nandivarman</em>, the repository of the aggregate (<i>good</i>) qualities of <lb/> all ancient kings, got possession of the prosperity of the family together with the earth <lb/> whose garments are the four oceans.</p>

<p>(V. 16.) Of this heroic lord of battalions (<i>or</i>, of rivers), and the home of many virtues (<i>or</i>, <lb/> of gems), as of the ocean, the chief queen was <em>Rēvā</em> who, like (<i>the river</i>) Rēvā, had (<i>her</i>) <lb/> birth from a great king (<i>or</i>, from a high mountain).</p>

<p>(V. 17.) To her was born on this (<i>earth</i>) the glorious king <em>Dantivarman</em>, a manifest-<lb break="no"/>ation of the lotus-eyed <em>(Vishṇu)</em> himself, who was the delight of the earth, whose (<i>sole</i>) <lb/> object (<i>of life</i>) was the protection of the three worlds and in whom the group of pure qualities <lb/> such as prowess, charity and gratitude attained eminence, as it were, after a long time <lb/> (<i>enjoying</i>) the pleasure of each other's company.</p>

<p>(V. 18.) Just as <em>Gaurī</em> (<i>was the wife</i>) of the conqueror of the (<i>three</i>) cities (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Śiva</em>), <lb/> the suitable chief queen of that lord of the earth, the foremost of heroes, the powerful <lb/> <em>Pallava-Mahārāja</em>, was (<i>she</i>) of a spotless race, who bore the name <em>Aggaḷanimmaṭī</em> <lb/> (<i>and was</i>) the daughter of the celebrated king—a crest-jewel of the <em>Kadamba</em> family.</p>

<p>(V. 19.) As the (<i>morning</i>) twilight (gives birth to) the resplendent one (<i>i.e.</i> the sun); <lb/> as <em>Ambikā</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Pārvatī</em>), (<i>to the god</i>) <em>Kumāra (Skanda)</em> possessed of the marvellous <lb/> (weapon) <i>Śakti</i> (<i>or</i>, of strength); as Śachī, to the victorious Jayanta; so did this <em>(Aggaḷa-<lb break="no"/>nimmaṭī)</em> give birth to (the glorious) <em>Nandivarman</em>.</p>

<p>(V. 20.) This <em>(Nandivarman)</em> puffed up with the prowess of his arms, acquired the <lb/> prosperity of the <em>(Pallava)</em> kingdom, not easy for others to obtain, by killing (<i>his</i>) enemies on <lb/> the battle-field which was laughing (<i>as it were</i>) with pearls dropping from the frontal globes <lb/> of elephants slain by (<i>his</i>) unsheathed sword.</p>

<p>(V. 21.) Never shone so (<i>thoroughly</i>) a garden with (<i>the advent of</i>) spring, nor men of <lb/> high birth with (<i>good</i>) qualities, nor women with morality, nor a millionaire with charity, nor <lb/> humility with knowledge, nor a lotus-tank with the sun, nor the expanse of the sky with <lb/> the moon at the end of the rainy season, as (<i>the people of</i>) this earth (<i>shone</i>), with that king.</p>

<p>(V. 22.) (<i>A subject</i>) of that king who was learned, modest and of established virtues, <lb/> who was named <em>Yajñabhaṭṭa</em> and surnamed <em>Bappa-Bhaṭṭāraka</em>, was widely famous <lb/> (<i>for his knowledge</i>) in the <i>Śāstra</i>, the <i>Vēda</i> and the <i>Sāṅkhya</i> and was celebrated for (<i>his</i>) <lb/> persistent devotion to (Śiva), built in the village named <em>Śrīkaṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> a temple for <em>Śiva</em> <lb/> similar to the high <em>Kailāsa</em> (<i>mountain</i>).</p>

<p>(V. 23.) His (<i>viz.</i> <em>Yajñabhaṭṭa's</em>) father was named <em>Śivadāsa</em>, who like the lord (<i>of <lb/> the goddess</i>) of speech (<i>i.e.</i> Brahmā) was possessed of pure intelligence. His mother was <em>[Drē]-<lb break="no"/>ṇamaṇi</em> who like the (<i>goddess</i>) earth was great for the exhuberance of her (<i>good</i>) qualities. <note n="2:511-1">A pun on the words <i>guṇa</i> and <i>garīyasī</i> is intended. The earth has all the <i>guṇas</i> such as form, taste, <i>etc</i>. <lb/> and is also heavy.</note><pb n="2:512"/></p>

<p>(V. 24.) His grandfather was named <em>Yajña</em> who, like the repository of the <i>kalās</i> (<i>i.e.</i> the <lb/> moon), is the abode of sciences (<i>kalā</i>), <note n="2:512-1">For a correct understanding of the sense, the phrase <i>nidhiḥ kalānām</i> has to be repeated twice.</note> has spotless character <note n="2:512-2"><i>Viśuddha-vṛittaḥ</i> would have been more apt.</note> (<i>as the moon, a white disc</i>), is the <lb/> best of the twice-born (<i>dvija</i>), the expeller of ignorance (<i>as the moon, of darkness</i>) and shines <lb/> with wide-spread fame.</p>

<p>(V. 25.) To that god <em>Śarva (Śiva)</em>, the king granted the village called <em>Tirukkāṭṭup-<lb break="no"/>paḷḷi</em> for (<i>maintaining</i>) the services (<i>connected with</i>) worship, feeding, <i>etc</i>.</p>

<p>(V. 26.) The heroic head-jewel of the <em>Chōḷa</em> race named <em>Kumārāṅkuśa</em>, the glory of <lb/> whose prowess was well-known, whose liberality was equal to that of <em>Rādhēya</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <lb/> <em>Karṇa</em>) and whose conduct was upright, made the (<i>necessary</i>) request (<i>vijñapti</i>) for (<i>securing</i>) <lb/> this (<i>grant</i>).</p>

<p>(V. 27.) The executor (<i>ājñapti</i>) here, was the king's minister named <em>Namba</em>, the autum-<lb break="no"/>nal moon in the firmament of the <em>Agradatta</em> family.</p>

<p>(V. 28.) The <i>Māhēśvara</i> <em>Manōdhīra</em>, the act of whose words, thoughts and body <lb/> were (<i>all</i>) for the benefit of others, composed this <i>praśasti</i>.</p>

<p>(Lines 47 to 63.) Whereas in the sixth year of <em>Kōvijaya-Nandivarman</em>, at the <lb/> request (<i>made by</i>) Chōḷa-Mahārāja and the <i>āṇatti</i> of <em>Iraiyūr-uḍaiyāṉ Nambaṉ</em>, <lb/> this (<i>village</i>) <em>Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em> of <i>pañchavaram āyirakkāḍi</i> <note n="2:512-3"><i>I.e.</i> whose yield under the head <i>pañchavaram</i>, was one thousand <i>kāḍi</i> of paddy. <i>Pañchavaram</i> may be a <lb/> mistake for <i>pañchavāram</i> ‘the five <i>vārams</i> or income in grain’; cp. the terms <i>mēl-vāram, kuḍi-vāram</i>, etc., which <lb/> are still in use. See also <i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. V., p. 138, foot-note 7.</note>, in <em>Nāyaṟu-nāḍu</em>, <lb/> (<i>a sub-division</i>) of <em>Puṛaṟ-kōṭṭam</em>, (<i>is</i>) excluded from the district (<i>nāṭṭu-nīṅgal</i>) (and) has <lb/> been assigned as an <i>uṭpuravu dēvadāna</i> in favour of (<i>the god</i>) <em>Mahādēva</em> of (<i>the temple of</i>) <lb/> <em>Yajñēśvara</em> built by <em>Śaṉṉakkuṟi Yajñabhaṭṭa</em> at <em>Tirukkāṭṭuppaḷḷi</em>, the immunities <lb/> (<i>parihāra</i>) secured (<i>therefor) viz. nāḍāṭchi, ūrāṭchi, puravu-poṉ, tirumukkāṇam, <note n="2:512-4">This term corresponds to <i>tirumugakkāṇam</i> of the Taṇḍantōṭṭam plates; see below, page 531, note 2. The <lb/> following other terms, <i>viz., vaṭṭi-nāṛi, pudāṛi, taṭṭukāyam, īṛam-pūṭchi</i> and <i>iḍai-ppūṭchi</i> also occur in the <lb/> Taṇḍantōṭṭam plates.</note> vaṭṭi-nāṛi, pudāṛi, <lb/> taṭṭukāyam, īṛam-pūṭchi, iḍai-ppūṭchi, maṉṟupāḍu</i>, brokerage, tax on looms, <i>kūlam</i>, good cow, <lb/> good bull, good sheep, watch-fee of the district, <i>ūḍupōkku</i>, taxes on marriages, potters and <lb/> quarries, <i>paṭṭina-śēri</i> and all other (<i>income</i>) of any kind which the king could receive and enjoy <lb/> within the boundary of this village, shall not (<i>henceforth</i>) be collected by the king but by <lb/> this Mahādēva of (<i>the temple of</i>) Yajñēśvara only. The (<i>following</i>) written declaration <lb/> (<i>vyavasthā</i>) is (<i>also</i>) granted (<i>for the guidance of the donee):</i> Mansions of burnt tiles (<i>bricks ?</i>) <lb/> may be built (<i>without special permission</i>); artimissia (<i>damanagam</i>), andropogan muricatum <lb/> (<i>iruvēli</i>), red-lilies (<i>śeṅgaṛunīr</i>) and <i>uḷḷi</i> may be grown (<i>in gardens ?</i>); cocoanut (<i>trees</i>) may be <lb/> planted in groves; reservoirs and wells may be sunk; large oil-presses may be used and the <lb/> toddy-drawers (<i>īṛavars</i>) may not climb, without the consent of this (<i>i.e.</i> the Mahādēva of <lb/> Yajnēśvara), the cocoanut and the palmyra (<i>trees</i>) planted within the boundaries of (this <lb/> village). With the written declaration thus defined (<i>the village</i>) was placed in the (<i>hands of <lb/> the</i>) assembly (<i>paraḍatti,</i>) as a <i>dēvadāna</i>, with all immunities, to the (<i>god</i>) <em>Mahādēva</em> of the <lb/> <em>Yajñēśvara</em> (<i>temple</i>).</p>

<p>(V. 29.) O ! Future rulers of earth ! He, <em>Nandivarman</em>, the banner among all kings, <lb/> with (<i>his</i>) lotus-like hands folded, bows down to you with (<i>his</i>) head which is marked by the head-<lb break="no"/>jewel (<i>viz.</i>) the lotus-feet of Hara <em>(Śiva)</em> (<i>and requests you</i>) to protect this good deed always !</p>

<p>(V. 30.) Thus does <em>Rāma</em> request again and again, all the present and future lords of <pb n="2:513"/> <lb/> the earth: “This bridge of (<i>religious</i>) charity is common to (<i>all</i>) kings; you must (<i>there-<lb break="no"/>fore</i>) protect (<i>it</i>) at all times.”</p>

<p>(V. 31.) This set of (<i>copper-</i>)sheets was engraved by the moon in the sky of the family <lb/> of carpenters, named <em>Pēraya</em>, the son of <em>Śiṟṟaya</em>, who has won (<i>his</i>) reputation for skill <lb/> in workman-ship.</p>

<p>(LI. 68 and 69.) The writing of <em>Pērayaṉ</em> son of the carpenter (<i>kāshṭhakārin</i>) of <lb/> <em>Maṉaichchēri</em> in <em>Kachchippēḍu</em>.</p>

<h4>POSTSCRIPT.</h4>

<p>On pages 180 and 181 of the <i>Epigraphia Indica</i>, Vol. IV., Professor Hultzsch gives an <lb/> extract of a set of five copper-plates of <em>Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</em> which were <lb/> discovered at <em>Bāhūr</em> near Pondicherry by M.J. de la Fon. The originals are not avail-<lb break="no"/>able but appear to be in the possession of some person at Paris. A transcript of the inscrip-<lb break="no"/>tion prepared by a Tamil Paṇḍit was supplied by the discoverer to Professor Hultzsch some <lb/> year ago. It is in many places defective. Still as the information conveyed appears to be <lb/> important for the study of the collateral branch of the <em>Pallava</em> family, known as <em>Gaṅga-<lb break="no"/>Pallavas</em>, I append below the <em>Sanskṛit</em> and <em>Tamil</em> texts as transcribed by the Paṇḍit.</p>

<p>It may be added by way of supplementing Professor Hultzsch's remarks that in V. 16 <lb/> reference is made to a victory gained by a <em>Pāṇḍya</em> king with the help of <em>Nṛipatuṅga</em>. <lb/> It is not stated who this <em>Pāṇḍya</em> was or where he fought the battle in which <em>Nṛipatuṅga</em> <lb/> could have helped him. The <em>Ambāsamudram</em> inscription of <em>Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</em> <lb/> (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. IX, pp. 84 to 94) states that that king advanced as far north as <lb/> <em>Araiśūr</em> on the Pennar in <em>Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam</em>. Mr. Venkayya distinguishes this <lb/> <em>Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</em> from his grandson <em>Varaguṇavarman</em> who fought the battle of <lb/> <em>Śrīpurambiyam</em> with <em>Pṛithivīpati</em> I and his ally <em>Aparājitavarman</em>, the last of the <lb/> <em>Gaṅga-Pallava</em> kings (Madras Epigraphical <i>Report</i> for 1906-7, Part II, paragraph <lb/> 21). It is not definitely known what relation existed between this <em>Aparājita</em> and <em>Nṛipa-<lb break="no"/>tuṅgavarman</em> of the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates. Anyhow <em>Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</em> who flourished <lb/> two generations before <em>Varaguṇavarman</em>, about the beginning of the 9th century A.D., <lb/> and who pushed his campaign in the north up to the bank of the river Pennar cannot be <lb/> far distant in time from <em>Nṛipatuṅgavarman</em>. Consequently, the <em>Pāṇḍya</em> referred to in <lb/> V. 16 of the <em>Bāhūr</em> plates may probably be <em>Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</em>. The enemy against <lb/> whom <em>Nṛipatuṅga</em> fought to help his friend <em>Varaguṇa-Mahārāja</em> was very likely a <lb/> king of the <em>Siṁhavishṇu</em> line who was ruling simultaneously with <em>Nṛipatuṅga</em> in <lb/> some portion of the <em>Toṇḍai-maṇḍalam</em>. <note n="2:513-1">Dantivarma-Mahārāja of the Bhāradvāja-<i>gōtra</i> mentioned in the Triplicane inscription is supposed to <lb/> have been the first of a line of kings who “spoke of themselves as belonging to the family of <i>Pallava-tilaka</i> in <lb/> order to distinguish themselves from the Gaṅga-Pallavas” (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. VIII., pp. 290-6). Nandippōt- <lb/> taraiyaṉ was another king of the same family whose queen Māṟambāvai figures as the donor in two <lb/> inscriptions at Tiruchcheṉṉampūṇḍi, Tanjore district, which are dated in the 18th and 22nd years of the reign <lb/> of Nṛipatuṅga (Nos. 303 and 300 of the Madras Epigraphical collection for 1901). This subordinate position <lb/> of Māṟambāvai suggests evidently either the defeat or the death of her husband at the hands of Nṛipatuṅga. <lb/> Consequently, Nandippōttaraiyaṉ of the <i>Pallava-tilaka</i> family must have been the enemy against whom Vara- <lb/> guṇa-Mahārāja and Nṛipatuṅga jointly fought.</note></p>

<p>The object of the grant was the donation of the three villages <em>Cheṭṭuppākkam <lb/> Viḷāṅgāṭṭaṅkaḍuvaṉūr</em> and <em>Iṟaippuṇaichchēri</em> to the <i>vidyāsthāna</i> (V. 23) at <lb/> <em>Bāhugrāma</em> (<i>i.e.</i>, <em>Bāhūr</em>) (V. 25), by a member of the <em>Baśāli</em> family and a descendant<pb n="2:514"/> <lb/> of the <em>Kuru</em> race (V. 18). This chief was the minister of <em>Tuṅgavarman</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Nṛipatuṅga</em>) <lb/> (V. 28) who issued the necessary order for the grant of the villages (V. 21). The college <lb/> (<i>vidyāsthāna</i>) at <em>Bāhūr</em> consisted of 14 <i>gaṇas</i> <note n="2:514-1">The Paṇḍit who supplied the transcript of the grant remarks that the 14 <i>guṇas</i> were the fourteen <lb/> divisions of learning and consisted of—the <i>Vēdas</i> (4), the <i>aṅgas</i> (6), <i>Mīmāṁsā</i> (1), <i>Nyāya</i> (1), <i>Purāṇa</i> (1) and the <lb/> <i>Dharmaśāstra</i> (1).</note> and was controlled by the learned men of that <lb/> village, being organised and maintained by them “as the <em>Ganges (Mandākinī)</em> descending <lb/> from the sky with all the fury of its rushing waves is borne by the god Śiva on one of his matted <lb/> locks” (Vv. 24 and 25). The composer of the <i>praśasti</i> was <em>Dāśaya</em> (V. 30). The Tamil <lb/> portion of the grant refers to the 8th year of <em>Vijaya-Nṛipatuṅgavarman</em> and states <lb/> that at the request of <em>Baśāli-Pērarayaṉ</em> and the <i>āṇatti (ājñapti</i>) of <em>Viḍōlaiviḍugu</em> (<i>i.e.</i>, <lb/> <em>Viḍēlviḍugu</em>) <em>Kāḍupaṭṭi-Tamiṛappēraraiyaṉ</em>, <note n="2:514-2">See below Vol. III, p. 92.</note> the grant of the three villages already <lb/> mentioned was announced to the residents of <em>Bāhūr-nāḍu</em>, a sub-division of <em>Aruvā-nāḍu</em>, <lb/> on its eastern side. As usual, the villages were granted after excluding previous donations <lb/> and expropriating former owners, for the sole benefit of the <i>vidyāsthāna</i> at <em>Bāhūr</em>. The order <lb/> was communicated to the assembly of Bāhūr-nāḍu (<i>nāṭṭār)</i> <note n="2:514-3">See Madras Epigraphical Report for 1913, Part II, paragraph 23.</note> who on receiving it, obeyed it <lb/> placing the order on their heads, circumambulated the village, planted stones and milk bush <lb/> and drew up the necessary document (<i>aṟaiy-ōlai</i>).</p>

<p>Among the boundaries described occur the names <em>Teṉmalippākkam, Nelvāyē-<lb break="no"/>ppākkam, Uṟattūr, Māmbākkam, Neriñjikkuṟumbu</em> and <em>Śiṟimāṉpātti</em>. The <lb/> land comprised within the described boundaries of the three villages was given away to the <lb/> members of the <i>vidyāsthāna</i> for the advancement of learning, after including these in <em>Bāhūr</em> <lb/> and giving them the same exemptions (<i>parihāra</i>) and written declarations (<i>vyavasthā</i>) as in <lb/> the case of <em>Bāhūr</em>. The goldsmith (<i>suvarṇakṛit</i>) <em>Nṛipatuṅga</em>, a jewel of the <em>Uditōdita</em> <lb/> family and a faithful servant of the <em>Pallavas</em>, wrote the grant (V. 32). The Tamil <lb/> passage at the end of the inscription states that this goldsmith's father was <em>Mādēvipperu-<lb break="no"/>daṭṭāṉ</em>, son of <em>Uditōdaya-Perudaṭṭāṉ</em>, a native of <em>Kachchippēḍu</em> (Conjeeveram).</p>

<p>Of the villages mentioned, <em>Bāhūr</em> is the only place that can be identified. It is the <lb/> head-quarters of a commune in the French territory and was the site of a battle between the <lb/> French and the English troops in A.D. 1752.</p>

<h4 ignore="yes">TEXT. <note n="2:514-4">From the transcript prepared by a Tamil Pandit.</note></h4>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>svasti śrīḥ [||*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>diśatu va[ḥ*] śriyamaṁbujalocanastridaśamaulinisṛiṣṭapadāṁbujaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>sakalalokabhayaṁkararākṣasapraśamaheturajo madhusūdanaḥ [|| 1*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><note n="2:514-5">The metre is faulty. The three first feet are Praharshiṇī with a long and a short missing. The <lb/> last foot is Anushṭubh.</note><de>śrībhartuśśayanaparasya netre yatteja[ḥ*] sthitilayasūtihetuḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>tannābherajani samastabījamabjamātmayonistato['*]bhavat [|| 2*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>aṁgirāstata utpanno lokanāthāccaturmukhāt [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>bṛihaspatistato mantrī śakrasya valabhedinaḥ [|| 3*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>tataśśaṁyustato jajñe bharadvājasamāhvayaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:514:98:0"><de>tato droṇo maheṣvāsassamare śakravikramaḥ [|| 4*]</de><pb n="2:515"/></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>tato droṇānmahābāhussarvāyudhaviśāradaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>aśvatthāmā kilāṁśena saṁbabhūva pinākinaḥ [|| 5*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>aśvatthāmnastato rājā pallavākhyo babhūva ha [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>rarakṣa navakhaṇḍasthān bhūpatīn sakṛiṣīvalān [|| 6*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>vimalakoṁkaṇikādi tadanvayādajani bṛindamaripramadānataṁ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>nihitaśāsanamanyanṛipeṣvapi priyatamaṁ jayaghoṣamanārataṁ [|| 7*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>bhutkvā bhuvaṁ svavīryeṇa catussāgaramekhalāṁ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>tatassvargaṁ vimānena gateṣu vimalādiṣu [|| 8*]</de> <lb/> AsIt</l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>purandarasamo rājā dṛiḍhabhaktirmuradviṣi [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>tantivarmā</de><note n="2:515-1">Read <de>dantivarmā</de>.</note><de>mahābāhuḥ kṣmāpālamakuṭīnataḥ [|| 9*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>dharmmeṇa pālanāt</de><note n="2:515-2">Read <de>pālanādbhūmiṁ</de>.</note><de>bhūmiṁ kalāvapi yuge nṛipaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>varṣaṇādapi dānasya parjanya iva nirbabhau [|| 10*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>ātmano bandiyuktān tān yamālayadidṛikṣayā [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de><note n="2:515-3">Read <de>pātheyaº</de>.</note>pādheyamiva kṛitvārīn khaṇḍāni vi[sa]sarja yaḥ [|| 11*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>nandivarmā mahābāhussañjāto</de><note n="2:515-4">Read <de>dantiº</de>.</note><de>tantivarmmaṇaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>samare vijitā bhūmirasahāyena yena saḥ [|| 12*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>āsīt</de><note n="2:515-5">Read <de>āsīcchaṁkhāº</de>.</note><de>śakhāhvayā devī tanvaṁgī nandivarmaṇaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>rāṣṭrakūṭa[ku]le jātā lakṣmīriva muradviṣaḥ [|| 13*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>kṣamāvatī dharitrīva mā[tṛi]vajjagataḥ priyā [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>babhau śaṁkhāhvayā devī rājña[ḥ*] śrīriva rūpiṇī [|| 14*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>tasyāṁ babhūva matikāntikalādimatyāṁ mānyaḥ kulena guṇavān bhuvanatrayeśaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>utpadyamānatapanādhipatulyatejā jiṣṇuḥ kalāvān samare nṛipatuṁgadevaḥ [|| 15*]</de><note n="2:515-6">The last foot of this Vasantatilaka verse is faulty.</note></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>yatprasādājjitā senā pāṇḍyena samare purā [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de><note n="2:515-7">In the word <de>pārericit</de> must be found the reference to the place where the enemy was defeated by <lb/> Nṛipatuṅga. Literally translated, it means ‘on the other bank of Arichit.’ I am not able to <lb/> identify (the river ?) Arichit.</note>pārericitsarājyaśrīrdadāha ripusaṁhatiṁ [|| 16*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>nṛipatuṁga iti khyāto bālopi bhuvaneśvaraḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>khyāto na kevalaṁ bhūmāvamuṣminnapi rāmavat [|| 17*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>tasyopakārasaṁyukto rājñaḥ kurukulotbhavaḥ</de><note n="2:515-8">Read <de>ºkulodbhavaḥ</de>.</note><de>[|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>baśālivaṁśamārttāṇḍaḥ prajānāṁ śaraṇe rataḥ [|| 18*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>śaśivattilako loke gāṁbhīryādessamudravat [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:515:98:0"><de>sūryavadrakṣaṇāllokān lokānāṁ nilayo nṛipaḥ [|| 19*]</de><pb n="2:516"/></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>tasmāttasyocitannāmni tulyatā bhāti devavat [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>āthava sutarānnāma pratyakṣatvādviśāṁpateḥ [|| 20*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>grātra yaṁ svarāṣṭre saḥ kuruvaṁśavivarddhanaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>vijñāpya nṛipatuṁgeśāllabdhamājñaptipūrvakaḥ</de><note n="2:516-1">Read <de>ºpūrvakaṁ</de>.</note><de>[|| 21*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>ceṭuppākkaṁ phalādhāraṁ grāmamekamathāparaṁ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>grāmaṁ</de><note n="2:516-2">In the Tamil portion this village is called Viḷāṅgāṭṭaṅkaḍuvaṉūr. I cannot explain how this full <lb/> name could be got out of the Sanskṛit verse.</note><de>vidyādviḷāṁgādirephāntapadanāmakaṁ [|| 22*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>tasmādi <ta>ṟaippuṇaiccērī</ta><de>ntritIyyaM</de><note n="2:516-3">Read <de>ºntṛitīyaṁ</de>.</note> sarvasaMpadaM [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>evaṁ grāmatrayaṁ labdhvā vidyāsthānāya dattavān [|| 23*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>mandākinīṁ samāyāntīmūrmivaṁśasamākulāṁ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>saṁbabhāra yathā devo dhūrjaṭirjaṭayaikayā [|| 24*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>vidyānadī tathāgāthā caturdaśagaṇākulā [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>bāhugrāmajuṣāṁ sthānaṁ vyāpya yasmādvyavasthitā [|| 25*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>tatsthānamevaṁ viduṣāṁ vidyāsthānaṁ pracakṣate [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>tebhyo datvā sa bhūpālo grāmānājñaptipūrvakān [|| 26*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>hastisañcārisīmāntānātmānaṁ bahumanyate [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>yuktān sarvaparīhārairākaratvena rakṣitān [|| 27*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>ājñābhīrurddharmmaśīlastrailokyeśvarapūjitaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>mantrī bṛihaspatiprakhyaḥ rājña[ḥ*] śrītuṁgavarmmaṇaḥ [|| 28*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>āgāminaḥ prajāpālān yācate kurunandanaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>dharmmasya tasya sāmānyāt pālanīya iti svayaṁ [|| 29*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>dāsa[ḥ*] sthānasya vidyāyāḥ bāhugrāmajuṣāmayaṁ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:516:98:0"><de>kṛitavān śāstratatvajñaḥ praśastindāśayassvataḥ [|| 30*]</de></l>

<p> <ta>kovicaiya nirupatoṅkavarumaṟku yāṇṭu eṭṭāvatu</ta> <gr>ba</gr><ta>cālipperarayaṉ viṇṇap-<lb break="no"/>pattāl viṭōlaiviṭuku kāṭupaṭṭittamiḻapperarayaṉ āṇattiyāka aruvānāṭṭukkiḻvaḻi <lb/> vākūrnāṭṭu nāṭṭār kāṇka [||*] tannāṭṭu ceṭṭuppākkamum viḷāṅkāṭṭaṅkaṭuvaṉūrum <lb/> iṟaippuṇaicceriyumāka immūṉṟūrum paḻayavaṟamum piramateyamum nīkki muṉpeṟṟārai <lb/> māṟṟi yāṇṭu eṭṭāvatu pākūr vittiyāstāṉattārkku vittiyāṉupokamākappaṇit-<lb break="no"/>tom [||*] tāṅkaḷum paṭākai naṭantu kalluṅkaḷḷiyum nāṭṭi aṟaiyolai ceytu viṭutaka-<lb break="no"/>veṉṟu nāṭṭārkkuttirumukam viṭa nāṭṭār tirumukaṅkaṇṭu toḻutu talaikku vaittu paṭā-<lb break="no"/>kai naṭantu kalluṅkaḷḷiyum nāṭṭi aṟaiyōlai ceytu nāṭṭārviṭutta aṟaiyōlaippaṭi <lb/> nilattukkellai [||*] viḷāṅkāṭṭaṅkaṭuvaṉūrkkum ceṭṭuppākkattukkumāka iraṇṭūrukkum <lb/> kīḻpāṟkellai kāṭṭu ellai oṉṟum teṉmalipākkattu yellaiyiṉ meṟkum teṉpāṟ-<lb break="no"/>kellai teṉmalipākkattellai oṉṟum nelvāyēppākkattellai oṉṟum uṟattūrel-<lb break="no"/>laikku vaṭakkum melpāṟkellai māmpākkattellai oṉṟum ivviḷāṅkāṭṭaṅkaṭuvaṉūr[p]-<lb break="no"/>pāṟ piramateyamāyiṉa aṟupatu ceṟuvukkukkiḻakkum vaṭapāṟkellai vākūrellaiyiṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟeṟkum [||*] iṟaippuṇaiccerikkellai kiḻpāṟkellai nattamuḷḷiṭṭa kāṭṭukku meṟkum <lb/> teṉpāṟkellai neriñcikkuṟumpiṉ ellaiyiṉ vaṭakkum melpāṟkellai vākūrellaiyiṉ <lb/> kiḻakkum vaṭapāṟkellai ciṟimāṉpātti ellaiyiṉ ṟeṟkumāka ivvicaitta perunāṉkel-<lb break="no"/>laikaḷilumakappaṭṭa nilaṉ nirnilaṉum puñceyum ūrum ūrirukkaiyum maṉaiyum maṉaippaṭappum <lb/> māṭuṅkaṉṟumēypāḻum kuḷamum kōṭṭakaramum kiṭaṅkum kēṇiyum kāṭuṅkaḷarum ōṭaiyum<pb n="2:517"/> <lb/> uṭaippum uḷḷiṭṭu nīrpūci neṭumparamapeṟintu uṭumpōṭi āmaitavaḻntatellām uṇ-<lb break="no"/>ṇilaṉoḻiviṉṟi vākūr vittiyāstāṉattārkku vittiyāṉupokamāy pākūrōṭē ēṟṟi <lb/> vākūrpeṟṟa parikāramum</ta> <gr>vya</gr><ta>vastaiyum peṟṟu carvaparikāramāy pirammateyamāy piracitti <note n="2:517-1">ṭhis word was perhaps <ta>paraṭatti</ta> in the original as in the Vēlūrpāḷaiyam plates, text, l. 63.</note> <lb/> ceṉṟatu [||*]</ta></p>

<l n="2:517:98:0"><de>puṇyaṁ samaṁ kṛitavatāṁ parirakṣatāñcet tadrakṣateti nṛipatirnnṛipatuṁgavarmmā [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:517:98:0"><de>āgāminaḥ kṣitipatīn praṇamatyajasraṁ mūrdhnā mukundacaraṇāṁbujaśekhareṇa [|| 31*]</de></l>

<l n="2:517:98:0"><de>uditoditakulatilakaḥ suvarṇakṛitsarvaśāstraniṣṇātaḥ [|*]</de></l>

<l n="2:517:98:0"><de>alikhannṛipatuṁgākhyaḥ pallavakulamūlabhṛityotra [|| 32*]</de></l>

<p> <ta>kaccippeṭṭukkiḻppaicārattu utitotayapperutaṭṭāṉ makaṉ mātevipperuta-<lb break="no"/>ṭṭāṉ makaṉ nirupatoṅkaṉ eḻuttu [||*]</ta>.</p>

</translation>

</edition>

</inscription>

<inscription n="2:517:99"><head>No. 99.—TANDANTOTTAM PLATES OF VIJAYA-NANDIVIKRAMAVARMAN.</head>

<p><em>Taṇḍantōṭṭam</em> (<i>i.e.</i> Tandantōttam, No. 134 of the Madras Survey map of the Kumba-<lb break="no"/>konam taluk) is a village 6 miles east of Kumbakōṇam in the Tanjore district of the Madras <lb/> Presidency. The existence of the plates was brought to the notice of the late Rai Bahadur <lb/> V.Venkayya, M.A., by Mr. Narayanaswami Aiyar, Sub-Inspector of Police, Madras City. <lb/> It is stated that they “were found with many other idols, while digging a foundation in the <lb/> premises of a Śiva temple in the village of Thandanthottam, Kumbakonam taluk of Tanjore <lb/> district, about 100 years ago. No one knew what it is and how they happened to be there.”</p>

<p>The plates are 14 in number, each measuring about 11(1/4)" by 3(3/4)". When they were <lb/> produced before Mr. Venkayya the plates were strung on a ring which did not appear to <lb/> have been previously cut. <note n="2:517-2">As in the sequel it will appear that many plates both in the beginning and in the middle are missing <lb/> the ring must have been cut open on some previous occasion and re-soldered.</note> The ring is somewhat oval with diameters measuring 6(1/2)" and <lb/> 7(3/4)". Its ends are secured at the bottom of a circular seal 3" in diameter. The seal bears in <lb/> relief a couchant Pallava bull facing the proper right. Along the margin of the seal is a <lb/> Grantha legend which is illegible. The ring on which the plates are strung was cut by <lb/> me with the permission of Mr. Narayanaswami Aiyar in order to change out the plates and <lb/> prepare ink-impressions.</p>

<p>The two sides of the first plate, the first side of the second plate and the first five lines of <lb/> its second side are in <em>Sanskṛit</em> verse, engraved in the <em>Grantha</em> alphabet and the rest, in <lb/> the Tamil language and characters. The inscription must originally have consisted of <lb/> many more plates, two or three of which at least are missing at the beginning. These <lb/> would have supplied a genealogy of the <em>Pallava</em> kings similar to that of the <em>Vēlūr-<lb break="no"/>pāḷaiyam</em> plates of <em>Vijaya-Nandivarman</em> published above. The concluding words of <lb/> some of the plates in the middle do not fit in with the opening words of the succeeding plates. <lb/> Consequently, it is presumed that a few plates <note n="2:517-3">The breaks noted at the foot of the text are five in number. The first of these is at the beginning of <lb/> the Sanskṛit portion. The second (1. 29) could not have counted more than one plate. The three others <lb/> (ll. 78, 126 and 158) must have consisted each of a single plate which contained on them the 64 missing names <lb/> of the donees.</note> of the grant portion are also lost. This <lb/> presumption is confirmed by the fact that while the number of the donees according to the <lb/> <em>Sanskṛit</em> portion has to be 308, the number actually registered is only 244, even including<pb n="2:518"/> <lb/> those whose names seem to have been added subsequently in comparatively later characters, or <lb/> at least in a different hand.</p>

<p>The first plate of the preserved portion begins by referring to a king who conquered the <lb/> South and stating that a certain <em>Hiraṇyavarman</em> was born “again” for the “welfare of <lb/> the worlds” (<i>jagatām hitāya</i> V. 1). His son was <em>Nandivarman</em> who perhaps held the <lb/> <i>biruda</i> <em>Ēkadhīra</em> <note n="2:518-1">See below p. 529, note 4.</note>. The next six verses are taken up with the praise of <em>Nandivarman</em>. <lb/> Two historical facts referred to in this part of the inscription are interesting. One of <lb/> them is that <em>Nandivarman</em> took away from the <em>Gaṅga</em> king a neck-ornament which <lb/> contained in it the gem called <i>Ugrōdaya</i> (V. 6). The name of this <em>Gaṅga</em> king, however, <lb/> is not furnished. The other is that <em>Nandivarman</em> was the owner of an elephant named <lb/> <i><em>Paṭṭavardhana</em></i> (V. 7). With the permission of the king, a certain <em>Dayāmukha</em> caused <lb/> a village to be granted to 308 Brāhmaṇas and called it <em>Dayāmukhamaṅgala</em> after his <lb/> own name (V. 9). The executor (<i>ājñapti</i>) of the grant was evidently the very same person <lb/> <em>Dayāmukha</em> entitled <em>Kumāra</em>, who is stated to have been the king's treasurer (V. 10). <lb/> The composer of the eulogy (<i>praśasti</i>) was <em>Paramēśvara Uttarakāraṇika</em> son of <lb/> <em>Param-Ōttarakāraṇika</em> (V. 14).</p>

<p>The <em>Tamil</em> portion is dated in the 58th year of <em>Kōvijaya-Nandivikramavar-<lb break="no"/>man</em> and registers a gift of land (converted into a village <note n="2:518-2">Evidently the Dayāmukhamaṅgala mentioned in V. 9.</note>) lying to the west of <em>Taṇḍattō-<lb break="no"/>ṭṭam</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Taṇḍantōṭṭam</em>) in <em>Teṉkarai-Naṟaiyūr-nāḍu</em>, a district of the <em>Chōḷa</em> <lb/> country, to a number of Brāhmaṇas of <em>Nalgūr</em> <note n="2:518-3">This village is not found on the map of the Kumbakōṇam tāluk. If by Nalgūr is meant Nallūr, which <lb/> is 6 miles west of Kumbakōṇam, we have to suppose that the 308 donees were residents of that village. The <lb/> word may also mean poor; but the idea of granting a village to Brāhmaṇas, purely on account of their <lb/> poverty is rather rare.</note>.</p>

<p>To judge from the high regnal year, the <em>Taṇḍattōṭṭam</em> plates must belong to the <lb/> reign of that <em>Pallava</em> king <em>Vijaya-Nandivikramavarman</em> whose <em>Tiruvallam</em> rock <lb/> inscription is dated in his 62nd year <i>i.e.</i> 4 years later than our plates <note n="2:518-4"><i>South-Ind. Inscrs</i>., Vol. III, p. 91.</note>. At the same time <lb/> the alphabet of the plates and the name of the king lead us to infer that the <em>Vijaya-Nan-<lb break="no"/>divikramavarman</em> who issued these plates may be identical with <em>Vijaya-Nandivarman</em> <lb/> III, the donor of the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates. If the inscription were preserved in full, this <lb/> question would not have been left to surmise and conjecture. The father of <em>Vijaya-Nan-<lb break="no"/>divikramavarman</em> is here stated to have been <em>Hiraṇyavarman</em>; while, the father of <lb/> <em>Vijaya-Nandivarman</em>, according to the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates, was <em>Dantivar-<lb break="no"/>man</em>. If the proposed identity of <em>Vijaya-Nandivikramavarman</em> with <em>Vijaya-<lb break="no"/>Nandivarman</em> is accepted, the apparent discrepancy in the name of the father could be <lb/> explained. The statement that <em>Hiraṇyavarman</em> “was born <i>again</i>,” evidently indicates <lb/> a second king of that name and we may suppose that <em>Dantivarman</em>, the father of <lb/> <em>Vijaya-Nandivikramavarman</em>, was also called <em>Hiraṇyavarman</em> like his grand-<lb break="no"/>father <em>Hiraṇyavarman</em> I the father of <em>Nandivarman Pallavamalla</em>. If the forego-<lb break="no"/>ing surmises are confirmed by future researches, the <em>Taṇḍantōṭṭam</em> grant would be 52 <lb/> years later than the <em>Vēlūrpāḷaiyam</em> plates of the same king.</p>

<p>The donees whose enumeration occupies more than eleven plates of the inscription <lb/> number 244. They belong to various <i>gōtras</i> and <i>sūtras</i>. To judge from their titles (such as<pb n="2:519"/> <lb/> <i>Chaturvēdin, Trivēdin, Sōmayājin, Vasantayājin, Shaḍaṅgavid, Bhaṭṭa, Kramavid, Sarvakratu-<lb break="no"/>yājin, Daśapurīya <note n="2:519-1">Daśapurīya means ‘belonging to or an emigrant from, Daśapura’ a village identified with Mandasor in <lb/> Malwa. Two grants of the Gūrjara chief Dadda IV Praśāntarāga which are referred to about the middle of <lb/> the 7th century A.D. (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. V., p. 38 f.) mention a donee who was an emigrant from Daśapura. <lb/> The spurious grant of Dharasēna II of date Śaka-Saṁvat 400, also mentions a corporation of the <i>Chatur- <lb/> vēdins</i> of Daśapura.</note>, Agnichit</i>, and <i>Vājapēyin</i>) most of them must have been learned men as <lb/> stated in verse 9. The largest number of shares assigned to a single individual is 12 and <lb/> such a recipient was <em>Attōṇa-Shaḍaṅgavi-Sōmayājin</em> (No. 109) whose <i>gōtra</i> and <i>sūtra</i> <lb/> are lost on one of the missing plates. The composer of the inscription, <i>viz.</i>, <em>Uttarakāra-<lb break="no"/>ṇika</em> <i>alias</i> <em>Ayyaṉ Paramēśvara</em> of the <em>Rathītara</em>-<i>gōtra</i> and <em>Paviṛiya</em>-<i>sūtra</i> <lb/> (No. 128) received two shares. Among the other donees, Tiruvaḍigaḷ (evidently the name <lb/> of the local Vishṇu temple or of the Śaiva devotees, as stated on page (41) of the <lb/> introduction) got 5 shares while <em>Mahādēva</em> (the <em>Śiva</em> temple) was assigned 2 shares. <lb/> One share was allotted to the reciter of the <i>Bhārata</i>; and the three arbitrators (<i>madhyastha</i>) <lb/> got one share each. A share was assigned for “pouring water” and for “lighting fire” in <lb/> the hall (<i>ambalam</i>). Perhaps this was the hall where the village assembly used to meet. <lb/> Apparently the <i>Bhārata</i> was also recited in this same hall. The donees seem to have belonged <lb/> to different parts of the country. The names of their native villages indicate that a pretty <lb/> large number of them must have been originally residents of the <em>Telugu</em> country. <lb/> <em>Taṇukkil, Kārambichchēḍu, Iṛakkandoṟu, Iruṅgaṇḍi, Nambūr, Karañjai <note n="2:519-2">Karañjai also spelt Kirāñji (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. VI., p. 228) may be the same as Krāñja, Kāza (<i>ibid.</i> p. 114), <lb/> a village in the Guntur tāluk of the Guntur district.</note>, <lb/> Piṇukkippaṟu <note n="2:519-3"><i>Paṟu</i> stands for <i>paṟṟu</i> (genitive <i>parti</i>) often found as an ending of village names in the Telugu districts. <lb/> It is possible that <i>paṟu</i> is a mistake for the Sanskṛit <i>pura</i> or a variant of the vernacular <i>pāḍu</i>.</note>, Vēlpaṟu, Poppaṟu, Vaṅgippaṟu, Aṭṭambaṟu, Muḍipaṟu</em> (<i>or</i> <lb/> <em>Muḍapaṟu</em>), <em>Virippaṟu, Arasappaṟu, Karippaṟu, Nūttilāppaṟu</em> and <em>Ponnam-<lb break="no"/>baṟu</em> are apparently names of villages which were probably situated in the Telugu country. <lb/> <em>Kumiṛūr, Kāṭṭukkuṟi, Maṇaṟkāl, Mandiram, Paṟiyalūr, Pāḍagam, Pāṟkuḷam, <lb/> Aṅgārai, Kaḷattūr, Veṇṇainallūr, Perumbūdūr, Kāynīrkuḷam, Īykkāṭṭuk-<lb break="no"/>kōyil, Śiṟupaṛuvūr, Puliyūr</em> (in <em>Miṛalai-nāḍu</em>), <em>Aruvāgūr</em> and <em>Taramanallūr</em> <lb/> (in <em>Aruvā-nāḍu</em>) <note n="2:519-4">This district included within it the village of Bāhūr; see above, Introduction, p. 28.</note> are distinctly <em>Tamil</em> names. The donees whose native villages may be <lb/> presumed to have been situated in the <em>Telugu</em> country need not necessarily have immigra-<lb break="no"/>ted into the <em>Chōḷa</em> country at the time of the grant. They might have been settled there <lb/> sometime before. In any case it is clear that there was a large colony of <em>Telugu</em> <lb/> Brāhmaṇas in the heart of the Chōḷa country during the first half of the 9th century A.D. <lb/> The <em>Telugu</em> <i>birudas</i> of the <em>Pallava</em> king <em>Mahēndravarman</em> found in the Trichinopoly <lb/> cave inscription, <note n="2:519-5"><i>Archaeological Survey Report</i> for 1903-4, p. 271.</note> testify to the influence of the <em>Telugu</em> people in the <em>Chōḷa</em> country <lb/> already in the 7th century A.D. It is worthy of note that a large number of the village <lb/> names are now held as titles by some well-known Śrī-Vaishṇava families—<em>Dvēdai-<lb break="no"/>kōmapuram (Vēdagōmapura), Vaṅgippaṟu (Vaṅgippura), Uruppiṭṭūr (Urup-<lb break="no"/>puṭṭūr), Kārambichchēḍu (Kārambichchēṭṭu), Śrīmalai (Tirumalai), Pat-<lb break="no"/>taṅgi, Vīravaḷḷi (Vīravalli), Muḍumbe, Taṇukkil, Kumāṇḍūr, Puttūr, Śēṭṭa-<lb break="no"/>lūr</em> and <em>Kuṇḍūr</em> being some. <em>Maṇaṟkāl</em> has evidently lent its name to one of the later <lb/> Vaishṇava <i>āchāryas</i> of the 12th century, named <em>Maṇakkāl-Nambi</em>.<pb n="2:520"/></p>

<edition>

<h4 ignore="yes">TEXT. <note n="2:520-1">From the original plates and a set of ink-impressions.</note></h4>

<h4><i>Plate Ia</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:520:99:1"><de>jayandatṣiṇāśām</de><note n="2:520-2">Read <de>ºjayandakṣiº</de>. Two or more plates before this, appear to have been lost. The portion of the <lb/> verse which commences this plate evidently refers to a king who conquered the southern country (<i>Dakshiṇāśā</i>).</note><de>©bhuraṇyutejāḥ punarāvirāsīdaraṇyasaṁsthāpitaśatrulokaḥ [|*] śaraṇyabhūtaśśara-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:2"><de>ṇonmukhānāṁ hiraṇyavarmmā jagatāṁ hitāya ©[1*]</de><note n="2:520-3">Read <de>ºmāñjitaº</de>.</note><de>śrīmāndhīmānjitaripugaṇastejasāndhāma rājā tīro-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:3"><de>pāntasthitajayagajassāgarāṇāñcaturṇṇānmā</de><note n="2:520-4">Read <de>ºturṇṇām | āsīº</de>.</note><de>sīdāśāparitatayaśā nandivarmmeti nāmnā jātastasmātsa-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:4"><de>miti mahitaḥ</de><note n="2:520-5">Read <de>mahitassarvvaśastraº</de>.</note><de>sarvaśāstraprayogaiḥ ©[2*] rājāhvayo yamanamanna mṛitāṁśureko <note n="2:520-6"><de>mṛitāṁśu</de> must be an elegant expression for the moon whose rays, dead in themselves, receive life and light <lb/> only from the sun.</note> yasmai jagatyakara-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:5"><de>do viṣayopyamartyaḥ [|*] yasminnagamyamavati</de><note n="2:520-7">Read <de><ch/>kṣītaº</de>.</note><de>tṣitimindrakalpe prasthānavartma narakam prati ca pra-<lb break="no"/>jānām ©[3*] ya-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:6"><de>ssaccakrasya bharttā haririva vibudhāśśakravadyaṁ śrayante yenābhūdbhūssanāthā sucaritamamalaṁ ro-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:7"><de>cate cāru yasmai [|*] yasmādbhīrekadhīrādyudhi paranṛibhujāṁ yasya kīrtyā daśāśā[ssaṁ]pūrṇṇā[ḥ*] śrīśca yasmi-</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate Ib</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:520:99:8"><de>nnivasati sucirantyaktacāpalyadoṣā ©[4*] udvegaḥ pavane vane capalatāsaṁgaḥ kalāvattṣa-</de><note n="2:520-8">Read <de>ºvatkṣaº</de>.</note></l>

<l n="2:520:99:9"><de>yaḥ</de><note n="2:520-9">Read <de>pakṣe</de>.</note>patṣe śuklavivarjjaye <note n="2:520-10">Read <de>ºvivarjake</de>.</note><de>viṣadharādhikyannidāghātyaye [|*] nistriṁśagrahaṇam bhaṭeṣu marutāñcitre</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:10"><de>vimānasthitiryyasminvipravaradviṣaśca bhujagā eva</de><note n="2:520-11">Read <de>ºkṣiti śāsati</de>.</note><de>tṣitiṁ śāsatiḥ ©[5*] dhatte gaṁgādapahṛitamugro-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:11"><de>dayakaustubhaṁ gaḷābharaṇaṁ [|*] svahṛidayasaṁnnihitācyutaśayanamivāhīndramurasā yaḥ ©[6*] svabha-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:12"><de>rturiva yammado jaya</de><note n="2:520-12">Read <de>ºvāñjaṁgaº</de>.</note><de>ivāṁgavānjaṁgamo girīndra iva paṭṭavarddhana iti dvipendrobhajat [|*] savibhrama-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:13"><de>paribhramadbhramarabṛindagaṇḍūṣita</de><note n="2:520-13">Read <de>ºkṣaraº</de>.</note><de>tṣaranmadaviśeṣaśeṣakṛitamaṇḍagaṇḍasthalaḥ ©[7*] <note n="2:520-14">Read <de>rakṣitasattvaº</de>.</note>ratṣitasatvacchā-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:14"><de>yaḥ priyasatyo ji[ṣṇu]racyuta[ḥ*] śrīmān [|*] yaḥ khalu narakāntātmā haririti bahumanyate vibudhaiḥ ©[8*]</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:520:99:15"><de>tasmai nivedya vidhināṣṭaśatatrayāya vedatrayasmṛitijuṣām viduṣāndvijānām [|*] nāmnā dayāmukha itī-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:16"><de>mamadāpayattaṁ grāmaṁ kṛitī kṛitadayāmukhamaṁgalākhyam ©[9*] asyājñaptirabhūtsa eva matimāndharmmārttha-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:17"><de>kāmopadhāśuddha[śśuddha]caritrapātramamadassvāmyekabhaktivrataḥ [|*] satsāmānyadhanaśca dharmmaśara-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:18"><de>ṇassa[m]bandhiniryyantriṇaḥ</de><note n="2:520-15">Read <de>ºniryyantraṇaḥ</de>.</note><de><note n="2:520-16">Read <de>ºśādhyakṣaº</de>.</note>kośāddhyatṣaniyogakarmmakuśalaḥ kulyaḥ kumārāhvayaḥ ©[10*] yo</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:19"><de>goṣpadāvadhimapi pradadāti bhūmiṁ yo vā haratyagaṇayanparipākamugram [|*] ācandratāramadhiti-</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:20"><de>ṣṭhata eva tau dvau nākaukasāñca sadanannarakañca ghoram ©[11*] dharmmaṁ śarmma kṛitammayā kṛitamimaṁ</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:21"><de><note n="2:520-17">Read <de>ºdīkṣāº</de>.</note><de>sāmrājyadītṣāvrato</de><note n="2:520-18">Read <de>rakṣatyakṣatalakṣaṇaṁ kṣitiº</de>.</note>ratṣatyatṣatalatṣaṇaṁ tṣititale yaḥ <note n="2:520-19">Read <de>kṣūtraº</de>.</note>tṣatracūḷāmaṇiḥ [|*] mūrddhanyatra muku-</de></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:520:99:22"><de>ndavandyacaraṇadvandvaṁ vihāyāpareṣvajñātapraṇato</de><note n="2:520-20">Read <de>ºpraṇatau vasatpeº</de>.</note><de>vasenpadayugantasyetyavocannṛipaḥ ©[12*]</de></l>

<l n="2:520:99:23"><de>gāvaḥ pāvanasarvagātraśucayaḥ kāmāya vassantu yāḥ śuddhiṁ svāmiva darśayanti hi payovyājā-</de><pb n="2:521"/></l>

<l n="2:521:99:24"><de>dduhānā</de><note n="2:521-1">Read <de>ºhānāssvayam</de>.</note><de>svayam [|*] mānyāḥ pāntu mahīsurāśca bhavato vāgāyudhā <note n="2:521-2">Read <de>ºyudhāssvargiṇāṁ</de>.</note>svarggiṇāṁ ye yāgepyamṛitāśi-</de></l>

<l n="2:521:99:25"><de>nāṁ sva[ha]viṣā santoṣamātanvate ©[13*] paramottarakāraṇikasyākṛita kavitāsvayamvṛita-</de></l>

<l n="2:521:99:26"><de>varasya [|*]uttarakāraṇikākhyastanayaḥ parameśvaraḥ praśastimimām ©[14*]</de> <ta>kovicaiya nantivik-<lb break="no"/>kirama-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:27"><ta>parumaṟku yāṇṭu aympatteṭṭāvatu coḻanāṭṭutteṉkarai naṟaiyūrnāṭṭu nā-<lb break="no"/>ṭṭā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:28"><ta>r kāṇka taṅkaṇāṭṭuttaṇṭattoṭṭattukku meṟkukkiṭanta kāṭuṅkarampaiyum ā-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:521:99:29"><ta>m <note n="2:521-3">ṭhis syllable cannot be connected with the letter <ta>ā</ta> at the end of plate II<i>b</i>. Consequently one plate, <lb/> at least, must be missing between II<i>b</i> and III<i>a</i>.</note> paṇṇiyum kuṟaṅkaṟuttum koḷḷappeṟuvā[ril]lātatākavum kūṟṟaṉvāymītey <lb/> uvaṉṟi</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:30"><ta>ceytu nīrkoṇṭu pontu pāyttappeṟuvatākavum cekkum taṟiyumulaviyakkūliyum <lb/> kaṇ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:31"><ta>ṇālakkāṇamum ūreṭṭum kucakkāṇamum taṭṭukkāyamum īḻampūṭciyumiṭaippūṭciyuṅ <lb/> kūla-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:32"><ta>mum tarakupāṭṭamun tirumukakkāṇamumuppukkocceykaiyum nallāvum nallerutum <lb/> vaṭṭinā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:33"><ta>ḻiyuṅ kaṭaiyaṭaikkāyum putānāḻiyumuḷḷiṭṭuk kottoṭṭuṇṇappālaṉa evva-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:34"><ta>kaippaṭṭaṉavumiṟātu ivvūr peṟṟa</ta> <gr>brāhma</gr><ta>ṇare yuṇṇappeṟuvārkaḷākavum tamaṉa-<lb break="no"/>kannaṭap-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:35"><ta>peṟuvatākavum cuṭṭiṭṭikaiyāṟ māṭamāḷikai yeṭukkappeṟuvatākavum turavukiṇaṟi-<lb break="no"/>ḻikkappe-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:36"><ta>ṟuvatākavum kāvuteṅkiṭappeṟuvatākavum peruñcekkiṭappeṟuvatākavum ivvūrel-<lb break="no"/>laiyiṟṟeṅkum</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:37"><ta>paṉaiyumīḻavarēṟappeṟātārākavum ivaiyuḷḷiṭṭa</ta> <gr>sarvvaparihāra</gr><ta>māy</ta> <gr>brahmade</gr><ta>ya[m] <lb/> peṟṟa nalkūr</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IIIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:521:99:38"><ta>naṟpāppār</ta> <gr>kāśyapagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampa cūttirattukkarañcai vattavaṉ kumārako-<lb break="no"/>vaccatu</ta><gr>rvve</gr><ta>ti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:39"><ta>ccomāci paṅkoṉṟum ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr vattavaṉ nārāyaṇa uru-</ta> <lb/> <gr>dra</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvve</gr><ta>ticcomā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:40"><ta>ci paṅkoṉṟum ikkōttiratticcūttirattivvūr vattavaṉ</ta> <gr>viṣṇudāsa</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <lb/> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:41"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattuk kuṇṭūrccaṉṉayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirat-<lb break="no"/>ticcūttirat-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:42"><ta>tivvūr ākkoccaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr <lb/> nārāyaṇa</ta> <gr>vasantayā-</gr></l>

<l n="2:521:99:43"><ta>ji paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr kumāraṭiccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum |||—ikkottiratti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:44"><ta>ccūttirattivvūr veṇṇayaccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattic cūttirat-<lb break="no"/>tivvūr tattakuṭṭic-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:45"><ta>caṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr tattakuṭṭi</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum |||—</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IVa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:521:99:46"><ta>ikkottiratticcūttirattu kuṇṭūr uḻuttirakantaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ik-<lb break="no"/>kottiratticcūt-</ta></l>

<l n="2:521:99:47"><ta>tirattu aṭṭampaṟuttu</ta> <gr>dā</gr><ta>maṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūtti-<lb break="no"/>rattu karippaṟuttu</ta><pb n="2:522"/></l>

<l n="2:522:99:48"><ta>nārāyaṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu vaṅkippaṟuttu <lb/> toṇamattiruve-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:49"><ta>ti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu uviyūr viñcakumāraccaṭaṅkavi paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum [|||—]</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:50"><ta>ikkottiratticcūttirattu amuttaṉūr kovaṭiccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ik-<lb break="no"/>kottiratti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:51"><ta>ccūttirattu uṟuppiṭṭur koṇṭamakkiramavittaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirat-<lb break="no"/>ticcūttirattu kāra-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:52"><ta>mpicceṭṭu kumāraṭittiruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu ceru-<lb break="no"/>ppaḷḷi nārāyaṇac-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:53"><ta>caṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>āśvalā</gr><ta>yaṉacūttirattu paṟiyalūr</ta> <gr>sū-<lb break="no"/>ryyadattabha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ pa-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IVb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:522:99:54"><ta>ṅki[ra]ṇṭum |||—ikkottirattu cantokacūttirattu pāṭakattu mātirupūticcaṭaṅkavic-<lb break="no"/>[co]māci paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:55"><ta>koṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu vāseṇicūttirattu nukuñcūṭṭukkuṇṭa</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ṉ <lb/> paṅku nāṉkum |||—</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:56"><ta>ikkottirattuppaviḻiyacūttirattu nimpey vaṭuka</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ttiruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikkot-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:57"><ta>tirattu ca[n]tokacūttirattu korañci kantakumāraccatu</ta><gr>[r]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—</ta> <lb/> <gr>gautamagotrat-</gr></l>

<l n="2:522:99:58"><ta>tu</ta> <gr>hiraṇyakeśi</gr><ta>cūttirattu pāṟkuḷattu nākakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibhaṭṭa</gr><ta>ccomāci paṅki-<lb break="no"/>raṇṭum ||—i-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:59"><ta>kkottiratticcūttirattu kāynirkkuḷattu kumārakaṇṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum ||| <lb/> ikkotti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:60"><ta>rattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu kuṟukoṭṭikkantakumārakkiramavittaṉ paṅkoṉṟum ||| <lb/> ikkottirat-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:61"><ta>ticcūttirattivvūr uḻuttiraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu āpattampa <lb/> cūttirattu nel-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate Va</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:522:99:62"><ta>lūr caṉṉayattiruveti</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu paṟān-<lb break="no"/>tūr accuvaṉa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:63"><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu aṅkāraikkumārakūḷaccatu-</ta> <lb/> <gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:64"><ta>ṉṟum ||| ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr kaṇṇakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum ||[|] <lb/> ikkottira-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:65"><ta>tticcūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu kaṇatāyaccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirat-<lb break="no"/>ticcū-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:66"><ta>ttirattu irāyūr attuvaccaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirat-<lb break="no"/>tu vaṅkippa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:67"><ta>ṟuttu tāmotiraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu ākki-<lb break="no"/>tatta</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ccaṭaṅkavi</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:68"><ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—āttiraiya</ta><gr>gotra</gr><ta>ttu āpattampacūttirattu vaṅkippaṟuttu tukka-</ta> <lb/> <gr>śarmmatri[ve]-</gr></l>

<l n="2:522:99:69"><gr>di</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum ||| ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr</ta> <gr>harisvā</gr><ta>miccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum |||—ikk[o]-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate Vb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:522:99:70"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattu</ta> <gr>dve</gr><ta>taikompaṟuttu</ta><note n="2:522-1">Read <gr>dve</gr><ta>taikōmpuṟattu;</ta> see above p. 259, note 3.</note><ta>maṇikkuṭṭaccatu </ta><gr>r[vvedi]</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum [|||] <lb/> ikkot[tiratti]c[cū]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:71"><ta>ttirattivvūr nārāyaṇauḻutaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||— ikkottiratticcūtti-<lb break="no"/>rattu mu[ṭi]paṟuttu</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:72"><ta>tāmotiraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattuppaṟā-<lb break="no"/>ntūr kumāraceṭṭac-</ta></l>

<l n="2:522:99:73"><ta>catu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu vaṅkippaṟuttu kantamaccatu-</ta> <lb/> <gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅko-</ta><pb n="2:523"/></l>

<l n="2:523:99:74"><ta>ṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu muṭapaṟuttu nārāyaṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum ||| ikkot-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:75"><ta>tiratticcūttirattu karañcai teva</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirat-<lb break="no"/>ticcūttirattu uhali vi-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:76"><ta>ṇṇayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu vaṅkippa-<lb break="no"/>ṟuttu tāmotiratti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:77"><ta>ruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu uhali nārāyaṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi-<lb break="no"/>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate VIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:523:99:78"><note n="2:523-1">A plate must be missing between V<i>b</i> and VI<i>a</i>.</note> <gr>vaskanda</gr><ta>ccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr</ta> <gr>svāmiśarmma</gr><ta>c-<lb break="no"/>caṭaṅkavi paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:79"><ta>ṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr</ta> <gr>viṣṇudattabha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ik-<lb break="no"/>kottiratticcūt-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:80"><ta>tirattu pāṭakattu</ta> <gr>svāmi</gr><ta>tevaccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>hiraṇya-<lb break="no"/>keśi</gr><ta>cūttirat-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:81"><ta>tuk kaḷattūr</ta> <gr>suku</gr><ta>māraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu āvattampa-<lb break="no"/>cūttirattu</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:82"><ta>kākkaimirāttu</ta> <gr>bhavadāsadaśa</gr><ta>puriyaṉ paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>āgniveśyagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvat-<lb break="no"/>tam-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:83"><ta>pacūttirattu virippaṟuttu viñcakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <lb/> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūtti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:84"><ta>rattu irāyūr kuṇṭicāmittiruveti paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>bhāradvājagotra</gr><ta>ttu cantoka-<lb break="no"/>cūttirattu ve-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:85"><ta>ṇṇainallūr</ta> <gr>agni</gr><ta>koṇṭaccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu <lb/> pattaṅki kū-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate VIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:523:99:86"><ta>ḷamaṇṭaiccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr attāḻic-<lb break="no"/>caṭaṅkavi paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:87"><ta>ṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattup pāṭakattu</ta> <gr>urudranantibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaccomāci paṅki-<lb break="no"/>raṇṭum |||—ik-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:88"><ta>kottirattu āvattampacūttirattu poppaṟuttu</ta> <gr>viṣṇu</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikkottirattu</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:89"><ta>iccūttirattu kuṇṭur kantakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>ratticcū-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:90"><ta>ttirattu k[ā]rampicceṭṭu akkoṟṟaccatu</ta><gr>[r]vvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum ||| ikkot-<lb break="no"/>tiratticcūtti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:91"><ta>rattu uviyūr nārā[ya*]ṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu <lb/> karañcai</ta> <gr>bhavaskanda</gr><ta>ccaṭaṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:92"><ta>kavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu paṟāntūr</ta> <gr>yajña</gr><ta>māta[va*]ccatu-</ta> <lb/> <gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ik-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:93"><ta>kottiratticcūttirattu uviyūr uḻutakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkot-<lb break="no"/>tiratticcūttirattu</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate VIIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:523:99:94"><ta>cāntūr aṇṇamañciccatu</ta><gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu pi-<lb break="no"/>ṇukkippaṟun-</ta><note n="2:523-2">Read <ta>piṇukkippaṟuttu</ta>.</note></l>

<l n="2:523:99:95"><ta>tu</ta> <gr>vi[ṣṇu]dāsa</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kuravacirip-<lb break="no"/>pavamātavaccatu</ta><gr>rvve-</gr></l>

<l n="2:523:99:96"><gr>di</gr><ta>ccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kumiḻur tevaṭiccatu</ta><gr>rvve-<lb break="no"/>di</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum [|*]</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:97"><ta>ikkottiratticcūttirattuttaṇukkil akkūḷaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:98"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattu poppaṟuttu maṇṭaiyaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr><ta>ccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:523:99:99"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattu kāṭṭukkuṟi kūḷa</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>ratticcūttirat-</ta><pb n="2:524"/></l>

<l n="2:524:99:100"><ta>tu uviyūr</ta> <gr>viṣṇu</gr><ta>kumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattic-<lb break="no"/>cūttirattut taṇukkil</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:101"><gr>viṣṇu</gr><ta>kumārattiruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kāṭṭukkuṟi-</ta> <lb/> <gr>brahmada</gr><ta>ttatti-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate VIIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:524:99:102"><ta>ruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu poṉṉampaṟuttu nārāya-<lb break="no"/>ṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr></l>

<l n="2:524:99:103"><ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr toṇayattiruveti paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum |||—ikkotti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:104"><ta>ratticcūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu uḻutakumārattiruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikko-<lb break="no"/>ttiratticcūttirattu</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:105"><ta>makacirai toṇamaṇṭaiccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu-<lb break="no"/>karañcai</ta> <gr>vrarddha</gr><ta>ma</ta><note n="2:524-1">Read <gr>vṛiddhaº</gr>.</note><ta>-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:106"><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kuravaciri viṇṇakantac-<lb break="no"/>catu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:107"><ta>ṉṟum ||| ikkottirattu iccūttirattu vaṅkippaṟuttu kantakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum |||—ikko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:108"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattu kāracciṟai caṉṉayattiruveticcomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikkottiratticcūttirat-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:109"><ta>tu kurovi veṇṇayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu-<lb break="no"/>kumiḻur kāmayaccatu-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate VIIIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:524:99:110"><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu ūṭṭukkūr nāka</ta><gr>viṣṇu</gr><ta>kkirama-<lb break="no"/>vittaṉ pa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:111"><ta>ṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu makacirai nārāyaṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum ||| [ik-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:112"><note n="2:524-2">The whole of this line is scored out in the original.</note> <ta>kottiratticcūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu] na • • • • •</ta> <ta>[yaccatu-</ta> <lb/> <gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—] i-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:113"><ta>kkottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu maṇaṟkāl</ta> <gr>sarvvakra</gr><ta>tuyāci tattaṅkumāṉ <note n="2:524-3">Read <ta>kumaraṉ</ta>.</note> paṅku <lb/> [mū]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:114"><ta>ṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr tattañcāttaṉ paṅkiraṇṭum |||—ik-<lb break="no"/>kottiratti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:115"><ta>ccūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu appūticcatu</ta><gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirat-<lb break="no"/>ticcūttirattu irā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:116"><ta>yūr nārāyaṇa</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr coṭ-<lb break="no"/>ṭe</ta><note n="2:524-4">Read <ta>coṭṭai </ta>.</note> <gr>mādhavabha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:117"><ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu ceṭṭalūr attāḻittiruveti paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum ||| i-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate VIIIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:524:99:118"><ta>kkottirattu paviḻiyacūttirattu aṇuppūr</ta> <gr>bha</gr><ta>varu</ta><gr>dra</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikkotti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:119"><ta>rattu</ta> <gr>bhāradvāja</gr><ta>cūttirattu [mi]rāṅkaḷūr nārāyaṇa</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ik-<lb break="no"/>kottiratticcūt-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:120"><ta>tirattu kāñcikkuṟi irāttamāttiruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu kāḷar-<lb break="no"/>caccūttirattu</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:121"><ta>mantirattu pavatāyattiruveti paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>vatsagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu <lb/> nampū-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:122"><ta>r veṇṇa</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu <lb/> kulaputti ve-</ta></l>

<l n="2:524:99:123"><ta>ṇṇayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu nampūr</ta> <gr>bhavasā</gr><ta>mic-<lb break="no"/>catu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅko-</ta><pb n="2:525"/></l>

<l n="2:525:99:124"><ta>ṉṟum [|]||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kulaputti attāyaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum <lb/> |||—ikkottira-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:125"><ta>tticcūttirattu nampūr</ta> <gr>yajña</gr><ta>māta[va*]ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikko-<lb break="no"/>ttiratticcūttirattu</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IXa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:525:99:126"><note n="2:525-1">A plate must be missing between VIII<i>b</i> and IX<i>a</i>.</note> <ta>ttiratticcūttirattu ceruppaḷḷi toṇamakkiramavittaṉum ivaṉ makaṉ kumāra[ṭi]k-<lb break="no"/>kiramavittaṉu[mā]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:127"><ta>yppaṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu tevapūticcatu-</ta> <lb/> <gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>[paṅ]koṉṟum [|]</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:128"><ta>ikkottiratticcūttirattu ayiyakki attoṇaccaṭaṅkaviccomāci paṅku panniraṇ-<lb break="no"/>ṭum ||—i-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:129"><ta>kkottiratticcūttirattu muṭumpeccaṉṉa kumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum <lb/> |||—ikk[o]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:130"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattu karañcai veṇṇayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>rattu canto-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:131"><ta>kacūttirattu muṭumpe akkantaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūtti-<lb break="no"/>rattu pippa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:132"><ta>rai akkantaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum [|||—] ikkottiratticcūttirattu muṭumpe-<lb break="no"/>kūḷa</ta><gr>śarmmakrama-</gr></l>

<l n="2:525:99:133"><ta>vittaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu kuṇṭur tāmo-<lb break="no"/>tiraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>pa-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate IXb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:525:99:134"><ta>ṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu veḷḷaiyūr</ta> <gr>viṣṇubhū</gr><ta>ticcatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <lb/> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>mu-</gr></l>

<l n="2:525:99:135"><note n="2:525-2">Read <gr>mudgala</gr>.</note> <gr>tgalagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu iḻakkantoṟuttu kaṭampa</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum |||—ikko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:136"><ta>ttiratticcūttirattu uṟuppiṭṭur</ta> <gr>bhavaskanda</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>ratticcūttirattu i-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:137"><ta>ḻakkantoṟuttu</ta> <gr>yajña</gr><ta>yaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattil-<lb break="no"/>vūr kāḷa</ta><gr>śa-</gr></l>

<l n="2:525:99:138"><gr>rmma</gr><ta>ttiruv[e]ti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr pavacāmittiru-<lb break="no"/>veti paṅkoṉṟu-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:139"><ta>m |||— ikkottiratticcūttirattu paṟāntūr eṟamattiruveti paṅkoṉṟum ||| ik-<lb break="no"/>kottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vaca-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:140"><ta>ṉacūttirattu ayyakki ceṭṭayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>śu</gr><ta>ṉaka</ta><gr>gotra</gr><ta>ttu <lb/> āvattampacūtti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:141"><ta>rattu maṇiyūr pocaṉpavvikkiramavittaṉ paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <note n="2:525-3">Read <gr>rathi</gr><ta>tara</ta>.</note> <gr>rāthi</gr><ta>tara</ta><gr>gotra</gr><ta>ttu ā-<lb break="no"/>vattampa[cū]-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate Xa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:525:99:142"><ta>ttirattu ōrikoṉṟai kumārapūticcatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattic-<lb break="no"/>cūttirattu kuravaciri ca-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:143"><ta>ṉṉakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr attiku-<lb break="no"/>ṭṭiccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:144"><ta>koṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu paviḻiyacūttirattu meṟṟāmaṇamaṅkalattu uttara-<lb break="no"/>k[ā]raṇikaṉāyiṉa</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:145"><ta>[ayyaṉ]</ta> <gr>parameśva</gr><ta>raṉ paṅkiraṇṭum</ta> |||— <gr>garggagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu kārama-<lb break="no"/>picceṭṭu</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:146"><ta>[m]ātavat[ti]ruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kuñcappayl <note n="2:525-4">Read <ta>ºpayal</ta>.</note> <lb/> ha</ta><gr>risvā</gr><ta>miccatu</ta><gr>rvve-</gr></l>

<l n="2:525:99:147"><gr>di</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr kantaṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅko-<lb break="no"/>ṉṟum |||—ikkottira-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:148"><ta>tticcūttirattu maṟṟalūr caṉṉayaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattic-<lb break="no"/>cūttirattu kuñcap-</ta></l>

<l n="2:525:99:149"><ta>pevil</ta> <gr>bhavaśarmma</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu paviḻiyacūt-<lb break="no"/>tirattu vaṅkippa-</ta><pb n="2:526"/></l>

<h4><i>Plate Xb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:526:99:150"><ta>ṟuttu tāmotira</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>vādhūlagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūtti-<lb break="no"/>rattu kārampicceṭ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:151"><ta>ṭu kantāṭai</ta> <gr>vāsu</gr><ta>tevaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu <lb/> karañcai maṇṭai[ya]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:152"><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu kantā-<lb break="no"/>ṭai</ta> <gr>vāsude</gr><ta>vaccatu</ta><gr>[rvve]-</gr></l>

<l n="2:526:99:153"><gr>dibha</gr><ta>ṭṭa</ta> <gr>agnicittasarvvakra</gr><ta>tuyāci paṅku muṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr</ta> <lb/> <gr>suyajñakeśa-</gr></l>

<l n="2:526:99:154"><ta>vaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr nārāya-<lb break="no"/>ṇaccatu</ta><gr>r[vve]di</gr> <ta>paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:155"><ta>koṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kuṇṭur caṉṉayattiruveti paṅkoṉṟum</ta> <lb/> |||— <gr>lohitago-</gr></l>

<l n="2:526:99:156"><gr>tra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu</ta> <gr>agniśarmma</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikkottiratti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:157"><ta>ccūttirattivvūr tiṇṭakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūt-<lb break="no"/>tirattivvūr tāmotirac-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:526:99:158"><note n="2:526-1">A plate must be missing between X<i>b</i> and XI<i>a</i>.</note> <ta>ttirattu śrīmalai</ta> <gr>agnirudra</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum [|||—] ikkottirat-<lb break="no"/>ticcūttirat-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:159"><ta>tu vaṅkippaṟuttu centakumāraccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>bhārggavagotra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <lb/> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉa cūtti-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:160"><ta>rattu maṇaṟkāl āytāṅki caṅkarañcentaṉ paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>kauśikagotra</gr><ta>ttu <lb/> āva-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:161"><ta>ttampacūttirattu irāttakkuṟi</ta> <gr>keśa</gr><ta>vaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>ratticcū-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:162"><ta>ttirattu velvaṭṭi nākoṇṭaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr><ta>ccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkot-<lb break="no"/>tirattic-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:163"><ta>cūttirattu karañcai</ta> <gr>jayanta</gr><ta>ru</ta><gr>dra</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūt-<lb break="no"/>tirattu paṟān-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:164"><ta>tūr uru</ta><gr>draśarmmadaśa</gr><ta>puriyaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu ceṭṭa-<lb break="no"/>ḷūr</ta> <gr>suyajñabha-</gr></l>

<l n="2:526:99:165"><ta>vasenattiruveti</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu <lb/> koṭṭuṅko-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:526:99:166"><ta>mpaṟuttu <note n="2:526-2">Read <ta>koṭṭuṅkompuṟattu</ta>.</note> uḻutakuṭṭi</ta><gr>daśa</gr><ta>puriyaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu <lb/> kuravaciri</ta> <gr>viṣṇu-</gr></l>

<l n="2:526:99:167"><ta>kumāra</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu karañcai <lb/> koraṭiccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr></l>

<l n="2:526:99:168"><ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu kumāṇṭur tiyampakaccaṭaṅkavi paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟu-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:169"><ta>m |||— ikkottiratticcūttirattu velvaṭṭi</ta> <gr>agni</gr><ta>cittaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—<lb break="no"/>ikko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:170"><ta>ttiratti[c]cūttirattivvūr kumāramaṇṭaittiruveti paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>rattu cant[o]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:171"><ta>kacūttirattu ēkampūr nārāyaṇaccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūtti-<lb break="no"/>rattu arasa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:172"><ta>ppaṟuttu toṇamaccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>bhāradvāja</gr><ta>cūttira-<lb break="no"/>ttu paṟāntūr</ta></l>

<l n="2:526:99:173"><gr>de</gr><ta>vakumāra</ta><gr>kra</gr><ta>mavittaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu kāḷarccacūttirattu pe-<lb break="no"/>ruvali ko-</ta><pb n="2:527"/></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:527:99:174"><ta>vaṭiccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu pava-<lb break="no"/>kkuṟi tiṇṭamā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:175"><ta>taccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr><ta>ccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr cāmiku-<lb break="no"/>ṭṭiccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:176"><ta>koṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>hiraṇyakeśi</gr><ta>cūttirattu perumpāṇṭur nārāyaṇa</ta><gr>bha-</gr> <lb/> <ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:177"><ta>koṉṟum [|||—]</ta> <gr>śālāvatagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu velpaṟuttu tūrkkamac-<lb break="no"/>catu</ta><gr>rvve-</gr></l>

<l n="2:527:99:178"><gr>di</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr kantakumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:179"><ta>ṟum |||—</ta> <gr>kutsagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu otimūkkil</ta> <gr>mādhava</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum |||—</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:180"><gr>vasiṣṭhagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu kuravaciri attikumāraccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:181"><ta>ṟum |||— ikkottiratticcūttirattu vīravaḷḷi accaṭṭittiruveti paṅkoṉṟum <lb/> |||— ikkottira-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:527:99:182"><ta>tticcūttirattu [va]ṅkippaṟuttu</ta> <gr>di</gr><ta>vākara</ta><gr>krama</gr><ta>vittaṉ paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkotti-<lb break="no"/>ratticcūttirat-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:183"><ta>tu eṭṭukkūr kaṇavuḻuttatiruveti paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>sāvarṇṇigotra</gr><ta>ttu canto-<lb break="no"/>kacūttira-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:184"><ta>ttu pāṭakattu nār[āya]ṇa</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum ||| ikkottiratticcūttirattivvūr <lb/> conikuṭṭic-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:185"><ta>catu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>parāśaragotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu kallakkūrp <lb/> pāppa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:186"><ta>ṭiccatu</ta><gr>r[vve]di</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu oṅkaḷūr akkumārac-<lb break="no"/>catu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:187"><ta>koṉṟum |||—ikkottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu vaṅkippaṟuttu accentattiru-<lb break="no"/>veti paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:188"><ta>ṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>vārakhyagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu pūṉiyattu ceṭṭa</ta><gr>śarmma</gr><ta>ṉ paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum |||—kapi-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:189"><gr>gotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu paṟāntūr</ta> <gr>maheśvara</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum |||— ik-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIIIa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:527:99:190"><ta>kottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu perumpūtūr kumāratattattiruveti paṅkoṉṟum</ta> <lb/> |||— <gr>dhūmrā-</gr></l>

<l n="2:527:99:191"><gr>yaṇagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu uṟuppiṭṭūrccaṉṉayattiruveti paṅkoṉ-<lb break="no"/>ṟum |||—</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:192"><ta>pauru</ta><gr>kutsagotra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu koṭṭi</ta> <gr>agniśarmma</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>[r]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅ-<lb break="no"/>koṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>gau-</gr></l>

<l n="2:527:99:193"><gr>tamagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu kārampicceṭṭu nantikuṭṭittiruveti paṅkoṉ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:194"><ta>ṟum</ta> |||— <gr>kāśyapagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu karañcai kantapūti</ta><gr>ddaśa</gr><ta>puriyaṉ <lb/> paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:195"><ta>ṉṟum ||</ta> <gr>sāṅkra</gr><ta>tikottirattu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉacūttirattu iruṅkaṇṭi ku</ta><gr>māraśarmma</gr><ta>ccaṭa-<lb break="no"/>ṅkavi paṅ-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:196"><ta>koṉṟum |||—hā</ta><gr>ritagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampacūttirattu kākkaimirāttu</ta> <gr>yajñaśarmma</gr><ta>c-<lb break="no"/>catu</ta><gr>rvvedi-</gr></l>

<l n="2:527:99:197"><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅk[o]ṉṟum |||—tiruvaṭikaḷukkuppaṅku ayintu</ta> <gr>mah[ā*]de</gr><ta>varkkuppaṅ-<lb break="no"/>kiraṇṭum</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIIIb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:527:99:198"><gr>bhāra</gr><ta>tam [v*]ācippāṉukkuppaṅkoṉṟum |||—taṭṭaḻikoṭṭikaḷukkuppaṅkoṉṟum</ta> <lb/> |||— <gr>madhyastha</gr><ta>r</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:199"><ta>mūvarkkum paṅku mūṉṟum ||— ampalantaṇṇīraṭṭuvārkkum tīyerippāṉukkumākappa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:527:99:200"><ta>ṅkoṉṟum |||—miḻalaināṭṭuppuliyūr</ta> <gr>ṛiṣivaikhānasan satya</gr><ta>kaṟpa</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉ-</ta><pb n="2:528"/></l>

<l n="2:528:99:201"><ta>ṟum |||— vai</ta><gr>dya</gr><ta>rkkuppaṅkiraṇṭum</ta> |||— <gr>vādhūlagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampa cūttirattu <lb/> kārampi-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:202"><ta>cceṭṭu kantāṭai</ta> <gr>vāsudeva</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>[r*]vvedibha</gr><ta>ṭṭa</ta><gr>agni</gr><ta>citta</ta><gr>ssarvvakra</gr><ta>tuvācaveci</ta><note n="2:528-1">Read <gr>sarvakra</gr><ta>tuvājapeyi</ta>.</note> <lb/> <ta>paṅko-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:203"><ta>ṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>vatsagotra</gr><ta>ttu āvattampa <note n="2:528-2"><ta>mpa</ta> is written below the line.</note>cūttirattu nūttilāppaṟuttu maṇṭaiyaccatu- </ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:204"><gr>rvvedi</gr><ta>ccomāci paṅkoṉṟum |||—ikkottiratticcūttirattu vaṅkippaṟuttu</ta> <lb/> <gr>bhava[ru]-</gr></l>

<l n="2:528:99:205"><gr>dra</gr><ta>ccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>pa[ṅ]koṉṟum |||— <note n="2:528-3">From the middle of this line beginning with <ta>kūṟṟaṉ vāy</ta> the writing is in a different hand.</note>kūṟṟaṉvāyiṉiṉṟum nirīyntavāṟuṇṇappaṇi-</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIVa</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:528:99:206"><ta>ttem</ta><note n="2:528-4">Read <ta>ºttom</ta>. The exact sense conveyed by this sentence is not clear. Literally translated it means <lb/> “we ordered that water may be utilised in the manner in which it is given from the main sluice.” In ll. 29 ff. <lb/> it is stated that the donees had to irrigate their fields from a head of water constructed somewhere outside the <lb/> main sluice. Perhaps the distribution of water was intended to be further specified by the phrase inserted here.</note> <gr>|||— bhāradvājagotra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vaccaṉṉa</ta><note n="2:528-5">Read <gr>prāvacana</gr>.</note><ta>cūttirattu irāyūr nārāyaṇa</ta><gr>[da]tta-<lb break="no"/>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:207"><ta>ṉ paṅkoṉṟum ||—ikkottirattu āvattampacūttirattu kāracciṟai caṉṉayaccatu-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:208"><gr>[r*]vvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum</ta> <gr>||— māṭharagotra</gr><ta>ttu</ta><note n="2:528-6">The subscript grantha <i>ya</i> in <gr>hiraṇa</gr>, is added to the Tamil <i>na</i> which is a mistake for <i>ṇa</i>.</note><ta>hi</ta><gr>raṇyakeśisūtra</gr><ta>ttu kommārai</ta> <lb/> <gr>svāmidatta-</gr></l>

<l n="2:528:99:209"><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum || kā</ta><gr>śyapagotra</gr><ta>ttu cantokacūttirattuppāṭakattukkaṉmā-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:210"><ta>taccaṭaṅkavi paṅkoṉṟum</ta> || <gr>garggagotra</gr><ta>ttu āva[t*]tampacūttirattu kuñcappevil</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:211"><ta>nakkat[o]ṇaccatu</ta><gr>rvvedi</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum || pātara[ṇi]</ta><gr>gotra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vaccaṉṉa</ta> <note type="repeated" n="2:528-5"/><ta>cū-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:212"><ta>ttirattu talaiccaṅkāṭṭukkalaiyañcomaṉ paṅkoṉṟum</ta> || <gr>bhāradvājago-</gr></l>

<l n="2:528:99:213"><gr>tra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vaccaṉṉa</ta> <note type="repeated" n="2:528-5"/><ta>cūttirattuppayyūrppaṭuvuḻāṉ</ta> <gr>di</gr><ta>vākarañcāmi paṅkoṉṟum</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:214"><gr>madhyastha</gr><ta>r</ta> <gr>pa</gr><ta>ṅku mu[ṉ*]ṟum perumpuḷḷe virakantaṉ oṉṟum (|) ivvūr</ta> <gr>ṛi[ṣa]bha</gr><ta>nanti <lb/> oṉṟum</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:215"><ta>pāṭakattu kuṇataraṉum [a]kaḻimaṅkalattuttiruppi[ṭavū]rccā[mi]yumāka oṉṟum pe-<lb break="no"/>ṟṟār [|||—*]</ta></l>

<h4><i>Plate XIVb</i>.</h4>

<l n="2:528:99:216"><ta>aruvānāṭṭu aruvākūr</ta> <gr>ṛi[ṣi]vaikhā</gr><ta>nasaṉ caṅkaranārāyaṇa</ta><gr>bha</gr><ta>ṭṭaṉ paṅkoṉṟum || <lb/> [vai]-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:217"><gr>dya</gr><ta>ppaṅkiraṉṭum <note n="2:528-7">Read <ta>paṅkiraṇṭum</ta>.</note> īykkāṭṭukkoyilāṉ para</ta><gr>meśvara</gr><ta>ṉ peṟṟāṉ [||] aruvānāṭṭut <lb/> tāma-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:218"><ta>nallūr</ta> <gr>ṛiṣivaikhānasan nārāyaṇabhaṭṭan</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum</ta> |||— <gr>sāva[r*]ṇṇi gottra-</gr> <lb/> <ta>ttu ciṟupaḻuvū</ta><gr>rttu</gr><ta>veti kāṭa-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:219"><ta>mpālaiy[ku]pperumakkaḷ paṇittukkuṭutta paṅkoṉṟum</ta> ||| <gr>vatsagotra</gr><ta>ttu</ta> <gr>prā</gr><ta>vacaṉa-</ta> <lb/> <gr>sūtra</gr><ta>ttu ku-</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:220"><ta>kkaṉūr [vi]ṭṭa</ta><gr>śarmmakramavittan</gr> <ta>paṅkoṉṟum ||—vāyttalaikkumuvaṉṟikkumāka paṅ-<lb break="no"/>ku mūṉṟum |||—</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:221"><ta>āttiraya</ta> <gr>gottra[t*]tu agniveśyacū</gr><ta>ttirattupputtūrc comācikāri paṅkiraṇṭum</ta></l>

<l n="2:528:99:222"><ta>ikkottiratticcū[ttira*]ttu ivvūr comāci[ta*]ttaṉ paṅkiraṇṭum |||—</ta></l>

<translation>

<h4 ignore="yes">TRANSLATION.</h4>

<p>(<i>Verse</i> 1.) (<i>Once</i>) again, for the good of the world was born <em>Hiraṇyavarman</em> of <lb/> stirring prowess who made (<i>his</i>) enemies settle in forests and was the asylum of those <lb/> who eagerly desired protection.</p>

<p>(V. 2.) From him was born the wise (<i>and</i>) prosperous king called Nandivarman who <lb/> was the home of prowess (<i>and</i>) conqueror of the hoards of (<i>his</i>) enemies, whose victorious <pb n="2:529"/> <lb/> elephants reached almost the shores of the four oceans, whose fame extended to the (<i>four</i>) <lb/> quarters and who was praised in battle for (<i>his knowledge in</i>) the use of all weapons.</p>

<p>(V. 3.) The only (<i>one</i>) of name <i>rāja</i> that did not bow to him was the dead-rayed <lb/> (<i>moon</i>) and the (<i>only</i>) country in this world, that did not pay him tribute was (<i>that</i>) where <lb/> no men exist (<i>i.e. the heaven where the undying gods live</i>). And while this (<i>king</i>), comparable <lb/> to Indra was ruling the earth, there was (<i>nothing</i>) unapproachable by the people (<i>except, <lb/> perhaps,</i>) the way leading to hell. <note n="2:529-1">There is a pun intended here in the words <i>rāja</i> (which means both ‘king’ and ‘moon’) and <i>amartya</i>. <lb/> In the second half of the verse the poet wants to say that the people were not allowed to go to hell (<i>i.e.</i> to <lb/> commit sin) but were free to achieve every other object of life.</note></p>

<p>(V. 4.) <note n="2:529-2">A rhetorical effect is aimed at by the use in their order of the seven cases of the pronoun <i>yat</i> which <lb/> refers to the king.</note>He is the lord of the circle of good people as <em>Hari</em> (is the possessor of the <lb/> powerful weapon <i>chakra</i>); him the wise cling to as (<i>gods</i>) to Śakra (<i>i.e. Indra</i>); by him the <lb/> earth <note n="2:529-3">The two well-known consorts of Vishṇu are the goddesses Lakshmī and the Earth.</note> has become coupled with a husband; to whom faultless good deeds are most welcome; <lb/> at whom the sole hero on the battle-field <note n="2:529-4">The actual words used for ‘sole hero’ are <i>ēka-dhīra</i>. It is not impossible that Ēkadhīra was a surname of <lb/> Nandivarman III. From the Kāśākuḍi plates we learn that Ēkadhīra was a surname of Nandivarman Pallava- <lb/> malla or of his minister Udayachandra. Ēkadhīramaṅgalam, the new name given to Koḍukoḷḷi in these <lb/> plates, corresponds to Ēkadhīra-chaturvēdimaṅgalam, a village somewhere near Tirunāmanallūr in the South <lb/> Arcot district (<i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. VII., p. 133).</note> the enemy-kings take fright; of whom the fame <lb/> fills the ten quarters; and in whom <em>Śrī</em> (<i>i.e.</i> <em>Lakshmī</em>) dwells permanently abandoning <lb/> (<i>her</i>) vice of fickleness.</p>

<p>(V. 5.) While this (<i>king</i>) was ruling the earth, anxiety (<i>or great rush) (was seen</i>) only <lb/> in the wind; tendency towards inconstancy (<i>or existence of the creeper chapalā</i>), in the forest; <lb/> decay of the learned (<i>or the waning of the moon</i>), in the dark-fortnight; increase of serpents <lb/> (<i>or abundance of clouds</i>) at the end of summer; merciless attack (<i>or the grasping of swords</i>), in <lb/> soldiers; dishonourable living (<i>or the riding on aerial cars</i>), in the pictures of gods; and <lb/> the enemies of good Brāhmaṇas (<i>or able snake-charmers</i>), in dissolute persons (<i>or serpents)</i>. <note n="2:529-5">The purport of the verse is that <i>anxiety, inconstancy, decay of learning, etc</i>., were not found in his <lb/> kingdom. This is expressed by the poet when he says, with pun, that they <i>were existing</i> elsewhere but not <lb/> in his kingdom.</note></p>

<p>(V. 6.) He wore on (<i>his</i>) breast, as (<i>if it were</i>) the lord of serpents, the bed of <lb/> <em>Achyuta</em> (<i>dwelling</i>) near his heart, a necklace which he had snatched away from the Gaṅga <lb/> (<i>king and in which was</i>) the gem called <em>Ugrōdaya</em> (<i>like the) Kaustubha</i>.</p>

<p>(V. 7.) To his lot (<i>also</i>) fell an excellent elephant named <em>Paṭṭavardhana</em> which (<i>in <lb/> appearance</i>) was like the (<i>manifest</i>) arrogance of its master, like victory in body, like a high <lb/> mountain moving about, (<i>and</i>) from whose temples the ornament (<i>of red paint</i>) was wiped <lb/> away by the excess of flowing rut sipped by the swarm of bees whirling about restlessly. <note n="2:529-6">The Śaiva saint Sundaramūrti-Nāyaṉār in his <i>Tiruppadiyam</i> on Vaḍamullaivāyil refers to a rutting <lb/> elephant which the god of that place is said to have controlled by binding it with a twig and thereby conferring <lb/> immeasurable joy on the Toṇḍaimāṉ, <i>i.e.</i>, the Pallava king. It is not impossible that in the verb <i>abhajat</i> which <lb/> also means ‘worshipped’, we may have to understand a parallel if not the identical incident mentioned <lb/> in the sacred hymn. The age of Sundaramūrti-Nāyaṉār could not have been long distant from that of Vijaya- <lb/> Nandivikramavarman III.</note></p>

<p>(V. 8.) Wise men (<i>and gods</i>) praise him as Hari (<i>himself</i>); because indeed he offers <lb/> protection to (<i>all</i>) living beings (<i>as Hari preserves within his own self the rudiments of life</i>);<pb n="2:530"/> <lb/> loves truth (<i>as Hari loves his consort <em>Satyā</em></i>); is victorious <i><em>(Jishṇu)</em></i>; firm <i><em>(Achyuta)</em></i>; <lb/> glorious (<i>as <em>Hari</em> is united with <em>Śrī</em> i.e. <em>Lakshmī</em></i>) and is, among men (<i>possessed</i>) of a <lb/> lovely body (<i>as <em>Hari</em> is an embodiment of Death to the demon <em>Naraka</em></i>).</p>

<p>(V. 9.) The pious man whose name was <em>Dayāmukha</em> having informed this (<i>king</i>) <lb/> according to rule, got that village which received the surname <em>Dayāmukhamaṅgala</em>, <lb/> granted to three hundred and eight learned Brāhmaṇas who had studied the three Vēdas and <lb/> the Smṛitis.</p>

<p>(V. 10.) That same respectable wise man named <em>Kumāra</em> who (<i>has stood</i>) the test of <lb/> honesty (<i>upadhā</i>) who is pure in (<i>enjoying</i>) religious merit (<i>dharma</i>), wealth (<i>artha</i>) and <lb/> desires (<i>kāma</i>), who is the receptacle of upright conduct, prideless and devoted solely to the <lb/> service of (<i>his</i>) master, whose wealth is shared by (<i>all</i>) good men, who seeks refuge in virtue, <lb/> is free to (<i>all his</i>) relations and is clever in discharging the duties of a treasurer, was the <lb/> <i>ājñapti</i> <note n="2:530-1">For the correct interpretation of the word <i>ājñapti</i> see <i>Ep. Ind</i>., Vol. VII., p. 183 f.</note> of this (<i>grant</i>).</p>

<p>(V. 11.) He that grants land even though it be (<i>in extent</i>) as big as the hoof of a cow and <lb/> he that robs (<i>it</i>) without caring for the disastrous end, shall both of them dwell, indeed, till <lb/> the moon and the stars last, (<i>the first, however,</i>) in the home of the gods and (<i>the second</i>) in <lb/> dreadful hell.</p>

<p>(V. 12.) The king says—I have sought shelter in religious merit. (<i>Every</i>) head-jewel <lb/> among kings who has taken the vow to maintain sovereignty on the surface of the earth, <lb/> shall protect this deed (<i>of mine</i>) without distrubing (<i>its</i>) scheme. May his pair of feet dwell <lb/> on this (<i>my</i>) head, which never knew of bowing down to others excepting to the pair of the <lb/> worshipful feet of <em>Mukunda (Vishṇu)</em>.</p>

<p>(V. 13.) May the sacred cows whose every limb is purifying (<i>and</i>) whose purity is indeed <lb/> demonstrated (<i>materially</i>), as it were, in the form of the (white) milk which they yield, grant <lb/> your desires ! And may the revered gods on earth (<i>viz.</i>, Brāhmaṇas), whose weapons are <lb/> (<i>their</i>) words <note n="2:530-2">This complimentry attribute to the Brāhmaṇas also occurs in Bhavabhūti's <i>Uttararāmacharita</i>, in the <lb/> passage <de><ch/>siddhaṁ hyetadvāci vīryaṁ dvijānām,</de> <i>etc</i>. The sense conveyed, however, may not be ironical as it is in the <lb/> passage quoted.</note> and who by the offerings (<i>which they make</i>) during sacrifices please even the <lb/> nectar-fed (<i>gods</i>) who dwell in heaven, protect you !</p>

<p>(V. 14.) This eulogy (<i>praśasti</i>) was drawn up by <em>Paramēśvara</em> surnamed <em>Uttarakā-<lb break="no"/>raṇika</em> son of <em>Param-Ōttarakāraṇika</em>, the self-chosen lord of Poetry.</p>

<p>(Ll. 26 to 38) In the fifty-eighth year (<i>of the reign</i>) of king <em>Vijaya-Nandivikrama-<lb break="no"/>varman:</em>—The inhabitants of <em>Teṉkarai Naṟaiyūr</em>-nāḍu in <em>Śōṛa-nāḍu</em> witnessing,—<lb break="no"/>the forest and (<i>other</i>) waste lands lying to the west of <em>Taṇḍattōṭṭam</em> situated in their <lb/> district, • • • • • None shall be permitted to make • • • <lb/> or cut channels (<i>kuraṅgu</i>). A head of water (<i>uvaṉṟi</i>) shall be constructed above the <lb/> main sluice (<i>kūṟṟaṉvāy</i>) only, and water taken (<i>from it</i>) for irrigation. No (<i>tax</i>) of any kind <lb/> such as (<i>duty on</i>) oil-presses and looms, <i>ulaviyakkūli</i> <note n="2:530-3">This term occurs in the Kāśākuḍi plates of Nandivarman as <i>ulliyakkūli</i> (above, p. 352, text-line 122) and <lb/> is translated ‘the hire of the well-diggers’.</note>, the fee (in money) on marriages, <lb/> <i>ūreṭṭu</i>, fee on potters, <i>taṭṭukkāyam</i> <note n="2:530-4">This may correspond to <i>taṭṭār-pāṭṭam</i> of the large Leyden plates and be translated ‘fee on <lb/> goldsmiths.</note>, duty <note n="2:530-5"><i>Pūṭchi</i> is a term not found in dictionaries. This obsolete word seems to denote a duty or tax. <lb/> <i>Iḍaippūṭchi</i> occurs as <i>Iḍaippāṭṭam</i> in the large Leyden plates.</note> on toddy-drawers and shepherds, (<i>fee on</i>)<pb n="2:531"/> <lb/> stalls, <note n="2:531-1">Also occurs in the Kūram plates (above, Vol. I., p. 151, text-line 77).</note> brokerage-fee, <i>tirumugakkāṇam <note n="2:531-2">This term which is perhaps the more correct form of <i>tirumukkāṇam</i> must denote a fee levied for remunera- <lb/> ting the man who brings orders (<i>tirumugam</i>) from the king.</note>, uppukkōchcheygai</i> <note n="2:531-3">This word may be divided into <i>uppu kō</i> and <i>śōygai</i> which perhaps means the royalty paid for <lb/> manufacturing salt.</note>, good cow, good bull, <i>vaṭṭināṛi</i> <lb/> (fee on <i>baskets</i> of grain brought to the market), areca-nuts (<i>exposed for sale</i>) in shops, <i>pudānāṛi</i> <note n="2:531-4">The Vēlūrpāḷaiyam plates give the form <i>pudāṛi</i> while, according to the printed text of the large Leyden <lb/> plates, the term occurs as <i>pitā-nāṛi</i>. The meaning is not clear.</note> <lb/> and others which the king could take and enjoy, shall be paid (<i>to the king</i>). The Brāhmaṇa <lb/> donees of this village alone shall enjoy (<i>the income specified above). Damanagam</i> may be <lb/> planted; mansions and large edifices may be built of burnt bricks; reservoirs and wells may <lb/> be sunk; cocoanut trees may be planted in groves; (and) large oil-presses may be used. The <lb/> cocoanut and palmyra trees (<i>grown</i>) within the boundaries of this village shall not be <lb/> climbed by the toddy-drawers (<i>īṛavar). (The names of</i>) the good Brāhmaṇas of <em>Nalgūr</em> <lb/> that received the <i>brahmadēya</i> with all immunities including the above (<i>were):</i>—</p>

<table><p>LIST OF DONEES. <lb/> [C1]<i>Number</i>. [C2]<i>Gōtra</i>. [C3]Sūtra. [C4]<i>Residence or house-name</i>. [C5]<i>Name of donee</i>. [C6]<i>Number of shares</i>. <lb/> [C1]1 [C2]Kāśyapa [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Karañjai [C5]Vattavaṉ Kumārakōva-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]2 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Vattavaṉ Nārāyaṇa-Rudra-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]3 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Vattavaṉ Vishṇudāsa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]4 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuṇḍūr [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]5 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Ākkochcha-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]6 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Vasantayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]7 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Kumāraḍi-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]8 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Veṇṇaya-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]9 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Tattakuṭṭi-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]10 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Tattakuṭṭi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]11 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. <note n="2:531-5">The name Kuṇḍūr is repeated in the original, although this same was the residence of the seven donees <lb/> mentioned immediately before.</note> [C5]Uṛuttirakanda (Rudraskanda)-Chatur-vēdin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]12 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Aṭṭambaṟu [C5]Dāmaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]13 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karippaṟu [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]14 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Dōṇama-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]15 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uviyūr [C5]Viñjakumāra-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]16 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Amuttaṉūr [C5]Kōvaḍi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]17 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uṟuppiṭṭūr [C5]Koṇḍama-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]18 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich-chēḍu. [C5]Kumāraḍi-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]19 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Cheruppaḷḷi [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]20 [C2]Do. [C3]Āśvalāyana [C4]Paṟiyalūr [C5]Sūryadatta-Bhaṭṭa [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]21 [C2]Do. [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Pāḍagam [C5]Mātirupūdi (Mātṛibhūti)-Shaḍaṅgavit-Sōmayājin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]22 [C2]Do. [C3]Vāsēṇi [C4]Nuguñjūḍu [C5]Kuṇḍaśarman [C6]4 <lb/> [C1]23 [C2]Do. [C3]Paviṛiya [C4]Nimbey [C5]Vaḍugaśarma-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]24 [C2]Do. [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Korañji [C5]Kandakumāra (Skandakumāra)-Chaturvēdin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]25 [C2]Gautama [C3]Hiraṇyakēśi [C4]Pāṟkuḷam [C5]Nāgakumāra-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa-Sōma-yājin. [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]26 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kāynīrkuḷam [C5]Kumārakaṇṇa (Kumārakṛishṇa)-Chaturvēdin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]27 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Kuṟukoṭṭi [C5]Kandakumāra-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]28 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Uṛuttira-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]29 [C2]Do. [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Nellūr [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Trivēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]30 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Achchuvaṉa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <pb n="2:532"/> <lb/> [C1]31 [C2]Gautama [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Aṅgārai [C5]Kumārakūḷa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]32 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Kaṇṇakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]33 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Kaṇadāya-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]34 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Irāyūr [C5]Attuvachcha-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]35 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Dāmōdara-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]36 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Ākki [C5]Tattaśarma-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]37 [C2]Ātrēya [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Tukkaśarma-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]38 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Harisvāmi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]39 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Dvēdaikōma- <lb/> puṟam. [C5]Maṇikkuṭṭa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]40 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Uṛuda (Rudra)-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]41 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Muḍipaṟu [C5]Dāmōdara-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]42 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Kumāraśēṭṭa (Kumārajyēshṭha)- <lb/> Chaturvēdin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]43 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Kandama-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]44 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Muḍapaṟu [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]45 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Dēvaśarma-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]46 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uhali [C5]Viṇṇaya-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]47 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Dāmōdara-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]48 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uhali [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]49 [C2]? [C3]? [C4]? [C5][Bha*]vaskanda-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]50 [C2]Ātrēya [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Uhali [C5]Svāmiśarma-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]51 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Vishṇudatta-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]52 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Pāḍagam [C5]Svāmidēva-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]53 [C2]Do. [C3]Hiraṇyakēśi [C4]Kaḷattūr [C5]Sukumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]54 [C2]Do. [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kākkaimirā [C5]Bhavadāsa-Daśapurīya [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]55 [C2]Āgnivēśya [C3]Do. [C4]Virippaṟu [C5]Viñjakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]56 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Irāyūr [C5]Kuṇḍiśāmi-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]57 [C2]Bhāradvāja [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Veṇṇainallūr [C5]Agnikoṇḍa-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]58 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Pattaṅgi [C5]Kūḷamaṇḍai-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]59 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Attāṛi-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]60 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Pāḍagam [C5]Rudranandi-Bhaṭṭa-Sōmayājin [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]61 [C2]Do. [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Poppaṟu [C5]Vishṇu-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]62 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuṇḍūr [C5]Kandakumāra-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]63 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Akkoṟṟa-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]64 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uviyūr [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]65 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Bhavaskanda-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]66 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Yajñamādhava-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]67 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uviyūr [C5]Uṛudakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]68 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Chāndūr [C5]Aṇṇamañji-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]69 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Piṇukkippaṟu [C5]Vishṇudāsa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]70 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuravaśiri [C5]Bhavamādhava-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]71 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kumiṛūr [C5]Tēvaḍi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]72 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Taṇukkil [C5]Akkūḷa-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]73 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Poppaṟu [C5]Maṇḍaya-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]74 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kāṭṭukkuṟi [C5]Kūḷaśarma-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]75 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uviyūr [C5]Vishṇukumāra-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]76 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Taṇukkil [C5]Vishṇukumāra-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]77 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kāṭṭukkuṟi [C5]Brahmadatta-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]78 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Poṉṉambaṟu [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]79 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Dōṇaya-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]80 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Uṛudakumāra-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]81 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Magaśirai [C5]Tōṇamaṇḍai-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]82 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Vṛiddhama-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]83 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuravaśiri [C5]Viṇṇakanda (Vishṇuskanda)-Chatur- <lb/> vēdin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]84 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Kandakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]85 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārachchiṟai [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Trivēdi-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]86 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kurōvi [C5]Veṇṇaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]87 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kumiṛūr [C5]Kāmaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]88 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uṭṭukkūr [C5]Nāgavishṇu-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]89 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Magaśirai [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]90 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu [C5] • • • -Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <pb n="2:533"/> <lb/> [C1]91 [C2]Bhāradvāja [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Maṇaṟkāl [C5]Sarvakratuyāji-Tattaṅkumaraṉ [C6]3 <lb/> [C1]92 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Tattañjāttaṉ [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]93 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Appūdi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]94 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Irāyūr [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]95 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Śoṭṭai-Mādhava-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]96 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Śēṭṭalūr [C5]Attāṛi-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]97 [C2]Do. [C3]Paviṛiya [C4]Aṇuppūr [C5]Bhavarudra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]98 [C2]Do. [C3]Bhāradvāja [C4]Mirāṅgaḷūr [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]99 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kāñjikkuṟi [C5]Irāttamā-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]100 [C2]Do. [C3]Kāḷarachcha <lb/> (<i>or</i> Kāḷarcha) [C4]Mandiram [C5]Bhavadāya-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]101 [C2]Vatsa [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Nambūr [C5]Veṇṇaśarma-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]102 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kulaputti [C5]Veṇṇaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]103 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Nambūr [C5]Bhavasvāmi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]104 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kulaputti [C5]Attāya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]105 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Nambūr [C5]Yajña-Mādha[va]-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]106 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]? [C5]? [C6]? <lb/> [C1]107 [C2]? [C3]? [C4]Cheruppaḷḷi [C5]Dōṇama-Kramavid and his son Ku- <lb/> māraḍi-Kramavid. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]108 [C2]Vatsa [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Dēvabhūti-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]109 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Ayiyakki [C5]Attōṇa-Shaḍaṅgavit-Sōmayājin [C6]12 <lb/> [C1]110 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Muḍumbe [C5]Chaṉṉakumāra-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]111 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Veṇṇaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]112 [C2]Do. [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Muḍumbe [C5]Akkanda-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]113 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Pipparai [C5]Do. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]114 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Muḍumbe [C5]Kūḷaśarma-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]115 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Kuṇḍūr [C5]Dāmōdara-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]116 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Veḷḷaiyūr [C5]Vishṇubhūti-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]117 [C2]Mudgala [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Iṛakkandoṟu [C5]Kaḍamba-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]118 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Uṟuppiṭṭūr [C5]Bhavaskanda-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]119 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Iṛakkandoṟu [C5]Yajñaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]120 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Kāḷaśarma-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]121 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Bhavasvāmi-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]122 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Eṟama-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]123 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Ayyakki [C5]Śēṭṭaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]124 [C2]Śunaka [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Maṇiyūr [C5]Pōśaṉ-Pavvi-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]125 [C2]Rathītara [C3]Do. [C4]Ōrikoṉṟai [C5]Kumārapūdi (Kumārabhūti)-Chatur- <lb/> vēdin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]126 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuravaśiri [C5]Chaṉṉakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]127 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Attikuṭṭi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]128 [C2]Do. [C3]Paviṛiya [C4]Mēṟṟāmaṇa- <lb/> maṅgalam. [C5]Uttarakāraṇika <i>alias</i> Ayyaṉ Paramēś- <lb/> vara. [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]129 [C2]Garga [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Mādhava-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]130 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuñjappayal [C5]Harisvāmi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]131 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Kandaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]132 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Maṟṟalūr [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]133 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuñjappevil [C5]Bhavaśarma-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]134 [C2]Do. [C3]Paviṛiya [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Dāmōdara-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]135 [C2]Vādhūla [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Kandāḍai Vāsudēva-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]136 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Maṇḍaiya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]137 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Kandāḍai Vāsudēva-Chaturvēdi- <lb/> Bhaṭṭa-Agnichitta-Sarvakratuyājin [C6]3 <lb/> [C1]138 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Suyajña-Kēśava-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]139 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]140 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuṇḍūr [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]141 [C2]Lōhita [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Agniśarma-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]142 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Tiṇḍakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]143 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Dāmōdara-[Chaturvēdin] [C6]? <lb/> [C1]144 [C2]? [C3]? [C4]Śrīmalai [C5]Agnirudra-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]145 [C2]Lōhita [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Śēndakumāra-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]146 [C2]Bhārgava [C3]Do. [C4]Maṇaṟkāl [C5]Āytāṅgi Śaṅkaraṉ Śēndaṉ [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]147 [C2]Kauśika [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Irāttakkuṟi [C5]Kēśava-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <pb n="2:534"/> <lb/> [C1]148 [C2]Kauśika [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Vēlvaṭṭi [C5]Nākoṇḍa-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]149 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Jayantarudra-Chatuvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]150 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Rudraśarma-Daśapurīya [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]151 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Śēṭṭalūr [C5]Suyajña-Bhavasēna-Trivēdi-Bhaṭṭa- <lb/> Sōmayājin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]152 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Koṭṭuṅgōmbuṟa [C5]Uṛudakuṭṭi-Daśapurīya [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]153 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kuravaśiri [C5]Vishṇukumāra-Bhaṭṭa-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]154 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Koraḍi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]155 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Kumāṇḍūr [C5]Tryambaka-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]156 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vēlvaṭṭi [C5]Agnichitta-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]157 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Kumāramaṇḍai-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]158 [C2]Do. [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Ēkambūr [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]159 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Arasappaṟu [C5]Dōṇama-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]160 [C2]Do. [C3]Bhāradvāja [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Dēvakumāra-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]161 [C2]Do. [C3]Kāḷarachcha (<i>or</i> <lb/> Kāḷarcha). [C4]Peruvali [C5]Kōvaḍi-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]162 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Pavakkuṟi [C5]Tiṇḍamāda-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]163 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Śāmikuṭṭi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]164 [C2]Do. [C3]Hiraṇyakēśi [C4]Perumbāṇḍūr [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]165 [C2]Śālāvata [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Vēlpaṟu [C5]Tūrkkama-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]166 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Kandakumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]167 [C2]Kutsa [C3]Do. [C4]Ōdimūkkil [C5]Mādhava-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]168 [C2]Vasishṭha [C3]Do. [C4]Kuravaśiri [C5]Attikumāra-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]169 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vīravaḷḷi [C5]Achchaṭṭi-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]170 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Divākara-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]171 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Eṭṭukkūr [C5]Kaṇavuṛutta (Gaṇarudra)-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]172 [C2]Sāvarṇi [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Pāḍagam [C5]Nārāyaṇa-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]173 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Śōnikuṭṭi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]174 [C2]Parāśara [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kallakkūr [C5]Pāppaḍi-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]175 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Oṅgaḷūr [C5]Akkumāra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]176 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Achchenda-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]177 [C2]Vārakhya [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Pūṉiyam [C5]Śēṭṭaśarman [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]178 [C2]Kapi [C3]Do. [C4]Paṟāndūr [C5]Mahēśvara-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]179 [C2]Do. [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Perumbūdūr [C5]Kumāradatta-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]180 [C2]Dhūmrāyaṇa [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Uṟuppiṭṭūr [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]181 [C2]Paurukutsa [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Koṭṭi [C5]Agniśarma-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]182 [C2]Gautama [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Nandikuṭṭi-Trivēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]183 [C2]Kāśyapa [C3]Do. [C4]Karañjai [C5]Kandapūdi (Skandabhūti)-Daśapurīya [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]184 [C2]Sāṁkṛiti [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Iruṅgaṇḍi [C5]Kumāraśarma-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]185 [C2]Hārīta [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kākkaimirā [C5]Yajñaśarma-Chaturvēdi-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]186 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]Tiruvaḍigaḷ (<i>i.e.</i> Vishṇu) [C6]5 <lb/> [C1]187 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]Mahādēva (<i>i.e.</i> Śiva) [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]188 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]Reader of the <i>[Mahā]bhārata</i> [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]189 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]Drummers (<i>taṭṭaṛikoṭṭi</i>) [C6]1 <lb/> [C1].. [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]The three arbitrators together <lb/> (received) three shares. [C6]See below <lb/> Nos. 202 <lb/> to 204. <lb/> [C1]190 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]Those who supply water for the hall <lb/> (<i>ambalam</i>) and kindle fire (<i>in it</i>). [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]191 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Puliyūr in <lb/> Miṛalai-nāḍu. [C5]Ṛishi-Vaikhānasa-Satyagarbha- <lb/> Bhaṭṭa. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1] [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]The doctor received two shares [C6]See below <lb/> No. 207. <lb/> [C1]192 [C2]Vādhūla [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kārambich- <lb/> chēḍu. [C5]Kandāḍai-Vāsudēva-Chaturvēdi- <lb/> Bhaṭṭa-Agnichitta-Sarvakratu-Vāja- <lb/> pēyin. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]193 [C2]Vatsa [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Nūttilāppaṟu [C5]Maṇḍaiya-Chaturvēdi-Sōmayājin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]194 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Vaṅgippaṟu [C5]Bhavarudra-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]195 [C2]Bhāradvāja [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Irāyūr [C5]Nārāyaṇadatta-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]196 [C2]Do. [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kārachchiṟai [C5]Chaṉṉaya-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]197 [C2]Māṭhara [C3]Hiraṇyakēśi [C4]Kommārai [C5]Svāmidatta-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]198 [C2]Kāśyapa [C3]Chhandōga [C4]Pāḍagam [C5]Kanmāda-Shaḍaṅgavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]199 [C2]Garga [C3]Āpastamba [C4]Kuñjappevil [C5]Nakkadōṇa-Chaturvēdin [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]200 [C2]Pādaraṇi [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Talaichcheṅ- <lb/> gāḍu. [C5]Kalaiyaṉ Śōmaṉ [C6]1 <pb n="2:535"/> <lb/> [C1]<i>Number</i>. [C2]<i>Gōtra</i>. [C3]<i>Sūtra</i>. [C4]<i>Residence or house- <lb/> name</i>. [C5]<i>Name of donee</i>. [C6]<i>Number of <lb/> shares</i>. <lb/> [C1]201 [C2]Bhāradvāja [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Payyūr [C5]Paḍuvuṛāṉ Divākaraṉ Śāmi [C6]1 <lb/> [C1] [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]The three shares of the arbitrators <lb/> (mentioned above) were thus distri- <lb/> buted:— [C6]... <lb/> [C1]202 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Perumbuḷḷe [C5]Vīrakandaṉ [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]203 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Do. [C5]Ṛishabhanandi [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]204 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Pāḍagam [C5]Guṇadaraṉ and [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]205 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Agaṛimaṅgalam [C5]Tirup[piḍa]vūr Śā[mi]. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]206 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Aruvāgūr in <lb/> Aruvā-nāḍu. [C5]Ṛishi-Vaikhānasa-Śaṅkaranārāyaṇa- <lb/> Bhaṭṭa. [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]207 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Īykkāṭṭukkōyil [C5]Paramēśvaraṉ received the two shares <lb/> set apart for the doctors (mentioned <lb/> above). [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]208 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]Dāmanallūr in <lb/> Aruvā-nāḍu. [C5]Ṛishi-Vaikhānasa-Nārāyaṇa-Bhaṭṭa [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]209 [C2]Sāvarṇi [C3]... [C4]Śiṟupaṛuvūr [C5]Tuvēdi (Dvivēdi)-Kāḍampālai; under <lb/> the orders of the assembly (<i>peru- <lb/> makkaḷ</i>). [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]210 [C2]Vatsa [C3]Prāvachana [C4]Kukkaṉūr [C5]Viṭṭaśarma-Kramavid [C6]1 <lb/> [C1]211 [C2]... [C3]... [C4]... [C5]For (<i>the maintenance of</i>) the (<i>head</i>) sluice <lb/> and the reservoir. [C6]3 <lb/> [C1]212 [C2]Ātrēya [C3]Āgnivēśya <note n="2:535-1">It may be noted that on p. 532 Agnivēśya appears under <i>gōtra</i>, in column 2.</note> [C4]Puttūr [C5]Śōmāśi-Kāri [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]213 [C2]Do. [C3]Do. [C4]Do. [C5]Śōmāśi-[Ta*]ttaṉ [C6]2 <lb/> [C1]Total [C2]244</p></table>

</translation>

</edition>

</inscription>

</volume>