<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>SII 12.119: original edition by V. Venkatasubba Ayyar</title>
                <title type="alt">No. 119. (A.R. No. 285 of 1921). ĀTTŪR, CHINGLEPUT TALUK AND DISTRICT. ON THE NORTH AND WEST WALLS OF THE MUKTĪŚVARA TEMPLE.</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author of digital edition</resp>
                    <persName ref="part:emfr">
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Francis</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSSIIv12p0i0119</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                        <idno/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>
                            
                            <p>This record is dated in the <hi rend="bold">5th year</hi> of <hi rend="bold">Sakalabhuvanachchakravartin Kōpperuñjiṅgadēva</hi> and it records the gift of the village <hi rend="bold">Āttūr</hi> <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">Rājarājanallūr</hi> in Āṟṟūr-nāḍu, a subdivision of Ūṟṟukkāṭṭūk-kōṭṭam in Jayaṅgoṇḍaśōḻa- maṇḍalam, by <hi rend="bold">Aḻagiyaśīyaṉ Avaṉiāḷappiṟandāṉ Kāḍavaṉ Kōpperuñjiṅgaṉ,</hi> for constructing, as a gōpura with 7 storeys, the southern entrance called ‘<foreign>Śokkachchīyaṉ-tirunilai</foreign>’ of the temple of Tiruchchiṟṟambalam-Uḍaiyār at Perumbaṟṟappuliyūr (i.e., Chidambaram). The Pāṇḍya emblems of a pair of fish and goad found in relief on the jambs and beams of this gōpura indicate that the construction must have been started in the reign of a Pāṇḍya king. It is stated that this inscription, besides being engraved at Āṟṟūr, was also ordered to be recorded in the temple of Tiruvēgamba-muḍaiya-Nāyaṉār, probably Ēkāmranātha at Conjeeveram. A copy of the record is found at Chidambaram wherein<note><hi rend="italic">A.R.</hi> No. 463 of 1902.</note> the engraving of the present inscription at Āttūr is also referred to. The document is attested by Kōpperuñjiṅga, Kurukularājaṉ and Villavarājaṉ.</p>
                            
                            <p>The wording in this inscription where the chief himself figures as donor is peculiar. This form, though not uncommon, is not often met with in inscriptions.</p>						
                            
                            <p>From the surname Aḻagiyaśīyaṉ and the probable reference to this gōpura of seven storeys in a record<note><hi rend="italic">A.R.</hi> No. 1 of 1936-37.</note> of the 24th year of Rājarāja III, i.e., A.D. 1240, the present inscription has to be assigned to Kōpperuñjiṅgadēva I.<note>[It is interesting to note that among the boundaries is mentioned the tax-free land of a <foreign>ghajikā.</foreign>—Ed].</note></p>						
                            
                        </summary>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <p/>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>           
            <change who="part:emfr" when="2025-03-17" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
            <change who="part:mime" when="2025-03-18" status="draft">Conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="tam" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">
                
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrīḥ</hi> <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="ddanda">.</g></supplied>
                </ab>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="grantha">sakala<sic>hu</sic><!--EF: typo?-->va</hi>na<hi rend="grantha">ccakravatti</hi> kopperuñciṅkatevarkku yāṇṭu 5<g type="dash"/>vatu taṉiyūr perumpaṟṟappuliyūr Uṭaiyār tirucciṟṟampalamuṭaiyārkku Aḻakiyaciyaṉ AvaṉiĀḷap piṟantāṉ kāṭavaṉ kopperuñ
                    <lb n="2" break="no"/>ciṅkaṉeṉ <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Iṉṉāyaṉār koyilt teṟkilt tiruvācal cokkacciyaṉ tirunilai Eḻukopura mākac ceyyat tiruppaṇikku Uṭalāka <hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>yaṅkoṇṭacoḻamaṇṭalattu Ūṟṟukkāṭṭukkoṭṭattu Āṟṟūrnāṭṭu Āṟṟūrāṉa <hi rend="grantha">rājarāja</hi>nallūrkku Ellai <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <lb n="3"/>Īñcalāṟṟuk kiḻkaraikku meṟkkum ceyyāṟu niroṭukālukku vaṭakkum villiyaṉpākkattu Ellaikkuk kiḻakkum cāttaṉampākkattum koṉkāṭṭu Ellaikkum teṟkkum naṭuvuḷppaṭṭa tarappaṭi nilam muṉṉūṟṟaṟupattu nālveli Itil Uḷḷūrt
                    <lb n="4" break="no"/>tevarkaḷ tevatāṉaṅkaḷum tiruviṭaiyāṭṭaṅkaḷum piṭāripaṭṭi tukkaipaṭṭi paḷḷi<sic>k</sic><!--EF: typo?-->cantam Uḷppaṭa nilam nāṟpattaṟu veliyum Akaram <hi rend="grantha">mahāvibhūticcaturvedi</hi>maṅkalam nilam paṉṉiru veliyum ceṭṭalūrp pirāṉpaṭṭaṉukkum māṭapocai varatarācapaṭṭaṉuk
                    <lb n="5" break="no"/>kum vaṅkipuṟattu karuṇākarapaṭṭaṉukkum <hi rend="grantha">bhaṭṭavṛ</hi>t=ti nilam Oru veliyum kaṭikaiyār Iṟaiyili nilam muṉṟekālum Āka nilam Aṟupattiraṇṭekāl nikki nikki<supplied reason="omitted">niṉṟa</supplied> nilam muṉṉūṟṟoṉṟe mukkālum kollaip puṉcaiyum kācāyaṅkaḷum veṭṭi pāṭikāvalum Arippāṭikāvalum Uḷppaṭa
                    <lb n="6"/>nellāyaṅkaḷum kācāyaṅkaḷum Ivvūrt tevarkaḷ tevatāṉam Akaraṅkaḷ Uḷppaṭṭa Iṟaiyilikaḷukku muṉpu koṇṭuvarum Āyaṅka ḷuḷppaṭa Aṉaittāyaṅkaḷum Uḷppaṭa tevatāṉa Iṟaiyiliyāka Añcāvatu Āṭi<hi rend="grantha">māsa</hi> mutal <hi rend="grantha"><sic>dva</sic><!--EF: typo?-->ndrāditya</hi>varai celvatāka Iṭṭom <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Uṭaiyār tiruvekampamuṭaiya
                    <lb n="7"/>nāyaṉār koyililum Āṟṟūril tirumutti<hi rend="grantha">śvara</hi>muṭaiyār koyililum kallumveṭṭi nāṟpāl Ellaiyilum tiruccūla<hi rend="grantha">sthā</hi>paṉamum paṇṇi koyil<surplus>p</surplus> paṇṭārattārkku Eṟakkaṭamai kuṭimai pokkaṟuppārkaḷākac coṉṉom <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ippaṭi ceyvate <supplied reason="subaudible"><g type="danda">.</g></supplied>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Ivai kopperuñciṅka ṉeḻuttu
                    <lb n="8"/>Eṉṟum Ivai kurukularā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi> ṉeḻuttu Eṉṟum
                    <lb n="9"/>Ivai villavarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi> ṉeḻuttu Eṉṟum vanta tiru
                    <lb n="10" break="no"/>mukappaṭi kal veṭṭiyatu <g type="pc">.</g> 
                </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="apparatus">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="commentary">
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="bibliography">
                
                <p>Digital edition of SII 12.119 by <bibl><ptr target="bib:VenkatasubbaAyyar1943_01"/></bibl> converted to DHARMA conventions by Emmanuel Francis.</p>
                
                <listBibl type="primary">
                    
                    <bibl n="SII">
                        <ptr target="bib:VenkatasubbaAyyar1943_01"/>
                        <citedRange unit="page">56-57</citedRange>
                        <citedRange unit="item">119</citedRange>
                    </bibl>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
                <listBibl type="secondary">
                    
                    <bibl/>
                    
                </listBibl>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
